<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE LISTINGS -- JULY 21-JULY 27</title>
    <meta content="21theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060725T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1777342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DD173FF932A15754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="14437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE LISTINGS -- JULY 21-JULY 27</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ALL THIS INTIMACY' In previews; opens Thursday. A romantically ambitious poet balances relationships with three women in this new play by Rajiv Joseph. Presented by Second Stage Theater (1:45). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway; (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' In previews; opens Tuesday. Based on the lives of the five cast members, this play, which incorporates dance and song, is about growing up in apartheid-era South Africa (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village; (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'INDIAN BLOOD' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Aug. 9. Primary Stages presents A. R. Gurney's new comedy about a rebellious American Indian boy coming of age in the 1940's. Mark Lamos directs (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL Through July 30. This always-buzzed-about summer showcase includes ''DruidSynge,'' the complete works of John Millington Synge (see below), and ''Grendel,'' an opera directed by Julie Taymor. Sites in and around Lincoln Center; (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>MIDTOWN INTERNATIONAL THEATER FESTIVAL Through Aug. 6. The seventh annual showcase often gets lost in the shuffle, despite its large and diverse collection of shows. There should be more than 60 productions this season, at four locations on 36th Street. Schedules and information; (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE HOUSE IN TOWN'  A wan new drama by Richard Greenberg about an American marriage slowly imploding in the days before the country's economy did the same, more suddenly and spectacularly, in 1929. A miscast Jessica Hecht stars as Amy Hammer, a well-to-do housewife sliding into despair as her remote husband looks on in frustration. Doug Hughes's production is pretty but desultory, as is Mr. Greenberg's typically eloquent but atypically empty writing (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diazand Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00).Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this old comedy from the 1930's, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). Bank Street Theater, 155 Bank Street, West Village, (212) 868-4444.(Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th-century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SUSAN AND GOD' The Mint Theater Company's fine revival of Rachel Crothers's 1937 comedy about religion, career and family features Leslie Hendrix of ''Law &amp; Order,'' excellent in the role of Susan. Jonathan Bank directs (2:20). The Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, third floor, Clinton, (212) 315-0231. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'TREASON' The poet Ezra Pound was a repellent fellow, judging from this play by Sallie Bingham: racist, anti-Semitic, eager to exploit the affections of the women who loved him. Just why women were drawn to him is never clear, but the play is thoughtful, and the acting, especially by Philip Pleasants as Pound, is superb (2:10). Perry Street Theater, 31 Perry Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'CHEKHOV &amp; MARIA'  Jovanka Bach's final play is a touching, beautifully acted if sometimes slow-paced study of Anton Chekhov's near-final days and his relationship with his sister, who cared for him (2:00). Barrow Group Theater, 312 West 36th Street; (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'FOOD FOR FISH' Adam Szymkowicz's fabulously weird and weirdly fabulous new comedy fools around with cross-dressing, suicidal writers and Chekhovian characters who long for New Jersey (2:00). Kraine Theater, 85 East Fourth Street, between Second and Third Avenues, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' A dancing encyclopedia of clichés set to music by Earth, Wind &amp; Fire. Numbing (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street; (212) 307-4100; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MANHATTAN MADCAPS of 1924' A not-very-madcap story is indeed included, but this is essentially a revue made of up of Rodgers and Hart songs, many of them fairly obscure. Better singing voices in the cast might help show them off to fuller advantage; as it is, the main attraction is a trio of songs with unfamiliar lyrics, but a very familiar tune: the one that, on the fourth try, became ''Blue Moon'' (1:20). Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400; closing Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SCHOOL OF THE AMERICAS' José Rivera, who wrote the screenplay for ''The Motorcycle Diaries,'' penned this rickety piece of historical speculation about the final two days of Che Guevara's life (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closing Sunday.(Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SHAKESPEARE IS DEAD' Orran Farmer's two-character drama about a struggling playwright and a drug-addicted actress-stripper is well-meaning, but tedious and often trite (1:00). Paradise Factory, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TROUBLE IN PARADISE' Ernst Lubitsch's 1932 film comedy about a con man, the con woman he loves and a wealthy Parisian widow lives again as a giddy, good-looking, quietly amusing play (1:30). Hudson Guild Theater, 441 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'LEONARD COHEN: I'M YOUR MAN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) This enthralling documentary combines pieces of an extended interview with Mr. Cohen, the Canadian singer-songwriter, poet and author, now 71, with a tribute concert at the Sydney Opera House in January 2005. Nick Cave, Rufus Wainwright, Kate and Anna McGarrigle, Martha Wainwright and Antony are among the featured performers. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'EDMOND' (R, 76 minutes) William H. Macy gives what may be the performance of his career in the faithful screen adaptation of David Mamet's raw, epithet-spattered spiritual fable about a buttoned-up milquetoast who heeds his inner demons and plummets into free fall; hateful and unforgettable. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'EXCELLENT CADAVERS' (No rating, 92 minutes, in English and Italian) Based on the book by Alexander Stille, this tough, brisk documentary follows Mr. Stille to Italy, where he reconstructs the recent history of the Italian mafia, focusing on the careers of two courageous prosecutors who took on organized crime and the political system that protected it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'GABRIELLE' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haute bourgeoisie Parisian marriage, circa 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-age white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KILL YOUR IDOLS' (No rating, 71 minutes) S. A. Crary's glib, unfocused music documentary examines the New York No Wave scene of the late 1970's -- an offshoot of punk, the anti-New Wave -- when the music was noisy (and genuinely noncommercial) and the clothes were black (and genuinely secondhand). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'MINI'S FIRST TIME' (R, 91 minutes) Yet another poor little rich girl tends to her festering inner wounds by becoming one of Southern California's children of the damned. Nikki Reed stars alongside the slumming likes of Alec Baldwin, Carrie-Anne Moss, Jeff Goldblum and Luke Wilson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LA MOUSTACHE' (No rating, 86 minutes, in French) Emmanuel Carrière's psychological mystery prepares you to bask in one of those sexy, bittersweet marital comedies that are a hallmark of sophisticated French cinema. Then, by degrees, it subverts those expectations to spiral down a rabbit hole of ambiguity and doubt. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PEACEFUL WARRIOR' (PG-13, 120 minutes) As ludicrous as the title promises yet supremely unembarrassed, this New Age enlightenment parable has its heart in the right place, but a mind of corny mush. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'PIRATES OF THE CARIBBEAN: DEAD MAN'S CHEST' Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ROAD TO GUANTÁNAMO' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom's powerful, slippery new film mixes documentary and fictional techniques to tell the true story of three British Muslims imprisoned by the United States government in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'RUSSIAN DOLLS' (No rating, 129 minutes, in English, Russian, French and Spanish) The sequel to the international hit ''L'Auberge Espagnole'' belongs to a long line of airy French films that induce a pleasant buzz of Euro-envy. Like its forerunner, it is a generational group portrait of young, smart, sexy, well-educated Europeans at work and play filmed in a style that might be called Truffaut Lite. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'71 FRAGMENTS OF A CHRONOLOGY OF CHANCE' (No rating, 95 minutes) This 1994 film from that great provocateur Michael Haneke follows a handful of seemingly unrelated characters, all of whom -- perhaps by chance, perhaps by divine intervention, though mostly through artistic contrivance -- have the grave misfortune to be in an Austrian bank when a student starts unloading his revolver. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'WAIST DEEP' (R, 97 minutes) Tyrese Gibson plays an ex-convict trying to rescue his son from ruthless criminal kidnappers in this far-from-terrible B movie, directed with style and heart by Vondie Curtis Hall. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WASSUP ROCKERS' (R, 105 minutes) The latest provocation from the director and photographer Larry Clark follows a group of teenage Hispanic skateboarders from South Central Los Angeles on a 24-hour adventure that takes them from one hell (the inner city) to another (decadent Beverly Hills) and back. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. ( Dargis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>YOU, ME AND DUPREE' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>GREAT VILLAINS IN CINEMA (Through July 30) BAMcinématek is honoring movie bad guys, from Dracula to Michael Corleone. This weekend's features include ''White Heat'' (1949), starring James Cagney as a psychotic killer with a mother fixation; and ''A Clockwork Orange'' (1971), with Malcolm McDowell as a hooligan with a taste for ultraviolence. BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) A 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962), one of the first directors to win an Oscar (for ''Seventh Heaven''), continues at the Museum of the Moving Image. This weekend's films include the western ''Until They Get Me'' (1917); ''Lazybones'' (1925), starring Buck Jones as a single father; and the original ''Humoresque'' (1920). 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HISTORIC HARLEM PARKS FESTIVAL: THROUGH AFRICAN EYES AND PRIZED PIECES (Through Aug. 3) This fifth annual outdoor festival continues Wednesday night with Zézé Gamboa's ''Hero'' (2004), about a homeless veteran of the civil war in Angola. Thursday night's feature is ''Beyond Beats and Rhymes'' (2006), Byron Hurt's study of sex roles in hip-hop and rap. Jackie Robinson Park, the basketball courts at 150th Street and Bradhurst Avenue, (212) 352-1720; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues Sunday and Tuesday with ''The Bad Sleep Well'' (1960), which places the ''Hamlet'' story in postwar corporate Japan. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>PREMIERE BRAZIL! (Through Sunday) The Museum of Modern Art's fourth annual program of contemporary Brazilian film concludes this weekend with the screening of seven features. They include ''If I Were You'' (2006), Daniel Filho's satire about sex-role stereotypes, and ''Black Orpheus'' (1959), Marcel Camus's classic retelling of the Greek legend, set at Carnival in Rio de Janeiro. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, 11 West 53rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SCANNERS: THE 2006 NEW YORK VIDEO FESTIVAL (Through July 30) The Film Society of Lincoln Center's 15th annual showcase of new media begins on Wednesday. The first offerings include ''The Magic Bus,'' an 80-minute program of shorts done in mixtape style; and ''Believe the Hype,'' a tribute to the music-video director Hype Williams. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DICKEY BETTS AND GREAT SOUTHERN (Wednesday) Kicked out of the Allman Brothers, a band he founded, the guitarist Dickey Betts wasted no time in going back on tour with his own group. His chiming, symmetrical guitar solos and the weary but amiable voice from songs like ''Blue Skies'' are intact, and he may even have something to prove. With Kenny Wayne Shepherd. At 9:30 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; $52. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>MARY J. BLIGE (Tonight) Mary J. Blige has long been emoting through hip-hop and soul for ''all my sisters, my troubled sisters.'' Her latest, ''The Breakthrough'' (Geffen), also finds her in a duet with U2. (She steals the show.) With Jaheim and LeToya. At 8, Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $59.50 to $129.50. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRAND NEW (Thursday) This Long Island emo band made a quantum leap with its second album three years ago, from whiny and unchallenging breakup songs to tangles of explosive melody with brooding, sometimes horrific lyrics. What the band will come up with on the as-yet-unscheduled album No. 3 is a subject of intense speculation among fans, who quickly snatched up all tickets for this tour. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JIM CAMPILONGO, JESSE HARRIS, MIKE VIOLA (Monday) Just another night at the Living Room, a plain Lower East Side cabaret that puts on one guitar-cradling singer-songwriter after another, some of them world-class. Mr. Campilongo is a well-traveled guitar whiz who plays with Norah Jones in her country band the Little Willies; here he leads his Electric Trio. Jesse Harris, who wrote Ms. Jones's hit ''Don't Know Why,'' sings in the graceful and guileless manner of Paul Simon and James Taylor when on his own. Mike Viola, jumping from piano to guitar, sings strident power-pop with some jagged wit. At 9 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* CAT POWER (Tuesday) For her most recent album, ''The Greatest'' (Matador), Chan Marshall, the superbly rueful singer known as Cat Power, recorded with a group of veteran Memphis soul players, yielding some of the most stirring -- and happiest -- music of her career. Performing solo, she is spellbindingly intense and mercurial. At 8 p.m., Hiro Ballroom at the Maritime Hotel, 371 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-4300; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CHEB I SABBAH (Tomorrow) Indian devotional music meets the beat, now and then, in the music of DJ Cheb I Sabbah, who swirls together various styles into heady meditations. He is joined on vocals by the singer Riffat Salamat Sultana, daughter of the Pakistani singer Ustad Salamat Ali Khan. At 7 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package.(Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>DON CABALLERO (Tonight) In the mid-1990's, Don Caballero, from Pittsburgh, was one of a handful of overachieving guitar bands whose knotty, laser-precise and deliberately undanceable instrumentals exemplified the fittingly named subgenre math-rock. The band broke up six years ago, but its drummer, Damon Che, has repopulated it with new players; its new album, ''World Class Listening Problem'' (Relapse), suggests that there was more to the old group's appeal than just math. With Blind Idiot God, Alger Hiss, Houston McCoy and the Victoria Lucas. At 8, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006; $13. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>'DOT DASH YEAR IV' (Thursday) Each summer Dot Dash, a little concert promoter in Brooklyn devoted to punk and garage-rock, throws a festival with some big-deal reunions -- big deals in the small and passionate world of garage-rock, anyway. This year its three-day series begins on Thursday with the return of the Dicks, a Texas band from the early 1980's that sang ragged and churlish complaints with titles like ''Hate the Police.'' Also on the bill are the Marked Men, the Carbonas and Live Fast Die. The highlight of the festival will be an appearance by Rocket From the Tombs on July 29. At 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236; $17. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EARLY MAN, BAD WIZARD, 3 INCHES OF BLOOD (Tuesday) The best retro bands do not just conjure up an old artist or even a specific era, but freely toy with their influences to suggest a past that never quite existed. Three Inches of Blood updates the galloping, swords-and-goblins rock of early-1980's groups like Iron Maiden and Manowar with harsh streaks of violence that recall later death-metal. Early Man, on its debut album, ''Closing In'' (Matador), begins in the comforting mud of Black Sabbath and ends airborne, with a speed and control that comes down from Metallica. Also on the bill is Bad Wizard, whose plodding re-creations of Grand Funk Railroad and Kiss illustrate a less imaginative kind of retro-rock. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MELISSA ETHERIDGE (Monday through Wednesday) Love takes on heroic dimensions in the songs of Melissa Etheridge. She puts her own mark on the brawny guitar riffs and raspy-voiced melodies of 1980's heartland rock, as adoring audiences sing along. At 8 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $39.50 to $104.50. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>GOLDEN SMOG (Wednesday) Even heartsick alt-country has its celebrity supergroups. Golden Smog includes Jeff Tweedy of Wilco, Dan Murphy of Soul Asylum, Gary Louris and Marc Perlman of the Jayhawks, and Kraig Johnson of Run Westy Run. Opening the show is David Poe, a singer and guitarist, whose wit and sparkle come through largely between songs. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOLD STEADY (Thursday) Like the E Street Band fronted by Shane MacGowan of the Pogues, the Hold Steady -- from Brooklyn, though with Minneapolis origins -- plays bare-knuckled guitar-rock while its singer, Craig Finn, free-associates about religion and sex in a boozy snarl. ''I guess I heard about original sin,'' he growls. ''I heard the dude blamed the chick.'' At 7 p.m., Castle Clinton National Monument, Battery Park, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789. Free; tickets available at 5 p.m., two per person. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JONATHAN KANE (Tomorrow) John Lee Hooker meets La Monte Young in the droning, bluesy incantations of Mr. Kane, a mainstay in the downtown avant-garde scene who has played drums with Swans, Rhys Chatham and Gary Lucas. He has a drummer's sense of steady dynamic development and an unapologetic love of noise. He plays two shows. At 2 p.m., with Dragons of Zynth, Home and Taiko Masala, East River Amphitheater, East River Park, south of Delancey Street, Lower East Side, ermp.org; free. At 9 p.m., with Golden Tongues, Mahi Mahi and Ambitious Orchestra, Sin-é, 150 Attorney Street, Lower East Side, (212) 388-0077; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JASON LYTLE (Tomorrow and Monday) In Grandaddy, Mr. Lytle sang as if he were Neil Young trapped inside a computer chip: with a voice tiny and yet infinite, yearning to be fully human yet stuck within the strictures of the information age. Grandaddy recently released its final album, ''Just Like the Fambly Cat'' (V2), but it is an unsatisfying epitaph; fans will crowd these rare solo shows for hints of a new direction. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Monday at 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MALDITA VECINDAD, KONONO NO. 1, DAARA J (Sunday) What do a ska-flavored Mexican hard-rock band, a Congolese group that makes trance music from amplified thumb pianos and a Senegalese rap trio have in common? Not much except that they can all be lumped into the world-music category, however puzzlingly. Maldita Vecindad paints its ska rhythms with ominous, distorted metal. Konono No. 1 titled one album ''Congotronics,'' an apt term for its polyrhythmic bubblings of amplified likembés -- hand-held thumb pianos made from thin strips of medal. Daara J speed-raps in at least four languages: English, French, Spanish and Wolof. At 3 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. Maldita Vecindad also plays Sunday night at S.O.B.'s, and Konono No. 1 plays there on Monday. At 8 and 10:30, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $22 in advance, $25 at the door on Sunday; $25 in advance, $28 at the door on Monday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THOMAS MAPFUMO AND THE BLACKS UNLIMITED (Tuesday) A musical pioneer with a rebel's courage, Thomas Mapfumo made music for the revolutionaries who unseated the white-ruled government from what was Rhodesia and is now Zimbabwe. The music transferred the brisk patterns of traditional thumb-piano music to guitar; the words sometimes sent coded messages. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>JOHN MAYALL AND THE BLUESBREAKERS (Tonight) In the 1960's John Mayall ran the premier finishing school for British blues-rock guitarists: at various times his band -- still called the Bluesbreakers despite 40-odd years of lineup changes -- included the young Eric Clapton, Mick Taylor (later of the Rolling Stones) and Peter Green (later of Fleetwood Mac), among others. At 8 and 10:30, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, (212) 997-4144; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OAKLEY HALL (Tonight) Patient country-folk mutates into dense psychedelic drones in the songs of this Brooklyn band led by Pat Sullivan, a former member of Brooklyn's other masters of psychedelic minimalism, Oneida. With Mike Wexler, Black Taj and Endless Boogie. At 8:30, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* OS MUTANTES (Tonight) The oddest, most exuberant and most wonderfully innovative band of the late-1960's tropicália movement in Brazil -- when there was no shortage of odd, exuberant and wonderfully innovative musicians -- was Os Mutantes (the Mutants), which filtered American and British psychedelic and garage-rock through bossa nova and a do-what-thou-wilt pop-art philosophy. The band broke up in 1978, and before this brief tour -- with some but not all of its original members -- had never performed in the United States. With Death Vessel. At 6:30, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; $50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PRETTY GIRLS MAKE GRAVES, JASON LYTLE (Sunday) In the weeks before the concert giant Live Nation begins to put on big-ticket concerts at the McCarren Park Pool in Greenpoint, Brooklyn (its first there is Bloc Party on July 29), a number of smaller, scrappier promoters have been using the space -- a 50,000-square-foot public pool closed since 1984 -- for free shows. Sunday afternoon features Pretty Girls Make Graves, a Seattle band with a knack for angular, heartfelt melodies that cut through clouds of noise; and Mr. Lytle, the lead singer of Grandaddy, who is in town this weekend for a few appearances (see above). With Bon Savants. At 3 p.m., Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, thepoolparties.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RASPUTINA (Tonight) Rasputina is a charmingly improbable project: part Marie Antoinette, part metal. Three women who are cellists in corsets (as well as a drummer) sing about Transylvanian concubines as their music seesaws between elaborate chamber-music counterpoint and grunting hard-rock chords, complete with distortion. At 9, Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BUTCH WALKER AND THE LET'S GO OUT TONITES (Wednesday) Mr. Walker first revealed his fondness for muscular mid-1970's pop-rock and his mocking obsession with stardom as the leader of the Marvelous 3. Now on his own, he hasn't lost his ambition or his sense of irony. With Boys Like Girls and As Fast As. At 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; sold out. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>STEVEN BERNSTEIN'S MILLENNIAL TERRITORY ORCHESTRA (Tonight and Monday) This little big band, led by the irrepressible slide trumpeter Steven Bernstein, has a forthcoming album called ''MTO Volume 1'' (Sunnyside) that is full of signature touches, like effervescent swing arrangements and covers of hits by Prince and Stevie Wonder. Tonight at 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, at Seventh Avenue, Manhattan, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. Monday at 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $12. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL BLAKE'S EULIPION ORCHESTRA (Sunday) Mr. Blake, a resourceful tenor and soprano saxophonist, leads a group inspired partly by the classic work of composer-arrangers like Gil Evans and Yusef Lateef. Its ranks include Marcus Rojas on tuba, Steven Bernstein on trumpet, Peck Almond on woodwinds and G. Calvin Weston on drums. At 9:30 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DON BYRON QUARTET (Wednesday through July 30) Mr. Byron is justifiably known for his independent-minded concept albums -- his next one will shine a spotlight on the rhythm-and-blues saxophonist Junior Walker -- but he is, first and foremost, a daring clarinetist. He plays here with several longtime associates: the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the bassist Lonnie Plaxico and the drummer Billy Hart. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $25, $30 on July 28 and 29. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE CARDENAS TRIO (Monday) A guitarist with a modern harmonic concept and a clear yet supple style, Mr. Cardenas features his own compositions in this group, which includes the established rhythm team of Ben Allison on bass and Matt Wilson on drums. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CELEBRATION OF RAY BARRETTO &amp; HILTON RUIZ (Tuesday through July 30) ''Standards Rican-ditioned,'' recently issued on Zoho Music, was the final studio album of the conga virtuoso Ray Barretto. It also turned out to be the last recorded effort by the pianist Hilton Ruiz. Both were New York-born musicians of Puerto Rican heritage and were pillars of Latin jazz. This tribute, fittingly programmed as the culmination of Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola's monthlong Latin in Manhattan Festival, includes Mr. Barretto's son Chris Barretto, as well as a two more-established saxophonists, Sonny Fortune and David Sánchez. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m. with an 11:30 p.m. set July 28 and 29, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KARL DENSON TRIO (Monday) Funk and soul are at the heart of Mr. Denson's music, whether he's leading his signature band, Tiny Universe, or spotlighting his alto saxophone in this smaller unit, with Anthony Smith on keyboards and Brett Sanders on drums. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $25 at tables, $15 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ORRIN EVANS QUINTET (Tomorrow) Mr. Evans is a percussive pianist equally attuned to hard bop and hip-hop, and he often surrounds himself with rhythmically assertive sidemen. Here that company includes the saxophonists Abraham Burton and J. D. Allen, the bassist Luques Curtins and the drummer Donald Edwards. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL FORMANEK, TIM BERNE, TOM RAINEY (Tomorrow) These three -- respectively a bassist, an alto saxophonist and a drummer -- have worked together often over the years, usually under the leadership of Mr. Berne. Here they perform as a collective, though the order of billing seems intentional: Mr. Formanek will also lead a preconcert instrumental workshop from 4 to 6 p.m. The concert begins at 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, near Third Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, www.schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12, with a separate $25 charge for the afternoon workshop. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JON GORDON QUINTET (Tuesday) Mr. Gordon, an alto and soprano saxophonist, projects standards through a slightly warped lens, with the help of Mike Moreno on guitar, Aaron Goldberg on piano, Joe Martin on bass and Adam Cruz on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WYCLIFFE GORDON QUARTET (Wednesday) Mr. Gordon, a high-spirited trombonist and one of the most authoritative soloists in the Jazz and Lincoln Center Orchestra, leads a swing-minded small group in a free outdoor show. At 7 p.m., Grant's Tomb, 122nd Street and Riverside Drive, Manhattan, www.jazzmobile.org; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID HANEY TRIO +1 (Sunday) Mr. Haney is a pianist drawn to experimental settings, and he creates a promising one here, with the bassist Mike Bisio, the drummer Adam Lane and as a featured guest, the veteran trombonist Julian Priester. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRED HERSCH TRIO (Wednesday) Mr. Hersch, a pianist strongly associated with solo recitals, leads a trio for this outdoor performance, and not with his usual partners. But the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Eric McPherson should make an excellent rhythm section, and each has experience with Mr. Hersch's literate and cosmopolitan style. At 7 p.m., Madison Square Park, Fifth Avenue and 23rd Street, (212) 538-6667, www.madisonsquarepark.org; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE INBETWEENS (Tuesday) Based in Brooklyn but with origins in Boston at the New England Conservatory of Music, this exploratory trio consists of the guitarist Mike Gamble, the bassist Noah Jarrett and the drummer Conor Elmes. At 8 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JAZZ IN JULY (Tuesday through Thursday) A year ago the pianist Bill Charlap presided over his first season as artistic director of this venerable traditional jazz series. The new season, which started a few days ago, concludes next week with a professional nod to the bossa-nova auteur Antonio Carlos Jobim on Tuesday; a piano summit involving Barry Harris and Cedar Walton, among others, on Wednesday; and a songbook salute to Harold Arlen, featuring Mr. Charlap's mother, the accomplished singer Sandy Stewart, on Thursday. At 8 p.m. each night, 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500 or www.92y.org, $50.(Chinen)</p>
        <p>LAGE LUND QUINTET (Tonight) Mr. Lund is an introspective guitarist whose compositional style can suggest the pastoral warmth of Brian Blade's Fellowship. It's no accident that his quintet includes a member of Fellowship, the pianist and composer Jon Cowherd, along with the alto-saxophonist Will Vinson, the bassist Matt Penman and the drummer Rodney Green. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONNY MCCASLIN GROUP (Wednesday) As on ''Soar'' (Sunnyside), his most recent album, the tenor-saxophonist Donny McCaslin applies his extroverted style to a Latin American-inspired contemporary fusion, benefiting greatly from the contributions of the guitarist Ben Monder, the bassist Scott Colley and the drummer Antonio Sanchez. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MODULAR THEATER (Tonight) Collective improvisation is the mode and mission of this ensemble, comprising the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the alto saxophonist Peter Epstein, the vocalist Will Jennings, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Mark Ferber. At 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, near Third Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, www.schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>The MPTHREE (Wednesday) Mike Pride, an intense and industrious drummer, introduces his song cycle ''Sour Work Dreams'' with an adventurous if goofily titled ensemble that also features Ken Filiano on bass and Mary Halvorson on guitar. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www .thestonenyc .com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEVIN NORTON AND JOHN LINDBERG (Wednesday) Mr. Norton is a probing drummer, vibraphonist and composer, although not always in that order; Mr. Lindberg is a versatile and imaginative bassist who also has a way with orchestration. Their interplay promises to be engagingly multilayered. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GREG OSBY QUARTET (Tuesday through July 30) Mr. Osby is an alto saxophonist with a predilection for jagged edges, and yet he's squarely within the jazz tradition. His rhythm section here consists of the pianist Frank LoCrasto, the bassist Matt Brewer and the drummer Tommy Crane. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAN ASIAN CHAMBER JAZZ ENSEMBLE (Wednesday) Led by the violinist, violist and vocalist Meg Okura, this six-piece group explores a contemporary chamber music infused with multicultural echoes and an ethos of improvisation. At 7:30 p.m., Makor, 35 West 67th Street, near Central Park West, (212) 415-5500; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE PAVONE SHOW (Thursday) An evening organized around the compositions of the violist Jessica Pavone, with such like-minded explorers as the trumpeter Peter Evans, the saxophonists Matana Roberts and Matt Bauder and the percussionist Aaron Siegel. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIERNEY SUTTON (Wednesday through July 29) Ms. Sutton's clear, sweetly sonorous voice isn't inherently a jazz timbre, but she is irrefutably a jazz singer, as she proved on her fine recent album, ''I'm With the Band'' (Telarc), which was recorded at Birdland. 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CLARK TERRY BIG BAND (Tuesday through July 30) Mr. Terry's big-band experience is extensive: from the late-1940's on, he served successively in the orchestras of Count Basie, Duke Ellington and Quincy Jones. Here Mr. Terry, an octogenarian trumpet and flugelhorn player, applies a lifetime of wit and experience to his swinging ensemble. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592. Cover: $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HENRY THREADGILL'S ZOOID (Through Sunday) Mr. Threadgill, the august composer, saxophonist and flutist, has always nursed a fascination with timbre. He indulges it best with this superb ensemble, with Liberty Ellman on acoustic guitar, Dana Leong on cello, Jose Davila on tuba, Tarik Benbrahim on oud and Dafnis Prieto on drums. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with an additional midnight show tonight and tomorrow night, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAKE TORIYAMA QUARTET (Sunday) Mr. Toriyama divides his attention between drumming and computer programming in this modern-sounding ensemble, which features the alto saxophonist and bass clarinetist Andrew D'Angelo, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the guitarist Ben Monder. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'DON GIOVANNI,' 'AN EVENING OF OPERA ACTS' (Tonight through Sunday) The New York-born soprano Martina Arroyo, who had a long career at the Metropolitan Opera, has in recent years been immersed in the work of the Martina Arroyo Foundation, which provides training and performance opportunities for fledgling singers. This weekend the foundation presents a fully staged production of Mozart's ''Don Giovanni,'' directed by Laura Alley and conducted by Steven Crawford, and ''An Evening of Opera Acts,'' with excerpts from ''Don Pasquale,'' ''Madama Butterfly'' and ''Falstaff,'' conducted by Willie Anthony Waters, the general and artistic director of the Connecticut Opera Association. ''Don Giovanni,'' tonight at 7:30 and Sunday at 2:30 p.m.; opera acts, tomorrow at 7:30 p.m.; El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, East Harlem, (347) 677-3854; $15 in advance, $20 at the door, $10 for students and 65+. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tonight through Monday, and Thursday) The drive from New York City to the Glimmerglass Opera in Cooperstown, N.Y., typically takes four hours, no matter what route you choose. But it is worth the trip. The company's intimate, airy and well-equipped house is an ideal place to hear opera. And the imaginative productions, which often wind up at New York City Opera, are best seen in their tryouts at Cooperstown. Tomorrow brings the major event of the season: the premiere of Stephen Hartke's opera ''The Greater Good, or the Passion of Boule de Suif.'' Also playing this week are Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' in a production by Lillian Groag and Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia'' in a production by Leon Major. ''Pirates,'' tonight and Thursday night at 8; ''The Greater Good,'' tomorrow night at 8 and Monday at 1:30 p.m.; ''Barbiere,'' Sunday at 1:30 p.m.; Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255; $64 to $112 tonight through Sunday; $36 to $99 Monday and Thursday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'HANSEL AND GRETEL' (Monday and Thursday) Humperdinck's orchestration for his opera ''Hansel and Gretel'' is rich and Wagnerian. But in some performances it can overwhelm this lyrical fairy tale. Kathleen Kelly, the music director of the Berkshire Opera, has prepared a chamber orchestra arrangement for that company's new fully staged production of the opera, to be performed in a new English translation by Cori Ellison at the intimate and magnificently restored theater of the Mahaiwe Performing Arts Center in Great Barrington, Mass. Ms. Kelly, an assistant conductor and coach at the Met, conducts. At 8 p.m., (413) 442-0099; $35 to $85. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY OPERA THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Founded in 2002, the New Jersey Opera Theater is striving to become the state's preeminent opera company. Besides presenting performances, the company also offers master classes and educational outreach programs. The final weekend of its summer season features Mozart's ''Così Fan Tutte'' in a production by Albert Sherman, conducted by Steven Mosteller; and an intriguing double bill of Puccini's comedy ''Gianni Schicchi'' and ''Buoso's Ghost,'' a one-act work from 1996 by the composer Michael Ching. ''Buoso's Ghost'' picks up the story of the clever Schicchi where Puccini's opera leaves off. Steven Condy sings Schicchi in both works; James Caraher conducts. ''Schicchi'' and ''Buoso,'' tonight at 8 and Sunday afternoon at 2; ''Così,'' tomorrow night at 8; Berlind Theater at the McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., (609) 258-2787; $42 and $49. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BANG ON A CAN SUMMER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Each summer since 2002, New York's dynamic new music collective Bang on a Can has moved north for its annual ''Banglewood'' residency at Mass MoCA. Tomorrow is its All-Stars program, which includes the premiere of David Lang's ''Sunray,'' Michael Nyman's score to the classic silent film ''Manhatta,'' a new work by Don Byron and pieces by Annie Gosfield and Edward Ruchalski. At 8 p.m., 7 Marshall Street, North Adams, Mass., (413) 662-2111; $35. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'BEOWULF' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Benjamin Bagby's short, fast, one-man take on the Beowulf story is part of the Lincoln Center Festival. At 8:30, Drama Theater at La Guardia High School of Music and Art and Performing Arts, Amsterdam Avenue at 65th Street, (212) 721-6500; $45. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Christine Brewer (Tomorrow) This fine soprano will sing Wagner's ''Wesendonck Lieder'' in the intimate barn at the Mount Lebanon Shaker Village, as part of the Tannery Pond Concerts series. She will be accompanied by the pianist Craig Rutenberg in an eclectic program that also includes songs by Richard Strauss, Joseph Marx, John Carter, Harold Arlen, Samuel Barber and Edwin McArthur. At 8 p.m., New Lebanon, N.Y., (888) 820-9441; $25 and 30. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL KEYBOARD INSTITUTE AND FESTIVAL (Tonight through Thursday) During the slow summer months, concertgoers who love the piano have plenty to keep them happy during the two weeks of this series at Mannes College, directed by the pianist Jerome Rose. Tonight Leslie Howard explores ''The Russian Romantic Piano Sonata'' with works by Tchaikovsky, Glazunov, Rachmaninoff and Anton Rubinstein. There are also recitals by the veteran pianists Fou Ts'ong (Tuesday) and Philippe Bianconi (Wednesday). At 8 p.m., Mannes College, a division of the New School for Music, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 580-0210, Ext. 4858; $20 for evening recitals, $15 for master classes, $10 for afternoon concerts. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>MARLBORO MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tomorrow and Sunday) Public concerts are the byproduct of this intensive-study chamber-music retreat. Beethoven and Brahms quintets and a Dvorak trio are offered Saturday at 8:30. It's Mozart, Shostakovich and more Beethoven Sunday at 2:30, Marlboro Music School and Festival, Marlboro, Vt., (802) 254-2394; $15 to $30; $5 for canopy areas. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* MAVERICK CONCERTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) This concert series near Woodstock, N.Y., offers its performances in an open-backed barn that allows the sounds of nature to mingle with the music. Tomorrow, Trio Solisti plays music by Gershwin and Paul Schoenfield, as well as an arrangement of Mussorgsky's ''Pictures at an Exhibition.'' On Sunday, the Pacific String Quartet plays Shostakovich's searing Quartet No. 8, Britten's Quartet No. 2 and Mozart's ''Dissonant'' Quartet. Tomorrow at 6 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m., Maverick Concert Hall, Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217; $20; $5 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>THOMAS MEGLIORANZA (Monday) Mr. Meglioranza, a young baritone who is fast making a name for himself singing a wide repertory, appears in the annual River to River Festival, accompanied by the able Reiko Uchida. Mr. Meglioranza's intriguingly eclectic program ranges from Schubert lieder to works by Derek Bermel and Milton Babbitt. At 7:30 p.m., Schimmel Center for the Arts, 3 Spruce Street, near Park Row, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free, but tickets are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NORFOLK CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow night) Bach and Kurtag occupy tonight's concert by the Keller Quartet. Tomorrow it's all Mozart, with instrumental duos, songs and arias. At 8, Ellen Battell Stoeckel Estate, Routes 44 and 272, Norfolk, Conn., (860) 542-3000; $15 to $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>S.E.M. ENSEMBLE (Tuesday) The composer Petr Kotik's daring S.E.M. Ensemble performs the works of established and emerging composers in John Zorn's avant-garde performance space, the Stone. The 8 p.m. set features Reiko Füting's ''Leaving Without/Palimpsest'' for piano and clarinet, Sam Hillmer's '' the night sweats and the day sweats ,'' Anne Guthrie's ''Margaret or Olivier'' and Morton Feldman's ''Why Patterns?'' The 10 p.m. program includes Julius Eastman's ''Piano 2,'' La Monte Young's ''Composition #7 1960'' and John Cage's ''Ryoanji.'' Avenue C at Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; $10. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* SUMMERGARDEN (Sunday) The student ensembles from the Juilliard School who play these concerts tend to be devoted to contemporary music and play it with virtuosity and polish. The works, all new to New York, include Pablo Ortiz's ''Falling From Grace,'' Betty Olivero's ''Bashra'v,'' Alberto Colla's ''Fugue on Thin Ice,'' Philip Carlsen's ''Landscape With Ladyslipper,'' Wen Deqing's ''Traces II'' and Martin Butler's ''Jazz Machines.'' At 8 p.m., Museum of Modern Art Sculpture Garden, West 54th Street between Fifth Avenue and Avenue of the Americas, (212) 708-9491; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday) With all the hoopla over James Levine's return to conducting, don't forget it's still the Mozart year. Tanglewood and Mr. Levine, leading the Boston Symphony Orchestra, remember this weekend. Tonight it's Mozart with the singer Susan Graham and the pianist Richard Goode. Tomorrow it's ''Don Giovanni'' in concert, and on Sunday more Mozart. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Lenox, Mass., (866) 266-1200; $18 to $87 tonight, with $8.50 lawn tickets; $18 to $87 tomorrow and Sunday, with $17 lawn tickets. (Holland)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>CAPACITOR: 'DIGGING IN THE DARK'  (Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday) From San Francisco, for hard-core fans of dances about geology. Call first to make sure the theater fans have been turned on. Through July 30. Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, between Eighth and Ninth Avenues, Manhattan, (212) 352-3101 or www.capacitor.org; $35.(Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* CELEBRATE BROOKLYN: RONALD K. BROWN/EVIDENCE (Tomorrow) The company will perform three works, including ''Grace,'' created for the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater by Mr. Brown, whose African-influenced modern-dance choreography has had a major influence on dance today. 8 p.m. Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-8999 or www.prospectpark.org; $3 suggested contribution. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHASHAMA OASIS FESTIVAL 2006 (Today and Sunday) Artists of all disciplines -- some, we suspect, wildly undisciplined in the grand tradition of Chashama productions -- will perform in a Midtown window and outdoors. Today from noon to 1:30 p.m. and 5:30 to 7 p.m., Chashama window performance, 217 East 42nd Street, between Second and Third Avenues, Manhattan. Sunday from 3 to 4 p.m. and 5 to 6 p.m., Red Shade Plaza, Riverside Park South, 62nd Street at the Hudson River, Manhattan, (212) 391-8151 or www.chashama.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>COMPANY C CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) A 12-member ballet troupe from San Francisco with an eclectic repertory presents works by Twyla Tharp, Patrick Corbin, Alexander Proia and its director, Charles Anderson. 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $25, $20 students and 65+. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>DANCE TACTICS PERFORMANCE GROUP BY KEITH THOMPSON (Thursday) The company makes its formal debut with dances choreographed by Keith A. Thompson, who performed with Trisha Brown, and set to music by Pergolesi, Ryuichi Sakamoto, Robert Een and Nate Aldrich. Through July 29. 7:30 p.m. Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 924-0077 or www.dtw.org; $12, $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DECADANCETHEATER (Thursday) This all-female hip-hop group from Brooklyn won plaudits for its reworking of Stravinsky's ''Firebird'' two years ago. Now its members are trying their hand at a 12th-century Japanese ghost story. But not to worry: there will be a live D.J. 8 p.m. Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street; (212) 334-7479. Thursday benefit tickets begin at $50.(Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>HEIDI DUCKLER COLLAGE DANCE THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Duckler is known as Los Angeles's ''queen of site-specific performance,'' the press release says. This production of ''Laundromatinee,'' part of the Lower Manhattan Cultural Council's Sitelines performances, may well show she deserves claim to the title. It involves dancers spinning in dryers and hanging from clotheslines, then -- this sounds like the best bit -- removing their clothes to sing ''Stand By Your Man.'' 8.30 p.m., Laundromat, 168 Elizabeth Street, between Spring and Kenmare Streets; (212) 219-9401, www.lmcc.net/sitelines; free. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday) Dance companies from Finland, Spain, India and Denmark occupy the week. The highly regarded Finnish choreographer Tero Saarinen and his company, accompanied by Shaker vocalists, will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend. They will be followed there on Wednesday and Thursday (and next weekend) by Eva Yerbabuena's Ballet Flamenco from Spain. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, Nrityagram, a highly regarded Indian ensemble specializing in Odissi dance, plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is the Danish Dance Theater, billed as that country's leading modern-dance ensemble. Mr. Saarinen's company, tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 p.m. and 8 p.m., and Sunday at 2 p.m.; $50. Yerbabuena, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, Shawn Theater, $50. Nrityagram tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15, tomorrow at 2:15 p.m. and Sunday at 5 p.m.; .$24. Danish Dance Theater, Thursday at 8:15 p.m., Duke Theater, $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, seniors 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions are at jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>PAULA HUNTER (Tonight and tomorrow) Ms. Hunter will perform ''I Am Karen Finley,'' an absurdist performance solo, as a free dance installation in a window in the Theater District. 5 and 7:30 p.m., Chashama, 112 West 44th Street, (212) 391-8151 or chashama.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL (Wednesday) The ubiquitous Noche Flamenca will open this festival, with dancing by Soledad Barrio, Alejandro Granados and Juan Ogalla. 8 p.m. Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows, Queens, (718) 760-0064 or www.QueensTheatre.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) The Batsheva Dance Company continues its performances of Ohad Naharin's new ''Telophaza'' tonight and tomorrow night at 8 at the New York State Theater at Lincoln Center; $25 to $65. Also this weekend, Saburo Teshigawa, the Japanese master solo dancer, is performing his new ''Bones in Pages'' tonight and tomorrow night at 8 at the Rose Theater, 60th Street and Broadway, at Columbus Circle; $20 to $50. Next week the San Francisco Ballet performs at the New York State Theater starting Tuesday. The opening-night gala, at 8, includes solos, pas de deux and excerpts from repertory dances by choreographers, including Jerome Robbins; the company director, Helgi Tomasson; Lar Lubovitch; and Yuri Possokhov. The San Francisco Ballet's production of Mark Morris's ''Sylvia'' is scheduled for Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; $30 to $75. And Yasmeen Godder and the Bloody Bench Players will perform Ms. Godder's new ''Strawberry Cream and Gunpowder'' on Thursday at 7 p.m. at the La Guardia Drama Theater, Amsterdam Avenue and 65th Street. Through July 29; $35. For reservations and information on all performances: (212) 721-6500 or www.lincolncenter.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW GENERATION DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Company founder and director Dardo Galletto mixes ballet, tango and modern dance and his ''Black-White Tango,'' whose cast includes guest dancers from American Ballet Theater and ''Forever Tango.'' Through July 30. Thursday at 8 p.m. Henry Street Settlement, 466 Grand Street, Lower East Side; (646) 342-9910; $30, $45 for opening-night gala. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>*NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Saturday, Sunday and Thursday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of last winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, is winding down its two-month run at the intimate Theater 80, which will end July 30. Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 and 5 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Theater 80, 80 St. Mark's Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45.(Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Tonight and tomorrow, Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless, but enormously popular for people of all ages. Three programs alternate for the run ending Aug. 12. Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday at 8 p.m. and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org, $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>'RIVER DEEP: A TRIBUTE TO TINA TURNER' (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Gabrielle Lansner pays tribute to Ms. Turner, who is played by Pat Hall, in a multimedia production set to music by Philip Hamilton. Through July 29. Tonight and Tuesday through Thursday at 8 p.m.; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m. Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton; (212) 279-4200 or gabriellelansner.com; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SUMMER IN THE SQUARE (Wednesday) As part of the Union Square Park's outdoor performance series, Performance Space 122 will present excerpts from the coming season. Saar Harari, whose ''Herd of Bulls'' was enthusiastically received last fall, will perform a section from ''Moopim''; the Palissimo dance company will perform Pavel Zustiak's ''Le Petit Mort''; and Chris Yon will dance with Taryn Griggs in the mysteriously titled ''Elephant (Terrible) Assisted Suicide [in ought 6].'' 6 p.m., Union Square Park, East 14th to East 17th Street, Manhattan; free. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* 'TAP CITY 2006' (Tonight and tomorrow) This spirited summer festival suggests that camaraderie and a sense of community are not dead in tap dance, on stage and in the audience. It includes two programs. ''Tap and Song,'' a celebration of traditional vaudeville, comedy and classic song-and-dance, stars the irrepressible Tony Waag, the festival's founder and director. He will be joined by a generous roster of artists, including the veteran tapper Mable Lee, the German Tap and Tray duo, the chic two-woman Tapage and the hoedown tapper Nate Cooper. ''Tap Forward'' features familiar tap soloists, cutting-edge types and up-and-comers. ''Tap and Song'' is tonight at 7 and 9:30 p.m.; ''Tap Forward'' is tomorrow at 7 and 9:30 p.m., the Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street; (212) 239-6200 or www.atdf.org; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>THOMAS-ORTIZ DANCE (Tonight and tomorrow) Ted Thomas and Frances Ortiz combine urban athleticism and Latin sensuality in choreographic explorations of socially relevant themes. 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 924-0077; $15, $25. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* CASSIE TERMAN AND SHINICHI MOMO KOGA (Tonight and tomorrow) Ms. Terman and Mr. Koga create a world full of humor and pathos out of empty space and perfectly attuned physical-theater skills. 8 p.m., Center for Remembering and Sharing, 123 Fourth Avenue, between 12th and 13th Streets, Manhattan; (212) 352-3101; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YOUNG DANCEMAKERS COMPANY (Thursday) These choreographers -- New York City high school students chosen by audition for a summer intensive in dance technique, performing and making dances -- know how to put on a very good show. It's free, too. Their tour of city sites continues through Aug. 3. Thursday at 2 p.m. Stern Auditorium, Mount Sinai Hospital, Fifth Avenue at 100th Street, Upper East Side; (718) 329-7250 or www.ecfs.org/ydc.asp; reservations required. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,'  through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedeker's guides, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>DAHESH MUSEUM OF ART: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Sept. 3. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION : 'JEAN-ÉTIENNE LIOTARD (1702-1789): SWISS MASTER,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including the young Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 3 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. (212) 535-7710. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MET: 'TREASURES OF SACRED MAYA KINGS,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. And wait till you see the painted ceramic vessel known as the ''Dazzler Vase,'' with its red and green patterns like jade on fire, you'll understand its name. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY AND MUSEUM: 'MASTERWORKS FROM THE MORGAN,'  through Sept. 10. Almost three years after closing to build an expansion, the Morgan is back and brilliant. What's new: Renzo Piano's four-story glass-and-steel court, a sort of giant solarium with see-through elevators; two good-size second-floor galleries; and a neat little strongbox of an enclosure, called the Cube, for reliquaries and altar vessels. What's not new: almost everything in this exhibition, which fills every gallery with mini-exhibitions of master drawings and musical manuscripts, as well as illuminated gospels and historical and literary autograph manuscripts from the Brontës to Bob Dylan. 225 Madison Avenue, at East 36th Street, (212) 685-0008 or www.themorgan.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF BIBLICAL ART: 'THE WORD ON THE STREET: THE PHOTOGRAPHS OF LARRY RACIOPPO,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: HERZOG &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer. (212) 708-9400. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN : CHIHULY AT THE NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDENS, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in formal reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY: LEGACIES: CONTEMPORARY ARTISTS REFLECT ON SLAVERY, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society. 170 Central Park West, (212) 873-3400. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 CONTEMPORARY ART CENTER: 'INTO ME/OUT OF ME,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* THE WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART : 'FULL HOUSE: VIEWS OF THE WHITNEY'S COLLECTION AT 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. If ''Full House'' is about one thing, it is about discord, about how harmonious America never was. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* SARAH SZE: 'CORNER PLOT' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* HANS BELLMER: ' PETITES ANATOMIES, PETITES IMAGES.'  This extraordinary show of more than 70 images takes you beyond the surface obsessions of Bellmer's girl-crazed art to unveil some of his working processes as a sculptor, installation artist, photographer, editor and hand-colorist whose preference for small scale intensifies the voyeuristic nature of his art. Ubu Gallery, 416 East 59th Street, (212) 753-4444, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* RUDY BURCKHARDT: 'NEW YORK PAINTINGS' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, (212) 262-5050, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>GEORGE HERMS Starting out as a beatnik in the 1950's, Mr. Herms has been creating and exhibiting his richly poetic assemblages of grungy found materials in California, his home state, for more than a half century. This show's eight works, from 1965 to 2002, variously call to mind Ernst, Duchamp, Cornell and Rauschenberg, but they have as well their own spiritually generous, heartfelt mix of hermetic imagination and Whitman-esque populism. Franklin Parrasch, 20 West 57th Street, (212) 246-5360, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>* 'A FOUR-DIMENSIONAL BEING WRITES POETRY ON A FIELD WITH SCULPTURES' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West Second Street, (212) 243-0200, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>JOE BIEL With an exacting illustrator's touch, Mr. Biel draws large, dreamily perverse images of children, like the one of a girl with rabbit ears and a whip peeking out of a cardboard box and the knife-wielding boy crouching atop a pile of rubble and examining a bone he found. Goff + Rosenthal, 537B West 23rd Street, (212) 675-0461, through Aug. 12. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* CRG PRESENTS: KLAUS VON NICHTSSAGEND GALLERY Including works by Liz Luisada, Samuel Lopes and Thomas Ovilsen, this group show of work by 17 emerging artists definitely has its moments, but the strongest impression is made by the gallery-within-a-gallery effect resulting from the re-creation of the storefront facade and reception desk of the small Von Nichtssagend Gallery in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. CRG Gallery, 535 East 22nd Street, (212) 229-2766, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Material Abuse' Unconventional uses of nontraditional materials include Shinique Smith's massive bale of all-white clothing; Michael Arcega's fleet of 300 tiny, balsa-wood tanks; Richard Klein's assemblage made from 10 years' worth of blown-out light-bulb filaments; Jean Shin's stacks of prescription pill bottles; Ray Beldner's dust-covered assemblages made of ordinary objects stolen from other people; and a star-and-stripe-patterned bikini made of map tacks by Devorah Sperber. Caren Golden, 539 West 23rd Street, (212) 727-8304, through Aug. 4. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Money Changes Everything' A show of artworks made at least partly out of actual money: dollar bills, mostly, but Iraqi dinar notes, too. Schroeder Romero, 637 West 27th Street, (212) 630-0722, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Photography Is Not An Art!' More than 100 examples of vernacular, often anonymous photographs from fields of medicine, forensics, space exploration and advertising prove that nonart photography is often as interesting as the fine-art variety. Alan Klotz, 511 West 25th Street, (212) 741-4764, through Aug. 19. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Vivan Sundaram: 'Re-Take of Amrita' The photographs in this beautiful, time-haunted show are all of past generations of the Indian artist Vivan Sundaram's family, and include images of his aunt, the modernist painter Amrita Sher-Gil (1913-1941). Thanks to digital technology, those generations mix in logically impossible combinations. The resulting pictures embody the past the way it survives in the mind: edited, layered, compressed, as if in a dream. Sepia International, 148 West 24th Street, 11th floor, (212) 645-9444, through July 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* THE NAME OF THIS SHOW IS NOT GAY ART NOW Characterized by its organizer, the artist Jack Pierson, as an ode to the passing of ''the notion of Gay Art,'' this exhibition embraces the work of about 60 artists (gay, straight and otherwise) to create a cacophonous celebration and suggest that everyone is a little bit gay, if they are lucky. Paul Kasmin Gallery, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212) 563-4474, closes today. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ALL THIS INTIMACY' In previews; opens Thursday. A romantically ambitious poet balances relationships with three women in this new play by Rajiv Joseph. Presented by Second Stage Theater (1:45). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway; (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' In previews; opens Tuesday. Based on the lives of the five cast members, this play, which incorporates dance and song, is about growing up in apartheid-era South Africa (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village; (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'INDIAN BLOOD' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Aug. 9. Primary Stages presents A. R. Gurney's new comedy about a rebellious American Indian boy coming of age in the 1940's. Mark Lamos directs (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL Through July 30. This always-buzzed-about summer showcase includes ''DruidSynge,'' the complete works of John Millington Synge (see below), and ''Grendel,'' an opera directed by Julie Taymor. Sites in and around Lincoln Center; (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>MIDTOWN INTERNATIONAL THEATER FESTIVAL Through Aug. 6. The seventh annual showcase often gets lost in the shuffle, despite its large and diverse collection of shows. There should be more than 60 productions this season, at four locations on 36th Street. Schedules and information; (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE HOUSE IN TOWN'  A wan new drama by Richard Greenberg about an American marriage slowly imploding in the days before the country's economy did the same, more suddenly and spectacularly, in 1929. A miscast Jessica Hecht stars as Amy Hammer, a well-to-do housewife sliding into despair as her remote husband looks on in frustration. Doug Hughes's production is pretty but desultory, as is Mr. Greenberg's typically eloquent but atypically empty writing (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diazand Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00).Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this old comedy from the 1930's, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). Bank Street Theater, 155 Bank Street, West Village, (212) 868-4444.(Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th-century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SUSAN AND GOD' The Mint Theater Company's fine revival of Rachel Crothers's 1937 comedy about religion, career and family features Leslie Hendrix of ''Law &amp; Order,'' excellent in the role of Susan. Jonathan Bank directs (2:20). The Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, third floor, Clinton, (212) 315-0231. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'TREASON' The poet Ezra Pound was a repellent fellow, judging from this play by Sallie Bingham: racist, anti-Semitic, eager to exploit the affections of the women who loved him. Just why women were drawn to him is never clear, but the play is thoughtful, and the acting, especially by Philip Pleasants as Pound, is superb (2:10). Perry Street Theater, 31 Perry Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'CHEKHOV &amp; MARIA'  Jovanka Bach's final play is a touching, beautifully acted if sometimes slow-paced study of Anton Chekhov's near-final days and his relationship with his sister, who cared for him (2:00). Barrow Group Theater, 312 West 36th Street; (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'FOOD FOR FISH' Adam Szymkowicz's fabulously weird and weirdly fabulous new comedy fools around with cross-dressing, suicidal writers and Chekhovian characters who long for New Jersey (2:00). Kraine Theater, 85 East Fourth Street, between Second and Third Avenues, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' A dancing encyclopedia of clichés set to music by Earth, Wind &amp; Fire. Numbing (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street; (212) 307-4100; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MANHATTAN MADCAPS of 1924' A not-very-madcap story is indeed included, but this is essentially a revue made of up of Rodgers and Hart songs, many of them fairly obscure. Better singing voices in the cast might help show them off to fuller advantage; as it is, the main attraction is a trio of songs with unfamiliar lyrics, but a very familiar tune: the one that, on the fourth try, became ''Blue Moon'' (1:20). Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400; closing Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SCHOOL OF THE AMERICAS' José Rivera, who wrote the screenplay for ''The Motorcycle Diaries,'' penned this rickety piece of historical speculation about the final two days of Che Guevara's life (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closing Sunday.(Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SHAKESPEARE IS DEAD' Orran Farmer's two-character drama about a struggling playwright and a drug-addicted actress-stripper is well-meaning, but tedious and often trite (1:00). Paradise Factory, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TROUBLE IN PARADISE' Ernst Lubitsch's 1932 film comedy about a con man, the con woman he loves and a wealthy Parisian widow lives again as a giddy, good-looking, quietly amusing play (1:30). Hudson Guild Theater, 441 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'LEONARD COHEN: I'M YOUR MAN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) This enthralling documentary combines pieces of an extended interview with Mr. Cohen, the Canadian singer-songwriter, poet and author, now 71, with a tribute concert at the Sydney Opera House in January 2005. Nick Cave, Rufus Wainwright, Kate and Anna McGarrigle, Martha Wainwright and Antony are among the featured performers. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'EDMOND' (R, 76 minutes) William H. Macy gives what may be the performance of his career in the faithful screen adaptation of David Mamet's raw, epithet-spattered spiritual fable about a buttoned-up milquetoast who heeds his inner demons and plummets into free fall; hateful and unforgettable. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'EXCELLENT CADAVERS' (No rating, 92 minutes, in English and Italian) Based on the book by Alexander Stille, this tough, brisk documentary follows Mr. Stille to Italy, where he reconstructs the recent history of the Italian mafia, focusing on the careers of two courageous prosecutors who took on organized crime and the political system that protected it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'GABRIELLE' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haute bourgeoisie Parisian marriage, circa 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-age white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KILL YOUR IDOLS' (No rating, 71 minutes) S. A. Crary's glib, unfocused music documentary examines the New York No Wave scene of the late 1970's -- an offshoot of punk, the anti-New Wave -- when the music was noisy (and genuinely noncommercial) and the clothes were black (and genuinely secondhand). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'MINI'S FIRST TIME' (R, 91 minutes) Yet another poor little rich girl tends to her festering inner wounds by becoming one of Southern California's children of the damned. Nikki Reed stars alongside the slumming likes of Alec Baldwin, Carrie-Anne Moss, Jeff Goldblum and Luke Wilson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LA MOUSTACHE' (No rating, 86 minutes, in French) Emmanuel Carrière's psychological mystery prepares you to bask in one of those sexy, bittersweet marital comedies that are a hallmark of sophisticated French cinema. Then, by degrees, it subverts those expectations to spiral down a rabbit hole of ambiguity and doubt. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PEACEFUL WARRIOR' (PG-13, 120 minutes) As ludicrous as the title promises yet supremely unembarrassed, this New Age enlightenment parable has its heart in the right place, but a mind of corny mush. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'PIRATES OF THE CARIBBEAN: DEAD MAN'S CHEST' Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ROAD TO GUANTÁNAMO' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom's powerful, slippery new film mixes documentary and fictional techniques to tell the true story of three British Muslims imprisoned by the United States government in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'RUSSIAN DOLLS' (No rating, 129 minutes, in English, Russian, French and Spanish) The sequel to the international hit ''L'Auberge Espagnole'' belongs to a long line of airy French films that induce a pleasant buzz of Euro-envy. Like its forerunner, it is a generational group portrait of young, smart, sexy, well-educated Europeans at work and play filmed in a style that might be called Truffaut Lite. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'71 FRAGMENTS OF A CHRONOLOGY OF CHANCE' (No rating, 95 minutes) This 1994 film from that great provocateur Michael Haneke follows a handful of seemingly unrelated characters, all of whom -- perhaps by chance, perhaps by divine intervention, though mostly through artistic contrivance -- have the grave misfortune to be in an Austrian bank when a student starts unloading his revolver. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'WAIST DEEP' (R, 97 minutes) Tyrese Gibson plays an ex-convict trying to rescue his son from ruthless criminal kidnappers in this far-from-terrible B movie, directed with style and heart by Vondie Curtis Hall. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WASSUP ROCKERS' (R, 105 minutes) The latest provocation from the director and photographer Larry Clark follows a group of teenage Hispanic skateboarders from South Central Los Angeles on a 24-hour adventure that takes them from one hell (the inner city) to another (decadent Beverly Hills) and back. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. ( Dargis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>YOU, ME AND DUPREE' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>GREAT VILLAINS IN CINEMA (Through July 30) BAMcinématek is honoring movie bad guys, from Dracula to Michael Corleone. This weekend's features include ''White Heat'' (1949), starring James Cagney as a psychotic killer with a mother fixation; and ''A Clockwork Orange'' (1971), with Malcolm McDowell as a hooligan with a taste for ultraviolence. BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) A 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962), one of the first directors to win an Oscar (for ''Seventh Heaven''), continues at the Museum of the Moving Image. This weekend's films include the western ''Until They Get Me'' (1917); ''Lazybones'' (1925), starring Buck Jones as a single father; and the original ''Humoresque'' (1920). 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HISTORIC HARLEM PARKS FESTIVAL: THROUGH AFRICAN EYES AND PRIZED PIECES (Through Aug. 3) This fifth annual outdoor festival continues Wednesday night with Zézé Gamboa's ''Hero'' (2004), about a homeless veteran of the civil war in Angola. Thursday night's feature is ''Beyond Beats and Rhymes'' (2006), Byron Hurt's study of sex roles in hip-hop and rap. Jackie Robinson Park, the basketball courts at 150th Street and Bradhurst Avenue, (212) 352-1720; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues Sunday and Tuesday with ''The Bad Sleep Well'' (1960), which places the ''Hamlet'' story in postwar corporate Japan. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>PREMIERE BRAZIL! (Through Sunday) The Museum of Modern Art's fourth annual program of contemporary Brazilian film concludes this weekend with the screening of seven features. They include ''If I Were You'' (2006), Daniel Filho's satire about sex-role stereotypes, and ''Black Orpheus'' (1959), Marcel Camus's classic retelling of the Greek legend, set at Carnival in Rio de Janeiro. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, 11 West 53rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SCANNERS: THE 2006 NEW YORK VIDEO FESTIVAL (Through July 30) The Film Society of Lincoln Center's 15th annual showcase of new media begins on Wednesday. The first offerings include ''The Magic Bus,'' an 80-minute program of shorts done in mixtape style; and ''Believe the Hype,'' a tribute to the music-video director Hype Williams. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DICKEY BETTS AND GREAT SOUTHERN (Wednesday) Kicked out of the Allman Brothers, a band he founded, the guitarist Dickey Betts wasted no time in going back on tour with his own group. His chiming, symmetrical guitar solos and the weary but amiable voice from songs like ''Blue Skies'' are intact, and he may even have something to prove. With Kenny Wayne Shepherd. At 9:30 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; $52. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>MARY J. BLIGE (Tonight) Mary J. Blige has long been emoting through hip-hop and soul for ''all my sisters, my troubled sisters.'' Her latest, ''The Breakthrough'' (Geffen), also finds her in a duet with U2. (She steals the show.) With Jaheim and LeToya. At 8, Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $59.50 to $129.50. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRAND NEW (Thursday) This Long Island emo band made a quantum leap with its second album three years ago, from whiny and unchallenging breakup songs to tangles of explosive melody with brooding, sometimes horrific lyrics. What the band will come up with on the as-yet-unscheduled album No. 3 is a subject of intense speculation among fans, who quickly snatched up all tickets for this tour. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JIM CAMPILONGO, JESSE HARRIS, MIKE VIOLA (Monday) Just another night at the Living Room, a plain Lower East Side cabaret that puts on one guitar-cradling singer-songwriter after another, some of them world-class. Mr. Campilongo is a well-traveled guitar whiz who plays with Norah Jones in her country band the Little Willies; here he leads his Electric Trio. Jesse Harris, who wrote Ms. Jones's hit ''Don't Know Why,'' sings in the graceful and guileless manner of Paul Simon and James Taylor when on his own. Mike Viola, jumping from piano to guitar, sings strident power-pop with some jagged wit. At 9 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* CAT POWER (Tuesday) For her most recent album, ''The Greatest'' (Matador), Chan Marshall, the superbly rueful singer known as Cat Power, recorded with a group of veteran Memphis soul players, yielding some of the most stirring -- and happiest -- music of her career. Performing solo, she is spellbindingly intense and mercurial. At 8 p.m., Hiro Ballroom at the Maritime Hotel, 371 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-4300; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CHEB I SABBAH (Tomorrow) Indian devotional music meets the beat, now and then, in the music of DJ Cheb I Sabbah, who swirls together various styles into heady meditations. He is joined on vocals by the singer Riffat Salamat Sultana, daughter of the Pakistani singer Ustad Salamat Ali Khan. At 7 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package.(Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>DON CABALLERO (Tonight) In the mid-1990's, Don Caballero, from Pittsburgh, was one of a handful of overachieving guitar bands whose knotty, laser-precise and deliberately undanceable instrumentals exemplified the fittingly named subgenre math-rock. The band broke up six years ago, but its drummer, Damon Che, has repopulated it with new players; its new album, ''World Class Listening Problem'' (Relapse), suggests that there was more to the old group's appeal than just math. With Blind Idiot God, Alger Hiss, Houston McCoy and the Victoria Lucas. At 8, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006; $13. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>'DOT DASH YEAR IV' (Thursday) Each summer Dot Dash, a little concert promoter in Brooklyn devoted to punk and garage-rock, throws a festival with some big-deal reunions -- big deals in the small and passionate world of garage-rock, anyway. This year its three-day series begins on Thursday with the return of the Dicks, a Texas band from the early 1980's that sang ragged and churlish complaints with titles like ''Hate the Police.'' Also on the bill are the Marked Men, the Carbonas and Live Fast Die. The highlight of the festival will be an appearance by Rocket From the Tombs on July 29. At 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236; $17. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EARLY MAN, BAD WIZARD, 3 INCHES OF BLOOD (Tuesday) The best retro bands do not just conjure up an old artist or even a specific era, but freely toy with their influences to suggest a past that never quite existed. Three Inches of Blood updates the galloping, swords-and-goblins rock of early-1980's groups like Iron Maiden and Manowar with harsh streaks of violence that recall later death-metal. Early Man, on its debut album, ''Closing In'' (Matador), begins in the comforting mud of Black Sabbath and ends airborne, with a speed and control that comes down from Metallica. Also on the bill is Bad Wizard, whose plodding re-creations of Grand Funk Railroad and Kiss illustrate a less imaginative kind of retro-rock. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MELISSA ETHERIDGE (Monday through Wednesday) Love takes on heroic dimensions in the songs of Melissa Etheridge. She puts her own mark on the brawny guitar riffs and raspy-voiced melodies of 1980's heartland rock, as adoring audiences sing along. At 8 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $39.50 to $104.50. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>GOLDEN SMOG (Wednesday) Even heartsick alt-country has its celebrity supergroups. Golden Smog includes Jeff Tweedy of Wilco, Dan Murphy of Soul Asylum, Gary Louris and Marc Perlman of the Jayhawks, and Kraig Johnson of Run Westy Run. Opening the show is David Poe, a singer and guitarist, whose wit and sparkle come through largely between songs. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOLD STEADY (Thursday) Like the E Street Band fronted by Shane MacGowan of the Pogues, the Hold Steady -- from Brooklyn, though with Minneapolis origins -- plays bare-knuckled guitar-rock while its singer, Craig Finn, free-associates about religion and sex in a boozy snarl. ''I guess I heard about original sin,'' he growls. ''I heard the dude blamed the chick.'' At 7 p.m., Castle Clinton National Monument, Battery Park, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789. Free; tickets available at 5 p.m., two per person. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JONATHAN KANE (Tomorrow) John Lee Hooker meets La Monte Young in the droning, bluesy incantations of Mr. Kane, a mainstay in the downtown avant-garde scene who has played drums with Swans, Rhys Chatham and Gary Lucas. He has a drummer's sense of steady dynamic development and an unapologetic love of noise. He plays two shows. At 2 p.m., with Dragons of Zynth, Home and Taiko Masala, East River Amphitheater, East River Park, south of Delancey Street, Lower East Side, ermp.org; free. At 9 p.m., with Golden Tongues, Mahi Mahi and Ambitious Orchestra, Sin-é, 150 Attorney Street, Lower East Side, (212) 388-0077; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JASON LYTLE (Tomorrow and Monday) In Grandaddy, Mr. Lytle sang as if he were Neil Young trapped inside a computer chip: with a voice tiny and yet infinite, yearning to be fully human yet stuck within the strictures of the information age. Grandaddy recently released its final album, ''Just Like the Fambly Cat'' (V2), but it is an unsatisfying epitaph; fans will crowd these rare solo shows for hints of a new direction. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Monday at 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MALDITA VECINDAD, KONONO NO. 1, DAARA J (Sunday) What do a ska-flavored Mexican hard-rock band, a Congolese group that makes trance music from amplified thumb pianos and a Senegalese rap trio have in common? Not much except that they can all be lumped into the world-music category, however puzzlingly. Maldita Vecindad paints its ska rhythms with ominous, distorted metal. Konono No. 1 titled one album ''Congotronics,'' an apt term for its polyrhythmic bubblings of amplified likembés -- hand-held thumb pianos made from thin strips of medal. Daara J speed-raps in at least four languages: English, French, Spanish and Wolof. At 3 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. Maldita Vecindad also plays Sunday night at S.O.B.'s, and Konono No. 1 plays there on Monday. At 8 and 10:30, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $22 in advance, $25 at the door on Sunday; $25 in advance, $28 at the door on Monday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THOMAS MAPFUMO AND THE BLACKS UNLIMITED (Tuesday) A musical pioneer with a rebel's courage, Thomas Mapfumo made music for the revolutionaries who unseated the white-ruled government from what was Rhodesia and is now Zimbabwe. The music transferred the brisk patterns of traditional thumb-piano music to guitar; the words sometimes sent coded messages. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>JOHN MAYALL AND THE BLUESBREAKERS (Tonight) In the 1960's John Mayall ran the premier finishing school for British blues-rock guitarists: at various times his band -- still called the Bluesbreakers despite 40-odd years of lineup changes -- included the young Eric Clapton, Mick Taylor (later of the Rolling Stones) and Peter Green (later of Fleetwood Mac), among others. At 8 and 10:30, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, (212) 997-4144; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OAKLEY HALL (Tonight) Patient country-folk mutates into dense psychedelic drones in the songs of this Brooklyn band led by Pat Sullivan, a former member of Brooklyn's other masters of psychedelic minimalism, Oneida. With Mike Wexler, Black Taj and Endless Boogie. At 8:30, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* OS MUTANTES (Tonight) The oddest, most exuberant and most wonderfully innovative band of the late-1960's tropicália movement in Brazil -- when there was no shortage of odd, exuberant and wonderfully innovative musicians -- was Os Mutantes (the Mutants), which filtered American and British psychedelic and garage-rock through bossa nova and a do-what-thou-wilt pop-art philosophy. The band broke up in 1978, and before this brief tour -- with some but not all of its original members -- had never performed in the United States. With Death Vessel. At 6:30, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; $50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PRETTY GIRLS MAKE GRAVES, JASON LYTLE (Sunday) In the weeks before the concert giant Live Nation begins to put on big-ticket concerts at the McCarren Park Pool in Greenpoint, Brooklyn (its first there is Bloc Party on July 29), a number of smaller, scrappier promoters have been using the space -- a 50,000-square-foot public pool closed since 1984 -- for free shows. Sunday afternoon features Pretty Girls Make Graves, a Seattle band with a knack for angular, heartfelt melodies that cut through clouds of noise; and Mr. Lytle, the lead singer of Grandaddy, who is in town this weekend for a few appearances (see above). With Bon Savants. At 3 p.m., Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, thepoolparties.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RASPUTINA (Tonight) Rasputina is a charmingly improbable project: part Marie Antoinette, part metal. Three women who are cellists in corsets (as well as a drummer) sing about Transylvanian concubines as their music seesaws between elaborate chamber-music counterpoint and grunting hard-rock chords, complete with distortion. At 9, Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BUTCH WALKER AND THE LET'S GO OUT TONITES (Wednesday) Mr. Walker first revealed his fondness for muscular mid-1970's pop-rock and his mocking obsession with stardom as the leader of the Marvelous 3. Now on his own, he hasn't lost his ambition or his sense of irony. With Boys Like Girls and As Fast As. At 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; sold out. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>STEVEN BERNSTEIN'S MILLENNIAL TERRITORY ORCHESTRA (Tonight and Monday) This little big band, led by the irrepressible slide trumpeter Steven Bernstein, has a forthcoming album called ''MTO Volume 1'' (Sunnyside) that is full of signature touches, like effervescent swing arrangements and covers of hits by Prince and Stevie Wonder. Tonight at 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, at Seventh Avenue, Manhattan, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. Monday at 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $12. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL BLAKE'S EULIPION ORCHESTRA (Sunday) Mr. Blake, a resourceful tenor and soprano saxophonist, leads a group inspired partly by the classic work of composer-arrangers like Gil Evans and Yusef Lateef. Its ranks include Marcus Rojas on tuba, Steven Bernstein on trumpet, Peck Almond on woodwinds and G. Calvin Weston on drums. At 9:30 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DON BYRON QUARTET (Wednesday through July 30) Mr. Byron is justifiably known for his independent-minded concept albums -- his next one will shine a spotlight on the rhythm-and-blues saxophonist Junior Walker -- but he is, first and foremost, a daring clarinetist. He plays here with several longtime associates: the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the bassist Lonnie Plaxico and the drummer Billy Hart. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $25, $30 on July 28 and 29. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE CARDENAS TRIO (Monday) A guitarist with a modern harmonic concept and a clear yet supple style, Mr. Cardenas features his own compositions in this group, which includes the established rhythm team of Ben Allison on bass and Matt Wilson on drums. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CELEBRATION OF RAY BARRETTO &amp; HILTON RUIZ (Tuesday through July 30) ''Standards Rican-ditioned,'' recently issued on Zoho Music, was the final studio album of the conga virtuoso Ray Barretto. It also turned out to be the last recorded effort by the pianist Hilton Ruiz. Both were New York-born musicians of Puerto Rican heritage and were pillars of Latin jazz. This tribute, fittingly programmed as the culmination of Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola's monthlong Latin in Manhattan Festival, includes Mr. Barretto's son Chris Barretto, as well as a two more-established saxophonists, Sonny Fortune and David Sánchez. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m. with an 11:30 p.m. set July 28 and 29, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KARL DENSON TRIO (Monday) Funk and soul are at the heart of Mr. Denson's music, whether he's leading his signature band, Tiny Universe, or spotlighting his alto saxophone in this smaller unit, with Anthony Smith on keyboards and Brett Sanders on drums. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $25 at tables, $15 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ORRIN EVANS QUINTET (Tomorrow) Mr. Evans is a percussive pianist equally attuned to hard bop and hip-hop, and he often surrounds himself with rhythmically assertive sidemen. Here that company includes the saxophonists Abraham Burton and J. D. Allen, the bassist Luques Curtins and the drummer Donald Edwards. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL FORMANEK, TIM BERNE, TOM RAINEY (Tomorrow) These three -- respectively a bassist, an alto saxophonist and a drummer -- have worked together often over the years, usually under the leadership of Mr. Berne. Here they perform as a collective, though the order of billing seems intentional: Mr. Formanek will also lead a preconcert instrumental workshop from 4 to 6 p.m. The concert begins at 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, near Third Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, www.schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12, with a separate $25 charge for the afternoon workshop. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JON GORDON QUINTET (Tuesday) Mr. Gordon, an alto and soprano saxophonist, projects standards through a slightly warped lens, with the help of Mike Moreno on guitar, Aaron Goldberg on piano, Joe Martin on bass and Adam Cruz on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WYCLIFFE GORDON QUARTET (Wednesday) Mr. Gordon, a high-spirited trombonist and one of the most authoritative soloists in the Jazz and Lincoln Center Orchestra, leads a swing-minded small group in a free outdoor show. At 7 p.m., Grant's Tomb, 122nd Street and Riverside Drive, Manhattan, www.jazzmobile.org; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID HANEY TRIO +1 (Sunday) Mr. Haney is a pianist drawn to experimental settings, and he creates a promising one here, with the bassist Mike Bisio, the drummer Adam Lane and as a featured guest, the veteran trombonist Julian Priester. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRED HERSCH TRIO (Wednesday) Mr. Hersch, a pianist strongly associated with solo recitals, leads a trio for this outdoor performance, and not with his usual partners. But the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Eric McPherson should make an excellent rhythm section, and each has experience with Mr. Hersch's literate and cosmopolitan style. At 7 p.m., Madison Square Park, Fifth Avenue and 23rd Street, (212) 538-6667, www.madisonsquarepark.org; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE INBETWEENS (Tuesday) Based in Brooklyn but with origins in Boston at the New England Conservatory of Music, this exploratory trio consists of the guitarist Mike Gamble, the bassist Noah Jarrett and the drummer Conor Elmes. At 8 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JAZZ IN JULY (Tuesday through Thursday) A year ago the pianist Bill Charlap presided over his first season as artistic director of this venerable traditional jazz series. The new season, which started a few days ago, concludes next week with a professional nod to the bossa-nova auteur Antonio Carlos Jobim on Tuesday; a piano summit involving Barry Harris and Cedar Walton, among others, on Wednesday; and a songbook salute to Harold Arlen, featuring Mr. Charlap's mother, the accomplished singer Sandy Stewart, on Thursday. At 8 p.m. each night, 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500 or www.92y.org, $50.(Chinen)</p>
        <p>LAGE LUND QUINTET (Tonight) Mr. Lund is an introspective guitarist whose compositional style can suggest the pastoral warmth of Brian Blade's Fellowship. It's no accident that his quintet includes a member of Fellowship, the pianist and composer Jon Cowherd, along with the alto-saxophonist Will Vinson, the bassist Matt Penman and the drummer Rodney Green. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONNY MCCASLIN GROUP (Wednesday) As on ''Soar'' (Sunnyside), his most recent album, the tenor-saxophonist Donny McCaslin applies his extroverted style to a Latin American-inspired contemporary fusion, benefiting greatly from the contributions of the guitarist Ben Monder, the bassist Scott Colley and the drummer Antonio Sanchez. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MODULAR THEATER (Tonight) Collective improvisation is the mode and mission of this ensemble, comprising the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the alto saxophonist Peter Epstein, the vocalist Will Jennings, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Mark Ferber. At 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, near Third Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, www.schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>The MPTHREE (Wednesday) Mike Pride, an intense and industrious drummer, introduces his song cycle ''Sour Work Dreams'' with an adventurous if goofily titled ensemble that also features Ken Filiano on bass and Mary Halvorson on guitar. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www .thestonenyc .com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEVIN NORTON AND JOHN LINDBERG (Wednesday) Mr. Norton is a probing drummer, vibraphonist and composer, although not always in that order; Mr. Lindberg is a versatile and imaginative bassist who also has a way with orchestration. Their interplay promises to be engagingly multilayered. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GREG OSBY QUARTET (Tuesday through July 30) Mr. Osby is an alto saxophonist with a predilection for jagged edges, and yet he's squarely within the jazz tradition. His rhythm section here consists of the pianist Frank LoCrasto, the bassist Matt Brewer and the drummer Tommy Crane. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAN ASIAN CHAMBER JAZZ ENSEMBLE (Wednesday) Led by the violinist, violist and vocalist Meg Okura, this six-piece group explores a contemporary chamber music infused with multicultural echoes and an ethos of improvisation. At 7:30 p.m., Makor, 35 West 67th Street, near Central Park West, (212) 415-5500; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE PAVONE SHOW (Thursday) An evening organized around the compositions of the violist Jessica Pavone, with such like-minded explorers as the trumpeter Peter Evans, the saxophonists Matana Roberts and Matt Bauder and the percussionist Aaron Siegel. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIERNEY SUTTON (Wednesday through July 29) Ms. Sutton's clear, sweetly sonorous voice isn't inherently a jazz timbre, but she is irrefutably a jazz singer, as she proved on her fine recent album, ''I'm With the Band'' (Telarc), which was recorded at Birdland. 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CLARK TERRY BIG BAND (Tuesday through July 30) Mr. Terry's big-band experience is extensive: from the late-1940's on, he served successively in the orchestras of Count Basie, Duke Ellington and Quincy Jones. Here Mr. Terry, an octogenarian trumpet and flugelhorn player, applies a lifetime of wit and experience to his swinging ensemble. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592. Cover: $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HENRY THREADGILL'S ZOOID (Through Sunday) Mr. Threadgill, the august composer, saxophonist and flutist, has always nursed a fascination with timbre. He indulges it best with this superb ensemble, with Liberty Ellman on acoustic guitar, Dana Leong on cello, Jose Davila on tuba, Tarik Benbrahim on oud and Dafnis Prieto on drums. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with an additional midnight show tonight and tomorrow night, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAKE TORIYAMA QUARTET (Sunday) Mr. Toriyama divides his attention between drumming and computer programming in this modern-sounding ensemble, which features the alto saxophonist and bass clarinetist Andrew D'Angelo, the bassist Chris Lightcap and the guitarist Ben Monder. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'DON GIOVANNI,' 'AN EVENING OF OPERA ACTS' (Tonight through Sunday) The New York-born soprano Martina Arroyo, who had a long career at the Metropolitan Opera, has in recent years been immersed in the work of the Martina Arroyo Foundation, which provides training and performance opportunities for fledgling singers. This weekend the foundation presents a fully staged production of Mozart's ''Don Giovanni,'' directed by Laura Alley and conducted by Steven Crawford, and ''An Evening of Opera Acts,'' with excerpts from ''Don Pasquale,'' ''Madama Butterfly'' and ''Falstaff,'' conducted by Willie Anthony Waters, the general and artistic director of the Connecticut Opera Association. ''Don Giovanni,'' tonight at 7:30 and Sunday at 2:30 p.m.; opera acts, tomorrow at 7:30 p.m.; El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, East Harlem, (347) 677-3854; $15 in advance, $20 at the door, $10 for students and 65+. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tonight through Monday, and Thursday) The drive from New York City to the Glimmerglass Opera in Cooperstown, N.Y., typically takes four hours, no matter what route you choose. But it is worth the trip. The company's intimate, airy and well-equipped house is an ideal place to hear opera. And the imaginative productions, which often wind up at New York City Opera, are best seen in their tryouts at Cooperstown. Tomorrow brings the major event of the season: the premiere of Stephen Hartke's opera ''The Greater Good, or the Passion of Boule de Suif.'' Also playing this week are Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' in a production by Lillian Groag and Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia'' in a production by Leon Major. ''Pirates,'' tonight and Thursday night at 8; ''The Greater Good,'' tomorrow night at 8 and Monday at 1:30 p.m.; ''Barbiere,'' Sunday at 1:30 p.m.; Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255; $64 to $112 tonight through Sunday; $36 to $99 Monday and Thursday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'HANSEL AND GRETEL' (Monday and Thursday) Humperdinck's orchestration for his opera ''Hansel and Gretel'' is rich and Wagnerian. But in some performances it can overwhelm this lyrical fairy tale. Kathleen Kelly, the music director of the Berkshire Opera, has prepared a chamber orchestra arrangement for that company's new fully staged production of the opera, to be performed in a new English translation by Cori Ellison at the intimate and magnificently restored theater of the Mahaiwe Performing Arts Center in Great Barrington, Mass. Ms. Kelly, an assistant conductor and coach at the Met, conducts. At 8 p.m., (413) 442-0099; $35 to $85. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY OPERA THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Founded in 2002, the New Jersey Opera Theater is striving to become the state's preeminent opera company. Besides presenting performances, the company also offers master classes and educational outreach programs. The final weekend of its summer season features Mozart's ''Così Fan Tutte'' in a production by Albert Sherman, conducted by Steven Mosteller; and an intriguing double bill of Puccini's comedy ''Gianni Schicchi'' and ''Buoso's Ghost,'' a one-act work from 1996 by the composer Michael Ching. ''Buoso's Ghost'' picks up the story of the clever Schicchi where Puccini's opera leaves off. Steven Condy sings Schicchi in both works; James Caraher conducts. ''Schicchi'' and ''Buoso,'' tonight at 8 and Sunday afternoon at 2; ''Così,'' tomorrow night at 8; Berlind Theater at the McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., (609) 258-2787; $42 and $49. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BANG ON A CAN SUMMER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Each summer since 2002, New York's dynamic new music collective Bang on a Can has moved north for its annual ''Banglewood'' residency at Mass MoCA. Tomorrow is its All-Stars program, which includes the premiere of David Lang's ''Sunray,'' Michael Nyman's score to the classic silent film ''Manhatta,'' a new work by Don Byron and pieces by Annie Gosfield and Edward Ruchalski. At 8 p.m., 7 Marshall Street, North Adams, Mass., (413) 662-2111; $35. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'BEOWULF' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Benjamin Bagby's short, fast, one-man take on the Beowulf story is part of the Lincoln Center Festival. At 8:30, Drama Theater at La Guardia High School of Music and Art and Performing Arts, Amsterdam Avenue at 65th Street, (212) 721-6500; $45. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Christine Brewer (Tomorrow) This fine soprano will sing Wagner's ''Wesendonck Lieder'' in the intimate barn at the Mount Lebanon Shaker Village, as part of the Tannery Pond Concerts series. She will be accompanied by the pianist Craig Rutenberg in an eclectic program that also includes songs by Richard Strauss, Joseph Marx, John Carter, Harold Arlen, Samuel Barber and Edwin McArthur. At 8 p.m., New Lebanon, N.Y., (888) 820-9441; $25 and 30. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL KEYBOARD INSTITUTE AND FESTIVAL (Tonight through Thursday) During the slow summer months, concertgoers who love the piano have plenty to keep them happy during the two weeks of this series at Mannes College, directed by the pianist Jerome Rose. Tonight Leslie Howard explores ''The Russian Romantic Piano Sonata'' with works by Tchaikovsky, Glazunov, Rachmaninoff and Anton Rubinstein. There are also recitals by the veteran pianists Fou Ts'ong (Tuesday) and Philippe Bianconi (Wednesday). At 8 p.m., Mannes College, a division of the New School for Music, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 580-0210, Ext. 4858; $20 for evening recitals, $15 for master classes, $10 for afternoon concerts. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>MARLBORO MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tomorrow and Sunday) Public concerts are the byproduct of this intensive-study chamber-music retreat. Beethoven and Brahms quintets and a Dvorak trio are offered Saturday at 8:30. It's Mozart, Shostakovich and more Beethoven Sunday at 2:30, Marlboro Music School and Festival, Marlboro, Vt., (802) 254-2394; $15 to $30; $5 for canopy areas. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* MAVERICK CONCERTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) This concert series near Woodstock, N.Y., offers its performances in an open-backed barn that allows the sounds of nature to mingle with the music. Tomorrow, Trio Solisti plays music by Gershwin and Paul Schoenfield, as well as an arrangement of Mussorgsky's ''Pictures at an Exhibition.'' On Sunday, the Pacific String Quartet plays Shostakovich's searing Quartet No. 8, Britten's Quartet No. 2 and Mozart's ''Dissonant'' Quartet. Tomorrow at 6 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m., Maverick Concert Hall, Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217; $20; $5 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>THOMAS MEGLIORANZA (Monday) Mr. Meglioranza, a young baritone who is fast making a name for himself singing a wide repertory, appears in the annual River to River Festival, accompanied by the able Reiko Uchida. Mr. Meglioranza's intriguingly eclectic program ranges from Schubert lieder to works by Derek Bermel and Milton Babbitt. At 7:30 p.m., Schimmel Center for the Arts, 3 Spruce Street, near Park Row, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free, but tickets are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NORFOLK CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow night) Bach and Kurtag occupy tonight's concert by the Keller Quartet. Tomorrow it's all Mozart, with instrumental duos, songs and arias. At 8, Ellen Battell Stoeckel Estate, Routes 44 and 272, Norfolk, Conn., (860) 542-3000; $15 to $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>S.E.M. ENSEMBLE (Tuesday) The composer Petr Kotik's daring S.E.M. Ensemble performs the works of established and emerging composers in John Zorn's avant-garde performance space, the Stone. The 8 p.m. set features Reiko Füting's ''Leaving Without/Palimpsest'' for piano and clarinet, Sam Hillmer's '' the night sweats and the day sweats ,'' Anne Guthrie's ''Margaret or Olivier'' and Morton Feldman's ''Why Patterns?'' The 10 p.m. program includes Julius Eastman's ''Piano 2,'' La Monte Young's ''Composition #7 1960'' and John Cage's ''Ryoanji.'' Avenue C at Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; $10. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* SUMMERGARDEN (Sunday) The student ensembles from the Juilliard School who play these concerts tend to be devoted to contemporary music and play it with virtuosity and polish. The works, all new to New York, include Pablo Ortiz's ''Falling From Grace,'' Betty Olivero's ''Bashra'v,'' Alberto Colla's ''Fugue on Thin Ice,'' Philip Carlsen's ''Landscape With Ladyslipper,'' Wen Deqing's ''Traces II'' and Martin Butler's ''Jazz Machines.'' At 8 p.m., Museum of Modern Art Sculpture Garden, West 54th Street between Fifth Avenue and Avenue of the Americas, (212) 708-9491; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday) With all the hoopla over James Levine's return to conducting, don't forget it's still the Mozart year. Tanglewood and Mr. Levine, leading the Boston Symphony Orchestra, remember this weekend. Tonight it's Mozart with the singer Susan Graham and the pianist Richard Goode. Tomorrow it's ''Don Giovanni'' in concert, and on Sunday more Mozart. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Lenox, Mass., (866) 266-1200; $18 to $87 tonight, with $8.50 lawn tickets; $18 to $87 tomorrow and Sunday, with $17 lawn tickets. (Holland)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>CAPACITOR: 'DIGGING IN THE DARK'  (Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday) From San Francisco, for hard-core fans of dances about geology. Call first to make sure the theater fans have been turned on. Through July 30. Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, between Eighth and Ninth Avenues, Manhattan, (212) 352-3101 or www.capacitor.org; $35.(Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* CELEBRATE BROOKLYN: RONALD K. BROWN/EVIDENCE (Tomorrow) The company will perform three works, including ''Grace,'' created for the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater by Mr. Brown, whose African-influenced modern-dance choreography has had a major influence on dance today. 8 p.m. Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-8999 or www.prospectpark.org; $3 suggested contribution. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHASHAMA OASIS FESTIVAL 2006 (Today and Sunday) Artists of all disciplines -- some, we suspect, wildly undisciplined in the grand tradition of Chashama productions -- will perform in a Midtown window and outdoors. Today from noon to 1:30 p.m. and 5:30 to 7 p.m., Chashama window performance, 217 East 42nd Street, between Second and Third Avenues, Manhattan. Sunday from 3 to 4 p.m. and 5 to 6 p.m., Red Shade Plaza, Riverside Park South, 62nd Street at the Hudson River, Manhattan, (212) 391-8151 or www.chashama.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>COMPANY C CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) A 12-member ballet troupe from San Francisco with an eclectic repertory presents works by Twyla Tharp, Patrick Corbin, Alexander Proia and its director, Charles Anderson. 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $25, $20 students and 65+. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>DANCE TACTICS PERFORMANCE GROUP BY KEITH THOMPSON (Thursday) The company makes its formal debut with dances choreographed by Keith A. Thompson, who performed with Trisha Brown, and set to music by Pergolesi, Ryuichi Sakamoto, Robert Een and Nate Aldrich. Through July 29. 7:30 p.m. Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 924-0077 or www.dtw.org; $12, $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DECADANCETHEATER (Thursday) This all-female hip-hop group from Brooklyn won plaudits for its reworking of Stravinsky's ''Firebird'' two years ago. Now its members are trying their hand at a 12th-century Japanese ghost story. But not to worry: there will be a live D.J. 8 p.m. Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street; (212) 334-7479. Thursday benefit tickets begin at $50.(Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>HEIDI DUCKLER COLLAGE DANCE THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Duckler is known as Los Angeles's ''queen of site-specific performance,'' the press release says. This production of ''Laundromatinee,'' part of the Lower Manhattan Cultural Council's Sitelines performances, may well show she deserves claim to the title. It involves dancers spinning in dryers and hanging from clotheslines, then -- this sounds like the best bit -- removing their clothes to sing ''Stand By Your Man.'' 8.30 p.m., Laundromat, 168 Elizabeth Street, between Spring and Kenmare Streets; (212) 219-9401, www.lmcc.net/sitelines; free. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday) Dance companies from Finland, Spain, India and Denmark occupy the week. The highly regarded Finnish choreographer Tero Saarinen and his company, accompanied by Shaker vocalists, will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend. They will be followed there on Wednesday and Thursday (and next weekend) by Eva Yerbabuena's Ballet Flamenco from Spain. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, Nrityagram, a highly regarded Indian ensemble specializing in Odissi dance, plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is the Danish Dance Theater, billed as that country's leading modern-dance ensemble. Mr. Saarinen's company, tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 p.m. and 8 p.m., and Sunday at 2 p.m.; $50. Yerbabuena, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, Shawn Theater, $50. Nrityagram tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15, tomorrow at 2:15 p.m. and Sunday at 5 p.m.; .$24. Danish Dance Theater, Thursday at 8:15 p.m., Duke Theater, $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, seniors 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions are at jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>PAULA HUNTER (Tonight and tomorrow) Ms. Hunter will perform ''I Am Karen Finley,'' an absurdist performance solo, as a free dance installation in a window in the Theater District. 5 and 7:30 p.m., Chashama, 112 West 44th Street, (212) 391-8151 or chashama.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL (Wednesday) The ubiquitous Noche Flamenca will open this festival, with dancing by Soledad Barrio, Alejandro Granados and Juan Ogalla. 8 p.m. Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows, Queens, (718) 760-0064 or www.QueensTheatre.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) The Batsheva Dance Company continues its performances of Ohad Naharin's new ''Telophaza'' tonight and tomorrow night at 8 at the New York State Theater at Lincoln Center; $25 to $65. Also this weekend, Saburo Teshigawa, the Japanese master solo dancer, is performing his new ''Bones in Pages'' tonight and tomorrow night at 8 at the Rose Theater, 60th Street and Broadway, at Columbus Circle; $20 to $50. Next week the San Francisco Ballet performs at the New York State Theater starting Tuesday. The opening-night gala, at 8, includes solos, pas de deux and excerpts from repertory dances by choreographers, including Jerome Robbins; the company director, Helgi Tomasson; Lar Lubovitch; and Yuri Possokhov. The San Francisco Ballet's production of Mark Morris's ''Sylvia'' is scheduled for Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; $30 to $75. And Yasmeen Godder and the Bloody Bench Players will perform Ms. Godder's new ''Strawberry Cream and Gunpowder'' on Thursday at 7 p.m. at the La Guardia Drama Theater, Amsterdam Avenue and 65th Street. Through July 29; $35. For reservations and information on all performances: (212) 721-6500 or www.lincolncenter.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW GENERATION DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Company founder and director Dardo Galletto mixes ballet, tango and modern dance and his ''Black-White Tango,'' whose cast includes guest dancers from American Ballet Theater and ''Forever Tango.'' Through July 30. Thursday at 8 p.m. Henry Street Settlement, 466 Grand Street, Lower East Side; (646) 342-9910; $30, $45 for opening-night gala. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>*NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Saturday, Sunday and Thursday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of last winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, is winding down its two-month run at the intimate Theater 80, which will end July 30. Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 and 5 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Theater 80, 80 St. Mark's Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45.(Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Tonight and tomorrow, Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless, but enormously popular for people of all ages. Three programs alternate for the run ending Aug. 12. Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday at 8 p.m. and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org, $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>'RIVER DEEP: A TRIBUTE TO TINA TURNER' (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Gabrielle Lansner pays tribute to Ms. Turner, who is played by Pat Hall, in a multimedia production set to music by Philip Hamilton. Through July 29. Tonight and Tuesday through Thursday at 8 p.m.; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m. Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton; (212) 279-4200 or gabriellelansner.com; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SUMMER IN THE SQUARE (Wednesday) As part of the Union Square Park's outdoor performance series, Performance Space 122 will present excerpts from the coming season. Saar Harari, whose ''Herd of Bulls'' was enthusiastically received last fall, will perform a section from ''Moopim''; the Palissimo dance company will perform Pavel Zustiak's ''Le Petit Mort''; and Chris Yon will dance with Taryn Griggs in the mysteriously titled ''Elephant (Terrible) Assisted Suicide [in ought 6].'' 6 p.m., Union Square Park, East 14th to East 17th Street, Manhattan; free. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* 'TAP CITY 2006' (Tonight and tomorrow) This spirited summer festival suggests that camaraderie and a sense of community are not dead in tap dance, on stage and in the audience. It includes two programs. ''Tap and Song,'' a celebration of traditional vaudeville, comedy and classic song-and-dance, stars the irrepressible Tony Waag, the festival's founder and director. He will be joined by a generous roster of artists, including the veteran tapper Mable Lee, the German Tap and Tray duo, the chic two-woman Tapage and the hoedown tapper Nate Cooper. ''Tap Forward'' features familiar tap soloists, cutting-edge types and up-and-comers. ''Tap and Song'' is tonight at 7 and 9:30 p.m.; ''Tap Forward'' is tomorrow at 7 and 9:30 p.m., the Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street; (212) 239-6200 or www.atdf.org; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>THOMAS-ORTIZ DANCE (Tonight and tomorrow) Ted Thomas and Frances Ortiz combine urban athleticism and Latin sensuality in choreographic explorations of socially relevant themes. 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 924-0077; $15, $25. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* CASSIE TERMAN AND SHINICHI MOMO KOGA (Tonight and tomorrow) Ms. Terman and Mr. Koga create a world full of humor and pathos out of empty space and perfectly attuned physical-theater skills. 8 p.m., Center for Remembering and Sharing, 123 Fourth Avenue, between 12th and 13th Streets, Manhattan; (212) 352-3101; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YOUNG DANCEMAKERS COMPANY (Thursday) These choreographers -- New York City high school students chosen by audition for a summer intensive in dance technique, performing and making dances -- know how to put on a very good show. It's free, too. Their tour of city sites continues through Aug. 3. Thursday at 2 p.m. Stern Auditorium, Mount Sinai Hospital, Fifth Avenue at 100th Street, Upper East Side; (718) 329-7250 or www.ecfs.org/ydc.asp; reservations required. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,'  through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedeker's guides, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>DAHESH MUSEUM OF ART: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Sept. 3. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION : 'JEAN-ÉTIENNE LIOTARD (1702-1789): SWISS MASTER,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including the young Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 3 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. (212) 535-7710. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MET: 'TREASURES OF SACRED MAYA KINGS,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. And wait till you see the painted ceramic vessel known as the ''Dazzler Vase,'' with its red and green patterns like jade on fire, you'll understand its name. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY AND MUSEUM: 'MASTERWORKS FROM THE MORGAN,'  through Sept. 10. Almost three years after closing to build an expansion, the Morgan is back and brilliant. What's new: Renzo Piano's four-story glass-and-steel court, a sort of giant solarium with see-through elevators; two good-size second-floor galleries; and a neat little strongbox of an enclosure, called the Cube, for reliquaries and altar vessels. What's not new: almost everything in this exhibition, which fills every gallery with mini-exhibitions of master drawings and musical manuscripts, as well as illuminated gospels and historical and literary autograph manuscripts from the Brontës to Bob Dylan. 225 Madison Avenue, at East 36th Street, (212) 685-0008 or www.themorgan.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF BIBLICAL ART: 'THE WORD ON THE STREET: THE PHOTOGRAPHS OF LARRY RACIOPPO,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: HERZOG &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer. (212) 708-9400. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN : CHIHULY AT THE NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDENS, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in formal reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY: LEGACIES: CONTEMPORARY ARTISTS REFLECT ON SLAVERY, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society. 170 Central Park West, (212) 873-3400. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 CONTEMPORARY ART CENTER: 'INTO ME/OUT OF ME,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* THE WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART : 'FULL HOUSE: VIEWS OF THE WHITNEY'S COLLECTION AT 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. If ''Full House'' is about one thing, it is about discord, about how harmonious America never was. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* SARAH SZE: 'CORNER PLOT' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* HANS BELLMER: ' PETITES ANATOMIES, PETITES IMAGES.'  This extraordinary show of more than 70 images takes you beyond the surface obsessions of Bellmer's girl-crazed art to unveil some of his working processes as a sculptor, installation artist, photographer, editor and hand-colorist whose preference for small scale intensifies the voyeuristic nature of his art. Ubu Gallery, 416 East 59th Street, (212) 753-4444, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* RUDY BURCKHARDT: 'NEW YORK PAINTINGS' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, (212) 262-5050, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>GEORGE HERMS Starting out as a beatnik in the 1950's, Mr. Herms has been creating and exhibiting his richly poetic assemblages of grungy found materials in California, his home state, for more than a half century. This show's eight works, from 1965 to 2002, variously call to mind Ernst, Duchamp, Cornell and Rauschenberg, but they have as well their own spiritually generous, heartfelt mix of hermetic imagination and Whitman-esque populism. Franklin Parrasch, 20 West 57th Street, (212) 246-5360, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>* 'A FOUR-DIMENSIONAL BEING WRITES POETRY ON A FIELD WITH SCULPTURES' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West Second Street, (212) 243-0200, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>JOE BIEL With an exacting illustrator's touch, Mr. Biel draws large, dreamily perverse images of children, like the one of a girl with rabbit ears and a whip peeking out of a cardboard box and the knife-wielding boy crouching atop a pile of rubble and examining a bone he found. Goff + Rosenthal, 537B West 23rd Street, (212) 675-0461, through Aug. 12. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* CRG PRESENTS: KLAUS VON NICHTSSAGEND GALLERY Including works by Liz Luisada, Samuel Lopes and Thomas Ovilsen, this group show of work by 17 emerging artists definitely has its moments, but the strongest impression is made by the gallery-within-a-gallery effect resulting from the re-creation of the storefront facade and reception desk of the small Von Nichtssagend Gallery in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. CRG Gallery, 535 East 22nd Street, (212) 229-2766, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Material Abuse' Unconventional uses of nontraditional materials include Shinique Smith's massive bale of all-white clothing; Michael Arcega's fleet of 300 tiny, balsa-wood tanks; Richard Klein's assemblage made from 10 years' worth of blown-out light-bulb filaments; Jean Shin's stacks of prescription pill bottles; Ray Beldner's dust-covered assemblages made of ordinary objects stolen from other people; and a star-and-stripe-patterned bikini made of map tacks by Devorah Sperber. Caren Golden, 539 West 23rd Street, (212) 727-8304, through Aug. 4. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Money Changes Everything' A show of artworks made at least partly out of actual money: dollar bills, mostly, but Iraqi dinar notes, too. Schroeder Romero, 637 West 27th Street, (212) 630-0722, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Photography Is Not An Art!' More than 100 examples of vernacular, often anonymous photographs from fields of medicine, forensics, space exploration and advertising prove that nonart photography is often as interesting as the fine-art variety. Alan Klotz, 511 West 25th Street, (212) 741-4764, through Aug. 19. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Vivan Sundaram: 'Re-Take of Amrita' The photographs in this beautiful, time-haunted show are all of past generations of the Indian artist Vivan Sundaram's family, and include images of his aunt, the modernist painter Amrita Sher-Gil (1913-1941). Thanks to digital technology, those generations mix in logically impossible combinations. The resulting pictures embody the past the way it survives in the mind: edited, layered, compressed, as if in a dream. Sepia International, 148 West 24th Street, 11th floor, (212) 645-9444, through July 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* THE NAME OF THIS SHOW IS NOT GAY ART NOW Characterized by its organizer, the artist Jack Pierson, as an ode to the passing of ''the notion of Gay Art,'' this exhibition embraces the work of about 60 artists (gay, straight and otherwise) to create a cacophonous celebration and suggest that everyone is a little bit gay, if they are lucky. Paul Kasmin Gallery, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212) 563-4474, closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 25, 2006, Tuesday  The introduction to excerpts from a theater review in Weekend on Friday of ''[title of show],'' which has reopened at the Vineyard Theater, misstated the telephone number. It is (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 27, 2006, Thursday  An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 about the exhibition ''CRG Presents: Klaus Von Nichtssagend Gallery,'' at the CRG Gallery through tomorrow, misstated the address. It is 535 West 22nd Street, not East 22nd.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 31, 2006, Monday  An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 for the exhibition ''A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field With Sculptures'' at the Matthew Marks Gallery misstated the address. It is 522 West 22nd Street, not West Second Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 25, 2006, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The introduction to excerpts from a theater review in Weekend on Friday of ''[title of show],'' which has reopened at the Vineyard Theater, misstated the telephone number. It is (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: July 27, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 about the exhibition ''CRG Presents: Klaus Von Nichtssagend Gallery,'' at the CRG Gallery through tomorrow, misstated the address. It is 535 West 22nd Street, not East 22nd.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: July 31, 2006, Monday</p>
        <p>An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 for the exhibition ''A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field With Sculptures'' at the Matthew Marks Gallery misstated the address. It is 522 West 22nd Street, not West Second Street.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
