<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>India and China Become Friendlier Rivals</title>
    <meta content="21india" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1806392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D6153EF932A15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>India and China Become Friendlier Rivals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Nov. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 40-year border dispute remains unresolved. Tibetan refugees continue to pour across the Himalayas. The memory of India's bruising military defeat by China in 1962 remains fresh in the minds of a certain generation.</p>
        <p>But as the president of China, Hu Jintao, arrived here Monday night to shore up relations between his nation and India, the territorial disputes were no longer the main focus of their relationship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 40-year border dispute remains unresolved. Tibetan refugees continue to pour across the Himalayas. The memory of India's bruising military defeat by China in 1962 remains fresh in the minds of a certain generation.</p>
        <p>But as the president of China, Hu Jintao, arrived here Monday night to shore up relations between his nation and India, the territorial disputes were no longer the main focus of their relationship.</p>
        <p>As India and China tend to their flourishing economies and strive to expand their global reach, they increasingly find themselves scrambling for natural resources and political influence around the world. At times these two giants of Asia appear to be linking arms; at times they are in active competition.</p>
        <p>But it is not exactly a relationship of equals. India lags behind on virtually every indicator, with the notable exceptions of the size of its software industry and the number of billionaires, in which it is far ahead.</p>
        <p>On Monday, India's minister of state for commerce, Jairam Ramesh, told an audience here that Indians would do well to stop competing against the Chinese and start admiring them. ''We are not in a race,'' he said at a seminar sponsored by the Confederation of Indian Industry. ''They have already won the race.''</p>
        <p>Some of the competition is in each other's neighborhoods. China, a longtime ally of Pakistan, is helping that nation fulfill its nuclear energy ambitions and is building a deep-water port at Gwadar on the Arabian Sea. On India's eastern flank, China has emerged as one of the largest trading partners of Bangladesh.</p>
        <p>India, meanwhile, signed a trade agreement with Singapore last year, and it is increasingly cozying up to the military junta in Myanmar, formerly Burma.</p>
        <p>Some of the competition is taking place oceans away as China and India, both hungering for raw materials ranging from fossil fuels to iron ore, aggressively court resource-rich countries like Nigeria and Kazakhstan.</p>
        <p>''As two large countries with their own oversized egos, with their sense of manifest destinies, the rivalry is natural,'' said C. Raja Mohan, the strategic affairs columnist for the English-language daily Indian Express. ''The self-perception in both China and India is that they have a larger stake in the world. Therefore there is a politics of balancing which has become more acute.''</p>
        <p>Never mind, many Indian analysts say, that the United States is seeking to shore up India as a bulwark against China. India has its own reasons to stand up to China -- or at times to collaborate.</p>
        <p>For instance, India and China are partners in an oil venture in Sudan, despite international pressure over what the United States has described as the genocide in the Darfur region of western Sudan. Both India and China have in fact stepped up their courtship of Africa.</p>
        <p>Trade between China and African nations, with their ample deposits of iron ore, copper and oil, has grown tenfold in the last 10 years, to nearly $40 billion last year. In most instances where both countries have bid for oil deals, China has managed to elbow out India.</p>
        <p>But Indian automakers are making sport utility vehicles for the African market, selling hair care products and bidding for hotels. India's bilateral trade with African countries inched up to around $12 billion last year.</p>
        <p>Their respective economic rises have gradually prompted India and China to put away distrust and start doing business together. Trade between them has more than doubled in the last two years, reaching nearly $18 billion in 2005. A report by the Confederation of Indian Industry forecast that it would reach $30 billion by 2010. A historic trade route at Nathula Pass reopened earlier this year, for the first time since the two countries went to war in 1962 over territorial disputes.</p>
        <p>Some of the suspicion has been hard to overcome, though. India claims a vast swath of Chinese-controlled territory in Kashmir. China contends that the Indian state of Arunachal Pradesh is part of China. Talks between the two countries have yet to resolve those issues.</p>
        <p>Pakistan is the other sore point. Mr. Hu, after the first visit by a Chinese president to India in 10 years, is scheduled to move on to Pakistan later in the week. Among the potential deals to be announced, there is the expansion of trade and further nuclear cooperation.</p>
        <p>For India, which is poised to acquire civilian nuclear technology from the United States, such overtures by Beijing are more than minor irritants and do not help to overcome its distrust of China.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
