<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Start the Wheels Turning</title>
    <meta content="29WEwinter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/29/opinion/nyregionopinions/29WEwinter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Department of Transportation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFD6103FF93AA15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Start the Wheels Turning</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Start the Wheels Turning</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robin Winter</byline>
      <dateline>Chappaqua</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I GREW up riding my bike to school. Starting in fourth grade, I'd pedal my blue Schwinn almost two miles from my home near Scarsdale village, arriving at Fox Meadow School in time to lock my bike to a rack by the playground and scurry up to class.</p>
        <p>That was the early 1970's, when children cycled all over Westchester's suburbs, on the same roads that parents drove their station wagons. We rode to school and to friends' houses. We were taught to be careful and were able to cross busy thoroughfares like Crane Road without incident. Our two-wheelers gave us a whiff of independence, and we thrived on our own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Biking to school can teach independence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I GREW up riding my bike to school. Starting in fourth grade, I'd pedal my blue Schwinn almost two miles from my home near Scarsdale village, arriving at Fox Meadow School in time to lock my bike to a rack by the playground and scurry up to class.</p>
        <p>That was the early 1970's, when children cycled all over Westchester's suburbs, on the same roads that parents drove their station wagons. We rode to school and to friends' houses. We were taught to be careful and were able to cross busy thoroughfares like Crane Road without incident. Our two-wheelers gave us a whiff of independence, and we thrived on our own.</p>
        <p>Fast forward more than 30 years to Chappaqua, where I now live. Children in Chappaqua rarely use bikes to get from here to there. News-media-driven fears about accidents and kidnappings have created a culture in which children now rely on parents to get everywhere. We even drive them to the North County Trailway so they can ride their bikes for recreation.</p>
        <p>My eldest son, Jacob, a seventh-grader at Robert E. Bell Middle School, loves cycling, be it down the lawn, around a nearby cul-de-sac or on the trailway. But he never considered riding to school, in the heart of the hamlet, about two miles downhill from our home.</p>
        <p>Instead, I rouse Jacob each morning at 6:45 so he can make the bus at 7:15, which delivers him to Bell for homeroom by 7:50. But this past spring, I started to wonder if he might want to ride his bike to school and experience the sort of independence that is largely absent in the supervised lives of today's children. Besides, the ride would take only 15 minutes, giving my growing adolescent a few more minutes of sleep.</p>
        <p>Little did I realize how old-fashioned my views of childhood had become since those days happily pedaling to Fox Meadow. At Bell, I discovered that it was rare for students to ride to school, and that there was no place to store a bike for those willing to make the trek. Evidently, the bike rack, which had been slammed into too many times by parents dropping their children off at school, had been removed several years ago and never replaced.</p>
        <p>Eager to make Chappaqua more bike friendly, I started looking for information about youth bicycle safety programs. In my research, I discovered a new federal program called Safe Routes to School, which helps communities develop initiatives to encourage children to ride and walk to school. According to the program's Web site, in 1969, about half of all students in the United States walked or bicycled to school. Today, that number is down to 15 percent. Federal policymakers see Safe Routes as a way to fight both childhood obesity and our reliance on fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The program, which was established as part of the federal transportation reauthorization bill, provides state financing for communities that adopt the safe routes program. For instance, according to the principal planner of Westchester County's Department of Transportation, New York State has access to $36 million over six years. This money can be used for community projects like studying of local traffic patterns, building safer street crossings and arranging workshops to encourage children to walk and bicycle to school.</p>
        <p>When I mentioned my interest in starting a Safe Routes to School program in Chappaqua to friends, some were concerned about safety, but most, nostalgic about their childhoods spent cycling all over town, thought the idea was worth pursuing.</p>
        <p>But school administrators and town officials, I discovered, felt differently. Even when I told them that a consultant to help set up the program wouldn't cost the town money, and that we could tap federal funds that were just waiting to be used for road-safety improvements and educational workshops, they were noncommittal. Encouraging children to walk to school seemed plausible to them, but bicycling was out of the question because they felt it just wasn't safe.</p>
        <p>Of course, walking is safer, but walking is really an option only for children who live near the school. For this program to reach critical mass, we need to encourage both walking and bicycling.</p>
        <p>Living is filled with risk and growing up involves developing strategies to cope with it. If we continue to raise our children in a risk-free community, then we're going to have a lot of risk-adverse adults. Chappaqua should take advantage of a federal program that could not only make our town a safer place for children, but also improve our roads. And maybe along the way, we'll encourage our children to learn what independence is all about.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Robin Winter, director of marketing and public relations at an engineering firm, is on the board of the Westchester Cycle Club.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robin Winter, director of marketing and public relations at an engineering firm, is on the board of the Westchester Cycle Club.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
