<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Writing a Play About the Play He Might Have Written</title>
    <meta content="04mort" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/04/theater/reviews/04mort.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061109T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1801983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurney, A R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benko, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burkett, Shannon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kromer, Christopher</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Post Mortem (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Flea Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gurney, A R</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Post Mortem (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EEDB103FF937A35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Writing a Play About the Play He Might Have Written</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Writing a Play About the Play He Might Have Written</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews A R Gurney play Post Mortem, directed by Jim Simpson; Tina Benko, Shannon Burkett and Christopher Kromer star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A. R. Gurney has written a play that, as accurately appraised by one admirer, has ''turned the world upside down.'' It can be said without exaggeration that this epochal work is directly responsible for, among other things, an effective universal health care system, world peace, smooth-running public transportation and significant declines in global warming and the divorce rate.</p>
        <p>Would that Mr. Gurney were alive to witness the effects of his miracle drama. Sadly, he was killed -- some say murdered (possibly by, ssshhh, Dick Cheney) -- before it was ever produced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In “Post Mortem,” a bubbly grievance list of a comedy, playwright A. R. Gurney uses a Midwestern university ruled by censorship to consider the plight of his beloved country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A. R. Gurney has written a play that, as accurately appraised by one admirer, has ''turned the world upside down.'' It can be said without exaggeration that this epochal work is directly responsible for, among other things, an effective universal health care system, world peace, smooth-running public transportation and significant declines in global warming and the divorce rate.</p>
        <p>Would that Mr. Gurney were alive to witness the effects of his miracle drama. Sadly, he was killed -- some say murdered (possibly by, ssshhh, Dick Cheney) -- before it was ever produced.</p>
        <p>''Post Mortem,'' the panacea of a play described above, is not to be confused with the bubbly grievance list of a comedy with the same title that opened this week in SoHo and is about a panacea of a play called ''Post Mortem.'' The ''Post Mortem'' now at the Flea Theater, directed by Jim Simpson, was also written by Mr. Gurney, who at last report was very much alive.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Gurney -- the theatrical sociologist who has devoted much of his career to recording the habits of the endangered American WASP in plays like ''The Cocktail Hour'' and ''The Dinner Party'' -- could be said to be more than alive. For the purposes of his latest offering, set ''sometime in the future'' at a Midwestern university ruled by censorship, he has become God, restructuring the world in his own image to consider the plight of his beloved country and the state of his beloved art.</p>
        <p>Though he is principally known as a practitioner of the ''middle-class comedy of manners'' (to borrow a dismissive self-description from this latest play), in recent years he has used the stage of the Flea for cathartic venting about a world that seems determined to destroy itself. His previous collaborations with Mr. Simpson include ''O Jerusalem!,'' ''Mrs. Farnsworth'' and ''Screenplay,'' all political fantasies of wish- and fear-fulfillment.</p>
        <p>Of these, only ''Mrs. Farnsworth,'' which starred Sigourney Weaver and John Lithgow, is a proper play with credible characters. The rest are basically topical essays delivered with theatrical brio, a category to which ''Post Mortem'' clearly also belongs.</p>
        <p>But in addition to taking sardonic aim at Mr. Gurney's usual favorite targets -- chiefly, the sins of the Bush administration -- this latest work deals specifically and wistfully with the role of drama in a culture that has increasingly little respect for it. On one level, ''Post Mortem'' isn't much more than a grab bag of Broadway insider jokes, polemical satire and cosmic lamentation. But its parental concern and love for theater lends the show an affecting sweetness that lingers.</p>
        <p>The springboard for the plot of ''Post Mortem'' is the discovery of the manuscript of the play-within-the play by Dexter (Christopher Kromer), a lusty student hoping to impress his sexy drama teacher, Alice (Tina Benko), at what Mr. Gurney calls a ''faith-based'' university. Alice had once hoped to become an actress, but felt such a career would be limited in an era when the government, bankrupted by the war in Iraq, had turned Broadway theaters into casinos.</p>
        <p>Hence Dexter's tantalizing description of a previously unknown, politically subversive play from the early 21st century intrigues her, though she has never heard of A. R. Gurney, who wrote it. Defying the collegiate and governmental powers that be, Dexter and Alice vow to perform ''Post Mortem'' all over the country. That they accomplish their goal is made evident in the play's second half, when they return to the now secularized university as celebrities and contenders for the Nobel Peace Prize.</p>
        <p>The United States of the future, in this production, looks much like the United States of the present, which is of course Mr. Gurney's point. Even after Alice and Dexter have reintroduced serious drama to the world, with momentous results, the American public remains in thrall to bad television, violent video games and the socially isolating effects of cellphones. A playwright's work, it seems, is never really done, and theater must constantly renew itself.</p>
        <p>The three cast members, who also include Shannon Burkett as a young cellphone-hating zealot and fan of Dexter and Alice, perform with an appealing mix of comic-strip exaggeration and idealistic ardor. Ms. Benko is particularly enjoyable as a woman whose thwarted theatrical instincts have turned her into a walking mass of dramatic affectations.</p>
        <p>And though the satire is at best scattershot -- with as many bad jokes as good ones -- it's hard not to be infected by the relish with which Mr. Gurney rewrites his own past, as well as invents a glorious posterity for himself. Early in the play Dexter talks about coming upon a rare copy of Mr. Gurney's privately printed autobiography, which reveals that he had affairs with many famous actresses, including Cameron Diaz and both Audrey and Katharine Hepburn.</p>
        <p>Hey, if you're going to be the author of your own life, you might as well make it juicy.</p>
        <p>Post Mortem</p>
        <p>By A. R. Gurney; directed by Jim Simpson; sets by Mimi Lien; lighting by Brian Aldous; costumes by Claudia Brown; sound by Jill DuBoff; scenic artist, Gary Levinson; stage manager, Jennifer Noterman; technical director, Joshua Higgason; assistant to the director, Dev Bondarin. Presented by the Flea Theater, Mr. Simpson, artistic director; Carol Ostrow, producing director. At the Flea Theater, 41 White Street, between Broadway and Church Street, TriBeCa; (212) 352-3101. Through Dec. 9. Running time: 1 hour 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Tina Benko (Alice), Shannon Burkett (Betsy) and Christopher Kromer (Dexter).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 9, 2006, Thursday  A theater review on Saturday about ''Post Mortem'' by A.R. Gurney, at the Flea Theater in TriBeCa, referred incorrectly to his work ''The Dinner Party.'' It was a magazine article, not a play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 9, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>A theater review on Saturday about ''Post Mortem'' by A.R. Gurney, at the Flea Theater in TriBeCa, referred incorrectly to his work ''The Dinner Party.'' It was a magazine article, not a play.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
