<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flunking the Oil Addiction Test</title>
    <meta content="04tue2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/04/opinion/04tue2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1751971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D81330F937A35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flunking the Oil Addiction Test</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flunking the Oil Addiction Test</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The muscle cars of yesteryear don't seem quite so impressive any more. In fact, as Matthew L. Wald pointed out in The Times the other day, the most powerful 2005 Toyota Camry, the ultimate plain-vanilla family sedan, accelerates more quickly than some 1975 Pontiac Firebird models. A 2005 Nissan sports wagon can outrun a '65 Mustang.</p>
        <p>These examples confirm a disturbing truth: most of the fancy technology developed over the years by automakers here and abroad has been used to make cars bigger and faster. Greater fuel efficiency -- the very thing that would reduce America's oil dependency, as well as its contribution to global warming -- has taken a back seat. Indeed, fuel economy has actually declined in the past 20 years, largely because of the popularity of minivans and S.U.V.'s, and other vehicles collectively known as light trucks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration's new standards for S.U.V.'s and other light trucks are extremely disappointing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The muscle cars of yesteryear don't seem quite so impressive any more. In fact, as Matthew L. Wald pointed out in The Times the other day, the most powerful 2005 Toyota Camry, the ultimate plain-vanilla family sedan, accelerates more quickly than some 1975 Pontiac Firebird models. A 2005 Nissan sports wagon can outrun a '65 Mustang.</p>
        <p>These examples confirm a disturbing truth: most of the fancy technology developed over the years by automakers here and abroad has been used to make cars bigger and faster. Greater fuel efficiency -- the very thing that would reduce America's oil dependency, as well as its contribution to global warming -- has taken a back seat. Indeed, fuel economy has actually declined in the past 20 years, largely because of the popularity of minivans and S.U.V.'s, and other vehicles collectively known as light trucks.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the Bush administration published new standards for S.U.V.'s and other light trucks, except for the very biggest. Officials called the standards ''the most ambitious fuel economy goals for light trucks ever developed.'' Measured against the need, as well as against what manufacturers are capable of doing with off-the-shelf technology, they are also extremely disappointing.</p>
        <p>The standards call for an 8.1 percent increase in miles per gallon over the four model years from 2008 to 2011. That change will save 10.7 billion gallons of gasoline over the lifetime of the new vehicles, the administration says, equal to about 227 million barrels of oil. That's useful, of course, but it really amounts to only about 25 days' worth of gasoline at today's consumption rates, and less than three weeks' worth of current oil imports -- a baby step toward President Bush's goal of reducing America's dependency on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>Buried deep in the rules is one other disappointment: a reassertion of the administration's view that only the federal government has the authority to set fuel efficiency standards and that any state program that has the effect of changing these standards is illegal.</p>
        <p>This is a direct challenge to a recent California law requiring automakers to cut greenhouse gas emissions from new cars by 30 percent by 2016 -- a target that can be reached, as a practical matter, only by significant increases in efficiency.</p>
        <p>This matter will ultimately be resolved in the courts or by Congress. In the meantime, the administration has missed another opportunity to address the twin problems of oil dependence and warming.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
