<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Twin Paths to the Conclusion Climatic Change Is Real</title>
    <meta content="27masl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/27/books/27masl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1742920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Winds of Change, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Weather Makers, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DE1631F934A15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Twin Paths to the Conclusion Climatic Change Is Real</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Twin Paths to the Conclusion Climatic Change Is Real</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Weather Makers  How Man Is Changing the Climate and What It Means for Life on Earth  By Tim Flannery  Illustrated. 357 pages. Atlantic Monthly Press. $24.</p>
        <p>The Winds of Change  Climate, Weather and the Destruction of Civilizations  By Eugene Linden  Illustrated. 302 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
        <p>An irrefutable fact about climate change is this: The subject is heating up at a breakneck pace. Thanks to giant leaps in research techniques, most notably the extraction (completed in 2004) of a two-mile-long layered sample from the ice sheets covering Greenland, paleoclimatology has moved to the cutting edge of scientific research. This subject rewards close study not only because so little could be proven about it previously but because wild weather is so apparent to the naked eye.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>These two overlapping new books do their best to intrigue and galvanize the armchair climatologist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Weather Makers  How Man Is Changing the Climate and What It Means for Life on Earth  By Tim Flannery  Illustrated. 357 pages. Atlantic Monthly Press. $24.</p>
        <p>The Winds of Change  Climate, Weather and the Destruction of Civilizations  By Eugene Linden  Illustrated. 302 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
        <p>An irrefutable fact about climate change is this: The subject is heating up at a breakneck pace. Thanks to giant leaps in research techniques, most notably the extraction (completed in 2004) of a two-mile-long layered sample from the ice sheets covering Greenland, paleoclimatology has moved to the cutting edge of scientific research. This subject rewards close study not only because so little could be proven about it previously but because wild weather is so apparent to the naked eye.</p>
        <p>The more intriguing and important this field becomes, the more we need clear, unbiased explications of what its evidence reveals. But writing about advances on this particular scientific frontier is problematic. First of all, the material is complicated: climate science is the study of shifting, interrelated and sometimes paradoxical patterns. For instance, although the melting of Arctic ice alters the salinity of the North Atlantic, it does not signal more warm weather. But the melting can slow down the Gulf Stream in ways that threaten a subsequent freeze.</p>
        <p>Second, the subject is loaded: its scientific facts and hypotheses are difficult to separate from their political and religious implications, which are obviously fraught. Analysis of Antarctic ice trumps even Darwin, since it presupposes weather events dating back almost a million years. The phrases ''global warming'' and ''greenhouse gases'' lead directly to debate about government policies. And even for scientific writers caught up in the excitement of new breakthroughs, enthusiasm is difficult to ignite. The overview is simply too bleak.</p>
        <p>But two overlapping new books do their best to intrigue and galvanize the armchair climatologist. ''The Weather Makers,'' by Tim Flannery, is the more volatile and flamboyant; ''The Winds of Change,'' by Eugene Linden, is more measured and takes a more penetrating historical view. And their lingering effects are different. While Mr. Linden ponders links between current circumstances and the destinies of earlier civilizations, Mr. Flannery provides much more urgent, specific evidence of imminent peril. He also makes sure that you will never again look at an electric-light switch in quite the same way. In a field of expertise that has already been popularized by writers as different as Jared Diamond (admired by both of these authors) and Michael Crichton (regarded as the Antichrist), some points are staples. Both books refer to James Lovelock's vision of Earth as the immense single organism he called Gaia. Both cite the temperature changes that occurred in the few days when airplanes over America were grounded after Sept. 11, 2001. Both discuss El Niño and Hurricane Katrina. Both bring up the ice-coated Hollywood doomsday scenario in ''The Day After Tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Both deplore the Bush administration's reluctance to agree to the Kyoto Protocol limiting carbon dioxide emissions. Both note that 9 of the 10 warmest years on record have occurred since 1990. For all their common ground, slight discrepancies in some of their statistics and numerical estimates illustrate the difficulty of nailing down any climate-related data with certainty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flannery, a globe-trotting adventurer with much anecdotal knowledge of how climate has affected frogs, eels, krill and salp, gives his material a more impassioned, fiery tone. And he conveys a stronger sense of alarm. Chapters here have titles like ''A Warning From the Golden Toad,'' ''The Last Act of God?'' and ''Last Steps on the Stairway to Heaven?'' With interlocking and sometimes breathlessly delivered sets of data, he builds a galvanizing, intentionally polarizing case for the urgency of altering our patterns of energy use. American readers will find it only dimly comforting that Mr. Flannery considers his own native land, Australia, to be the world's worst offender in this regard.</p>
        <p>''The Weather Makers'' works hard to make its points -- too hard, at times. When a quotation about carbon use has been translated into English, why show off by identifying the source as ''Arvid Gustav Hobgom, 'Om Sannolikheton FoSekulara Forandringar I Atmosfarens Kolsyrehalt?' '' When dealing in sweeping generalities, why make them needlessly confusing? ''We must remember,'' he writes, ''that if we act now, it lies within our power to save two  species for every one that is currently doomed.'' But in the next sentence: ''If we carry on with business as usual, in all likelihood three out of every five species will not be with us at the dawn of the next century.'' In any case, there is no mistaking his overall point. And ''The Weather Makers'' is detail-packed to the point of terrible fascination. Meanwhile, Mr. Linden's common-sense approach finds its own illustrations in larger, more fundamental human certitudes, not least of them the reluctance of editors and television producers to illuminate tough, confusing issues when snap judgments will do. And he appreciates the value of complex, ambiguous data in forging roundabout paths to new discoveries. As one of his sources in oceanography says admiringly of another, ''Republicans would call him a flip-flopper, but he's really just a good scientist.''</p>
        <p>''The Winds of Change'' can be overly levelheaded. (One part of the book studies insurance companies' fiscal view of increasingly violent weather.) But its scope and seriousness are impressive, even if Mr. Linden insists on characterizing climate as ''a serial killer.'' And its links between areas of study are very valuable. Mr. Linden credits the archaeologist Harvey Weiss ''for breaking down the barriers that previously confined climate scientists and ancient historians to parallel universes that rarely intersected.''</p>
        <p>With that in mind, these studies prompt renewed interest in the mother of all climate-historical synergy: the much-reviled, still dazzling cosmic theories of Immanuel Velikovsky, whose 1950 book ''Worlds in Collision'' postulated that global meteorological cataclysms could be pieced together by analyzing the texts of ancient civilizations. The author's weather mysteries, explicated with a scholarly fervor that brings to mind ''The Da Vinci Code,'' remain mind-blowing. There was a time when extrapolating historical events by studying oxygen isotopes trapped in ice bubbles would have seemed just as strange.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
