<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking a National Voice, 15 Mayors Meet on Gun Violence</title>
    <meta content="26guns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/26/nyregion/26guns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1757242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan, Sewell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Menino, Thomas M (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2DF133FF935A15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking a National Voice, 15 Mayors Meet on Gun Violence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeking a National Voice, 15 Mayors Meet on Gun Violence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Mayor Michael R Bloomberg and Boston Mayor Thomas M Menino meet in New York with mayors of 13 other cities to put pressure on federal government to combat illegal firearms; mayors pledge to take steps to intensify fight against illegal firearms in absence of federal effort (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Asserting that the federal government had failed to curb gun trafficking, mayors from 15 cities gathered yesterday at Gracie Mansion and agreed to intensify efforts to combat illegal firearms.</p>
        <p>Mayors Michael R. Bloomberg of New York and Thomas M. Menino of Boston, the organizers of the meeting, said the mayors needed to use every tool, from crackdowns on irresponsible gun dealers to new gun-tracing technologies, because federal authorities had abdicated their responsibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The meeting was the most visible example of Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's determination to put the gun issue at the forefront of the nation's consciousness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Asserting that the federal government had failed to curb gun trafficking, mayors from 15 cities gathered yesterday at Gracie Mansion and agreed to intensify efforts to combat illegal firearms.</p>
        <p>Mayors Michael R. Bloomberg of New York and Thomas M. Menino of Boston, the organizers of the meeting, said the mayors needed to use every tool, from crackdowns on irresponsible gun dealers to new gun-tracing technologies, because federal authorities had abdicated their responsibility.</p>
        <p>''It is time for national leadership in the war on gun violence, and if the leadership won't come from Congress or come from the White House, then it has to come from us,'' said Mr. Bloomberg, who has made gun violence a signature issue of his second term. ''When Congress does not take the lead on a major problem that affects the whole nation -- whether it's global warming, welfare, immigration -- it's up to the cities and states to do it.''</p>
        <p>The meeting was the most visible example of Mr. Bloomberg's determination to put the gun issue at the forefront of the nation's consciousness. With the city's efforts to combat gun trafficking faltering at the Congressional and legal levels, the mayor is working to enlist politicians nationwide in the fight to put pressure on Congress and others to tighten the availability of guns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menino said that there were 73 homicides last year in Boston, the highest number in a decade, and that shootings were up so far this year. He described gun violence as an epidemic fueled by a ''code of silence'' among fearful residents, the return of former inmates to their neighborhoods and a growing phenomenon of ''community guns'' used by multiple criminals.</p>
        <p>''The federal government has vigorously taken on bird flu, another epidemic we hear about daily, but has not done one thing about illegal guns and gun violence on the streets,'' Mr. Menino said. The group included the mayors of Washington, Dallas, Philadelphia, Seattle and Milwaukee, among others.</p>
        <p>They signed a six-point ''statement of principles'' that called for punishing gun possession ''to the maximum extent of the law,'' prosecuting dealers who knowingly sell guns to criminals through so-called straw purchasers and opposing two bills before the House of Representatives that would restrict cities' access to gun-tracing data.</p>
        <p>The statement also called for better technologies to detect illegal guns, coordinated legislative and litigation strategies and outreach to other cities.</p>
        <p>The leaders pledged to meet again before the end of the year and to expand the number of mayors involved to at least 50. Several said they hoped the meetings would be the start of a national movement to draw attention to gun deaths, which, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, total 30,000 a year in the United States. Scholars believe that the vast majority of guns used in crimes in this country are acquired illegally.</p>
        <p>However, the mayors have little formal influence over national firearms policy, and the political climate in Washington has been largely hostile to new gun restrictions. ''There's very little that an individual city can do or that an individual state can do to halt the sale of guns to criminals,'' Mr. Bloomberg conceded, adding, ''This is a national issue that requires national attention.''</p>
        <p>Several mayors spoke passionately about their frustration with the porous boundaries exploited by gun traffickers. ''Even though we have very strict gun laws in New Jersey, it's so easy for a person to go to Pennsylvania and buy straw purchases and come over to the city of Trenton and use them,'' said Mayor Douglas H. Palmer of Trenton.</p>
        <p>Mayor Tom Barrett of Milwaukee recalled the anguish of receiving phone calls at home informing him that a child or a bystander had been shot. ''We've had enough,'' he said. ''We want the Congress to respond. We want the Congress to listen to us. We want the Congress to answer these phone calls.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Gregory J. Nickels of Seattle said, ''We're tired of being told that we can't keep our people safe.''</p>
        <p>Mayors Barrett and Nickels, along with Mayors Laura Miller of Dallas and John F. Street of Philadelphia, made presentations to the group about antigun efforts in their cities. The mayors also heard from experts in the field of gun violence.</p>
        <p>''We are not an aberrant country in terms of crime or in terms of violence,'' said David Hemenway, a professor at the Harvard School of Public Health, who compared the United States with other industrialized democracies. ''The only difference is homicides, where we are way out of whack. We have many more handguns and much weaker gun laws than any other country.''</p>
        <p>Douglas A. Muzzio, a professor of public affairs at Baruch College, said Mr. Bloomberg's power may be largely limited to moral suasion, particularly given the continuing declines in crime in New York City.</p>
        <p>''If gun violence were out of control in the cities, as it was in the cowboy days of the late 80's and early 90's, he might have a better chance,'' he said. ''That said, it might be good politics for the mayor to hold such a high-level meeting. It could crystallize the opinions of urban constituents who disproportionately suffer from gun violence.''</p>
        <p>Two gun industry groups said that the mayors should focus on enforcement rather than blame gun makers and dealers.</p>
        <p>''The policies of the Bloomberg administration on guns reek of elitism,'' said Wayne LaPierre, executive vice president of the National Rifle Association, who said that it was easy for rich or famous residents to obtain gun permits ''while the criminals skirt the system.''</p>
        <p>The National Shooting Sports Foundation, which represents gun manufacturers and retailers, said that Mr. Bloomberg's office had denied its request for a chance to make its case to the mayors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg and Mayor Philip A. Amicone of Yonkers were the only Republicans among the mayors who gathered yesterday. Others who took part were Byron W. Brown of Buffalo; David N. Cicilline of Providence, R.I.; Jerramiah T. Healy of Jersey City; Frank Melton of Jackson, Miss.; Eddie A. Perez of Hartford; Kathy Taylor of Tulsa, Okla.; and Anthony A. Williams of Washington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
