<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Lifts but Little Change in the Berkshires</title>
    <meta content="27ski" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/27/travel/escapes/27ski.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1734978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="SKI REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Berkshires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Berkshires (Mass)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Massachusetts</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEED6103FF934A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Lifts but Little Change in the Berkshires</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">More Lifts but Little Change in the Berkshires</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTH EGREMONT, Mass.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I was growing up in southern New England, a skiing day trip for me would often begin with my father's hand on my shoulder, shaking me awake in the predawn darkness of my bedroom.</p>
        <p>''Got to get up there before the good snow is skied off,'' he would say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The greatest appeal of skiing in the Berkshires is its understated pace, an approach that suits families seeking a less outsized skiing experience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I was growing up in southern New England, a skiing day trip for me would often begin with my father's hand on my shoulder, shaking me awake in the predawn darkness of my bedroom.</p>
        <p>''Got to get up there before the good snow is skied off,'' he would say.</p>
        <p>This was not, in fact, a legitimate concern in those days before anyone knew about global warming, but longtime New Englanders pursue life at a certain pace, and when it comes to outdoor excursions, the pursuit begins early. If you don't believe me, you've never stood in the icy cold waters of a New England stream on the first day of fishing season, nearly shoulder to shoulder with 75 other overly organized people waiting for the sun to come up.</p>
        <p>For the nearest skiing in the winter, we would head to the Berkshire Mountains of western Massachusetts, ambling along twisting, narrow country roads that I always felt mimicked the kind of turns I wanted to make when we finally got there. Once we arrived, the walk to the lodge never seemed long enough to remember. Inside the lodge, the smell was of burning logs and hot chocolate. People were sitting around reading the newspaper. Outside, there was no line at the lift.</p>
        <p>Yes, everyone got there early. Then everyone relaxed. That was the pace of skiing the Berkshires, mountains that often go unobserved by the masses barreling by on their way to Vermont's larger celebrated peaks. Visitors to the Berkshires get off the highway and stop.</p>
        <p>I went back to ski the Berkshires a few weeks ago and saw plenty of change -- more crowds, more lifts, more terrain. But when I walked into the old wooden lodge at the Catamount Ski Area, the 32-trail mountain that straddles the Massachusetts and New York border near Connecticut, there were people lounging around reading the newspaper. One family was playing cards. A guy was strumming his folk guitar, gazing dreamily up at the slopes.</p>
        <p>And here's the best example of how things have changed, and yet not changed.</p>
        <p>Bill Gilbert, Catamount's general manager, has installed a new triple chair lift and plans to replace an aging summit lift next season. But Mr. Gilbert, who has been at Catamount for 32 years, is emphatic that the new quad chair will not be a high-speed lift. He doesn't want his new lift flooding Catamount's trails with waves of skiers and riders rapidly deposited at the top.</p>
        <p>It's about the pace of the place. Or, as Mr. Gilbert said, ''The quality of the skiing is more important than the quality of the ride up the hill.''</p>
        <p>This was and still is the nature of skiing and riding in the Berkshires, which includes several ski areas loosely knit along Massachusetts Route 7, which runs north and south. Catamount, in South Egremont, is the most southern, Ski Butternut is a few miles up the road in Great Barrington and Bousquet Ski Area is farther north in Pittsfield. The largest and most northern areas, Jiminy Peak Mountain Resort in Hancock and Berkshire East in Charlemont, are about a three-hour drive from New York City and Boston. These are not mountains to compare in dimension or scope to Eastern magnets like Stowe or Sunday River, but they are ski areas to be appreciated for their accessibility, affordability and traditional charm and style.</p>
        <p>The Berkshires region in general has gone through a noticeable makeover, altered by a booming second-home market. Once-sleepy locations like Great Barrington can now feature traffic jams. But it's also true that new blood has brought new hotels and dining choices, something the area sorely needed.</p>
        <p>The ski areas have gone along with the tide of progress. Catamount is hoping to break ground on a hotel/condo project this spring, and Jiminy Peak recently completed a 21-year development that has spurred the growth of a large, spectacular base village at the bottom of the resort's 43 trails. Public squares and walkways link lodges, condos, a new children's center, restaurants and a brewery. Jiminy Peak has become a destination with more than 2,400 beds on-site.</p>
        <p>That popularity can mean congested trails on peak days, but that is true of the best-known resorts across the Vermont border, too. My advice (and you know where I got it): Get out there before the good snow is skied off and be in the hot tub by 2 p.m.</p>
        <p>But the greatest appeal of skiing in the Berkshires remains its understated pace, an approach that suits families seeking a less outsized skiing experience. Some people aren't looking for the most gnarly backcountry chute around. For goodness' sake, they're trying to relax for the weekend and maybe introduce their kids to a snow sport. To that end, can there be a less intimidating, more kid-friendly name for a ski area than Butternut?</p>
        <p>My father was just trying to pass on his love of skiing, and the Berkshires seemed a natural, nearby choice. Ten years ago, I took my daughter to Catamount for her first ski lesson. It was free.</p>
        <p>Now she wakes me up to go skiing.</p>
        <p>SKI REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
