<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Autopsy Ties Boy's Death To Boot Camp</title>
    <meta content="06bootcamp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/06/us/06bootcamp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1759532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asphyxiation and Suffocation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Autopsies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Martin Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ober, Mark (State Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sexton, Christine Jordan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Jeb (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1DB1F3FF935A35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Autopsy Ties Boy's Death To Boot Camp</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Autopsy Ties Boy's Death to Boot Camp</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE JORDAN SEXTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sexton, Christine Jordan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New autopsy in Florida shows that Martin Lee Anderson, 14-year-old boy who died in boot camp, died from suffocation; initial autopsy blamed sickle cell ailment, despite video showing guards beating youth; State Atty Mark Ober continues investigation ordered by Gov Jeb Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin Lee Anderson, a 14-year-old boy who died in January a day after entering a boot camp in northwest Florida, died from suffocation and not sickle cell trait, a new autopsy released yesterday concluded.</p>
        <p>The initial medical examiner in Bay County contended that the boy had died from the rare condition of sickle cell trait despite a video that showed guards at the boot camp beating him. But State Attorney Mark Ober, who was appointed by Gov. Jeb Bush to investigate Martin's death, ordered a new autopsy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new autopsy said a 14-year-old boy who died at a boot camp in northwest Florida died from suffocation and not sickle cell trait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Martin Lee Anderson, a 14-year-old boy who died in January a day after entering a boot camp in northwest Florida, died from suffocation and not sickle cell trait, a new autopsy released yesterday concluded.</p>
        <p>The initial medical examiner in Bay County contended that the boy had died from the rare condition of sickle cell trait despite a video that showed guards at the boot camp beating him. But State Attorney Mark Ober, who was appointed by Gov. Jeb Bush to investigate Martin's death, ordered a new autopsy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ober released the autopsy results, but did not make any arrests yesterday and said in a statement that he had no ''timeline'' for completing the investigation.</p>
        <p>At a press conference in Tallahassee the boy's parents, Gina Jones and Robert Anderson, and their lawyer, Ben Crump, thanked Governor Bush, Mr. Ober and the Hillsborough County medical examiner, Vernard I. Adams, a medical doctor who conducted the second autopsy.</p>
        <p>''The truth is out,'' Ms. Jones said. ''We all knew how Martin passed away so I am relieved and happy today. It's a beginning. Justice needs to be served.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Adams concluded that the beating on Jan. 5 by boot camp guards left bruises but did not directly cause Martin's death. Guards punched and choked the boy after he said he was unable to finish running laps. The beating was captured on tape.</p>
        <p>''Martin Anderson's death was caused by suffocation due to actions of the guards at the boot camp,'' Dr. Adams said in a release.</p>
        <p>He added, ''The suffocation was caused by manual occlusion of the mouth, in concert with the forced inhalation of ammonia fumes that cause spasms of the vocal cords, resulting in internal blockage of the upper airway.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Adams consulted with several pathologists as well as a pediatric critical-care specialist and a pediatric hematologist. He also asked NASA to improve the quality of the videotape, and it reduced glare and inserted a digital clock.</p>
        <p>While the parents were satisfied with the release of the second autopsy, members of the Florida Black Legislative Caucus expressed anger that no arrests had been made.</p>
        <p>''If the guards caused his death, then they need to be arrested immediately,'' said State Senator Frederica A. Wilson, a Democrat from Miami, who added, ''We can't accept that.''</p>
        <p>The death has sparked protests and was partly to blame for the sudden resignation of one of Florida's top law-enforcement officials. The Florida Department of Law Enforcement executive director, Guy Tunnell, resigned after the discovery that he had sent e-mail messages to the Bay County sheriff discussing the continuing investigation into the death. After the discovery, Mr. Ober removed Mr. Tunnell's agency from any role in the investigation.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush appointed Mr. Ober after criticism of the initial autopsy done by the Bay County medical examiner, Dr. Charles Siebert. It concluded that Martin died from complications of sickle cell trait.</p>
        <p>Dr. Siebert said yesterday that he stood by the findings of his autopsy.</p>
        <p>''I am still sticking to my findings at this point, since I don't have any proof of his findings, said Dr. Siebert, who added that he had ruled out suffocation as a cause of the boy's death based on hospital reports that, Dr. Siebert said, indicated that the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood were low.</p>
        <p>Dr. Siebert said that there was an ''automatic'' assumption that Dr. Adams's results were correct and that ''is very premature at this point.'' He also said he expected the Florida Medical Examiners Commission to assemble a probable-cause panel to review if there was any wrongdoing and whether his licenses should be revoked.</p>
        <p>''I don't see a way of avoiding it,'' Dr. Siebert said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said in a release that he considered the actions of the Bay County boot camp guards ''deplorable'' and that he was committed to providing any resources Mr. Ober might need to complete the investigation ''as quickly as possible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
