<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rebuilding Jamaica Bay, One Load of Sand at a Time</title>
    <meta content="07bay" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/07/nyregion/07bay.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1774326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reclamation of Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jamaica Bay (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Conservation Department (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Park Service</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Anthony D (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Confessore, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reclamation of Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reclamation of Land</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DF1030F934A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rebuilding Jamaica Bay, One Load of Sand at a Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rebuilding Jamaica Bay, One Load of Sand at a Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS CONFESSORE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Confessore, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Work begins on ambitious $13 million campaign to rebuild salt marshes in first major reclamation effort at Jamaica Bay in New York City; 12,000 acre estuary is home to numerous crab, fish and bird species; marshes would disappear over next 15 years if current rate of attrition continues; plan is to repair erosion using sand mixed with water to create new mudflats; Rep Anthony D Weiner led efforts to gain financing for project, which is combined effort of Army Corps of Engineers, New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, National Parks Service and Port Authority of New York and New Jersey; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the past few decades, for reasons nobody fully understands, the salt marshes of Jamaica Bay have been washing away. The grasses that anchor the bay's island archipelago have slowly withered, leaving the sand to drift off with the tides, the disintegration accelerating as time went on until nearly 50 acres of marsh disappeared with each passing year.</p>
        <p>''It was a war of attrition,'' said Dan Mundy, the founder of the environmental group Jamaica Bay Ecowatchers, as he stood yesterday on Elders Point Island, a marsh island that has shrunk to a fraction of its original size. ''Every day, we're losing thousands of square feet.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the past few decades, for reasons nobody fully understands, the salt marshes of Jamaica Bay have been washing away. The grasses that anchor the bay's island archipelago have slowly withered, leaving the sand to drift off with the tides, the disintegration accelerating as time went on until nearly 50 acres of marsh disappeared with each passing year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the past few decades, for reasons nobody fully understands, the salt marshes of Jamaica Bay have been washing away. The grasses that anchor the bay's island archipelago have slowly withered, leaving the sand to drift off with the tides, the disintegration accelerating as time went on until nearly 50 acres of marsh disappeared with each passing year.</p>
        <p>''It was a war of attrition,'' said Dan Mundy, the founder of the environmental group Jamaica Bay Ecowatchers, as he stood yesterday on Elders Point Island, a marsh island that has shrunk to a fraction of its original size. ''Every day, we're losing thousands of square feet.''</p>
        <p>But during the last month, work began on an ambitious $13 million campaign to rebuild the salt marshes, which would otherwise disappear over the next 15 years if the current rate of attrition were to continue. It is the first major reclamation effort targeted at Jamaica Bay -- a 12,000-acre estuary where numerous clam, crab, fish and bird species can be found -- and one of the largest environmental projects in the city's history.</p>
        <p>''We have to make sure the marshlands and the ecosystem they support are around for future generations,'' Representative Anthony D. Weiner, a Democrat whose Congressional district includes many neighborhoods in Brooklyn and Queens that ring the bay, said at a news conference and marsh tour yesterday that commemorated the early stages of the reclamation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiner led efforts to gain financing for the project, a combined effort by the Army Corps of Engineers, the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, the National Park Service and the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, officials from those agencies assembled on Elders Point Island, where their speeches were periodically interrupted by the sounds of jumbo jets from nearby Kennedy International Airport, and their audience was made up mostly of seagulls and reporters. A stiff breeze rustled pots of cordgrass sitting nearby, as construction crews spread wet sand on the water's edge.</p>
        <p>Over the last few weeks, 120,000 cubic yards of sand have been added to the eastern half of Elders Point. In the next two years, the project will restore about 70 more acres, anchoring future reclamation projects in the marshes.</p>
        <p>The project had to overcome some significant early resistance. During the 1990's, residents of Broad Channel, the island neighborhood that sits in Jamaica Bay between Howard Beach and the Rockaways, began noticing that the marshes they considered their backyard were shrinking. State environmental officials, however, were initially slow to agree.</p>
        <p>''It took an enormous amount of arguing with the powers that be to convince those of us in government that there was a problem,'' Mr. Weiner said.</p>
        <p>Satellite photography in the late 1990's showed conclusively that the marsh islands -- there are 16 left in Jamaica Bay -- were ebbing away, and that Elders Point would most likely go next. (Elders Point, once a single island of 132 acres, is now two islands totaling about 21 acres.) A 2002 report prepared by a panel of environmentalists and scientists laid out several theories for the marshes' disintegration, from rising sea levels to overly clean bay water that deprived the islands of waterborne sediment.</p>
        <p>The restoration plan is financed by the Corps of Engineers, in connection with a $1.6 billion project to deepen New York Harbor, and by the Port Authority.</p>
        <p>The current plan repairs the erosion using sand that was dredged last year from near the Rockaways. Stored at nearby Floyd Bennett Field, the sand -- mixed with water -- is being pumped through a three-mile-long pipe along the bay floor and spit out near the reclamation area. During the next two years, workers will place by hand about 900,000 marsh plants, mostly cordgrass, on the new mudflats.</p>
        <p>The plants, too, have local roots. They were grown from seeds collected at the site last year and germinated at federal greenhouses in New Jersey, Maryland, Michigan and West Virginia.</p>
        <p>''What's there now are remnants of the historic marsh, like a patchwork quilt,'' said Scott Nicholson, a project manager for the Corps of Engineers. Within about five years, he said, the new marsh should achieve the density of the existing one, after which the corps will continue to monitor the island's stability for another five years.</p>
        <p>''What we're going to see out there is a high-density marsh island with grass that will bend and wave in the wind,'' Mr. Nicholson added. ''The birds will be attracted to the kinds of shellfish and fish that thrive in that sort of marsh environment. And we expect the island to be a vital part of the Jamaica Bay ecosystem. It will be really beautiful.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
