<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Keep Flying and Stay Green</title>
    <meta content="15prac" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/15/travel/15prac.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061022T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1797171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER: ECO-CONSCIOUS TRAVEL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0DB1330F936A25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Keep Flying and Stay Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Eco-Conscious Travel: How to Keep Flying and Stay Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE HIGGINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONCERNED about her impact on the environment, Nora Miller, 56, from Tucson, regularly recycles papers and plastics. She saves energy by keeping the lights and air-conditioning off when she can and setting her thermostat at 79 degrees or higher -- even on some of Arizona's hottest days. But when it comes to travel, Ms. Miller said, she isn't always as conscientious.</p>
        <p>''I feel a little bit stuck when I'm traveling,'' she said, pointing out that on business trips she tends to stay wherever her company puts her up, and to get there she must use planes and cars that emit heat-trapping greenhouse gases. ''I think about it,'' she added, ''but I don't always do a good job of doing something about it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of travel Web sites and nonprofit groups are selling so-called carbon offsets designed to compensate for travel-generated emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONCERNED about her impact on the environment, Nora Miller, 56, from Tucson, regularly recycles papers and plastics. She saves energy by keeping the lights and air-conditioning off when she can and setting her thermostat at 79 degrees or higher -- even on some of Arizona's hottest days. But when it comes to travel, Ms. Miller said, she isn't always as conscientious.</p>
        <p>''I feel a little bit stuck when I'm traveling,'' she said, pointing out that on business trips she tends to stay wherever her company puts her up, and to get there she must use planes and cars that emit heat-trapping greenhouse gases. ''I think about it,'' she added, ''but I don't always do a good job of doing something about it.''</p>
        <p>She did find an opportunity to do something, however, when she booked a trip to Portland, Ore., on Travelocity.com this summer. Among all the add-ons that the site pushed during the booking process was a new program that offers to neutralize the environmental impact of customer trips by planting trees, which absorb carbon dioxide, the primary greenhouse gas. Ms. Miller promptly paid $25 to have enough trees planted, by the calculations of the nonprofit Conservation Fund, the group running the program, to offset the carbon emissions that could be attributed to her trip -- and assuaged her travel guilt.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of nice when you're up there motoring along at 500 miles an hour, spewing stuff into the atmosphere, to know at least a little bit will be taken care of,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Call it penance for eco-conscious travelers: a growing number of travel Web sites and nonprofit groups are selling so-called carbon offsets designed to compensate for travel-generated emissions by reducing levels of greenhouse gases in some unrelated way.</p>
        <p>Here's how it works: Travelers go to one of several carbon-offset Web sites and use an online ''carbon calculator'' to determine the approximate amount of carbon dioxide produced when they drive, fly or otherwise burn fossil fuels. Then they buy ''offsets,'' donating money for projects that promise to produce energy without burning fossil fuels or otherwise reduce greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. The reduction financed by the purchase is supposed to equal the amount of gas the trip created, per passenger. Typically the price is anywhere from $5 to $30, depending on the length of the trip and the form of transportation. Some sites also offer predetermined fees based on popular itineraries so travelers don't have to log their exact miles.</p>
        <p>Expedia, for example, which teamed up with TerraPass, a Web-based for-profit company in Menlo Park, Calif., and started offering carbon offsets in August, charges $5.99 to offset about 1,000 pounds of carbon dioxide -- the amount emitted, per passenger, on a round-trip flight of up to 2,200 miles; $16.99 for a cross-country flight of up to 6,500 miles; and $29.99 for an international flight of up to 13,000 miles. A traveler who buys offsets for a medium or long-haul flight gets a free ''Carbon Balanced Flyer'' luggage tag.</p>
        <p>Yet it is unclear how much impact these programs actually have on climate change -- or whether they function mostly as a way for travelers to justify the amount of pollution they generate on trips. Some, like the Conservation Fund's Go Zero program, plant trees on protected land. Others, like MyClimate, offered by Sustainable Travel International, create renewable energy, often through projects in developing countries. A MyClimate donation, for example, might go toward replacing diesel boilers with solar power to heat water in schools.</p>
        <p>In the two years or so since these programs appeared, they have become increasingly popular among the growing number of travelers who take vacations where they can volunteer on humanitarian projects, stay in eco-friendly lodges and drive hybrid rental cars. MyClimate collected $342,926 from the sales of carbon offsets last year, which it said neutralized about 30,000 metric tons of carbon dioxide. So far this year, the company has already collected more than $2 million, which according to its figures will offset roughly 170,000 metric tons of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>While that may be a start, it's far from a solution to the problem of global warming. Offset programs acknowledge this. ''Climate change is a six-and-a-half-gigaton problem,'' Tom Arnold, chief executive of TerraPass, said. ''You're not going to need a sweater after you buy one of these things.''</p>
        <p>Rather, he said, voluntary carbon offsetting is just one part of a comprehensive strategy needed to tackle global warming, encourage corporate action and promote long-term public policy on climate change.</p>
        <p>Passengers who contribute typically understand the limitations and give the money anyway. ''Honestly, I can't really believe this could result in significant carbon emission improvements at any corporation,'' said Justine Johnson, a veterinarian from East Greenwich, R.I., who paid more than $200 at MyClimate.com to offset the impact of her car and plane trips for the year. ''But it also was such a small investment that I figured I would do it anyway. Mainly I was casting a vote. I thought that if enough people demonstrate a willingness to put money toward solving this problem, then maybe the government will start listening.''</p>
        <p>There are several things to keep in mind when deciding where to put your money. Most of the new travel-related carbon reduction programs say they base their offset calculations on guidelines developed by the World Resources Institute, a nonprofit environmental group in Washington. But there are no widely accepted common standards for determining how much money will offset how much carbon. To ensure you're making a genuine contribution to efforts to slow global warming, be sure that an independent third party has evaluated the program to confirm that it is delivering on the carbon reductions it promises.</p>
        <p>Green-e (www.green-e.org), a renewable electricity certification program administered by the nonprofit Center for Resource Solutions in San Francisco, is working with the World Resources Institute and other environmental groups on certification standards for voluntary offset programs. The Center for Resource Solutions has also performed independent verifications for some carbon offset programs, including TerraPass.</p>
        <p>Sustainable Travel International, a nonprofit organization based in Boulder, Colo., offers information about several carbon offset programs at www.carbonoffsets.org, including the percentage of funds invested in actual projects and whether the program is verified by a third party.</p>
        <p>It's important to ask a simple question, said Mark Trexler, president of Trexler Climate and Energy Services, a climate change consulting firm in Portland, Ore.: ''Is something in the world around us changing as a result of what you are doing?'' If the project would occur regardless of funds from an offset project -- say, the government already mandates the program -- then a traveler's donation isn't really offsetting anything.</p>
        <p>Planting trees has its complications, too. Trees typically don't sequester much carbon until they mature, so it could take years for your offset to take effect.</p>
        <p>Bottom line, said Mr. Trexler: ''If it is a new project and your money is making that happen, then the argument for 'I've offset my emissions' is a legitimate one. If you're flying jumbo jets and simply making a philanthropic contribution to something that isn't changing behavior and isn't resulting in new projects, it's simply increasing someone's profit margin.''</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER: ECO-CONSCIOUS TRAVEL</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 22, 2006, Sunday  The Practical Traveler column last Sunday about eco-conscious travel misstated the Internet address for MyClimate, a program to aid development of renewable energy sources. It is www.myclimate.org.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 22, 2006, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Practical Traveler column last Sunday about eco-conscious travel misstated the Internet address for MyClimate, a program to aid development of renewable energy sources. It is www.myclimate.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
