<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Headline</title>
    <meta content="D--Erasmo.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/13/books/review/D_Erasmo.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1782396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Books by Lori Lansens and Shelley Jackson"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Shelley</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Half Life (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Girls, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E5D9103FF930A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Headline</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">My Sister and Me</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STACEY D'ERASMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">D'Erasmo, Stacey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE GIRLS</p>
        <p>By Lori Lansens.</p>
        <p>345 pp. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>HALF LIFE</p>
        <p>By Shelley Jackson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 440 pp.</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two new novels imagine the lives of conjoined girls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE GIRLS</p>
        <p>By Lori Lansens.</p>
        <p>345 pp. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>HALF LIFE</p>
        <p>By Shelley Jackson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 440 pp.</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
        <p>As great as the odds are against conjoined, or Siamese, twins being born, they must be greater still against two novels arriving in the same season -- or three, if you count DBC Pierre's ''Ludmila's Broken English,'' published in May -- that concern the lives and loves of conjoined twins. One wishes to make some sort of bold, sweeping cultural statement about this phenomenon, that it's because of George Bush or global warming or gay marriage or late capitalism. One wishes, also, to pun and execute clever critical moves: two novels, joined at the hip; a pair of books that must be read together, one the secret sharer or doppelgänger of the other; better yet, one the slightly asymmetrical reflection of the other; two curiosities; maybe an allusion to ''Persona'' and female subjectivity (both novels are written by women, and concern conjoined females); double lives; a modern insecurity about identity; and so on. The image of conjoined twins is already so metaphorical, so poetic, that it's nearly impossible to resist the impulse to read with your metafictional radar set on high, to hover closely over the conceit and attempt to solve the novels as if they were a matching pair of riddles.</p>
        <p>Just like certain sets of more ordinary twins, however, these two books are alike only on the surface. Their aims are as different as the styles in which they are written. ''The Girls,'' by Lori Lansens, is a ballad, a melancholy song of two very strange, enchanted girls who live out their peculiar, ordinary lives in a rural corner of Canada. Shelley Jackson's ''Half Life'' is the textual equivalent of an installation, a multivocal, polymorphous, dialogic, dystopian satire wrapped around a murder mystery wrapped around a bildungsroman. ''The Girls'' glides by like a watercolor dream, finding its poetry in dailiness and the universalities of human desire and connection; ''Half Life'' is a Molotov cocktail of highly combustible intelligence. If these women, six of them counting the authors, share anything at all, it is an interest in ambivalence. They want to know: Are two heads better than one? What is the price of autonomy? Is a life that's so dependent, so vexed and so apparently freakish worth living? The one place where these two otherwise unique books meet is a tender juncture we can all recognize: separation anxiety.</p>
        <p>''The Girls'' tells the story of Rose and Ruby Darlen, who are not only literally but spiritually attached for eternity. Born joined at the head in 1974 to a feckless teenage mother who abandons them, and reared by a delightfully open-minded adoptive couple, the Darlen girls are darling girls, indeed. Rose is the writer and the physically stronger of the two; Ruby collects Indian artifacts and reluctantly agrees to Rose's idea that they write, together, the story of their life in alternating chapters. Ruby's are much shorter and fewer. (''Books are not my thing,'' as she says.) They live in a small Canadian town called Leaford, where they both are and aren't a continual spectacle, working in the local library and weathering the usual stuff of life: births, deaths, love, friendship, loss. They also share a sad secret that makes their lives, already rare, potentially more precious still. Lansens, who has a gentle, open way of writing, makes of these two girls a kind of perfect marriage, harmonious and everlasting. ''In our first-floor bedroom,'' writes Rose, ''with the queen-size bed and the entwined-hearts comforter and the shelf for Ruby's stuffed animals and the rack for my baseball cards and library books, my sister and I were sheltered in the essence of normal. We were not hidden, but unseen. The orange farmhouse was our castle.'' Their only enemy is time, because twins joined at the head don't often live past 30. If this dream of union sometimes flirts with sentimentality, it is also engagingly perverse. For Lansens and her ever-loving girls, separation -- for romance, say, or sex, or individual pursuits -- really isn't necessary. Surgery is not remotely interesting to them. Rose and Ruby never divide, they just add: lovers, interests, sensations. They're fine with being double, and they live happily ever after for however long they have left, in a world of love.</p>
        <p>Not so the restless, jagged, post-everything Nora Olney of Shelley Jackson's ''Half Life,'' who despises her conjoined twin, Blanche, and wants nothing so much as to cut off Blanche's pretty but annoying head. This is partly understandable considering that a) Blanche appears to have been asleep for the last 15 years and so is just bobbing there, vestigially and b) evidence accumulates throughout the book that Blanche isn't asleep at all, but is actually awake and a murderer. It's complicated. In fact, the entire novel is quite complicated, a whirligig of futuristic constructs, elaborate adventures, Venn diagrams, black comedy, Boolean systems, hilarious send-ups of identity politics, lists, songs and mad science. Nora is avidly scribbling the whole thing down in a notebook in her ''small, black, left-leaning script.'' Jackson is the author of ''Patchwork Girl,'' an acclaimed hypertext novel that reimagines ''Frankenstein''; ''The Melancholy of Anatomy,'' a book of short stories; two children's books; and ''Skin,'' a story written in tattoos on the bodies of nearly 3,000 participants, who are the only ones who will ever know what the complete story actually says. With her sister, Pamela, Jackson has also constructed a fascinating Web site called ''The Doll Games,'' which is simultaneously a game, a meditation, an art project, a remembrance and an exploration of the various things dolls can get up to, some of which are decidedly not nice. Jackson is fascinated by the uncanny places where like and unlike things meet: words and various media, like skin, page and screen; bodies and body parts; real girls and fake ones; philosophy and fiction.</p>
        <p>The ambition of ''Half Life'' is truly glorious, and passage by passage Jackson is capable of fantastic runs. Chief among the many pleasures of the novel is her creation of an alternative present where nuclear explosions have created an entire populace of conjoined twins, a thriving, energetic subculture of ''twofers'' who have their own Pride days, marketing niches, film festivals, political candidates and some rather ingenious sexual practices. Amid all this twofer political correctness and boosterism, Nora is a rebel because of her retrograde hunger: she wants to be one person at a time. In fact, she'd kill for it, though she has to go to London for a back-alley removal of the troublesome Blanche. Things don't quite work out as planned, of course, though the putative object of Nora's quest, individuality, seems less interesting as a fictional subject to Jackson than individuality as an irresolvable metaphysical dilemma: the awkward, ambiguous, sometimes slapstick scramble for selfhood as Nora bounces and careers through a world fanatically devoted to couples and the joys of permanent togetherness, no matter that it was produced by radioactive fallout.</p>
        <p>All this razzle-dazzle, all the allusions, the narrative loop-de-loops: it gets a bit busy. By the middle of the book, I wasn't sure how many more cleverness hurdles I could clear, and I'm sure I stumbled over some. I don't really know what a Boolean system is; I looked it up, then I forgot again. I skipped past the Venn diagram, though it was charmingly drawn. Instead, I found myself squinting along another, less intricate line that also runs the entire length of the book, and, in fact, of Lansens's as well: it's the story of a woman attempting to write her own life story. To be, in Nora's case, the author. The only one. Getting there, for Jackson, is a comedy and it's also a bloody war, and it's never clear who's winning. For Lansens, writing of a sweeter, kinder place with sweeter citizens, it's more a case of nobody's perfect as we all race the clock. But in either case, or both cases, there really aren't two joined women at the center of these novels. There's just one woman, writing.</p>
        <p>Books by Lori Lansens and Shelley Jackson Stacey D'Erasmo's most recent novel is ''A Seahorse Year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Stacey D'Erasmo's most recent novel is ''A Seahorse Year.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
