<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Fuel for a Stalled Upstate Economy</title>
    <meta content="14shelby" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/14/nyregion/14shelby.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1761744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Shelby Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shelby (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Western New York Energy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staba, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D9143EF937A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Fuel for a Stalled Upstate Economy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Fuel for a Stalled Upstate Economy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STABA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Staba, David</byline>
      <dateline>SHELBY, N.Y., May 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Western New York Energy plans to build an $87 million ethanol production facility on old cabbage farm in Shelby, NY; local officials are hoping region's agricultural base and growing interest in alternative forms of fuel will bring economic rebirth to withered industrial areas of upstate New York; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The railroad once carried the economy of this rural town and its upstate New York neighbors.</p>
        <p>Farmers took their crops to the nearest depot to send to market. Massive blocks of sandstone from local quarries were shipped out by rail. And vegetable processors like H. J. Heinz and the toy manufacturer Fisher-Price located factories here to take advantage of the trains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials in Shelby, N.Y., and nearby areas see an opportunity to revive their economies by getting into the alternative fuel business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The railroad once carried the economy of this rural town and its upstate New York neighbors.</p>
        <p>Farmers took their crops to the nearest depot to send to market. Massive blocks of sandstone from local quarries were shipped out by rail. And vegetable processors like H. J. Heinz and the toy manufacturer Fisher-Price located factories here to take advantage of the trains.</p>
        <p>But the industrial base of western New York has slowly withered over the last 50 years, with people following jobs out of the region. Fisher-Price in nearby Medina closed its plant in 1995, putting 700 people out of work. And rail traffic slowed to a trickle in the long economic decline, with little more than excursions these days runs by the Medina Railroad Museum.</p>
        <p>Now, however, local officials are hoping to parlay the railroads, the region's agricultural base and a growing interest in alternative forms of fuel into an economic rebirth.</p>
        <p>Western New York Energy, headed by a farmer who has lived in the area all his life and is backed by local investors, announced last week that it intends to build an $87 million ethanol production facility on an old cabbage farm in Shelby. Construction is set to begin soon, and once the plant is up and running in 2008, it will transform 20 million bushels of corn a year into 50 million gallons of fuel.</p>
        <p>''We're basically an agricultural community,'' said Dale S. Root, president of the Orleans County Farm Bureau and a fifth-generation farmer. ''We have no major cities and no big factories. This ethanol plant is going to be the biggest thing to happen here in a long time.''</p>
        <p>The announcement has provided the area with sorely needed good news. A week earlier, Bernzomatic, a maker of hand-held torches and one of the last remaining manufacturers in what was once a thriving industrial district, announced it would transfer operations -- and 200 or more jobs -- to Shanghai.</p>
        <p>And in Lockport, about 15 miles to the west, the future of the region's largest employer, Delphi, is in limbo. Last week, lawyers for the auto-parts manufacturer asked a federal bankruptcy court judge to allow it to nullify its contract with the United Auto Workers, which represents about 3,000 workers at the Lockport plant. Union members on Thursday and Friday voted to give their leaders authority to call a strike if Delphi's request is granted.</p>
        <p>Shelby's location in the midst of a traditionally agricultural area and adjacent to an underused rail line makes it a natural site for the ethanol plant, said John Sawyer, Western New York Energy's chief executive.</p>
        <p>''I really believe in alternative fuels,'' said Mr. Sawyer, who grew up in nearby Albion and operated a grain farm to the southeast in Livingston County until two years ago. ''It's an important issue in our country, and I've thought that for a long time. Until the price of gas climbed to the point it has in the past year, I don't think people in our country really wanted to take it seriously.''</p>
        <p>New York State is taking the gasoline alternative seriously enough that Gov. George E. Pataki attended Monday's news conference and has pledged $6 million in state funds to the effort, plus low-cost power and a package of tax incentives.</p>
        <p>Groundbreaking at the 144-acre site is set for June, with production expected to begin by January 2008. Company officials hope it will be the first functioning ethanol plant in the state.</p>
        <p>While the ethanol plant is expected to employ about 50 workers, Mr. Pataki predicted the development would ultimately create about 500 jobs, including those on the railroad and at a carbon dioxide processing plant that would handle waste gas produced by the production process. Another marketable byproduct will be high-protein, high-fat animal feed.</p>
        <p>''I look at this as a tool for development,'' said Merle L. Draper, the Shelby town supervisor. ''The size of this project reopens the rail.''</p>
        <p>Plans call for an offshoot of the line to run through the site and to increase rail traffic from 600 cars to 6,500 annually, Mr. Draper said. About half of the state's contribution will be used to improve the existing rails and extend them.</p>
        <p>Michael Sawyer, John Sawyer's son and the company's project manager, said that while most ethanol plants in the United States are in the Midwest's grain belt, Western New York Energy chose the area because it is near the enormous potential customer base in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>While some of the corn required will be shipped in, the company plans to buy as much as possible from local farmers, Michael Sawyer said. As in much of the rural upstate areas, agriculture remains the leading industry in Orleans County.</p>
        <p>''With a demand of more than 20 million bushels per year, we'll spur even more production,'' he said. ''We're confident we'll buy as much of our corn as possible from farmers right here in New York State.''</p>
        <p>The plant will encourage area farmers to put fallow land into production, as well as saving them on transportation costs, Mr. Root said.</p>
        <p>''It's going to give our farmers a market that's desperately needed,'' he said. ''Right now, we have to ship 50 to 100 miles away. Now we'll be able to just take it into town.''</p>
        <p>Shelby Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
