<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Sweet Debt</title>
    <meta content="305wwln--lede.1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/05/magazine/305wwln_lede.1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1744208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 3-05-06"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirn, Walter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DB1631F936A35750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Sweet Debt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Home Sweet Debt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Kirn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirn, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Kirn column on how Americans' feelings about their homes have been affected by fact that a house or apartment is now frequently owner's chief economic asset, with potential to grow and decline in value, and a mortgage is complicated financial instrument at mercy of interest rate fluctuations; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every night, like millions of other homeowners, I lock the doors, turn off the lights, peer out the windows to check for burglars and go to bed inside my money. It's all around me, in the walls and ceilings, under the floors and spread across the yard. Some nights, when I'm lying very still, I imagine that I can even feel it growing. That faint vibration in the foundation? That subtle rumbling in the Sheetrock? It's not a small earthquake; it's equity accumulating in the cozy three-bedroom portfolio I call home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Does taking on greater financial risk to own a house prevent you from bonding with it?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every night, like millions of other homeowners, I lock the doors, turn off the lights, peer out the windows to check for burglars and go to bed inside my money. It's all around me, in the walls and ceilings, under the floors and spread across the yard. Some nights, when I'm lying very still, I imagine that I can even feel it growing. That faint vibration in the foundation? That subtle rumbling in the Sheetrock? It's not a small earthquake; it's equity accumulating in the cozy three-bedroom portfolio I call home.</p>
        <p>Or maybe it's equity vanishing? I can't tell. I'm not a banker or a broker. When I bought my house several years ago, paying the asking price without a fuss after selling another house at its asking price, I didn't regard it as an investment but as a dwelling place that suited my needs. It reminded me of the house that I grew up in, whose value I never once thought to ask my parents about because it wasn't expressible in dollars. I loved that old house for its feeling of security, its reassuring wooden solidity, and that feeling was what I hoped to duplicate when I moved into this one decades later.</p>
        <p>But things had changed, I realized, as time went on and my book of mortgage coupons grew thinner. The physical structure in which I hung my clothes and arranged my furniture was also a financial structure, and the security it seemed to offer fluctuated with the market -- not only the local housing market but the national and international credit markets. A refuge? A castle? It didn't quite feel that way. Once I had remodeled the place, refinanced it and borrowed against its appreciating value to buy a depreciating car, I discovered -- as so many of us do these days -- that I was living in a bond with bathrooms, a stock certificate with a front porch.</p>
        <p>I know I'm not alone in my mixed feelings about the economic and cultural shifts that have turned what we once called ''houses'' and ''apartments'' into what we now refer to as ''residential real estate.'' It's a chilly, bureaucratic term that reflects an unsentimental fact: Americans have far more than their emotions tied up in their homes these days. They're our chief economic assets, in many cases -- our sleep-in piggy banks and even our slot machines -- and we're spending more and risking more in order to acquire them and hang on to them.</p>
        <p>And many of us are worrying about being able to, thanks to a hyperactive lending industry that has been making it easier than ever to get in over our heads. The simple fixed-rate mortgages of old whose first and final payments were the same (and which I remember occasioning backyard barbecues when they were finally paid off) have mutated into complicated instruments that make borrowers more susceptible than ever to the fickle gods of finance. This is good and bad. Adjustable-rate mortgages (including the misleadingly named and popular ''interest only'' variety) have brought down initial payments for many people who might not have been able to buy a home at all, but they have also induced a lot of folks to purchase more home than they can handle. Big spenders have also been lured by lenders' willingness to raise the ceilings on the amounts they'll lend.</p>
        <p>The new mortgages, which amount to bets that a borrower's income will keep pace if interest rates rise (which they're doing and look as if they'll go on doing), cast doubt on whether the word ''homeowner'' is even widely suitable anymore. ''Home-hoper'' or merely ''occupier'' might be better. Even in the bubbliest local markets, like those on both coasts and in certain favored ZIP codes, it's hard to know if the four walls around you are standing firm or closing in. It all depends, and on so many things.</p>
        <p>As an adjustable-rate-mortgage holder whose loan will reset in 2007 (along with an estimated $1 trillion in similarly structured personal debt), I find myself reading the papers nowadays with an especially anxious eye for looming short- to midterm problems that might somehow boost my payments to the moon. Unfortunately, like many in my position, I lack the sophistication to discern what sort of problems I need to be afraid of. A dirty bomb? Global warming? The bird flu? Will they help or harm me? Not as a human being, I mean, or as a citizen, but as a guy on a budget whose old frame house could, frankly, use a second bathroom, if he could only get the financing.</p>
        <p>It's easy to fall into shameful solipsism when your ability to retain your dwelling -- or to draw on its worth for a range of goods and services, from riding mowers to Carnival Cruises to children's college tuitions -- is subject to distant unmanageable forces, many of which weren't even manifest when you first bought the place. I sometimes think that it doesn't seem fair to have signed a mortgage before the War on Terrorism, as my monthly payments may rise because of it. Maybe I should have negotiated this exemption: ''The party of the first part shall not be penalized for any inflationary processes not evident to him at the time of closing.''</p>
        <p>Isn't the idea of a home to give a person a sanctuary from history? To grant him shelter from the worldwide storm? Maybe in theory. Maybe way back when. Today, however, our ''residential properties'' (because of the ways we have arranged to pay for them) are a source of our vulnerability. I live in Montana, on a farm, which ought to be as fine a place to hide as this enormous continent can offer, yet I jump every time the federal government releases what the business pages call ''new numbers.'' I don't want new numbers! I want the old numbers to stay the same! I want to hold on to my house -- or, even better, to sell it at a profit and buy another one, maybe in Alaska.</p>
        <p>But maybe I'm overcorrecting, as the financial writers say. According to some studies, there's encouraging news hiding inside all the jargon and statistics that homeowners nowadays must keep abreast of even when they're neither selling nor buying but merely trying to determine where they stand and wondering how their standing can be improved. In a lot of regions in America, the percentage of the median income needed to buy the median-priced home is lower than it was 20 years ago. Housing is cheaper in these places, relatively speaking. But is it, really? Not if, like me and millions of other homeowners, people have turned the roofs over their heads into gigantic credit cards by taking out home-equity credit lines. And not if taxes are rising, as they are here, along with insurance rates and power bills and the price of those rotary gizmos that you push to spread fertilizer pellets on the lawn.</p>
        <p>Having your home as your chief asset sounds like a snug and tidy situation, but when you consider all the ways that such an asset can shrink, seduce you into overreaching, expose you to uncontrollable global troubles or just plain fall to ruin, it can make you nostalgic for passbook savings accounts. It can also, in subtle ways, prevent you from truly bonding with the place. Can an asset -- a thing of numbers -- be a home? Eudora Welty, the writer, died a few years ago, at 92, while residing in the same Mississippi house that she lived in as a child. I've been in a few such long-tenanted domiciles. They feel like shells excreted by their occupants, like extensions of their owners' souls and bodies. They barely feel physical, in some respects. They're human biographies written in brick and wood, and it's hard to imagine them on the open market, suffering the pragmatic molestations of appraisers, real-estate agents and inspectors. Worse is imagining how theymight be advertised in the reductive language of the trade: ''3 br, 1* baths, fenced yard, all appliances inc., needs some updates.''</p>
        <p>Although there's no telling how long I'll keep my house or what the market will do to our relationship, I like to think that the place is part of me and reflects my spirit, tastes and habits. I know that it has begun to smell like me. I also know some of the stories behind its worn spots, like the groove in the kitchen floor where I slide back and forth in my chair while writing. To be honest, I'm wary of growing too attached. Sometimes at night I lay down my weary head, and it feels as if I'm resting inside a big thick checkbook. Whose balance I don't (and may not want to) know.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 3-05-06 Walter Kirn, a frequent contributor, is the author, most recently, of ''Mission to America,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Kirn, a frequent contributor, is the author, most recently, of ''Mission to America,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
