<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: August 18 - August 24</title>
    <meta content="18thea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1783535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EFD9143EF93BA2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="15327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: August 18 - August 24</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' In previews; opens on Wednesday. If you were one of the people who missed the 17,162 performances of this show the last time around, good news: Harvey Schmidt and Tom Jones's romantic musical, which closed in 2002, is back (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'MOTHER COURAGE AND HER CHILDREN' In previews; opens on Monday. Meryl Streep plays the title character in Tony Kushner's translation of Brecht's seminal play about a world at war. Kevin Kline also stars, and George C. Wolfe directs (2:30). Delacorte Theater, Central Park, (212) 539-8750; free. 'MR. DOOLEY'S AMERICA' In previews; opens on Sunday. Meet Mr. Dooley, the fictional everyman who appeared in the newspaper columns of Peter Finley Dunne a century ago. Charlotte Moore directs a show based on those articles. (1:40). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737.</p>
        <p>'SEVEN GUITARS' In previews; opens on Thursday. Signature Theater presents its first August Wilson revival since the playwright's death last year. Ruben Santiago-Hudson, who starred in the 1996 Broadway production, directs (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'KIKI AND HERB: ALIVE ON BROADWAY' This transcendental lounge act -- made up of Kiki (Justin Bond), a molting songbird for all seasons, and Herb (Kenny Mellman), her happily suffering shadow and accompanist -- has the heat and dazzle of great balls of fire. Vital, funny and surprisingly affecting (2:00). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street; (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ANAIS NIN: ONE OF HER LIVES' Angela Christian is superb as Nin in this uneven but largely rewarding production about her affair with Henry Miller and his wife, June, in Paris in the 1930's (1:30). Beckett Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'CREATION: A CLOWN SHOW' Lucas Caleb Rooney is a cross between Red Skelton and Will Ferrell in this sweet, funny, poignant mostly one-man show about the Bible story of earth's first seven days (1:15). Theater Five, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'EVERYTHINgS TURNING INTO BEAUTIFUL' Seth Zvi Rosenfeld's thrill-free demi-musical about a pair of commitment-wary songwriters (Daphne Rubin Vega and Malik Yoba) is clearly intended to progress from wintry loneliness to heated confrontation and eroticism. But it remains stolidly at room temperature. Directed by Carl Forsman, with songs by Jimmie James. (1:50). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GARDEL: THE MUSICAL' A standard-issue bio-musical about the tango legend Carlos Gardel wallows in melodrama (1:30). Gramercy Theater, 138 East 27th Street, (212) 225-9920. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOUT!' A mini-skirted, go-go booted zombie of a musical about women searching for love in London in the 1960's. You won't see anything this groovy, this far-out, this with-it outside of, oh, maybe the show room of a Carnival Cruise ship (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A STONE CARVER' Despite the high cliché factor, William Mastrosimone's play about an Italian immigrant who is losing his house to a highway exit is timely and sporadically touching, in large part because of Dan Lauria's over-the-top performance as the title character and old-world patriarch who makes a mean barrel of wine and never talks when he can shout (1:40). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE DISPUTE' Marivaux's 1744 comedy about sex roles is like a sci-fi romance and, in the hands of the National Asian American Theater Company, an enchanting piece of theater (1:10). The Abingdon Theater, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Spectacles</p>
        <p>'ABSINTHE' Think Cirque du Soleil as channeled through ''Rocky Horror'' and painted by George Grosz. Part cabaret, part circus, ''Absinthe'' aims at a kind of seedy decadence that's mingled with the simple, aw-shucks wonder of knife-jugglers, sword-swallowers and a man creating constructions out of soap bubbles. It's the main event at the Spiegeltent, a vintage European tradition that's come to visit the South Street Seaport this summer. Spiegeltent, at the former site of the Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, South Street, under the Brooklyn Bridge, (212) 279-4200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' Another excavation of what seems to have become Broadway's favorite musical terrain -- call it Scamalot, where con men are king (see ''The Producers''). Now starring Keith Carradine and Brian D'Arcy James as the mismatched swindlers (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). New World Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' Tormenting memories dissolve into soaring music, and pain is salved by a collective embrace in this heartfelt, powerfully performed theater piece about life under apartheid. The recollections of the five cast members and authors are woven together with a cappella performances of spirituals from the apartheid years and vignettes performed by the full cast. The actors all but glow with a sense of mission, as if telling their stories has given them new purpose and power (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 307-4100; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'IF YOU GIVE A MOUSE A COOKIE &amp; OTHER STORY BOOKS' This children's musical, made up of 10 sketches based on 8 books, is diverse, adorable and free. Also, the adults laugh (1:00). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 642-9033; closing tonight. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ANT BULLY' (PG, 90 minutes) A young boy goes to live among the ants, who talk remarkably like Academy Award-winning actors. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'BARNYARD' (PG, 88 minutes) The barnyard animals in this crude 3-D animation walk, talk and party down like human beings. Way too often the male ''cows,'' as the film calls them, also flash their udders. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'The Beales of Grey Gardens' (No rating, 90 minutes) The Maysles brothers dig into their archives for this collection of outtakes from ''Grey Gardens,'' their 1975 cinema vérité classic about the most fascinating cat ladies in the Hamptons. Essential viewing for drag queens. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'BOYNTON BEACH CLUB' (No rating, 104 minutes) A fast-paced romantic comedy about frisky 60-something residents of a Florida ''active adult'' community, ''Boynton Beach Club'' is a rose-colored fantasy about aging that has just enough credibility to make you care about its characters and wish them merrily on their way. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE BRIDESMAID' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) The great Claude Chabrol again takes up a sharp instrument and directs it at one of his favorite targets, the family. Yet while his aim remains true, his touch has become gentler, more forgiving. (Dargis) 'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt- putt-putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Calvaire' (No rating, 90 minutes) In this pretentious horror flick from the Belgian newcomer Fabrice du Welz, a lounge singer (Lucus Laurent) plays the girl in an all-male nightmare populated by savagely violent cretins. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'The Celestine Prophecy' (PG, 100 minutes) A delectable fusion of new age babble and luridly bad filmmaking based on the best-selling book by James Redfield. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'CLERKS II' (R, 98 minutes) More than a decade later, Kevin Smith's New Jersey underachievers have moved from a convenience store to a fast-food franchise. The humor is reliably filthy and frequently hilarious, and the filmmaking is a few steps above rudimentary, but the movie's poignant sweetness is disarming. It has a dirty mind, but its heart is remarkably pure. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CONVERSATIONS WITH OTHER WOMEN' (No rating, 84 minutes) Two old flames meet, years after parting, and have a short fling. An arch, banal conceit, of some interest for Aaron Eckhart and Helena Bonham Carter's performances and the split-screen gimmick that keeps them apart even in their intimate moments. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DESCENT' (R, 99 minutes) A total horror freakout from the British writer and director Neil Marshall about six women on a caving expedition who meet their fears and some scary monsters, too. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'Gabrielle' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haut-bourgeois Parisian marriage, about 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems that Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over, and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'Half Nelson' (R, 107 minutes) In their beautiful bummer about the relationship between a white teacher (Ryan Gosling) and a black student (Shareeka Epps), the gifted young director Ryan Fleck and his writing partner, Anna Boden, offer a lament for the radical fires of the 1960's and a suggestion for life and politics after the new left. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HOUSE OF SAND' (R, 115 minutes, in Portuguese) Beautifully shot in a sandy, remote corner of northern Brazil, this film tells the story of three generations of women, all of them played by Fernanda Montenegro and Fernanda Torres, mother and daughter in real life and two of the national treasures of Brazilian cinema. (Scott)'I Like Killing Flies' (R, 79 minutes) The documentary filmmaker Matt Mahurin paints an engaging if glib portrait of Kenny Shopsin, of the legendary or notorious, depending on your experience, Greenwich Village eatery that bears his name. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'Little Miss Sunshine' (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Lunacy' (No rating, 118 minutes) In the latest phantasmagoria from the Czech filmmaker Jan Svankmajer, a young man (Pavel Liska) meets an aristocrat (Jan Triska) and, with help from Edgar Allan Poe and the Marquis de Sade, tumbles down a very strange rabbit hole. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MIAMI VICE' (R, 133 minutes) This updating of the 1980's television series cost more than the annual budget of the real-life Miami Police Department, making it the most expensive experimental art film ever made. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. A trio of intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MOONLIGHT' (No rating, 90 minutes) In the English-language Dutch thriller ''Moonlight,'' a 13-year-old girl (Laurien Van den Broeck) and a young Afghan drug courier fall in love while fleeing his employers. Though the film is rife with topics and images American audiences may find offensive, the director, Paula van der Oest, addresses them fearlessly and with some artistry, creating a fevered fairy tale that suggests that the veneer of civilization is a thin one. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'MY COUNTRY, MY COUNTRY' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Arabic, English and Kurdish) Filmed in Iraq from June 2004 to February 2005, ''My Country, My Country'' views the prelude to the January elections primarily through the eyes of Dr. Riyadh, a Sunni candidate and physician who runs a free clinic in Baghdad. Without comment but with unusual sensitivity, the director, Laura Poitras, exposes the emotional toll of occupation on Iraqis and United States soldiers alike, leaving us feeling that this particular mission is far from accomplished. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE NIGHT LISTENER' (R, 82 minutes) Robin Williams plays a writer and radio host who strikes up a long-distance friendship with a young man who may not exist. An intriguing premise, but not satisfyingly realized. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'Pulse' (PG-13, 87 minutes) Evil technology menaces idiotic teenagers in this cynical remake of a Japanese horror film. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'QUINCEAÑERA' (R, 90 minutes) This portrait of a Mexican-American family living in a Latino neighborhood of Los Angeles is as smart and warm-hearted an exploration of an upwardly mobile immigrant culture as American independent cinema has produced. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Satellite' (No rating, 100 minutes) In this captivating romantic fairy tale for grown-ups, made on a shoestring, two young lovers in New York flee yuppie hell into a life of petty theft. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'Scoop' (PG-13, 96 minutes) A not especially funny yet oddly appealing comedy in which Woody Allen and Scarlett Johansson make like Nick and Nora, but with more shtick and no martinis (or Asta). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STEP UP' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Ever since Kevin Bacon's rebellious hips ignited a small-town uproar in ''Footloose,'' the modern high school romance has placed a premium on rhythm. In ''Step Up'' a rough Baltimore kid (Channing Tatum), armed only with a killer smile and hip-hop moves, falls for a classically trained dancer (Jenna Dewan). Bland but likable, the movie fashions social equality from big musical numbers. If ballet and hip-hop can coexist, it asks, why can't we all be friends? (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TALLADEGA NIGHTS: THE BALLAD OF RICKY BOBBY' (PG-13, 110 minutes) Fast, fun and silly, with Will Ferrell as a Nascar driver, Sacha Baron Cohen as his nemesis, and a new course record for product placements per gallon. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'13 Tzameti'  (No rating, 90 minutes) The flashy black-and-white directorial debut of the Georgian filmmaker Gela Babluani is a sadistic, arty thriller that suggests a French new wave film infected by a virulent strain of Eastern European nihilism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'The Trouble With Men and Women' (No rating, 74 minutes) This tiny, well-acted movie about the romantic troubles besetting two young couples in London feels at once utterly real and banal. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'WORLD TRADE CENTER' (PG-13, 129 minutes) From Oliver Stone, a return to the emotions of 9/11. Powerful and almost unbearably moving. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'You, Me and Dupree' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Zoom' (PG, 83 minutes) Tim Allen is Jack Shepard, a k a Captain Zoom, a washed-up superhero called back into service to train a group of gifted kids for a secret mission to save Earth. Too infantile for tweens and too stagnant for tots, ''Zoom'' bleeds boredom from every frame. The younger cast members work hard, but no superpower on earth can neutralize Mr. Allen's weary shtick. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>THE BEST OF BUSTER: KEATON COMEDY CLASSICS (Through Sept. 25) Film Forum's eight-film, eight-week festival of the silent comedies of the brilliantly stone-faced Keaton (1895-1966) continues on Monday night with ''Seven Chances'' (1925), about a man who will inherit $7 million (real money back then) if he gets married -- immediately. Also playing is ''Three Ages'' (1923), a romantic comedy set in the Stone Age, ancient Rome and the 20th century. 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8110; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Sunday) The 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962) winds up at the Museum of the Moving Image with four 1940's films this weekend. The closing feature is ''I've Always Loved You'' (1946), a Technicolor B movie about a concert pianist (Catherine McLeod) torn between her maestro and the boy back home. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FROM THE TSARS TO THE STARS: A JOURNEY THROUGH RUSSIAN FANTASTIK CINEMA (Through Aug. 24) The Film Society of Lincoln Center's tribute to Russian science fiction and fantasy films continues. This weekend's features include Pavel Klushanstev's ''Planet of Storms'' (1961), about cosmonauts who find prehistoric beasts on Venus, and Aleksandr Ptushko's last film, ''Ruslan and Ludmila'' (1972), which features a sorcerer, a hunchbacked witch and a kidnapped bride. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues this weekend with ''Ikiru'' (1952), starring Takashi Shimura as an office bureaucrat who learns that he has a terminal illness. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE LEADING MEN OF FRENCH CINEMA (Through Aug. 27) BAMcinématek's tribute to 17 French actors continues this weekend. The attractions include Maurice Ronet in Louis Malle's ''Fire Within'' (1963), about a recovering alcoholic just out of rehab, and Jean-Louis Trintignant in ''My Night at Maud's'' (1969), Éric Rohmer's Oscar-nominated drama about a good Roman Catholic's encounter with a seductive divorcée. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RAISING HELL: SAM PECKINPAH (Through Aug. 29) BAMcinématek's monthlong tribute to Peckinpah (1925-1984) continues. Monday night's feature is ''The Killer Elite'' (1975), with James Caan as a wounded spy out for revenge. Tuesday night's is ''Bring Me the Head of Alfredo Garcia'' (1974), starring Warren Oates as a piano player on an unusual bounty hunt in Mexico. BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>'AMSTERJAM' (Tomorrow) The concept: a handful of big-name acts from disparate pop genres pair up for live mash-ups, playing two or more songs simultaneously in search of playful serendipities. In the hands of skilled (and computer-assisted) producers, the gimmick can have astonishing effects, but there is good reason that it is not often attempted live. The ringmaster: the R &amp; B superproducer Jermaine Dupri (Mariah Carey, Janet Jackson). The players: Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers with the Foo Fighters; L L Cool J with the reggaetón star Tego Calderón; and Busta Rhymes with the Latin band Yerba Buena. At 3 p.m., Randalls Island, near Icahn Stadium, 1 Randalls Island, (212) 307-7171, amsterjam.com; $57. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ARCHIE BELL, THE MIGHTY HANNIBAL (Sunday) Not everyone playing at the McCarren Park Pool this summer is under 30 and shops at American Apparel. In 1968 Archie Bell, with his band the Drells, scored one of the great R &amp; B novelty hits with ''Tighten Up,'' a combination dance-instruction and introduce-the-band number that is blessedly aimless. The turbaned Mighty Hannibal began his career in 1958 with ''Big Chief Hug-Um an' Kiss-Um'' and went on to record great soul-funk nuggets like ''Jerkin' the Dog'' and ''Get in the Groove.'' At 3 p.m., Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, thepoolparties.com; free. Mr. Bell also plays on Monday at 9:30 p.m. at Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CHARLES BISSELL (Tuesday) In the Wrens, a New Jersey indie-rock band that formed in the late 1980's and is known as much for its struggles in making records as for its wonderful music, Mr. Bissell sings about exhaustion, day jobs and failed dreams with an intensity seldom matched by rockers half his age. While fans wait for a new album -- they are used to waiting -- Mr. Bissell is playing in residence on Tuesday nights in the small Tap Bar downstairs at the Knitting Factory. With Koester. At 8 p.m., 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MARIAH CAREY (Wednesday) Before there was ''Idol'' there was Mariah, who made octave-hopping melisma a sport and never met a song she couldn't ride to No. 1. Young singers afraid of being a flash in the pan could learn a lot from her recent comeback, which relied on fresh and up-to-date hip-hop producers and songwriters. With Sean Paul. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $19.50 to $154.50 (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NEKO CASE, JOANNA NEWSOM, MARTHA WAINWRIGHT (Thursday) A decade ago the most influential women in rock were the angry ones. Now it might be the mellow women's turn. Neko Case began in punk and indie-rock bands before finding herself and her voice -- a bewitching, burgundy alto -- in country-tinged Southern gothic. With a froggy, girlish voice, Joanna Newsom plays elegant and completely entrancing reveries on the harp. Martha Wainwright's passionate and earthy songs swirl from her acoustic guitar into grand arrangements but never lose their intimacy. At 5 p.m., McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (212) 307-7171; $32.50 in advance, $36 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CROSBY, STILLS, NASH AND YOUNG (Sunday, Tuesday and Wednesday) It's the fourth partner, Neil Young, who just might push this alliance beyond self-satisfied baby-boom nostalgia and vocal harmonies into something like rock. Sunday at 8 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698, artscenter.com; sold out. Tuesday and Wednesday nights at 8, Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000, nikonjonesbeach.com; $46 to $251. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133, dannysgrandseapalace.com; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>FOO FIGHTERS, FRANK BLACK (Monday) The Foo Fighters' long-promised acoustic tour is a family affair. Joining Dave Grohl and his band will be Pat Smear, of the great Los Angeles punk group the Germs in the 1970's, and who was an auxiliary member of Nirvana in the 90's; and the violinist Petra Hayden and the keyboardist Rami Jaffee, who both played on the Foo Fighters' most recent album, ''In Your Honor'' (RCA). Opening the show is Frank Black, making his first solo appearances since the Pixies reunion. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; sold out. Frank Black also plays tomorrow night at 8 and 11:30 at Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Thursday) Though she is invariably dressed in black, with her face in witchy streaks of makeup, Diamanda Galás needs only her voice to terrify, seduce and beguile. She slides from a low, sensual growl to painful yet musically precise shrieks, and has a vast repertory that ranges from Johnny Cash ballads to her own chilling AIDS Masses. In the third of four shows at the Spiegeltent downtown, she offers songs associated with Marlene Dietrich, Peggy Lee, Judy Garland, Frank Sinatra, Édith Piaf and Timi Yuro. At 6 p.m., Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JAMES GANG (Tomorrow) Before joining the Eagles, Joe Walsh joined this Cleveland blues-boogie band, whose ''Funk #49'' is the platonic ideal of all 70's blues boogies. The band -- which also includes the bassist Dale Peters and the drummer Jim Fox -- has reunited periodically, including at an election rally for Bill Clinton 10 years ago, and is touring this summer. With J D and the Straight Shot. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; $63.50 to $128.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER OUT OF DOORS (Today through Sunday) A highlight of this series each summer is the Roots of American Music minifestival, which this year has a particular emphasis on blues and soul. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. at the Damrosch Park Bandshell are the 1960's soul vets Eddie Floyd (''Knock on Wood'') and Percy Sledge (''When a Man Loves a Woman''). On the North Plaza, beginning at 2 p.m., are Joe Jencks, Dan Milner and Bob Conroy, the Wiyos, Stairwell Sisters, and Robin and Linda Williams. Sunday's lineup at the bandshell, at 7 p.m., includes Mavis Staples of the pioneering gospel-funk Staple Singers, and the country singer Marty Stuart. The Blue Vipers of Brooklyn, Larry Johnson, Murray Porter and Adrienne Young play on the North Plaza, at 2 p.m. Two concerts today serve as preludes to the Roots festival: ''Evolution of the Blues'' with Guy Davis and Michael Hill, on the North Plaza at 5:30 p.m., and a strong lineup of Mr. Davis, Chico Hamilton and Buster Williams, Murray Porter, Hazel Dickens and Bettye LaVette at the bandshell, at 7. (212) 875-5766, lincolncenter.org; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAGIK MARKERS, EXCEPTER, BLUES CONTROL, FERN KNIGHT (Tomorrow) An afternoon of noise rock at the East River Amphitheater, where the most discordant music can sound almost pastoral. The trio Magik Markers' clangorous improvisations reach back to New York's early-1980's No Wave scene. Excepter, from Brooklyn, lists its influences as ''weather, traffic, electricity, magic.'' Blues Control's distorted rumblings sound like Mountain or Cream songs emanating from a sunken submarine. And since no noise-rock show these days is complete without a ''freak folk'' act, Fern Knight, a droney acoustic band from Philadelphia, is on the bill. At 2 p.m., East River Park, south of Delancey Street, Lower East Side, ermp.org; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RAUL MALO (Tuesday) Mr. Malo, the leader of the Mavericks, has never let himself be bound by the strictures of country. His music looks back to the 1950's and 60's with a clear-eyed nostalgia, and he has the soaring tenor voice of a dedicated Roy Orbison fan. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK DOLLS (Tonight) Never say die. With its only two surviving original members well into their 50's, this proto-punk, proto-glam band, which made trashy cross-dressing a rock 'n' roll virtue, recently released its first new album in 32 years, ''One Day It Will Please Us to Remember Even This'' (Roadrunner), and its appetite for sleazy vamps and hilarious wickedness is undiminished. ''You're designed so intelligent/Ain't no way that was an accident,'' David Johansen sings in ''Dance Like a Monkey.'' ''Come on shake your monkey hips, my pretty little creationist.'' At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789, seaportmusicfestival.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RANCID (Thursday) This long-running band of studious Clash revivalists said two years ago it was going on hiatus, but that didn't last long. Rancid is said to be working on a new album and on Thursday begins four nights at the B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, promising that no two nights will be the same. With H20 and FVK. At 8 p.m., 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>STEVE RILEY AND THE MAMOU PLAYBOYS (Sunday) The accordionist Steve Riley leads one of the best bands from the Louisiana bayous. It reaches back to some of the oldest Cajun tunes and can play them in traditional style, but it's not afraid of swamp-rock or a touch of country, either. At 7:30 p.m., with a free zydeco dance lesson at 6:30, Connolly's, 121 West 45th Street, Manhattan, (212) 685-7597, letszydeco.com; $22. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>THE SHINS, J MASCIS (Wednesday) The Shins emerged from Albuquerque at the turn of the millennium with a sound that slowly but inevitably catapulted them to the upper ranks of the indiesphere: wistful and acoustic, with an adventurousness that sometimes leads to something like psychedelia. (Natalie Portman's exhortation in ''Garden State'' that the band's music will ''change your life'' didn't hurt.) J Mascis led Dinosaur Jr., one of the greatest and most influential original grunge bands, whose juxtaposition of mopey lyrics and furious guitar sludge prefigured Nirvana. With Sam Jayne. At 6:30 p.m., McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (212) 307-7171; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* P. F. Sloan (Thursday) One of the few songwriters who can be said to have truly captured the extremes of the 1960's -- he wrote both ''Eve of Destruction'' and ''Secret Agent Man'' -- P. F. Sloan left the music business in the 70's and has mostly stayed out until now. He makes a rare appearance at Joe's Pub on Thursday, two days after the release of ''Sailover'' (Hightone), his first new album in many years. At 7:30 p.m., 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* WU-TANG CLAN (Tonight) The eight surviving representatives of hip-hop's most ingenious and eccentric band-cum-brand name team up for a tour in tribute to Russell Tyrone Jones, better known as Ol' Dirty Bastard, the especially ingenious, eccentric and self-destructive member who died in 2004. With Lord Jamar. At 7, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* GERI ALLEN TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) ''Timeless Portraits and Dreams'' (Telarc), a soulfully earnest new album by Geri Allen, showcases her piano playing in a number of different settings, including one with a vocal chorus. Here she appears in a basic but eminently rewarding lineup, with her longtime associate Darryl Hall on bass and the venerable Jimmy Cobb on drums. Through Aug. 27. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum.(Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>PECK ALLMOND KALIMBA KOLLECTIVE (Tuesday) This ensemble finds Mr. Allmond augmenting his usual arsenal of horns with kalimbas, or African thumb pianos. The group also includes an electric five-string cello, played by Rufus Cappadocia, and Haitian hand drums, courtesy of Bonga Jean-Baptiste. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ED CHERRY TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow) Ed Cherry is a blues-influenced guitarist with solid credentials, including tours of duty with Dizzy Gillespie and Henry Threadgill. Here he works in an organ trio, his favorite setting of late. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., the River Room, Riverbank State Park, Riverside Drive at 145th Street, Harlem (212) 491-1500, theriverroomofharlem.com; no cover; dinner or two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHARLIE HADEN'S QUARTET WEST (Tonight through Sunday) In 20 years Quartet West has never wavered in its commitment to romance. The heart of the group is Ernie Watts, with his ardent tenor saxophone style; its soul is the bass playing of Mr. Haden. Alan Broadbent's sophisticated piano playing and arranging could be, so to speak, its brain. Rodney Green fills in for Larance Marable on drums. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAËL ATTIAS AND RENKU (Wednesday) Mr. Attias, an alto saxophonist, develops compositional fragments into compact expeditions in this group with the bassist John Hebert, the keyboardist Russ Lossing and the drummer Satoshi Takeishi. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MATT DARRIAU'S PARADOX TRIO (Tonight) The exuberant Balkan fusion once associated with the Knitting Factory is still kicking; at least it is for this band, which issued an album on Enja last year. In addition to Mr. Darriau's clarinet, alto saxophone and gaida (or Balkan bagpipe), Paradox Trio features the electric guitar of Brad Shepik, the cello of Rufus Cappadocia and the percussion of Seido Salifoski. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDREW DRURY'S CONTENT PROVIDER (Tomorrow and Thursday) Mr. Drury is a thoughtfully avant-garde drummer and composer whose primary working band, Content Provider, includes the trumpeter Peter Evans, the alto saxophonist Briggan Krauss and the tenor saxophonist and clarinetist Chris Speed. Tomorrow the group will appear, without Mr. Speed, in the East Village; on Thursday the entire group performs in Brooklyn. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. Thursday at 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MONCEF GENOUD (Tuesday) Tunisian born and Swiss raised, Mr. Genoud applies an uncommon perspective to his acoustic piano playing, as he demonstrates on a strong new album, ''Aqua'' (Savoy). He will perform with a trio, his most comfortable setting. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY GREENE QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow) Mr. Greene brings an athletic self-assurance to his saxophone playing, and leads a top-shelf band with Xavier Davis on piano, Reuben Rogers on bass and Eric Harland on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DREW GRESS'S 7 BLACK BUTTERFLIES (Tomorrow through Monday) A stalwart bassist both in and out of the contemporary avant-garde, Mr. Gress has composed new music inspired by the paintings of Mark Rothko. He has the right accompanists for this variety of disciplined abstraction: the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the alto saxophonist Tim Berne, the keyboardist Craig Taborn and the drummer Tom Rainey. Tomorrow and Sunday at 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. Monday at 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* ROY HAYNES FOUNTAIN OF YOUTH BAND (Tuesday through Thursday) The redoubtable drummer Roy Haynes is in his 80's, though you'd never guess it by the freshness and ferocity of his playing. His working quartet features musicians many years his junior: the alto saxophonist Jaleel Shaw, the pianist Martin Bejerano and the bassist David Wong. Through Aug. 27. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARI HOENIG AND CHRIS POTTER (Tonight) Mr. Hoenig, a drummer, and Mr. Potter, a saxophonist, are two of the sharpest musicians in modern post-bop circles, and their duo exchange is a thing of intensity and poise. At 6 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LAN XANG (Wednesday) This quartet was a compact powerhouse on the experimental scene in the middle to late 1990's, after which its four members -- the saxophonists Donny McCaslin and Dave Binney, the bassist Scott Colley and the drummer Kenny Wollesen -- separately established successful careers. They have all crossed paths often, but this one-night engagement marks a rare reunion. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TANIA MARIA (Tuesday through Thursday) On her album ''Intimidade,'' recently released on Blue Note, Tania Maria applies her conversational vocals and piano playing to a brand of acoustic pop well seasoned by the sound of her native Brazil. She'll create a similar fusion here with a group consisting of the bassist Sergio Brandao and the percussionists Rick Sebastian and Mestre Carneiro. Through Aug. 27. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ERIC McPHERSON, NASHEET WAITS, ABRAHAM BURTON (Thursday) Mr. McPherson and Mr. Waits are two of jazz's most engagingly expressive younger drummers, united by a common gift for slippery propulsion. They join Mr. Burton, a tenor saxophonist, in an experimental exchange. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MULGREW MILLER AND WINGSPAN (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Miller is a pianist with an earthy style and a particular gift for the blues. But his ensemble Wingspan pursues a distinctly airy sensibility, with help from the saxophonist Steve Wilson, the trumpeter Duane Eubanks, the vibraphonist Steve Nelson, the bassist Ivan Taylor and the drummer Rodney Green. Through Aug. 27. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>OSCAR NORIEGA TRIO (Thursday) Oscar Noriega, a clarinetist and saxophonist, taps raw but focused energies -- and a book of Mexican folk songs -- in this group with the bassist Trevor Dunn and the drummer Tom Rainey. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID SÁNCHEZ QUARTET (Through Sunday) A tenor and soprano saxophonist equally conversant in the rigors of post-bop and the nuances of Latin folk music, Mr. Sánchez digs in here with some longtime colleagues: Edsel Gomez on piano, Ben Street on bass and Adam Cruz on drums. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN TRIO (Thursday through Sunday) Jenny Scheinman is a violinist attracted to rusticity but committed to a modern language; the same could be said, more or less, of the drummer Paul Motian and the pianist Jason Moran. Still, this all-star trio carries the burden of a small spectacle: it could be transcendent or a train wreck, and either way it will be something to behold. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHRISTIAN SCOTT SEXTET/ERIC PERSON'S META-FOUR (Tonight) Christian Scott is an excellent young trumpeter whose recent debut, ''Rewind That'' (Concord), signaled his intention to establish a modern funk-based sound; he succeeded, but at the cost of spontaneity, a problem that will probably not resurface here. Also on the bill is Meta-Four, a group led by Mr. Person, a saxophonist and composer. At 9 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $18, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TRAVIS SULLIVAN'S BJORKESTRA (Tonight) A big band with a muse, a method, a growing reputation and a roster of good young players. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; tonicnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHARLES TOLLIVER BIG BAND (Tonight through Sunday) Charles Tolliver leads an upgraded edition of his acclaimed orchestra of the 1970's, with such top-shelf talent as the saxophonists Billy Harper and Craig Handy, the trombonist Clark Gayton, the pianist Robert Glasper and the bassist Cecil McBee. The band will be featured on a forthcoming Blue Note album, but that's no reason not to absorb its visceral impact in person. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAKE TORIYAMA'S TBA (Tonight) Mr. Toriyama is a drummer with ever-expanding credentials in the Brooklyn experimental scene. Despite what the name might imply, he does know the other members of his band: Drew Gress and Chris Lightcap, accomplished bassists both. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RANDY WESTON (Wednesday) The pianist Randy Weston has been one of the principal agents of an African jazz aesthetic since his first visit to Nigeria, in the 1960's. He turned 80 this year, the ostensible reason for this special concert, which assembles a number of guests, including the saxophonists Dewey Redman and Billy Harper, the conga legend Candido Camero, the pipa player Min Xiao Fen and the kora player Abdou Mboup. At 8 p.m., Damrosch Park, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5766; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SARAH WILSON QUINTET (Tuesday and Wednesday) Sarah Wilson is a trumpeter and composer based in San Francisco, though she has extensive New York ties, including a post as musical director for the annual puppet spectacle presented by Lincoln Center Out of Doors. On Tuesday night she leads the same band of improvisers featured on her new album, ''Music for an Imaginary Play'' (Evander Music); on Wednesday she features a different group, with the violinist Charlie Burnham, the trombonist Art Baron, the bassist Jerome Harris and the drummer Satoshi Takeishi. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'AFTERNOON ARIAS' (Today) One of New York's most popular places for people to bring their lunches on a pleasant summer afternoon is Bryant Park, right behind the New York Public Library. Today, in the last of four presentations, the New York City Opera is offering music for visitors to the park to have their lunch by and otherwise enjoy. ''Afternoon Arias'' is the name of the concert, featuring singers from the City Opera, accompanied by the pianist Gerald Steichen, in excerpts from ''La Bohème,'' ''Hansel and Gretel,'' ''Carmen,'' ''Faust'' and other works. Midge Woolsey from WQXR is the host. At 12:30 p.m., Avenue of the Americas, at 42nd Street, (212) 870-7787, nycopera.com; free. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPera (Today through Tuesday, and Thursday) Opera can be formal or pure fluff, and this season's program at Glimmerglass about equally balances the two. All four of this year's operas are in rotation over the next week, with the lighter side predominating: Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' (today at 1:30 and 8 p.m., Monday at 1:30 p.m.); Rossini's classic ''Barber of Seville'' (tomorrow and Tuesday at 1:30 p.m., Thursday night at 8); Steven Hartke's new Maupassant-based opera ''The Greater Good'' (tomorrow night at 8); and Janacek's dark ''Jenufa,'' in Jonathan Miller's production (Sunday afternoon at 1:30). Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255, glimmerglass.org; $69 to $117 today through Sunday; $41 to $104 Tuesday and Thursday. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'IDOMENEO'  (Wednesday) William Christie and Les Arts Florissants have attained something like rock-star status in the early-music world as they help illuminate all kinds of unexpected corners of the 17th- and 18th-century repertory. Mozart's opera seria ''Idomeneo'' is practically pop compared with some of the more obscure works the group has championed. But it has done some fine Mozart performances, and expectations are high for this one. Paul Agnew takes the title role in this semistaged production. At 7:30 p.m., Rose Theater, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $35 to $75. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MET IN THE PARKS (Tuesday and Wednesday) The opening of the Metropolitan Opera's season may be weeks away, but opera lovers can enjoy two enduringly popular works in the Met's series of concert performances in the parks of New York and New Jersey. The tour begins on Tuesday at the Great Lawn in Central Park with Verdi's ''Traviata,'' starring the luminous soprano Hei-Kyung Hong as Violetta. On Wednesday, at the same site, the Met offers Verdi's ''Rigoletto,'' with the commanding baritone Mark Delavan in the title role. These two works will then play in parks in the Bronx, Staten Island, Queens, Brooklyn and New Jersey through Sept. 2. This popular series is celebrating its 40th anniversary. The Met estimates that some 7.5 million people have attended performances over the years. At 8 p.m., (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; free. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARD MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) Round 2 of Leon Botstein's attempt to resuscitate Franz Liszt begins tonight at Bard College, with the pianists Jeremy Denk and Piers Lane, the mezzo-soprano Jill Grove, the violinist Ani Kavafian and others performing works by Liszt and his contemporaries. Tomorrow's morning program explores the influence of exotic music on European composers, and the afternoon focuses on Liszt and chamber music. In the evening Mr. Botstein will lead the American Symphony Orchestra in Liszt's ''Faust Symphony'' and in excerpts from his oratorio ''Christus'' and Berlioz's ''Enfance du Christ.'' The apparent aim of Sunday's afternoon program is to reveal a mature, spiritual Liszt by focusing on his chamber and choral works. The concluding concert highlights a connection to Wagner, with Liszt's ''Missa Solemnis'' and ''The Bells of Strasbourg'' and the Prelude and Good Friday Music from Wagner's ''Parsifal.'' Tonight at 8 ($20 to $45); tomorrow at 10 a.m. ($30), and 1:30 ($35) and 8 p.m. ($25 to $55); Sunday at 1:30 ($35) and 5:30 p.m. ($25 to $55). Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7900, summerscape.bard.edu. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall (a former coffee barge) on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight Edward Arron, the cellist, supported at the piano by Jeewon Park, plays works by Stravinsky, Mendelssohn and Rachmaninoff. Tomorrow and Sunday the Gala Quartet is joined by Gerald Robbins, a pianist, in the Brahms F minor Piano Quintet; it also plays Haydn's ''Emperor'' Quartet and Turina's ''Oración del Torero.'' And on Thursday the Neighborhood Composers' Chorus and the Orfeo Duo offer works by Elizabeth Adams, James Blachly, Sarah Dawson and others. Tonight, tomorrow night and Thursday night at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m.; Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org. Tonight and Thursday: $35, and $20 for students; on Thursday, $30 for 65+. Tomorrow and Sunday: $40, and $25 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MOZART (Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) On Sunday Joshua Bell and friends -- including the pianist Frederic Chiu, the Miró Quartet and the violinist Colin Jacobsen -- continue the Mozart festivities with the composer's Piano Quartet in G minor, followed by the New York premiere of a new work by Edgar Meyer. On Tuesday and Wednesday Lisa Batiashvili, a rising star violinist, makes her Mostly Mozart debut with the premiere of a concerto by the Finnish composer Magnus Lindberg, with Louis Langrée leading the festival orchestra. The program also features Lars Vogt playing Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 23 in A and the overtures to ''Le Nozze di Figaro'' and ''Don Giovanni.'' The International Contemporary Ensemble offers a late-night departure from Mozart on Tuesday with Lindberg's Clarinet Quintet, ''Linea d'Ombra'' and the American premiere of ''Zona.'' Later on Wednesday evening Mr. Vogt and Ms. Batiashvili play Mozart sonatas at the Kaplan Penthouse. Members of the Emerson String Quartet and the pianist Leon Fleisher play Beethoven's String Trio in G, Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 12 in A and Brahms's Sextet No. 2 on Thursday at Avery Fisher Hall. The late-night concert features the Daedalus Quartet playing Ravel and Mozart. Sunday at 5 p.m.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; at Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center. Late-night concerts at 10:30 at the Kaplan Penthouse, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $38 to $65 on Sunday; $35 to $55 for 8 p.m. concerts on Tuesday through Thursdays; $35 for late-night concerts. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* TRIO SETTECENTO (Thursday) This Chicago-based Baroque music ensemble includes Rachel Barton Pine, a superb violinist; David Schrader, the harpsichordist; and John Mark Rozendaal on the viola da gamba, and makes its New York debut with works by Bach, Stradella, Veracini and Handel. At 6 p.m., the Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 547-0709, frick.org; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday) Because of illness, the Spanish conductor Rafael Frühbeck de Burgos is being replaced in two scheduled concerts with the Boston Symphony Orchestra this weekend. Ludovic Morlot takes over tonight in a greatest-hits concert of Falla (''Nights in the Garden of Spain''), Debussy (''La Mer'') and Ravel (''Boléro''). Pinchas Steinberg steps in on Sunday's all-Brahms program, including the second piano concerto with Peter Serkin. Tomorrow night Herbert Blomstedt will conduct the violin star Hilary Hahn in the Dvorak concerto; Ms. Hahn will also make a modest appearance before tonight's concert playing chamber music (a Mozart trio, to be exact) with members of the Boston Symphony. On Wednesday Yo Yo Ma and Emanuel Ax offer Beethoven. Tonight and tomorrow and Wednesday nights at 8:30 (preconcert chamber program tonight at 6); Sunday afternoon at 2:30; Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; $17 to $87 tonight through Sunday; $20 to $95 on Wednesday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TANNERY POND CONCERTS (Tomorrow) Christian Steiner is well known for his photography, and less well known, perhaps, as a musician. But he is least known as the artistic director of this lovely little concert series, for which he lures leading musicians up to the Berkshires (over the New York border) to perform in an enchanting little wooden hall. This weekend Wu Han and David Finckel, the husband-and-wife collaborators as pianist and cellist who are also the artistic directors of the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, let their hair down with their close colleague Da-Hong Seetoo, a violinist, in a program of Shostakovich and Tchaikovsky. At 8 p.m., Mount Lebanon Shaker Village, New Lebanon, N.Y., (888) 820-9441, tannerypondconcerts.org; $25 and $30. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>ARIANE ANTHONY AND CEDRIC NEUGEBAUER (Tonight and tomorrow night) The wildly imaginative Ms. Anthony will present a new collaboration with Mr. Neugebauer, as well as a recent solo, ''Snail,'' with costumes of wearable sculpture by Agata Oleksiak and music by John Stone. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, the Field's FAR Space, 521 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (718) 349-0008; suggested donation, $10. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>BATTERY DANCE COMPANY: DOWNTOWN DANCE FESTIVAL (Monday through Thursday) A rite of summer now in its 25th year, this festival will present 16 companies and a wide range of styles in two downtown locations, through Aug. 27. The centerpiece is probably ''Oceans of Light,'' on a shared program on Thursday with Kathak Ensemble, in which modern dancers from New Orleans will perform with South Asian classical dancers. The work pays homage to the victims of Hurricane Katrina and the Asian tsunami by exploring water's beauty, grace and wrath. Monday through Thursday from noon to 1:30 p.m., Chase Plaza, Nassau Street between Liberty and Pine Streets, Lower Manhattan, batterydance.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Thursday) For an informal Thursday evening series this month, the company opens up its intimate theater to the street and turns it into an installation for a 90-minute program of multimedia dance created by company members. At 6 p.m., Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 244-0015, cedarlakedance.com; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHOREOGRAPHY CAFÉ (Wednesday) Jeremy Nelson is the featured artist in this informal series presented by Dancewave, which invites professional choreographers to work with child and teenage dancers. At 2:15 p.m., Old First Reformed Church, 729 Carroll Street, at Seventh Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 522-4696, dancewave.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CITY PARKS DANCE (Tomorrow) Nicholasleichterdance, which fuses modern dance and pop-culture movement, and Jamel Gaines's Creative Outlet Dance Theater of Brooklyn, which addresses sociocultural themes in movement, theater, song and poetry, will share the bill in this program. Mr. Gaines will teach the open dance class that begins the event. Tomorrow at 3 p.m., Von King Park, 670 Lafayette Avenue, between Marcy and Tompkins Avenues, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (212) 360-8290, cityparksfoundation.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'GRIMM' (Thursday) Otis Cook, choreographer for Momix, and Faith Pilger, a dancer and choreographer, have created in ''Grimm'' a dance theater piece that explores fear and parenthood, rebellion and discovery, through a retelling of ''Hansel and Gretel.'' Through Aug. 27. At 8 p.m., the Duke, 229 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200, agrimmproduction.com; $30; $20 for students and 65+; $15 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) Peter Boal's Pacific Northwest Ballet from Seattle, or at least a touring ensemble, will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend, followed there Tuesday through Thursday (and next weekend, to the end of this summer's festival) by the Mark Morris Dance Group. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, Choreftes, a Greek company in its United States debut, plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is Rubberbandance Group, which comes from Montreal and combines hip-hop with contemporary ballet. Pacific Northwest Ballet, tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., $50; Morris, Tuesday through Thursday nights at 8, $58, Shawn Theater. Choreftes, tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15, tomorrow at 2:15 p.m. and Sunday at 5 p.m.; Rubberbandance, Thursday at 8:15 p.m., Duke Theater, $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, ages 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions can be found at jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* 'MOZART DANCES' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Another month, another major work from Mark Morris. This one was commissioned by the Mostly Mozart Festival and offers the Mark Morris Dance Group performing to two Mozart piano concertos (K. 413 and 595) and the Sonata in D for two pianos (K. 448), with Louis Langrée conducting the Festival Orchestra and the pianists Emanuel Ax and Yoko Nozaki. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $25 to $75. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NICHOLAS ANDRE DANCE THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Directed by Nick Seligson-Ross, the company will perform five pieces set to composers including Handel and Mancini. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, nicholasandredance.com; $19 and $35 in advance, and $20 and $36 at the door. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>RIVER TO RIVER FESTIVAL (Today) The Lower Manhattan Cultural Council Sitelines series offers ''Oasis,'' a performance by H. T. Chen and Sharon Estacio that celebrates parks as gathering spaces. Today at 12:30 p.m., Columbus Park, intersection of Baxter, Mulberry, Worth and Bayard Streets, Chinatown, rivertorivernyc.com; free. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>SITELINES: ELLIS WOOD DANCE (Monday through Wednesday) In the last installment of this festival, 20 women will move across exterior balconies of an ornate old downtown building in Ms. Wood's new ''Fire on Wall Street,'' which explores the element of fire with what the choreographer describes as sensual abandon. Position those safety nets. Through Aug. 30. At noon and 12:30 p.m., Cipriani, 55 Wall Street, Lower Manhattan, lmcc.net; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SMUIN BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow) A lively San Francisco company offers two new works by Michael Smuin: ''Bluegrass/Slyde,'' to bluegrass music, and ''Symphony of Psalms,'' to Stravinsky. They share the program with ''Fly Me to the Moon,'' to Frank Sinatra recordings. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $42. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>SUDDEN ENLIGHTENMENT THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Hey Jeong Yoon and Eun Hee Kim, both from Seoul, will present the timely-sounding ''Beyond the DMZ,'' which documents the division of Korea more than 50 years ago. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 5 p.m., the Poet's Den Theater, 309 East 108th Street, Spanish Harlem, (718) 651-7725; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Folk Art Museum: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' through Sept. 17. The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040, folkartmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this engrossing if somewhat strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606, daheshmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestoes and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best-known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 (1114 is the school) Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* INternational Center of Photography: 'atta kim: On Air,' through Aug. 27. The South Korean artist Atta Kim's best-known body of work is a series called ''The Museum Project'' (1995-2002), for which he photographed his human subjects -- families, nude couples, maimed war veterans -- locked inside plexiglass exhibition cases like specimens on display. The series eventually took a religious turn, with models posing as Buddhist deities. The pictures here, in his first major American solo show, continue this spiritual trajectory. Filmed using long exposure times, figures, landscapes and religious icons have been turned into apparitions. People, art and museums may last for a while, Mr. Kim seems to say, but all things eventually melt away. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'ANGLOMANIA: TRADITION AND TRANSGRESSION IN BRITISH FASHION,' through Sept. 4. Ranging from early-18th-century gowns to next season's evening wear, this show crowds 65 extravagantly clad mannequins into the Met's normally serene English period rooms, trying to connect the sartorial innovations of the English dandy, the aggressive tribal attire of punk and the deconstructive impulses of today's British fashion stars. A certain confusion, both intellectual and visual, reigns, but there is more than enough to look at. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* met: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early 19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 4 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. Further sharpness comes from the placement of all parts of the altarpiece at eye level, creating a viewing intensity that more than compensates for the fact that they have not been reassembled. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Museum of Arts AND Design: 'THE EAMES LOUNGE CHAIR: AN ICON OF MODERN DESIGN,' through Sept. 3. Celebrating the 50th anniversary of a chair whose combination of declarative modernist structure and sheer creature comfort was both innovative and a bit alien, this exhibition is a successful design object in its own right. It pays homage with drawings, advertising ephemera, precursors, vintage television clips, a wonderful documentary and three versions of the chair itself, enshrined, exploded and usable. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535, madmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500, mobia.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer, and it makes some interesting points about the spectacle of the museum, the Modern included. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Museum of Modern Art: Douglas Gordon: 'Timeline,' through Sept 4. This selection of works by the artist known for appropriating and inventively manipulating Hollywood movies includes his projection of Alfred Hitchcock's ''Psycho,'' which runs so slowly that it takes 24 hours to complete, and a large-scale video installation that studies a circus elephant performing in an empty art gallery. 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer,  through Sept. 18. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Las Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle-shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: Had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden: Chihuly at the New York Botanical Garden, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700, nybg.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, (212) 873-3400, nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. The museum entrance is at 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088, noguchi.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Rubin Museum of Art : 'What is it? HimalAyan Art' This museum is an oasis of calm in the city; you can feel your tension dissolve the minute you walk in the door. At the same time, the place jumps with activities, including lectures, films and exhibitions, many devoted to aspects of Himalayan culture. And for a basic guide to the art of Tibet and Nepal, you will do no better than to take a slow walk through this show, which, using an array of gorgeous objects, distills knotty visual and spiritual systems to a soothing but stimulating entry-level form. 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Wadsworth Atheneum: 'American Splendor: Hudson River School Masterworks From the Wadsworth Atheneum,' through Dec. 31. Back from a two-and-a-half-year tour at six other American museums, the Wadsworth's formidable collection of 19th-century Hudson River School paintings is on display in this homecoming show. Not every Hudson River collection can boast 11 works by Frederic Edwin Church, 13 by Thomas Cole and 5 by Albert Bierstadt,, a leading painter of the American West, along with powerful examples by other artists of the school. They are among the more than 60 paintings on display here. It's rare that you see these ultrafamiliar paintings in such concentration; their combined presence gives the show a synergistic sparkle and energy that you don't get when you see them in smaller groupings. 600 Main Street, Hartford, (860) 278-2670, www.wadsworthatheneum.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>YES BRUCE NAUMAN There has never been much in the way of ''No'' to the influential Post-Minimalist and sculptor-of-all-trades Bruce Nauman. But this astutely structured, if male-dominated, exhibition considers his importance anew, especially his use of language, neon and the body, and his visceral sense of form. The show's title is taken from a 1989 work by Jessica Diamond that is included, along with pertinent efforts by Paul McCarthy, Charles Ray, Glenn Ligon, Jason Rhoades, Peter Coffin, Diana Thater, John Bock and, of course, Mr. Nauman himself. Zwirner &amp; Wirth, 32 East 69th Street, (212) 517-8677, zwirnerandwirth.com, through Sept. 9. (The gallery will be closed Aug. 21 through Aug. 25.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* GALERIE DANIEL BUCHHOLZ AT METRO PICTURES This well-known Cologne gallery presents a surprisingly sweeping view of current art that includes Americans and Europeans and, despite its Conceptual slant, an impressive range of mediums and sensibilities. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, (212) 206-7100, metropicturesgallery.com, through Sept. 16. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Materiality' Inventive works made of all sorts of materials in this show include a stuffed leather-and-plywood tree by Carolyn Salas; a geometric landscape with a slowing-moving, wartlike kinetic element, covered in reflective Mylar, by Charlotte Becket; a neat display of more than 200 pieces of breakfast cereal by Tom Friedman; and a sumptuous stuffed object resembling a much-enlarged amoeba by Ernesto Neto. Kravets/Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238, kravetswehbygallery.com, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Howardena Pindell: 'In My Lifetime' Thirty years ago Howardena Pindell was well known for meditative, process-based abstract work, though her art has always had two aspects. In the 1970's and 80's it assumed and maintained an overtly political direction in large-scale pieces that combined abstraction, words and figures to deal with social and political issues, from AIDS and homelessness to the present war in Iraq. Both types are in this informal gallery retrospective, which makes clear how thoroughly they are based on -- and emerge from and are fueled and inflected by -- the individual experiences and memories of the artist herself. G. R. N'Namdi Gallery, 526 West 26th Street, Suite 316, (212) 929-6645, grnnamdi.com, through Aug. 31. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>'WAR ON 45/MY MIRRORS ARE PAINTED BLACK (FOR YOU)' The latest word from the boys in black is a show of six artists organized by the head boy, Banks Violette. The stark glamour of it cannot be denied, but it looks too much like graphic design. Bortolami Dayan, 510 West 25th Street, (212) 727-2050, bortolamidayan.com, through Sept. 2. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* JAMES J. WILLIAMS III: 'BY REQUEST, MY EPITAPH' Despite debts to artists like Jack Pierson, Karen Kilimnik, Richard Prince and Nan Goldin, this Havershamish environment and solo debut exude a promising fusion of modesty and narcissism. Its deep teal walls display scores of Polaroids, drawings, collages, notebooks and thrift-shop-worthy paintings, along with many of the artist's well-worn belongings. An illusion of stylish, if impoverished, full disclosure results. Self-conscious bohemianism teeters between nostalgia and irony, and art emerges as an incessant if nonchalant activity at the center of an eked-out existence. Envoy, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 242-7524, envoygallery.com, through Sept. 9. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* Amer Kobaslija: 'Large-Scale Studio Paintings' Large, exhaustively detailed, sensuously painted fish-eye views of the artist's studio. George Adams, 525 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 564-8480, georgeadamsgallery.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* 'A BROKEN ARM' The title is a tribute to Duchamp. The works review various strategies of using found objects or images in photography, painting and sculpture. The seven artists include Gedi Sibony, Arnold Odermatt and Karen Kilimnik. All has been orchestrated by Mari Spirito, the gallery's director. 303 Gallery, 525 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-1121, 303gallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'DERECONSTRUCTION' Matthew Higgs, director of the alternative space White Columns, has assembled a handsome show that in typical Higgs fashion brings together outsider, emerging, hip and formerly hip artists. Variations on collage and assemblage predominate without feeling stale. The larger point: deconstruction has had its day, and it is time to start putting things back together again. The putters range from A. R. Penck and Lucas Samaras to Carter and Alexandra Bircken. Gladstone Gallery, 515 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-9300, gladstonegallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Dreamland: Coney Island, 1905-1925' Coney Island lovers will appreciate this show of early-20th-century photographs, artifacts, drawings and engineering plans. Most surprising are drawings from the W. F. Mangels Company, which built many of the area's amusement park rides and games; the precise, watercolor-tinted shooting gallery drawings look like contemporary artworks. And the wooden carousel horse head is a beautiful piece of sculpture. Ricco Maresca, 529 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 627-4819, riccomaresca.com; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Group Show' Four interesting Conceptualists: Pierre Bismuth folds a giant reproduction of a Jasper Johns flag painting into a Donald Judd-like box; Ryan Gander makes large photographs of bulletin boards bearing puzzling documents; Karl Haendel covers a wall with his large, handmade graphite copies of consumer-culture ephemera; and T. Kelly Mason constructs a walk-in, padded environment with soft, rain-related sounds and a video. Cohan &amp; Leslie, 138 10th Avenue, near 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-8710, cohanandleslie.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'MEN' This show of 10 paintings of men by 10 women, organized by the painter Ellen Altfest, covers a lot of stylistic ground and includes an only partly tongue-in-cheek denunciation from the lesbian collective Redykeulous. Realism makes the strongest impression. I-20, 557 West 23rd Street, Chelsea, (212) 645-1100, I-20.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. Concentrating on books, but also including prints and drawings, it retells the tale of the French avant-garde on a relatively egalitarian playing field. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089 or nypl.org; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Photography Is Not An Art!' More than 100 examples of vernacular, often anonymous photographs from the fields of medicine, forensics, space exploration and advertising prove that nonart photography is often as interesting as the fine-art variety. Alan Klotz, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 741-4764, photocollect.com; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Prevailing Climate' This intelligent group show, organized by Rachel Gugelberger and Jeffrey Walkowiak, is about atmospheric conditions and also psychic and political weather. Storms come and go in Joy Garnett's paintings of fiery, storm-swollen skies and in Christoph Draeger's jigsaw-puzzle photograph of the aftermath of a tsunami, while the subject of John Jurayj's vivid paintings of bombed hotels in Beirut speak of a different kind of turbulence. Sara Meltzer Gallery, 525-531 West 26nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-9330, sarameltzergaller.com; closes today. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>'The Social History of Objects,' At present, in some quarters of the art world, there's a push to circle back to a pre-Conceptualist state in which well-fashioned paintings and sculptures are art, and everything else is not. So it makes sense that an against-the-grain space like Triple Candie is offering a group show entirely of ready-mades or, as the gallery puts it, ''common objects collected from friends and acquaintances.'' The range is wide: a baseball cap, a sock, a Plaza Hotel ashtray, a stone chip, each accompanied by a history. Certain items were found by their present owners; others given as hand-me-downs or gifts. A few have been attributed Proustian powers to evoke a time or place or a personality. Together they teach the old Duchamp lesson that art is an attitude, and that the mind is every bit as much a shaping organ as the hand and the eye. Triple Candie, 461 West 126th Street, Harlem, (212) 865-0783, triplecandie.org; closes Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' In previews; opens on Wednesday. If you were one of the people who missed the 17,162 performances of this show the last time around, good news: Harvey Schmidt and Tom Jones's romantic musical, which closed in 2002, is back (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'MOTHER COURAGE AND HER CHILDREN' In previews; opens on Monday. Meryl Streep plays the title character in Tony Kushner's translation of Brecht's seminal play about a world at war. Kevin Kline also stars, and George C. Wolfe directs (2:30). Delacorte Theater, Central Park, (212) 539-8750; free. 'MR. DOOLEY'S AMERICA' In previews; opens on Sunday. Meet Mr. Dooley, the fictional everyman who appeared in the newspaper columns of Peter Finley Dunne a century ago. Charlotte Moore directs a show based on those articles. (1:40). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737.</p>
        <p>'SEVEN GUITARS' In previews; opens on Thursday. Signature Theater presents its first August Wilson revival since the playwright's death last year. Ruben Santiago-Hudson, who starred in the 1996 Broadway production, directs (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'KIKI AND HERB: ALIVE ON BROADWAY' This transcendental lounge act -- made up of Kiki (Justin Bond), a molting songbird for all seasons, and Herb (Kenny Mellman), her happily suffering shadow and accompanist -- has the heat and dazzle of great balls of fire. Vital, funny and surprisingly affecting (2:00). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street; (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ANAIS NIN: ONE OF HER LIVES' Angela Christian is superb as Nin in this uneven but largely rewarding production about her affair with Henry Miller and his wife, June, in Paris in the 1930's (1:30). Beckett Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'CREATION: A CLOWN SHOW' Lucas Caleb Rooney is a cross between Red Skelton and Will Ferrell in this sweet, funny, poignant mostly one-man show about the Bible story of earth's first seven days (1:15). Theater Five, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'EVERYTHINgS TURNING INTO BEAUTIFUL' Seth Zvi Rosenfeld's thrill-free demi-musical about a pair of commitment-wary songwriters (Daphne Rubin Vega and Malik Yoba) is clearly intended to progress from wintry loneliness to heated confrontation and eroticism. But it remains stolidly at room temperature. Directed by Carl Forsman, with songs by Jimmie James. (1:50). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GARDEL: THE MUSICAL' A standard-issue bio-musical about the tango legend Carlos Gardel wallows in melodrama (1:30). Gramercy Theater, 138 East 27th Street, (212) 225-9920. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOUT!' A mini-skirted, go-go booted zombie of a musical about women searching for love in London in the 1960's. You won't see anything this groovy, this far-out, this with-it outside of, oh, maybe the show room of a Carnival Cruise ship (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A STONE CARVER' Despite the high cliché factor, William Mastrosimone's play about an Italian immigrant who is losing his house to a highway exit is timely and sporadically touching, in large part because of Dan Lauria's over-the-top performance as the title character and old-world patriarch who makes a mean barrel of wine and never talks when he can shout (1:40). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE DISPUTE' Marivaux's 1744 comedy about sex roles is like a sci-fi romance and, in the hands of the National Asian American Theater Company, an enchanting piece of theater (1:10). The Abingdon Theater, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Spectacles</p>
        <p>'ABSINTHE' Think Cirque du Soleil as channeled through ''Rocky Horror'' and painted by George Grosz. Part cabaret, part circus, ''Absinthe'' aims at a kind of seedy decadence that's mingled with the simple, aw-shucks wonder of knife-jugglers, sword-swallowers and a man creating constructions out of soap bubbles. It's the main event at the Spiegeltent, a vintage European tradition that's come to visit the South Street Seaport this summer. Spiegeltent, at the former site of the Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, South Street, under the Brooklyn Bridge, (212) 279-4200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' Another excavation of what seems to have become Broadway's favorite musical terrain -- call it Scamalot, where con men are king (see ''The Producers''). Now starring Keith Carradine and Brian D'Arcy James as the mismatched swindlers (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). New World Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' Tormenting memories dissolve into soaring music, and pain is salved by a collective embrace in this heartfelt, powerfully performed theater piece about life under apartheid. The recollections of the five cast members and authors are woven together with a cappella performances of spirituals from the apartheid years and vignettes performed by the full cast. The actors all but glow with a sense of mission, as if telling their stories has given them new purpose and power (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 307-4100; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'IF YOU GIVE A MOUSE A COOKIE &amp; OTHER STORY BOOKS' This children's musical, made up of 10 sketches based on 8 books, is diverse, adorable and free. Also, the adults laugh (1:00). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 642-9033; closing tonight. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ANT BULLY' (PG, 90 minutes) A young boy goes to live among the ants, who talk remarkably like Academy Award-winning actors. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'BARNYARD' (PG, 88 minutes) The barnyard animals in this crude 3-D animation walk, talk and party down like human beings. Way too often the male ''cows,'' as the film calls them, also flash their udders. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'The Beales of Grey Gardens' (No rating, 90 minutes) The Maysles brothers dig into their archives for this collection of outtakes from ''Grey Gardens,'' their 1975 cinema vérité classic about the most fascinating cat ladies in the Hamptons. Essential viewing for drag queens. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'BOYNTON BEACH CLUB' (No rating, 104 minutes) A fast-paced romantic comedy about frisky 60-something residents of a Florida ''active adult'' community, ''Boynton Beach Club'' is a rose-colored fantasy about aging that has just enough credibility to make you care about its characters and wish them merrily on their way. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE BRIDESMAID' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) The great Claude Chabrol again takes up a sharp instrument and directs it at one of his favorite targets, the family. Yet while his aim remains true, his touch has become gentler, more forgiving. (Dargis) 'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt- putt-putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Calvaire' (No rating, 90 minutes) In this pretentious horror flick from the Belgian newcomer Fabrice du Welz, a lounge singer (Lucus Laurent) plays the girl in an all-male nightmare populated by savagely violent cretins. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'The Celestine Prophecy' (PG, 100 minutes) A delectable fusion of new age babble and luridly bad filmmaking based on the best-selling book by James Redfield. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'CLERKS II' (R, 98 minutes) More than a decade later, Kevin Smith's New Jersey underachievers have moved from a convenience store to a fast-food franchise. The humor is reliably filthy and frequently hilarious, and the filmmaking is a few steps above rudimentary, but the movie's poignant sweetness is disarming. It has a dirty mind, but its heart is remarkably pure. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CONVERSATIONS WITH OTHER WOMEN' (No rating, 84 minutes) Two old flames meet, years after parting, and have a short fling. An arch, banal conceit, of some interest for Aaron Eckhart and Helena Bonham Carter's performances and the split-screen gimmick that keeps them apart even in their intimate moments. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DESCENT' (R, 99 minutes) A total horror freakout from the British writer and director Neil Marshall about six women on a caving expedition who meet their fears and some scary monsters, too. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'Gabrielle' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haut-bourgeois Parisian marriage, about 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems that Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over, and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'Half Nelson' (R, 107 minutes) In their beautiful bummer about the relationship between a white teacher (Ryan Gosling) and a black student (Shareeka Epps), the gifted young director Ryan Fleck and his writing partner, Anna Boden, offer a lament for the radical fires of the 1960's and a suggestion for life and politics after the new left. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HOUSE OF SAND' (R, 115 minutes, in Portuguese) Beautifully shot in a sandy, remote corner of northern Brazil, this film tells the story of three generations of women, all of them played by Fernanda Montenegro and Fernanda Torres, mother and daughter in real life and two of the national treasures of Brazilian cinema. (Scott)'I Like Killing Flies' (R, 79 minutes) The documentary filmmaker Matt Mahurin paints an engaging if glib portrait of Kenny Shopsin, of the legendary or notorious, depending on your experience, Greenwich Village eatery that bears his name. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'Little Miss Sunshine' (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Lunacy' (No rating, 118 minutes) In the latest phantasmagoria from the Czech filmmaker Jan Svankmajer, a young man (Pavel Liska) meets an aristocrat (Jan Triska) and, with help from Edgar Allan Poe and the Marquis de Sade, tumbles down a very strange rabbit hole. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MIAMI VICE' (R, 133 minutes) This updating of the 1980's television series cost more than the annual budget of the real-life Miami Police Department, making it the most expensive experimental art film ever made. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. A trio of intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MOONLIGHT' (No rating, 90 minutes) In the English-language Dutch thriller ''Moonlight,'' a 13-year-old girl (Laurien Van den Broeck) and a young Afghan drug courier fall in love while fleeing his employers. Though the film is rife with topics and images American audiences may find offensive, the director, Paula van der Oest, addresses them fearlessly and with some artistry, creating a fevered fairy tale that suggests that the veneer of civilization is a thin one. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'MY COUNTRY, MY COUNTRY' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Arabic, English and Kurdish) Filmed in Iraq from June 2004 to February 2005, ''My Country, My Country'' views the prelude to the January elections primarily through the eyes of Dr. Riyadh, a Sunni candidate and physician who runs a free clinic in Baghdad. Without comment but with unusual sensitivity, the director, Laura Poitras, exposes the emotional toll of occupation on Iraqis and United States soldiers alike, leaving us feeling that this particular mission is far from accomplished. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE NIGHT LISTENER' (R, 82 minutes) Robin Williams plays a writer and radio host who strikes up a long-distance friendship with a young man who may not exist. An intriguing premise, but not satisfyingly realized. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'Pulse' (PG-13, 87 minutes) Evil technology menaces idiotic teenagers in this cynical remake of a Japanese horror film. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'QUINCEAÑERA' (R, 90 minutes) This portrait of a Mexican-American family living in a Latino neighborhood of Los Angeles is as smart and warm-hearted an exploration of an upwardly mobile immigrant culture as American independent cinema has produced. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Satellite' (No rating, 100 minutes) In this captivating romantic fairy tale for grown-ups, made on a shoestring, two young lovers in New York flee yuppie hell into a life of petty theft. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'Scoop' (PG-13, 96 minutes) A not especially funny yet oddly appealing comedy in which Woody Allen and Scarlett Johansson make like Nick and Nora, but with more shtick and no martinis (or Asta). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STEP UP' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Ever since Kevin Bacon's rebellious hips ignited a small-town uproar in ''Footloose,'' the modern high school romance has placed a premium on rhythm. In ''Step Up'' a rough Baltimore kid (Channing Tatum), armed only with a killer smile and hip-hop moves, falls for a classically trained dancer (Jenna Dewan). Bland but likable, the movie fashions social equality from big musical numbers. If ballet and hip-hop can coexist, it asks, why can't we all be friends? (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TALLADEGA NIGHTS: THE BALLAD OF RICKY BOBBY' (PG-13, 110 minutes) Fast, fun and silly, with Will Ferrell as a Nascar driver, Sacha Baron Cohen as his nemesis, and a new course record for product placements per gallon. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'13 Tzameti'  (No rating, 90 minutes) The flashy black-and-white directorial debut of the Georgian filmmaker Gela Babluani is a sadistic, arty thriller that suggests a French new wave film infected by a virulent strain of Eastern European nihilism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'The Trouble With Men and Women' (No rating, 74 minutes) This tiny, well-acted movie about the romantic troubles besetting two young couples in London feels at once utterly real and banal. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'WORLD TRADE CENTER' (PG-13, 129 minutes) From Oliver Stone, a return to the emotions of 9/11. Powerful and almost unbearably moving. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'You, Me and Dupree' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Zoom' (PG, 83 minutes) Tim Allen is Jack Shepard, a k a Captain Zoom, a washed-up superhero called back into service to train a group of gifted kids for a secret mission to save Earth. Too infantile for tweens and too stagnant for tots, ''Zoom'' bleeds boredom from every frame. The younger cast members work hard, but no superpower on earth can neutralize Mr. Allen's weary shtick. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>THE BEST OF BUSTER: KEATON COMEDY CLASSICS (Through Sept. 25) Film Forum's eight-film, eight-week festival of the silent comedies of the brilliantly stone-faced Keaton (1895-1966) continues on Monday night with ''Seven Chances'' (1925), about a man who will inherit $7 million (real money back then) if he gets married -- immediately. Also playing is ''Three Ages'' (1923), a romantic comedy set in the Stone Age, ancient Rome and the 20th century. 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8110; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Sunday) The 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962) winds up at the Museum of the Moving Image with four 1940's films this weekend. The closing feature is ''I've Always Loved You'' (1946), a Technicolor B movie about a concert pianist (Catherine McLeod) torn between her maestro and the boy back home. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FROM THE TSARS TO THE STARS: A JOURNEY THROUGH RUSSIAN FANTASTIK CINEMA (Through Aug. 24) The Film Society of Lincoln Center's tribute to Russian science fiction and fantasy films continues. This weekend's features include Pavel Klushanstev's ''Planet of Storms'' (1961), about cosmonauts who find prehistoric beasts on Venus, and Aleksandr Ptushko's last film, ''Ruslan and Ludmila'' (1972), which features a sorcerer, a hunchbacked witch and a kidnapped bride. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues this weekend with ''Ikiru'' (1952), starring Takashi Shimura as an office bureaucrat who learns that he has a terminal illness. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE LEADING MEN OF FRENCH CINEMA (Through Aug. 27) BAMcinématek's tribute to 17 French actors continues this weekend. The attractions include Maurice Ronet in Louis Malle's ''Fire Within'' (1963), about a recovering alcoholic just out of rehab, and Jean-Louis Trintignant in ''My Night at Maud's'' (1969), Éric Rohmer's Oscar-nominated drama about a good Roman Catholic's encounter with a seductive divorcée. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RAISING HELL: SAM PECKINPAH (Through Aug. 29) BAMcinématek's monthlong tribute to Peckinpah (1925-1984) continues. Monday night's feature is ''The Killer Elite'' (1975), with James Caan as a wounded spy out for revenge. Tuesday night's is ''Bring Me the Head of Alfredo Garcia'' (1974), starring Warren Oates as a piano player on an unusual bounty hunt in Mexico. BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>'AMSTERJAM' (Tomorrow) The concept: a handful of big-name acts from disparate pop genres pair up for live mash-ups, playing two or more songs simultaneously in search of playful serendipities. In the hands of skilled (and computer-assisted) producers, the gimmick can have astonishing effects, but there is good reason that it is not often attempted live. The ringmaster: the R &amp; B superproducer Jermaine Dupri (Mariah Carey, Janet Jackson). The players: Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers with the Foo Fighters; L L Cool J with the reggaetón star Tego Calderón; and Busta Rhymes with the Latin band Yerba Buena. At 3 p.m., Randalls Island, near Icahn Stadium, 1 Randalls Island, (212) 307-7171, amsterjam.com; $57. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ARCHIE BELL, THE MIGHTY HANNIBAL (Sunday) Not everyone playing at the McCarren Park Pool this summer is under 30 and shops at American Apparel. In 1968 Archie Bell, with his band the Drells, scored one of the great R &amp; B novelty hits with ''Tighten Up,'' a combination dance-instruction and introduce-the-band number that is blessedly aimless. The turbaned Mighty Hannibal began his career in 1958 with ''Big Chief Hug-Um an' Kiss-Um'' and went on to record great soul-funk nuggets like ''Jerkin' the Dog'' and ''Get in the Groove.'' At 3 p.m., Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, thepoolparties.com; free. Mr. Bell also plays on Monday at 9:30 p.m. at Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CHARLES BISSELL (Tuesday) In the Wrens, a New Jersey indie-rock band that formed in the late 1980's and is known as much for its struggles in making records as for its wonderful music, Mr. Bissell sings about exhaustion, day jobs and failed dreams with an intensity seldom matched by rockers half his age. While fans wait for a new album -- they are used to waiting -- Mr. Bissell is playing in residence on Tuesday nights in the small Tap Bar downstairs at the Knitting Factory. With Koester. At 8 p.m., 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MARIAH CAREY (Wednesday) Before there was ''Idol'' there was Mariah, who made octave-hopping melisma a sport and never met a song she couldn't ride to No. 1. Young singers afraid of being a flash in the pan could learn a lot from her recent comeback, which relied on fresh and up-to-date hip-hop producers and songwriters. With Sean Paul. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $19.50 to $154.50 (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NEKO CASE, JOANNA NEWSOM, MARTHA WAINWRIGHT (Thursday) A decade ago the most influential women in rock were the angry ones. Now it might be the mellow women's turn. Neko Case began in punk and indie-rock bands before finding herself and her voice -- a bewitching, burgundy alto -- in country-tinged Southern gothic. With a froggy, girlish voice, Joanna Newsom plays elegant and completely entrancing reveries on the harp. Martha Wainwright's passionate and earthy songs swirl from her acoustic guitar into grand arrangements but never lose their intimacy. At 5 p.m., McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (212) 307-7171; $32.50 in advance, $36 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CROSBY, STILLS, NASH AND YOUNG (Sunday, Tuesday and Wednesday) It's the fourth partner, Neil Young, who just might push this alliance beyond self-satisfied baby-boom nostalgia and vocal harmonies into something like rock. Sunday at 8 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698, artscenter.com; sold out. Tuesday and Wednesday nights at 8, Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000, nikonjonesbeach.com; $46 to $251. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133, dannysgrandseapalace.com; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>FOO FIGHTERS, FRANK BLACK (Monday) The Foo Fighters' long-promised acoustic tour is a family affair. Joining Dave Grohl and his band will be Pat Smear, of the great Los Angeles punk group the Germs in the 1970's, and who was an auxiliary member of Nirvana in the 90's; and the violinist Petra Hayden and the keyboardist Rami Jaffee, who both played on the Foo Fighters' most recent album, ''In Your Honor'' (RCA). Opening the show is Frank Black, making his first solo appearances since the Pixies reunion. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; sold out. Frank Black also plays tomorrow night at 8 and 11:30 at Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Thursday) Though she is invariably dressed in black, with her face in witchy streaks of makeup, Diamanda Galás needs only her voice to terrify, seduce and beguile. She slides from a low, sensual growl to painful yet musically precise shrieks, and has a vast repertory that ranges from Johnny Cash ballads to her own chilling AIDS Masses. In the third of four shows at the Spiegeltent downtown, she offers songs associated with Marlene Dietrich, Peggy Lee, Judy Garland, Frank Sinatra, Édith Piaf and Timi Yuro. At 6 p.m., Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JAMES GANG (Tomorrow) Before joining the Eagles, Joe Walsh joined this Cleveland blues-boogie band, whose ''Funk #49'' is the platonic ideal of all 70's blues boogies. The band -- which also includes the bassist Dale Peters and the drummer Jim Fox -- has reunited periodically, including at an election rally for Bill Clinton 10 years ago, and is touring this summer. With J D and the Straight Shot. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; $63.50 to $128.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER OUT OF DOORS (Today through Sunday) A highlight of this series each summer is the Roots of American Music minifestival, which this year has a particular emphasis on blues and soul. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. at the Damrosch Park Bandshell are the 1960's soul vets Eddie Floyd (''Knock on Wood'') and Percy Sledge (''When a Man Loves a Woman''). On the North Plaza, beginning at 2 p.m., are Joe Jencks, Dan Milner and Bob Conroy, the Wiyos, Stairwell Sisters, and Robin and Linda Williams. Sunday's lineup at the bandshell, at 7 p.m., includes Mavis Staples of the pioneering gospel-funk Staple Singers, and the country singer Marty Stuart. The Blue Vipers of Brooklyn, Larry Johnson, Murray Porter and Adrienne Young play on the North Plaza, at 2 p.m. Two concerts today serve as preludes to the Roots festival: ''Evolution of the Blues'' with Guy Davis and Michael Hill, on the North Plaza at 5:30 p.m., and a strong lineup of Mr. Davis, Chico Hamilton and Buster Williams, Murray Porter, Hazel Dickens and Bettye LaVette at the bandshell, at 7. (212) 875-5766, lincolncenter.org; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAGIK MARKERS, EXCEPTER, BLUES CONTROL, FERN KNIGHT (Tomorrow) An afternoon of noise rock at the East River Amphitheater, where the most discordant music can sound almost pastoral. The trio Magik Markers' clangorous improvisations reach back to New York's early-1980's No Wave scene. Excepter, from Brooklyn, lists its influences as ''weather, traffic, electricity, magic.'' Blues Control's distorted rumblings sound like Mountain or Cream songs emanating from a sunken submarine. And since no noise-rock show these days is complete without a ''freak folk'' act, Fern Knight, a droney acoustic band from Philadelphia, is on the bill. At 2 p.m., East River Park, south of Delancey Street, Lower East Side, ermp.org; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RAUL MALO (Tuesday) Mr. Malo, the leader of the Mavericks, has never let himself be bound by the strictures of country. His music looks back to the 1950's and 60's with a clear-eyed nostalgia, and he has the soaring tenor voice of a dedicated Roy Orbison fan. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK DOLLS (Tonight) Never say die. With its only two surviving original members well into their 50's, this proto-punk, proto-glam band, which made trashy cross-dressing a rock 'n' roll virtue, recently released its first new album in 32 years, ''One Day It Will Please Us to Remember Even This'' (Roadrunner), and its appetite for sleazy vamps and hilarious wickedness is undiminished. ''You're designed so intelligent/Ain't no way that was an accident,'' David Johansen sings in ''Dance Like a Monkey.'' ''Come on shake your monkey hips, my pretty little creationist.'' At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789, seaportmusicfestival.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RANCID (Thursday) This long-running band of studious Clash revivalists said two years ago it was going on hiatus, but that didn't last long. Rancid is said to be working on a new album and on Thursday begins four nights at the B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, promising that no two nights will be the same. With H20 and FVK. At 8 p.m., 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>STEVE RILEY AND THE MAMOU PLAYBOYS (Sunday) The accordionist Steve Riley leads one of the best bands from the Louisiana bayous. It reaches back to some of the oldest Cajun tunes and can play them in traditional style, but it's not afraid of swamp-rock or a touch of country, either. At 7:30 p.m., with a free zydeco dance lesson at 6:30, Connolly's, 121 West 45th Street, Manhattan, (212) 685-7597, letszydeco.com; $22. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>THE SHINS, J MASCIS (Wednesday) The Shins emerged from Albuquerque at the turn of the millennium with a sound that slowly but inevitably catapulted them to the upper ranks of the indiesphere: wistful and acoustic, with an adventurousness that sometimes leads to something like psychedelia. (Natalie Portman's exhortation in ''Garden State'' that the band's music will ''change your life'' didn't hurt.) J Mascis led Dinosaur Jr., one of the greatest and most influential original grunge bands, whose juxtaposition of mopey lyrics and furious guitar sludge prefigured Nirvana. With Sam Jayne. At 6:30 p.m., McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (212) 307-7171; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* P. F. Sloan (Thursday) One of the few songwriters who can be said to have truly captured the extremes of the 1960's -- he wrote both ''Eve of Destruction'' and ''Secret Agent Man'' -- P. F. Sloan left the music business in the 70's and has mostly stayed out until now. He makes a rare appearance at Joe's Pub on Thursday, two days after the release of ''Sailover'' (Hightone), his first new album in many years. At 7:30 p.m., 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* WU-TANG CLAN (Tonight) The eight surviving representatives of hip-hop's most ingenious and eccentric band-cum-brand name team up for a tour in tribute to Russell Tyrone Jones, better known as Ol' Dirty Bastard, the especially ingenious, eccentric and self-destructive member who died in 2004. With Lord Jamar. At 7, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* GERI ALLEN TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) ''Timeless Portraits and Dreams'' (Telarc), a soulfully earnest new album by Geri Allen, showcases her piano playing in a number of different settings, including one with a vocal chorus. Here she appears in a basic but eminently rewarding lineup, with her longtime associate Darryl Hall on bass and the venerable Jimmy Cobb on drums. Through Aug. 27. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum.(Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>PECK ALLMOND KALIMBA KOLLECTIVE (Tuesday) This ensemble finds Mr. Allmond augmenting his usual arsenal of horns with kalimbas, or African thumb pianos. The group also includes an electric five-string cello, played by Rufus Cappadocia, and Haitian hand drums, courtesy of Bonga Jean-Baptiste. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ED CHERRY TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow) Ed Cherry is a blues-influenced guitarist with solid credentials, including tours of duty with Dizzy Gillespie and Henry Threadgill. Here he works in an organ trio, his favorite setting of late. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., the River Room, Riverbank State Park, Riverside Drive at 145th Street, Harlem (212) 491-1500, theriverroomofharlem.com; no cover; dinner or two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHARLIE HADEN'S QUARTET WEST (Tonight through Sunday) In 20 years Quartet West has never wavered in its commitment to romance. The heart of the group is Ernie Watts, with his ardent tenor saxophone style; its soul is the bass playing of Mr. Haden. Alan Broadbent's sophisticated piano playing and arranging could be, so to speak, its brain. Rodney Green fills in for Larance Marable on drums. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAËL ATTIAS AND RENKU (Wednesday) Mr. Attias, an alto saxophonist, develops compositional fragments into compact expeditions in this group with the bassist John Hebert, the keyboardist Russ Lossing and the drummer Satoshi Takeishi. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MATT DARRIAU'S PARADOX TRIO (Tonight) The exuberant Balkan fusion once associated with the Knitting Factory is still kicking; at least it is for this band, which issued an album on Enja last year. In addition to Mr. Darriau's clarinet, alto saxophone and gaida (or Balkan bagpipe), Paradox Trio features the electric guitar of Brad Shepik, the cello of Rufus Cappadocia and the percussion of Seido Salifoski. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDREW DRURY'S CONTENT PROVIDER (Tomorrow and Thursday) Mr. Drury is a thoughtfully avant-garde drummer and composer whose primary working band, Content Provider, includes the trumpeter Peter Evans, the alto saxophonist Briggan Krauss and the tenor saxophonist and clarinetist Chris Speed. Tomorrow the group will appear, without Mr. Speed, in the East Village; on Thursday the entire group performs in Brooklyn. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. Thursday at 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MONCEF GENOUD (Tuesday) Tunisian born and Swiss raised, Mr. Genoud applies an uncommon perspective to his acoustic piano playing, as he demonstrates on a strong new album, ''Aqua'' (Savoy). He will perform with a trio, his most comfortable setting. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY GREENE QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow) Mr. Greene brings an athletic self-assurance to his saxophone playing, and leads a top-shelf band with Xavier Davis on piano, Reuben Rogers on bass and Eric Harland on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DREW GRESS'S 7 BLACK BUTTERFLIES (Tomorrow through Monday) A stalwart bassist both in and out of the contemporary avant-garde, Mr. Gress has composed new music inspired by the paintings of Mark Rothko. He has the right accompanists for this variety of disciplined abstraction: the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the alto saxophonist Tim Berne, the keyboardist Craig Taborn and the drummer Tom Rainey. Tomorrow and Sunday at 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. Monday at 8 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* ROY HAYNES FOUNTAIN OF YOUTH BAND (Tuesday through Thursday) The redoubtable drummer Roy Haynes is in his 80's, though you'd never guess it by the freshness and ferocity of his playing. His working quartet features musicians many years his junior: the alto saxophonist Jaleel Shaw, the pianist Martin Bejerano and the bassist David Wong. Through Aug. 27. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARI HOENIG AND CHRIS POTTER (Tonight) Mr. Hoenig, a drummer, and Mr. Potter, a saxophonist, are two of the sharpest musicians in modern post-bop circles, and their duo exchange is a thing of intensity and poise. At 6 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LAN XANG (Wednesday) This quartet was a compact powerhouse on the experimental scene in the middle to late 1990's, after which its four members -- the saxophonists Donny McCaslin and Dave Binney, the bassist Scott Colley and the drummer Kenny Wollesen -- separately established successful careers. They have all crossed paths often, but this one-night engagement marks a rare reunion. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TANIA MARIA (Tuesday through Thursday) On her album ''Intimidade,'' recently released on Blue Note, Tania Maria applies her conversational vocals and piano playing to a brand of acoustic pop well seasoned by the sound of her native Brazil. She'll create a similar fusion here with a group consisting of the bassist Sergio Brandao and the percussionists Rick Sebastian and Mestre Carneiro. Through Aug. 27. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ERIC McPHERSON, NASHEET WAITS, ABRAHAM BURTON (Thursday) Mr. McPherson and Mr. Waits are two of jazz's most engagingly expressive younger drummers, united by a common gift for slippery propulsion. They join Mr. Burton, a tenor saxophonist, in an experimental exchange. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MULGREW MILLER AND WINGSPAN (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Miller is a pianist with an earthy style and a particular gift for the blues. But his ensemble Wingspan pursues a distinctly airy sensibility, with help from the saxophonist Steve Wilson, the trumpeter Duane Eubanks, the vibraphonist Steve Nelson, the bassist Ivan Taylor and the drummer Rodney Green. Through Aug. 27. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>OSCAR NORIEGA TRIO (Thursday) Oscar Noriega, a clarinetist and saxophonist, taps raw but focused energies -- and a book of Mexican folk songs -- in this group with the bassist Trevor Dunn and the drummer Tom Rainey. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID SÁNCHEZ QUARTET (Through Sunday) A tenor and soprano saxophonist equally conversant in the rigors of post-bop and the nuances of Latin folk music, Mr. Sánchez digs in here with some longtime colleagues: Edsel Gomez on piano, Ben Street on bass and Adam Cruz on drums. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN TRIO (Thursday through Sunday) Jenny Scheinman is a violinist attracted to rusticity but committed to a modern language; the same could be said, more or less, of the drummer Paul Motian and the pianist Jason Moran. Still, this all-star trio carries the burden of a small spectacle: it could be transcendent or a train wreck, and either way it will be something to behold. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHRISTIAN SCOTT SEXTET/ERIC PERSON'S META-FOUR (Tonight) Christian Scott is an excellent young trumpeter whose recent debut, ''Rewind That'' (Concord), signaled his intention to establish a modern funk-based sound; he succeeded, but at the cost of spontaneity, a problem that will probably not resurface here. Also on the bill is Meta-Four, a group led by Mr. Person, a saxophonist and composer. At 9 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $18, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TRAVIS SULLIVAN'S BJORKESTRA (Tonight) A big band with a muse, a method, a growing reputation and a roster of good young players. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; tonicnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHARLES TOLLIVER BIG BAND (Tonight through Sunday) Charles Tolliver leads an upgraded edition of his acclaimed orchestra of the 1970's, with such top-shelf talent as the saxophonists Billy Harper and Craig Handy, the trombonist Clark Gayton, the pianist Robert Glasper and the bassist Cecil McBee. The band will be featured on a forthcoming Blue Note album, but that's no reason not to absorb its visceral impact in person. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAKE TORIYAMA'S TBA (Tonight) Mr. Toriyama is a drummer with ever-expanding credentials in the Brooklyn experimental scene. Despite what the name might imply, he does know the other members of his band: Drew Gress and Chris Lightcap, accomplished bassists both. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RANDY WESTON (Wednesday) The pianist Randy Weston has been one of the principal agents of an African jazz aesthetic since his first visit to Nigeria, in the 1960's. He turned 80 this year, the ostensible reason for this special concert, which assembles a number of guests, including the saxophonists Dewey Redman and Billy Harper, the conga legend Candido Camero, the pipa player Min Xiao Fen and the kora player Abdou Mboup. At 8 p.m., Damrosch Park, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5766; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SARAH WILSON QUINTET (Tuesday and Wednesday) Sarah Wilson is a trumpeter and composer based in San Francisco, though she has extensive New York ties, including a post as musical director for the annual puppet spectacle presented by Lincoln Center Out of Doors. On Tuesday night she leads the same band of improvisers featured on her new album, ''Music for an Imaginary Play'' (Evander Music); on Wednesday she features a different group, with the violinist Charlie Burnham, the trombonist Art Baron, the bassist Jerome Harris and the drummer Satoshi Takeishi. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'AFTERNOON ARIAS' (Today) One of New York's most popular places for people to bring their lunches on a pleasant summer afternoon is Bryant Park, right behind the New York Public Library. Today, in the last of four presentations, the New York City Opera is offering music for visitors to the park to have their lunch by and otherwise enjoy. ''Afternoon Arias'' is the name of the concert, featuring singers from the City Opera, accompanied by the pianist Gerald Steichen, in excerpts from ''La Bohème,'' ''Hansel and Gretel,'' ''Carmen,'' ''Faust'' and other works. Midge Woolsey from WQXR is the host. At 12:30 p.m., Avenue of the Americas, at 42nd Street, (212) 870-7787, nycopera.com; free. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPera (Today through Tuesday, and Thursday) Opera can be formal or pure fluff, and this season's program at Glimmerglass about equally balances the two. All four of this year's operas are in rotation over the next week, with the lighter side predominating: Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' (today at 1:30 and 8 p.m., Monday at 1:30 p.m.); Rossini's classic ''Barber of Seville'' (tomorrow and Tuesday at 1:30 p.m., Thursday night at 8); Steven Hartke's new Maupassant-based opera ''The Greater Good'' (tomorrow night at 8); and Janacek's dark ''Jenufa,'' in Jonathan Miller's production (Sunday afternoon at 1:30). Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255, glimmerglass.org; $69 to $117 today through Sunday; $41 to $104 Tuesday and Thursday. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'IDOMENEO'  (Wednesday) William Christie and Les Arts Florissants have attained something like rock-star status in the early-music world as they help illuminate all kinds of unexpected corners of the 17th- and 18th-century repertory. Mozart's opera seria ''Idomeneo'' is practically pop compared with some of the more obscure works the group has championed. But it has done some fine Mozart performances, and expectations are high for this one. Paul Agnew takes the title role in this semistaged production. At 7:30 p.m., Rose Theater, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $35 to $75. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MET IN THE PARKS (Tuesday and Wednesday) The opening of the Metropolitan Opera's season may be weeks away, but opera lovers can enjoy two enduringly popular works in the Met's series of concert performances in the parks of New York and New Jersey. The tour begins on Tuesday at the Great Lawn in Central Park with Verdi's ''Traviata,'' starring the luminous soprano Hei-Kyung Hong as Violetta. On Wednesday, at the same site, the Met offers Verdi's ''Rigoletto,'' with the commanding baritone Mark Delavan in the title role. These two works will then play in parks in the Bronx, Staten Island, Queens, Brooklyn and New Jersey through Sept. 2. This popular series is celebrating its 40th anniversary. The Met estimates that some 7.5 million people have attended performances over the years. At 8 p.m., (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; free. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARD MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) Round 2 of Leon Botstein's attempt to resuscitate Franz Liszt begins tonight at Bard College, with the pianists Jeremy Denk and Piers Lane, the mezzo-soprano Jill Grove, the violinist Ani Kavafian and others performing works by Liszt and his contemporaries. Tomorrow's morning program explores the influence of exotic music on European composers, and the afternoon focuses on Liszt and chamber music. In the evening Mr. Botstein will lead the American Symphony Orchestra in Liszt's ''Faust Symphony'' and in excerpts from his oratorio ''Christus'' and Berlioz's ''Enfance du Christ.'' The apparent aim of Sunday's afternoon program is to reveal a mature, spiritual Liszt by focusing on his chamber and choral works. The concluding concert highlights a connection to Wagner, with Liszt's ''Missa Solemnis'' and ''The Bells of Strasbourg'' and the Prelude and Good Friday Music from Wagner's ''Parsifal.'' Tonight at 8 ($20 to $45); tomorrow at 10 a.m. ($30), and 1:30 ($35) and 8 p.m. ($25 to $55); Sunday at 1:30 ($35) and 5:30 p.m. ($25 to $55). Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7900, summerscape.bard.edu. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall (a former coffee barge) on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight Edward Arron, the cellist, supported at the piano by Jeewon Park, plays works by Stravinsky, Mendelssohn and Rachmaninoff. Tomorrow and Sunday the Gala Quartet is joined by Gerald Robbins, a pianist, in the Brahms F minor Piano Quintet; it also plays Haydn's ''Emperor'' Quartet and Turina's ''Oración del Torero.'' And on Thursday the Neighborhood Composers' Chorus and the Orfeo Duo offer works by Elizabeth Adams, James Blachly, Sarah Dawson and others. Tonight, tomorrow night and Thursday night at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m.; Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org. Tonight and Thursday: $35, and $20 for students; on Thursday, $30 for 65+. Tomorrow and Sunday: $40, and $25 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MOZART (Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) On Sunday Joshua Bell and friends -- including the pianist Frederic Chiu, the Miró Quartet and the violinist Colin Jacobsen -- continue the Mozart festivities with the composer's Piano Quartet in G minor, followed by the New York premiere of a new work by Edgar Meyer. On Tuesday and Wednesday Lisa Batiashvili, a rising star violinist, makes her Mostly Mozart debut with the premiere of a concerto by the Finnish composer Magnus Lindberg, with Louis Langrée leading the festival orchestra. The program also features Lars Vogt playing Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 23 in A and the overtures to ''Le Nozze di Figaro'' and ''Don Giovanni.'' The International Contemporary Ensemble offers a late-night departure from Mozart on Tuesday with Lindberg's Clarinet Quintet, ''Linea d'Ombra'' and the American premiere of ''Zona.'' Later on Wednesday evening Mr. Vogt and Ms. Batiashvili play Mozart sonatas at the Kaplan Penthouse. Members of the Emerson String Quartet and the pianist Leon Fleisher play Beethoven's String Trio in G, Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 12 in A and Brahms's Sextet No. 2 on Thursday at Avery Fisher Hall. The late-night concert features the Daedalus Quartet playing Ravel and Mozart. Sunday at 5 p.m.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; at Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center. Late-night concerts at 10:30 at the Kaplan Penthouse, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $38 to $65 on Sunday; $35 to $55 for 8 p.m. concerts on Tuesday through Thursdays; $35 for late-night concerts. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* TRIO SETTECENTO (Thursday) This Chicago-based Baroque music ensemble includes Rachel Barton Pine, a superb violinist; David Schrader, the harpsichordist; and John Mark Rozendaal on the viola da gamba, and makes its New York debut with works by Bach, Stradella, Veracini and Handel. At 6 p.m., the Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 547-0709, frick.org; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday) Because of illness, the Spanish conductor Rafael Frühbeck de Burgos is being replaced in two scheduled concerts with the Boston Symphony Orchestra this weekend. Ludovic Morlot takes over tonight in a greatest-hits concert of Falla (''Nights in the Garden of Spain''), Debussy (''La Mer'') and Ravel (''Boléro''). Pinchas Steinberg steps in on Sunday's all-Brahms program, including the second piano concerto with Peter Serkin. Tomorrow night Herbert Blomstedt will conduct the violin star Hilary Hahn in the Dvorak concerto; Ms. Hahn will also make a modest appearance before tonight's concert playing chamber music (a Mozart trio, to be exact) with members of the Boston Symphony. On Wednesday Yo Yo Ma and Emanuel Ax offer Beethoven. Tonight and tomorrow and Wednesday nights at 8:30 (preconcert chamber program tonight at 6); Sunday afternoon at 2:30; Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; $17 to $87 tonight through Sunday; $20 to $95 on Wednesday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TANNERY POND CONCERTS (Tomorrow) Christian Steiner is well known for his photography, and less well known, perhaps, as a musician. But he is least known as the artistic director of this lovely little concert series, for which he lures leading musicians up to the Berkshires (over the New York border) to perform in an enchanting little wooden hall. This weekend Wu Han and David Finckel, the husband-and-wife collaborators as pianist and cellist who are also the artistic directors of the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, let their hair down with their close colleague Da-Hong Seetoo, a violinist, in a program of Shostakovich and Tchaikovsky. At 8 p.m., Mount Lebanon Shaker Village, New Lebanon, N.Y., (888) 820-9441, tannerypondconcerts.org; $25 and $30. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>ARIANE ANTHONY AND CEDRIC NEUGEBAUER (Tonight and tomorrow night) The wildly imaginative Ms. Anthony will present a new collaboration with Mr. Neugebauer, as well as a recent solo, ''Snail,'' with costumes of wearable sculpture by Agata Oleksiak and music by John Stone. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, the Field's FAR Space, 521 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (718) 349-0008; suggested donation, $10. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>BATTERY DANCE COMPANY: DOWNTOWN DANCE FESTIVAL (Monday through Thursday) A rite of summer now in its 25th year, this festival will present 16 companies and a wide range of styles in two downtown locations, through Aug. 27. The centerpiece is probably ''Oceans of Light,'' on a shared program on Thursday with Kathak Ensemble, in which modern dancers from New Orleans will perform with South Asian classical dancers. The work pays homage to the victims of Hurricane Katrina and the Asian tsunami by exploring water's beauty, grace and wrath. Monday through Thursday from noon to 1:30 p.m., Chase Plaza, Nassau Street between Liberty and Pine Streets, Lower Manhattan, batterydance.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Thursday) For an informal Thursday evening series this month, the company opens up its intimate theater to the street and turns it into an installation for a 90-minute program of multimedia dance created by company members. At 6 p.m., Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 244-0015, cedarlakedance.com; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHOREOGRAPHY CAFÉ (Wednesday) Jeremy Nelson is the featured artist in this informal series presented by Dancewave, which invites professional choreographers to work with child and teenage dancers. At 2:15 p.m., Old First Reformed Church, 729 Carroll Street, at Seventh Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 522-4696, dancewave.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CITY PARKS DANCE (Tomorrow) Nicholasleichterdance, which fuses modern dance and pop-culture movement, and Jamel Gaines's Creative Outlet Dance Theater of Brooklyn, which addresses sociocultural themes in movement, theater, song and poetry, will share the bill in this program. Mr. Gaines will teach the open dance class that begins the event. Tomorrow at 3 p.m., Von King Park, 670 Lafayette Avenue, between Marcy and Tompkins Avenues, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (212) 360-8290, cityparksfoundation.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'GRIMM' (Thursday) Otis Cook, choreographer for Momix, and Faith Pilger, a dancer and choreographer, have created in ''Grimm'' a dance theater piece that explores fear and parenthood, rebellion and discovery, through a retelling of ''Hansel and Gretel.'' Through Aug. 27. At 8 p.m., the Duke, 229 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200, agrimmproduction.com; $30; $20 for students and 65+; $15 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) Peter Boal's Pacific Northwest Ballet from Seattle, or at least a touring ensemble, will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend, followed there Tuesday through Thursday (and next weekend, to the end of this summer's festival) by the Mark Morris Dance Group. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, Choreftes, a Greek company in its United States debut, plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is Rubberbandance Group, which comes from Montreal and combines hip-hop with contemporary ballet. Pacific Northwest Ballet, tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., $50; Morris, Tuesday through Thursday nights at 8, $58, Shawn Theater. Choreftes, tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15, tomorrow at 2:15 p.m. and Sunday at 5 p.m.; Rubberbandance, Thursday at 8:15 p.m., Duke Theater, $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, ages 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions can be found at jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* 'MOZART DANCES' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Another month, another major work from Mark Morris. This one was commissioned by the Mostly Mozart Festival and offers the Mark Morris Dance Group performing to two Mozart piano concertos (K. 413 and 595) and the Sonata in D for two pianos (K. 448), with Louis Langrée conducting the Festival Orchestra and the pianists Emanuel Ax and Yoko Nozaki. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $25 to $75. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NICHOLAS ANDRE DANCE THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Directed by Nick Seligson-Ross, the company will perform five pieces set to composers including Handel and Mancini. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, nicholasandredance.com; $19 and $35 in advance, and $20 and $36 at the door. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>RIVER TO RIVER FESTIVAL (Today) The Lower Manhattan Cultural Council Sitelines series offers ''Oasis,'' a performance by H. T. Chen and Sharon Estacio that celebrates parks as gathering spaces. Today at 12:30 p.m., Columbus Park, intersection of Baxter, Mulberry, Worth and Bayard Streets, Chinatown, rivertorivernyc.com; free. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>SITELINES: ELLIS WOOD DANCE (Monday through Wednesday) In the last installment of this festival, 20 women will move across exterior balconies of an ornate old downtown building in Ms. Wood's new ''Fire on Wall Street,'' which explores the element of fire with what the choreographer describes as sensual abandon. Position those safety nets. Through Aug. 30. At noon and 12:30 p.m., Cipriani, 55 Wall Street, Lower Manhattan, lmcc.net; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SMUIN BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow) A lively San Francisco company offers two new works by Michael Smuin: ''Bluegrass/Slyde,'' to bluegrass music, and ''Symphony of Psalms,'' to Stravinsky. They share the program with ''Fly Me to the Moon,'' to Frank Sinatra recordings. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $42. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>SUDDEN ENLIGHTENMENT THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Hey Jeong Yoon and Eun Hee Kim, both from Seoul, will present the timely-sounding ''Beyond the DMZ,'' which documents the division of Korea more than 50 years ago. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 5 p.m., the Poet's Den Theater, 309 East 108th Street, Spanish Harlem, (718) 651-7725; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Folk Art Museum: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' through Sept. 17. The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040, folkartmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this engrossing if somewhat strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606, daheshmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestoes and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best-known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 (1114 is the school) Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* INternational Center of Photography: 'atta kim: On Air,' through Aug. 27. The South Korean artist Atta Kim's best-known body of work is a series called ''The Museum Project'' (1995-2002), for which he photographed his human subjects -- families, nude couples, maimed war veterans -- locked inside plexiglass exhibition cases like specimens on display. The series eventually took a religious turn, with models posing as Buddhist deities. The pictures here, in his first major American solo show, continue this spiritual trajectory. Filmed using long exposure times, figures, landscapes and religious icons have been turned into apparitions. People, art and museums may last for a while, Mr. Kim seems to say, but all things eventually melt away. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'ANGLOMANIA: TRADITION AND TRANSGRESSION IN BRITISH FASHION,' through Sept. 4. Ranging from early-18th-century gowns to next season's evening wear, this show crowds 65 extravagantly clad mannequins into the Met's normally serene English period rooms, trying to connect the sartorial innovations of the English dandy, the aggressive tribal attire of punk and the deconstructive impulses of today's British fashion stars. A certain confusion, both intellectual and visual, reigns, but there is more than enough to look at. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* met: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early 19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 4 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. Further sharpness comes from the placement of all parts of the altarpiece at eye level, creating a viewing intensity that more than compensates for the fact that they have not been reassembled. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Museum of Arts AND Design: 'THE EAMES LOUNGE CHAIR: AN ICON OF MODERN DESIGN,' through Sept. 3. Celebrating the 50th anniversary of a chair whose combination of declarative modernist structure and sheer creature comfort was both innovative and a bit alien, this exhibition is a successful design object in its own right. It pays homage with drawings, advertising ephemera, precursors, vintage television clips, a wonderful documentary and three versions of the chair itself, enshrined, exploded and usable. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535, madmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500, mobia.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer, and it makes some interesting points about the spectacle of the museum, the Modern included. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Museum of Modern Art: Douglas Gordon: 'Timeline,' through Sept 4. This selection of works by the artist known for appropriating and inventively manipulating Hollywood movies includes his projection of Alfred Hitchcock's ''Psycho,'' which runs so slowly that it takes 24 hours to complete, and a large-scale video installation that studies a circus elephant performing in an empty art gallery. 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer,  through Sept. 18. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Las Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle-shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: Had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden: Chihuly at the New York Botanical Garden, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700, nybg.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, (212) 873-3400, nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. The museum entrance is at 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088, noguchi.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Rubin Museum of Art : 'What is it? HimalAyan Art' This museum is an oasis of calm in the city; you can feel your tension dissolve the minute you walk in the door. At the same time, the place jumps with activities, including lectures, films and exhibitions, many devoted to aspects of Himalayan culture. And for a basic guide to the art of Tibet and Nepal, you will do no better than to take a slow walk through this show, which, using an array of gorgeous objects, distills knotty visual and spiritual systems to a soothing but stimulating entry-level form. 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Wadsworth Atheneum: 'American Splendor: Hudson River School Masterworks From the Wadsworth Atheneum,' through Dec. 31. Back from a two-and-a-half-year tour at six other American museums, the Wadsworth's formidable collection of 19th-century Hudson River School paintings is on display in this homecoming show. Not every Hudson River collection can boast 11 works by Frederic Edwin Church, 13 by Thomas Cole and 5 by Albert Bierstadt,, a leading painter of the American West, along with powerful examples by other artists of the school. They are among the more than 60 paintings on display here. It's rare that you see these ultrafamiliar paintings in such concentration; their combined presence gives the show a synergistic sparkle and energy that you don't get when you see them in smaller groupings. 600 Main Street, Hartford, (860) 278-2670, www.wadsworthatheneum.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>YES BRUCE NAUMAN There has never been much in the way of ''No'' to the influential Post-Minimalist and sculptor-of-all-trades Bruce Nauman. But this astutely structured, if male-dominated, exhibition considers his importance anew, especially his use of language, neon and the body, and his visceral sense of form. The show's title is taken from a 1989 work by Jessica Diamond that is included, along with pertinent efforts by Paul McCarthy, Charles Ray, Glenn Ligon, Jason Rhoades, Peter Coffin, Diana Thater, John Bock and, of course, Mr. Nauman himself. Zwirner &amp; Wirth, 32 East 69th Street, (212) 517-8677, zwirnerandwirth.com, through Sept. 9. (The gallery will be closed Aug. 21 through Aug. 25.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* GALERIE DANIEL BUCHHOLZ AT METRO PICTURES This well-known Cologne gallery presents a surprisingly sweeping view of current art that includes Americans and Europeans and, despite its Conceptual slant, an impressive range of mediums and sensibilities. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, (212) 206-7100, metropicturesgallery.com, through Sept. 16. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Materiality' Inventive works made of all sorts of materials in this show include a stuffed leather-and-plywood tree by Carolyn Salas; a geometric landscape with a slowing-moving, wartlike kinetic element, covered in reflective Mylar, by Charlotte Becket; a neat display of more than 200 pieces of breakfast cereal by Tom Friedman; and a sumptuous stuffed object resembling a much-enlarged amoeba by Ernesto Neto. Kravets/Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238, kravetswehbygallery.com, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Howardena Pindell: 'In My Lifetime' Thirty years ago Howardena Pindell was well known for meditative, process-based abstract work, though her art has always had two aspects. In the 1970's and 80's it assumed and maintained an overtly political direction in large-scale pieces that combined abstraction, words and figures to deal with social and political issues, from AIDS and homelessness to the present war in Iraq. Both types are in this informal gallery retrospective, which makes clear how thoroughly they are based on -- and emerge from and are fueled and inflected by -- the individual experiences and memories of the artist herself. G. R. N'Namdi Gallery, 526 West 26th Street, Suite 316, (212) 929-6645, grnnamdi.com, through Aug. 31. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>'WAR ON 45/MY MIRRORS ARE PAINTED BLACK (FOR YOU)' The latest word from the boys in black is a show of six artists organized by the head boy, Banks Violette. The stark glamour of it cannot be denied, but it looks too much like graphic design. Bortolami Dayan, 510 West 25th Street, (212) 727-2050, bortolamidayan.com, through Sept. 2. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* JAMES J. WILLIAMS III: 'BY REQUEST, MY EPITAPH' Despite debts to artists like Jack Pierson, Karen Kilimnik, Richard Prince and Nan Goldin, this Havershamish environment and solo debut exude a promising fusion of modesty and narcissism. Its deep teal walls display scores of Polaroids, drawings, collages, notebooks and thrift-shop-worthy paintings, along with many of the artist's well-worn belongings. An illusion of stylish, if impoverished, full disclosure results. Self-conscious bohemianism teeters between nostalgia and irony, and art emerges as an incessant if nonchalant activity at the center of an eked-out existence. Envoy, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 242-7524, envoygallery.com, through Sept. 9. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* Amer Kobaslija: 'Large-Scale Studio Paintings' Large, exhaustively detailed, sensuously painted fish-eye views of the artist's studio. George Adams, 525 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 564-8480, georgeadamsgallery.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* 'A BROKEN ARM' The title is a tribute to Duchamp. The works review various strategies of using found objects or images in photography, painting and sculpture. The seven artists include Gedi Sibony, Arnold Odermatt and Karen Kilimnik. All has been orchestrated by Mari Spirito, the gallery's director. 303 Gallery, 525 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-1121, 303gallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'DERECONSTRUCTION' Matthew Higgs, director of the alternative space White Columns, has assembled a handsome show that in typical Higgs fashion brings together outsider, emerging, hip and formerly hip artists. Variations on collage and assemblage predominate without feeling stale. The larger point: deconstruction has had its day, and it is time to start putting things back together again. The putters range from A. R. Penck and Lucas Samaras to Carter and Alexandra Bircken. Gladstone Gallery, 515 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-9300, gladstonegallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Dreamland: Coney Island, 1905-1925' Coney Island lovers will appreciate this show of early-20th-century photographs, artifacts, drawings and engineering plans. Most surprising are drawings from the W. F. Mangels Company, which built many of the area's amusement park rides and games; the precise, watercolor-tinted shooting gallery drawings look like contemporary artworks. And the wooden carousel horse head is a beautiful piece of sculpture. Ricco Maresca, 529 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 627-4819, riccomaresca.com; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Group Show' Four interesting Conceptualists: Pierre Bismuth folds a giant reproduction of a Jasper Johns flag painting into a Donald Judd-like box; Ryan Gander makes large photographs of bulletin boards bearing puzzling documents; Karl Haendel covers a wall with his large, handmade graphite copies of consumer-culture ephemera; and T. Kelly Mason constructs a walk-in, padded environment with soft, rain-related sounds and a video. Cohan &amp; Leslie, 138 10th Avenue, near 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-8710, cohanandleslie.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'MEN' This show of 10 paintings of men by 10 women, organized by the painter Ellen Altfest, covers a lot of stylistic ground and includes an only partly tongue-in-cheek denunciation from the lesbian collective Redykeulous. Realism makes the strongest impression. I-20, 557 West 23rd Street, Chelsea, (212) 645-1100, I-20.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. Concentrating on books, but also including prints and drawings, it retells the tale of the French avant-garde on a relatively egalitarian playing field. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089 or nypl.org; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Photography Is Not An Art!' More than 100 examples of vernacular, often anonymous photographs from the fields of medicine, forensics, space exploration and advertising prove that nonart photography is often as interesting as the fine-art variety. Alan Klotz, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 741-4764, photocollect.com; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Prevailing Climate' This intelligent group show, organized by Rachel Gugelberger and Jeffrey Walkowiak, is about atmospheric conditions and also psychic and political weather. Storms come and go in Joy Garnett's paintings of fiery, storm-swollen skies and in Christoph Draeger's jigsaw-puzzle photograph of the aftermath of a tsunami, while the subject of John Jurayj's vivid paintings of bombed hotels in Beirut speak of a different kind of turbulence. Sara Meltzer Gallery, 525-531 West 26nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-9330, sarameltzergaller.com; closes today. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>'The Social History of Objects,' At present, in some quarters of the art world, there's a push to circle back to a pre-Conceptualist state in which well-fashioned paintings and sculptures are art, and everything else is not. So it makes sense that an against-the-grain space like Triple Candie is offering a group show entirely of ready-mades or, as the gallery puts it, ''common objects collected from friends and acquaintances.'' The range is wide: a baseball cap, a sock, a Plaza Hotel ashtray, a stone chip, each accompanied by a history. Certain items were found by their present owners; others given as hand-me-downs or gifts. A few have been attributed Proustian powers to evoke a time or place or a personality. Together they teach the old Duchamp lesson that art is an attitude, and that the mind is every bit as much a shaping organ as the hand and the eye. Triple Candie, 461 West 126th Street, Harlem, (212) 865-0783, triplecandie.org; closes Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
