<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Ice Carnival Time in the Catskills, but the Ice Isn't Cooperating</title>
    <meta content="01towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/01/nyregion/01towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1736365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Our Towns"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Livingston Manor (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDC1F3FF932A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="976" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Ice Carnival Time in the Catskills, but the Ice Isn't Cooperating</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It's Ice Carnival Time in the Catskills, but the Ice Isn't Cooperating</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Applebome</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>LIVINGSTON MANOR, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Applebome Our Towns column on unseasonably warm winter weather that causes Livingston Manor, NY, to postpone winter carnival; some speculate about global warming; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you want to be technical, there is ice for what was supposed to be the 47th Annual Livingston Manor Rotary Ice Carnival, but it's not the kind you could skate on, just a thin mushy residue at the skating rink lying under puddles of water from yesterday's intermittent drizzle.</p>
        <p>And, for the record, there's a little snow too, but it's not the kind you can build snow dinosaurs or bears out of.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 47th Annual Livingston Manor Rotary Ice Carnival has been postponed twice because it's too warm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you want to be technical, there is ice for what was supposed to be the 47th Annual Livingston Manor Rotary Ice Carnival, but it's not the kind you could skate on, just a thin mushy residue at the skating rink lying under puddles of water from yesterday's intermittent drizzle.</p>
        <p>And, for the record, there's a little snow too, but it's not the kind you can build snow dinosaurs or bears out of.</p>
        <p>Maybe, if it gets cold again, there will be a stripped-down version of the ice carnival, the biggest seasonal event in these parts. Maybe this is just an aberrant spell of unusually warm weather.</p>
        <p>But in this normally frigid corner of the Catskills, people are trying to make sense of this toothless January that on Monday brought temperatures around 50 to what's normally a winter deep freeze and yesterday was rainy and gray. ''Look at this, it's unbelievable,'' said Barry Foster as he and Thomas Babich and George Silverman, all Rotary Club members, examined the soupy ice rink after the carnival, which draws more than a thousand people every winter, was postponed two weekends in a row.</p>
        <p>''It's devastating,'' said Mr. Babich, the local Rotary Club president.</p>
        <p>''It's both,'' replied Mr. Foster. ''It's unbelievable, and it's devastating.''</p>
        <p>Rotary members decided last night that there was no way to salvage the whole carnival, which usually runs two days and over the years has included performances by skating instructors from the old Catskill hotels and imported brand-name stars like Jo Jo Starbuck, Elaine Zayak or Emily Hughes.</p>
        <p>But if the weather gets cold, they hope to freeze the rink and hold a stripped-down version sometime later this month with races for local children and free hot dogs and hot chocolate. It probably won't happen soon. This week's forecast calls for daily highs from 39 to 42 instead of an extended bout of below-freezing temperatures.</p>
        <p>It's not that things don't periodically go wrong for the ice carnival, which includes an ice carnival dance, crowning of the ice carnival king and queen, a snow sculpture contest, performances by ice skaters, horse-drawn sleigh rides and the like.</p>
        <p>It's been canceled because of too much snow. There have been years when it's been too cold for people to stay out long enough to admire the snow sculptures or watch more than a few minutes of the skating. Sometimes tuba valves and trombone slides will freeze, and the Mountain Tones Community Band will decide it's too cold to keep playing. And at least once in the past it was canceled because the weather was too warm.</p>
        <p>But with all the talk of global climate change, it's hard these days just to see weather as weather. So is this just a reprieve from the normal big chill and a break from killer heating bills, or does it signal the end of the world? Who knows?</p>
        <p>Mr. Babich, who runs Babich Auto Service, thinks there's something more than normal fluctuations going on.</p>
        <p>''We have never seen weather as warm as this,'' he said. ''We used to have more snow, and the winters used to be colder. We used to have to plow with bulldozers, not with pickup trucks. If you ask me, it has to be connected to what man's doing to the planet -- too much, too much, too fast.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silverman, 84, and Mr. Foster, 64, who have seen a lot of winters between them, agreed that winter has lost much of its sting.</p>
        <p>But Gary Siegel, who said he's serving a life sentence as chairman of the event (''I used to be Mr. Ice. Now I'm Mr. Slush.'') wasn't convinced.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the weather's any different than it used to be,'' he said. ''It probably rained when I was a kid, but what I remember was snow waist high. But I was shorter. Ask the Russians about global warming. They're having the coldest winter in memory. And, remember, it's only the end of January. I think all you can say for sure about the weather is it's consistently inconsistent.''</p>
        <p>For the microproblem -- whether they can have any kind of a carnival -- forecasters at Accuweather.com predict much colder temperatures in February, perhaps below normal (as December was), and its Web site is full of scary blue arrows and headlines like ''Get Ready, the Cold Is Coming!'' So with four or five days of below-freezing temperatures, the Livingston Manor Rotarians could make enough ice to operate the rink.</p>
        <p>And for the long run, there's talk of building a refrigerated covered rink -- something never deemed necessary in the past.</p>
        <p>As for the world ending, experts nearly all agree that some smokestack and tailpipe gases are warming the global climate. But projections of the amount and impact of future warming remain uncertain, and debate still rages over how quickly and deeply to cut the emissions.</p>
        <p>Whether that explains the puddles on the skating rink is harder to tell.</p>
        <p>''People's impressions of the old days can be a little exaggerated,'' said Stephen Fybish, a weather historian in Manhattan. ''I was checking the London Times index for the years 1785 to 1790. You have some people saying it's the coldest weather since the 1740's and others saying it's not like it was in the good old days.''</p>
        <p>Our Towns peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
