<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ROOM TO IMPROVE</title>
    <meta content="10room" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/10/garden/10room.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1781870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Room to Improve"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DC1F3FF933A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ROOM TO IMPROVE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Help! Mosquitoes Are Sending My Weekend Guests Fleeing Back to Manhattan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mitchell Owens</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. Help! Mosquitoes are sending my weekend guests fleeing back to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A. Put down that can of Off! and pay close attention, because August is the peak season for finding mosquitoes infected with West Nile virus, according to health officials in the New York region. Short of hermetically sealing your house and basking in the impersonal comfort of central air-conditioning, or sequestering yourself and your guests inside a screened porch, you are going to have to put up with the critters.</p>
        <p>There are a few solutions, of sorts. My family and I recently visited a friend in Bedford, N.Y., and managed to sit on her lawn, lounge around her pool and spend time on her patio for an entire weekend without suffering a single bite. Think about it: that was 48 hours of my partner, our daughter and me not slapping our faces, legs, arms or necks, or fleeing to the safety of the house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A. Put down that can of Off! and pay close attention, because August is the peak season for finding mosquitoes infected with West Nile virus, according to health officials in the New York region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. Help! Mosquitoes are sending my weekend guests fleeing back to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A. Put down that can of Off! and pay close attention, because August is the peak season for finding mosquitoes infected with West Nile virus, according to health officials in the New York region. Short of hermetically sealing your house and basking in the impersonal comfort of central air-conditioning, or sequestering yourself and your guests inside a screened porch, you are going to have to put up with the critters.</p>
        <p>There are a few solutions, of sorts. My family and I recently visited a friend in Bedford, N.Y., and managed to sit on her lawn, lounge around her pool and spend time on her patio for an entire weekend without suffering a single bite. Think about it: that was 48 hours of my partner, our daughter and me not slapping our faces, legs, arms or necks, or fleeing to the safety of the house.</p>
        <p>What was our hostess's secret? She had purchased a cordless mosquito trap by Mosquito Magnet.</p>
        <p>Based on its success that weekend, I ordered one myself.</p>
        <p>The Mosquito Magnet resembles an outboard motor perched on a wheeled display stand like a piece of industrial art. It uses a propane tank that dispenses carbon dioxide mixed with an attractant. This invisible cloud seduces mosquitoes and other flying varmints into a vacuum nozzle. They are then sucked into the machine, where they eventually die.</p>
        <p>Made by American Biophysics, the Mosquito Magnet is sold at home improvement and garden shops across the country and is available in models suited to residential and commercial use. Residential models range in price from $199 for a factory-reconditioned Defender that the company says will eradicate mosquitoes over a half-acre to $853 for a Liberty Plus cordless model that takes care of one acre and comes with a variety of attachments, which also are available separately.</p>
        <p>Information is at mosquitomagnet.com or (877) 699-8727.</p>
        <p>Somewhat lower-tech in the insect-avoidance category -- but infinitely prettier -- is a colorful polyester mosquito net hung from a hook attached to the ceiling and draped over your bed. I picked up several such nets a few years ago at Klamboe, a company in Amsterdam, which has some of the best-looking ones around. Given all the canals in the Netherlands, it should come as no surprise that the Dutch are plagued with mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Klamboe's nets come in a multitude of colors and several styles; they also come with or without decorative canopies that evoke ''Arabian Nights.''</p>
        <p>Prices range from about $37 for a tentlike model to $97 for a king-size circular mosquito net. Information is at www.klamboe.com or 011-31-20-6206358.</p>
        <p>Room to Improve</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
