<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Like Others Considering a Presidential Bid, Pataki Unveils a National Energy Plan</title>
    <meta content="08pataki" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/08/nyregion/08pataki.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1781542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D81E3FF93BA3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Like Others Considering a Presidential Bid, Pataki Unveils a National Energy Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Just Like Others Considering a Presidential Bid, Pataki Unveils a National Energy Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Gov George E Pataki lays out energy plan that calls for cutting American consumption of oil by one-fourth of current levels over next 10 years during speech in Washington, DC; Pataki proposal is seen as rite of presidential candidacy, though he has not publicly discussed any presidential ambitions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, stopping here Monday between trips to New Hampshire and Iowa, laid out an energy plan that called for cutting American consumption of oil by one-fourth of current levels over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>Emphasizing policies that set him apart from many of his fellow Republicans, Mr. Pataki proposed incentives for companies to produce alternatives to gasoline and diesel, to market the substitute fuels, and to build cars capable of burning them. In a half-hour speech, he called for a national campaign to reduce dependence on foreign oil, an effort that he compared to World War II and the American Revolution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emphasizing policies that set him apart from many of his fellow Republicans, Gov. George E. Pataki of New York proposed incentives for companies to produce alternatives to gasoline and diesel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, stopping here Monday between trips to New Hampshire and Iowa, laid out an energy plan that called for cutting American consumption of oil by one-fourth of current levels over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>Emphasizing policies that set him apart from many of his fellow Republicans, Mr. Pataki proposed incentives for companies to produce alternatives to gasoline and diesel, to market the substitute fuels, and to build cars capable of burning them. In a half-hour speech, he called for a national campaign to reduce dependence on foreign oil, an effort that he compared to World War II and the American Revolution.</p>
        <p>''One of America's defining characteristics, as a people and as a nation, is our knack for accepting and overcoming great challenges,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The challenge now, he said, is that much of the imported oil comes from hostile regimes. He cited Iran and said that each time the price went up $5 a barrel, that provided ''$85 million more a day, that they can use to advance their nuclear program or buy more Katyusha rockets for Hezbollah.''</p>
        <p>(In fact, Mr. Pataki's office later acknowledged that the number is closer to $85 million a week.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has not publicly discussed any presidential ambitions, and said he was looking forward to a trip to Iowa in the near future to help campaign for Republicans there. But proposing an energy policy is becoming as much a rite of a presidential candidacy as stumping in Iowa, which traditionally holds the first caucus to choose delegates to the national nominating conventions, and his call for relying on corn-based fuels like ethanol is likely to resonate in that state.</p>
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, who also has not said if she wants to run in 2008, made an energy speech in May in the same place, the National Press Club. She called for cutting imports in half by 2025.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki proposed relying more on ethanol from corn, which is already in the marketplace, and ethanol from cellulose, which is not, and biodiesel, which is made from vegetable oil. He said the government should not pick the technology, but only offer companies financial incentives to work on the problem. For example, he said, companies constructing plants that make fuel from vegetable matter should be able to expense their capital investments.</p>
        <p>He said governments should lead the way, as New York has done, by cutting their consumption, especially of petroleum. And he noted that last week he signed a bill that prohibits oil companies from preventing gas stations they supply from selling alternative fuels.</p>
        <p>New cars could be built with the ability to burn gasoline or ethanol at a cost that was ''about the same price they would pay to buy floor mats,'' he said. Building such cars and running them on biofuels whenever possible would wean the country from ''the petroleum that is enriching our enemies and polluting our air,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The nation is spending $1 billion a day on oil imports, money that should be spent domestically, he said. ''How much longer must we, the world's greatest nation, be made to hold our breath whenever oil ministers meet in some exotic foreign locale?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Asked why President Bush had not set up so ambitious a policy, Mr. Pataki said that the Bush administration had made major progress. In fact, Mr. Pataki's plan shares many elements with a variety of proposals made by elected officials since gasoline hit $3 a gallon.</p>
        <p>On a particularly contentious oil issue, whether drilling should be allowed in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, he said that drilling in American territory should be expanded but that he could not rule anything in or out. He also said he did not favor increasing the federal gasoline tax, a step that economists say would encourage people to use less gasoline.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki said he was studying whether carbon dioxide, a global warming gas emitted by power plants, could be captured and permanently stored underground, perhaps in old oil fields where it would force more oil to the surface. He added that New York, with his support, was one of seven Northeastern states that signed an agreement last December that seeks to limit carbon dioxide output from power plants.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
