<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of This World</title>
    <meta content="2160--well--tasmania.rev--" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Travel Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="123" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/19/travel/tmagazine/19tasmania.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tasmania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frey, Darcy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Tasmania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tasmania (Australia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Australia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DB163EF93AA25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="3854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of This World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tasmania Is Out of This World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Darcy Frey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frey, Darcy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Darcy Frey travel article on Tasmania; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tasmania, said to be the world's most mountainous island and perhaps also its rainiest, is a wind-lashed, wave-carved atoll, the Southern Hemisphere's last terrestrial gasp before it sinks into the Southern Ocean. In the southwest corner of this dense, drenched island lies Tasmania's wildest region: hundreds of miles of steep dolerite cliffs, cool dripping rain forest and glacial valleys virtually untouched since the last ice age. The highest peak in this ancient wilderness is a denuded, boulder-strewn uplift called Mount Anne, where not far below the summit a small stone hut offers shelter for hikers caught in the sudden, violent storms that rake this open ridge and give Tasmania's southwest its unforgettable sobriquet: ''Hell without the fire.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Woolly wombats, 3,000-year-old pines and a river called Styx: Tasmania is a mythical place, wondrous and weird.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tasmania, said to be the world's most mountainous island and perhaps also its rainiest, is a wind-lashed, wave-carved atoll, the Southern Hemisphere's last terrestrial gasp before it sinks into the Southern Ocean. In the southwest corner of this dense, drenched island lies Tasmania's wildest region: hundreds of miles of steep dolerite cliffs, cool dripping rain forest and glacial valleys virtually untouched since the last ice age. The highest peak in this ancient wilderness is a denuded, boulder-strewn uplift called Mount Anne, where not far below the summit a small stone hut offers shelter for hikers caught in the sudden, violent storms that rake this open ridge and give Tasmania's southwest its unforgettable sobriquet: ''Hell without the fire.''</p>
        <p>Weather conditions were characteristic when I came upon the hut in August, at the tail end of the Tasmanian winter. I had plans to reach Mount Anne's summit -- plans that were quickly reappraised when, as I passed the hut, the trail rose onto a steep ridge, the rain swept in horizontally and gauzy, upwelling clouds converged, causing the small rock cairns that marked the way to dreamily disappear. I backtracked to the empty hut, but even at 3 in the afternoon, the interior of that pelted, trembling shelter was so dark it took several hours before I noticed an old tin box, pried out the logbook inside and climbed the ladder to the sleeping loft with my headlamp:</p>
        <p>Arrived last night cold, wet and pleased to see the hut. Too cold for us Brits -- aborting our plans for the summit in favour of the Derwent Bridge Pub!</p>
        <p>Took us five hours to get here struggling through the snow. Unfortunately, didn't make the summit -- 40 knot winds!</p>
        <p>Which planet are we on? The sky is nothing but mist, the ground is root-riddled and muddy and our ship is buried in a swamp.</p>
        <p>They were like messages in a bottle tossed out by castaways at sea, though where exactly did that leave me? Outside, the rain had turned to hail; up in the loft, it sounded like rocks from the summit were landing on the eaves. I checked the dates in the book: just four entries in the last four months, and no one on that mountain since the beginning of July.</p>
        <p>Now, where again is Tasmania? Some African nation that's shucked off its colonial name? One of Captain Cook's stopovers during his Polynesian tour? It's a question even Tasmanians ask themselves, having seen their island-state 150 miles off the southeast coast of Australia sometimes left off the map. ''We were an offshore island off the shore of an offshore continent, victims of a twofold alienation,'' wrote Peter Conrad in his memoir of a Tasmanian childhood. ''Australia was chosen for settlement because it was so remote, and because it could scarcely sustain life. It served as a place of ultimate banishment and estrangement. Yet beneath its south-eastern tip was an even remoter version of itself, a site of internal exile.''</p>
        <p>For much of its history, Tasmania -- or Van Diemen's Land, as it was called until 1856 -- was known, if it was known at all, for its brutality. Throughout the first half of the 19th century, it was the site of Australia's most lethal penal colony. It also witnessed one of the world's most efficient genocides: the European settlers' slaughter of the island's Aboriginal population. As hunters drove the island's most distinguished megafauna, the thylacine (or Tasmanian tiger), to extinction; as the hydroelectric industry dammed rivers and drowned mountains; and as timber companies left valleys looking like the hide of some wild animal with its fur ripped away, Tasmania limped through much of the 20th century as, in Conrad's words, ''Australia's shame and embarrassment.''</p>
        <p>Now that far-flung isolation has become an exploitable natural resource of its own, however, Tasmania -- with a latitude more southerly than that of the Cape of Good Hope and a waterfront capital facing Antarctica -- is back on the map. ''Swap the remote for the remote,'' urges the state's official tourism Web site, while offering images of seemingly endless alpine ranges, one of the world's last temperate rain forests, ancient stands of old-growth eucalyptus and golden buttongrass moorlands reminiscent of Scotland. To complement the island's astonishing diversity of habitats, Tasmanians have lately created a modern infrastructure -- mostly in and around the capital, Hobart -- of hotels, restaurants, cinemas and cafes that has helped to reverse decades-old patterns of emigration, to attract young people to the island and even to spur a small real estate boom, especially among second-home buyers from the mainland.</p>
        <p>Civic pride around Tasmania (or ''Tassie,'' as everyone calls it) seems rivaled only by the cheerful informality of its citizens. ''No worries, mate!'' is the conclusion to every transaction, and even the street signs are solicitous: ''15 more meters to the public restroom!'' Park rangers who dispense hours of arcane trail advice, a hotel proprietor who offers to wash her guests' filthy clothes, a fellow hiker who lends his watch so you won't get caught on the trail after dark, a pharmacist who leads you into her back room for a confidential chat about your bowels -- everyone wants to lend a hand, everyone wants you to love Tassie just as much as they do. Still, much of the state's charm lies in its disorienting contradictions, the still-exposed seams of transition between centuries of isolation and a decade of ''rediscovery.'' Indeed, just beneath Tasmania's amiable surface lies a furious debate over the island's future, particularly of its fierce but fragile environment. In a way, Tasmanians are still drawing the charts for themselves, 350 years after the Dutch navigator Abel Tasman, the first European to see the island, dropped anchor off this soaked jungle of rock.</p>
        <p>Most contemporary visitors to Tasmania set their rudders by heading directly to Hobart, and if you arrive in the Antipodes as I did, having flown for 21 hours to find that summer is winter, day is night, traffic keeps to the wrong side of the road and the sun, crossing the northern sky, casts perplexing shadows to the south side of objects, there's something soothingly familiar about this tidy Anglophilic city, with its rows of Georgian sandstone buildings and town squares with pedestaled statues of British luminaries gazing stonily out to sea. On top of this colonial base (Hobart is Australia's second-oldest city), Tasmanians have lately added a layer of Soho and South Kensington: angular, track-lighted establishments like the Henry Jones Art Hotel in a lovingly restored jam factory and dozens of waterfront restaurants serving fresh-harvested fish, local produce and Tasmanian pinot noirs.</p>
        <p>But Hobart, though it seems so at first, isn't some fashionable gastropub-lined market town in the English Midlands. It sits at the base of brooding Mount Wellington, which itself sits at the southernmost reach of the Tasmanian highlands -- a topographical reality that may remain out of sight but not out of mind when the so-called katabatic winds of the Roaring 40's, those notorious currents of air that circle the globe at this latitude, come screaming down from the hills, emptying the streets and upsetting the clanking white masts in the harbor. At those moments, Hobart seems like the lonely outpost it is. One evening I was down by Constitution Dock, eating at one of the moored barges that serve as takeaway seafood stalls, when I happened to look out the window and saw five dolphins breaking the water's surface. Apparently confused by their harbored confinement, they slalomed about the barges, pinwheeling in synchronicity, until they found an opening and headed out to sea, nothing now between them and the bottom of the world.</p>
        <p>Feeling confined myself and eager to hit the trail, I headed toward the Freycinet Peninsula on Tasmania's east coast, where temperatures were said to be mildest and the rainfall (relatively) light. The Freycinet, a 20-mile-long peninsula jutting into the Tasman Sea, is home to Tasmania's most famous vista, the aptly named Wineglass Bay, with its goblet-shaped beach and shimmering, azure waters bound by high, pink granite outcrops known as the Hazards. Visitors who arrive at the Freycinet having read about Wineglass in their guidebooks are often surprised to find no road access to the bay; it requires a vigorous three-hour return hike up and over the Hazards. Everything beyond Wineglass Bay exceeds the reach of even a day hike. If you hope to explore the Freycinet's outermost precincts, you must carry tent, food, even water in the event that the creeks are dry.</p>
        <p>The creeks were dry when I was there, but luckily so were the skies. By day, I hiked along the cliffs and coastal heaths, passing through silent stands of marble-barked eucalyptus trees and listening to the gristly wing-flap of black cockatoos as they wheeled from branch to branch. And from every break in the forest, I watched the humpbacked Hazards under changing light: glowing pink and red in sunshine, purple and gray at dusk. At night I set up camp along the beach, then lay on rocks just above the tide to watch the circumpolar constellations of the southern sky. Tasmania's fauna come out at night as well -- Bennet's wallabies, wombats, ring-tailed possums -- their red hungry eyes lighting up in the beam of my headlamp. Pesky and dexterous as they are (one possum can unfasten Velcro, two can flip a backpack), I communed with the gentle wallabies and one particular possum, a wounded, one-eyed thing limping around my tent on three legs. So it was poignant to recross the isthmus the next morning, back to ''rediscovered'' Tasmania, where one restaurant served as its ''slow-cooked dish of the day'' braised wallaby, and another offered what may turn out to be the official state dish: possum in pinot noir.</p>
        <p>Not all Tasmanians care for such refinement, of course. Back in Hobart, I was having breakfast one morning in my hotel when I pulled out a map of the Overland Track, Tasmania's most renowned multiday trek. In no time, the other guests -- all of them Tasmanian -- had abandoned their corn flakes and were leaning over me to point out sights of beauty and horror, danger and depravity:</p>
        <p>''I knew a father and daughter who tried the Overland this time of year. Up on Cradle Mountain, trail was icy, daughter stepped back to get a picture and went right over the edge!''</p>
        <p>''Did you hear about the young woman who went up to the Labyrinth? Twenty years old. Goes for a day hike. Never heard from again!''</p>
        <p>The bespectacled pharmacist from Devonport, the well-fed businessman from Launceston -- they didn't look like bushwalkers. But they'd all done the Overland, and just about every other major hike on the island, and were exercising their prerogative to scare the bejesus out of the flat-voweled American with their backcountry encounters.</p>
        <p>''I did the Overland once -- went right up to my chest in mud!''</p>
        <p>''Yeah, it rains seven out of ten days up there. You do the math.''</p>
        <p>The Overland Track, which traverses the Tasmanian highlands from Cradle Mountain in the north to Lake St. Clair in the south, takes between five and seven days. With not that much time to spare, I went in from the south, walking first through the dark, dense rain forest of the Cephissus Valley: towering, moss-covered eucalyptus and the dripping, pineapple-like fronds of the Pandani, cool moist air and needles of sunlight trying to reach all that fallen, decaying undergrowth. Tasmania was once part of the ancient supercontinent of Gondwana; when Australia, India, Antarctica, Africa and South America went their separate ways, some species survived only in Tasmania. In that rain forest along the Cephissus River, you could see them -- King Billy pine, pencil- and celery-top pine -- making a last stand.</p>
        <p>The next day I hiked up to the Labyrinth, a high alpine plateau of rocky outcroppings, glacial lakes and dizzying views to all horizons. It was somewhere in that remote, mazelike region that a 20-year-old woman had wandered off in December 2000, never to be heard from again. ''Do not proceed further unless at least 2 people in your party are competent at navigation with a map and compass,'' a sign warned. ''There are extensive areas of remote country adjacent to the Labyrinth where finding a lost walker would be like looking for a needle in a haystack.'' With a map scaled too large for backcountry route finding, I wouldn't have ventured farther myself if I hadn't met up with four strapping members of the Sydney Bushwalkers Club who -- ''no worries, mate!'' -- invited me along.</p>
        <p>All afternoon, we hiked across the Labyrinth's snow gums and boggy flats, scrambling from tarn to hill to take in the surrounding, classically named peaks (the Acropolis, the Parthenon) and the heart-stopping long-distance views to the west, where range after range reached to the vanishing point. This was the heart of the Tasmanian highlands -- and in winter, too. But when we descended back to the small hut, the place was teeming. At least 15 more bushwalkers had made it down the Overland Track and into the Cephissus Valley, all peeling off wet clothes, lining boots by the coal stove and cooking up freeze-dried delights on camp stoves on the long table inside. The place was aromatic with sweat, wet wool and kerosene.</p>
        <p>As Australia's most famous track, the Overland now draws upward of 9,000 bushwalkers a year.</p>
        <p>To protect both them and the environment, Tasmania's Parks Department keeps the trail beautifully maintained: there are boardwalks over muddy sections, suspension bridges over creeks, even mesh-covered stairs. In addition to sleeping bunks, tables and coal heaters, all nine huts along the track have rainwater tanks and composting outhouses. To avoid overcrowding, the Parks Department has been forced in recent years to institute new rules; from November to April, walkers must reserve a departure date, pay a $100 fee and trek in the same direction (north to south) to avoid degrading the trail. The numbers have the rangers worried. ''The creek water there used to be good, but so many people walk the track that we can no longer guarantee the quality of the water,'' one said to me. ''The problem is, the Overland is just getting loved to death,'' said another. That night in the hut, I watched one of the Sydney giants trying to insert himself among the mummified bodies already crowding the double-decker bunks. I took another whiff inside the hut and found a nice spot for my tent in the woods nearby.</p>
        <p>In 1981, Tasmania was nominated to become a Unesco World Heritage Area. In order to share that rarefied appellation with places like Angkor Wat, Easter Island and the Great Wall of China, an area must satisfy at least one of 10 criteria, ranging from natural beauty to fascinating human or cultural history. The Tasmania World Heritage Area, which includes four contiguous national parks -- Cradle Mountain-Lake St. Clair, Franklin-Gordon Wild Rivers, Walls of Jerusalem and the Southwest -- satisfied a record seven categories. No larger than Ireland, Tasmania nevertheless possesses one of the planet's last great temperate wildernesses, and with 19 national parks, almost 40 percent of it is in some way protected.</p>
        <p>This did not happen without a fight. Around the time Tasmania was nominated for World Heritage status, the Hydro-Electric Commission, the state body that had already built power stations and pipelines on the Central Plateau and flooded Lake Pedder in the southwest, moved to dam the lower Franklin and Gordon Rivers, a spectacular white-water area of rapids tearing through deep gorges. An extraordinary set of events ensued.</p>
        <p>In order to block the dams, the Tasmanian Wilderness Society proposed protecting the riverine lands within a national park that would be included in the World Heritage area. Though the federal government in Canberra supported the Wilderness Society's proposal, Tasmania's pro-development premier, Robin Grey, revoked parts of the Franklin-Gordon Wild Rivers National Park to enable dam construction, and the Hydro-Electric Commission moved forward with its plans.</p>
        <p>The issue then went to the public. When Tasmania's state government put forth a referendum asking voters to choose between two different dam schemes, and announced that writing ''no dams'' on ballots would render them invalid, almost half of the voters did just that. A year later, in federal elections, 41 percent of Australian voters wrote ''no dams'' on their ballots as well.</p>
        <p>On the day the Wild Rivers National Park was inscribed as a World Heritage Area and the United Nations went so far as to express its concern over the effects of dam construction, Hydro-Electric's heavy equipment moved into the Franklin-Gordon area. As construction began, protesters set off from nearby Strahan to form what was called the ''Franklin River Blockade,'' during which 1,400 of them were arrested, many thrown in jail. Only when the Franklin River dam became the major issue of the 1983 federal election and the reigning prime minister was tossed out did the government fully implement the Franklin and Gordon Rivers' World Heritage status and halt dam construction. It was the flooding of Lake Pedder, and battles like this, that prompted Tasmanians to form the world's first Green Party.</p>
        <p>One might think that the Franklin River imbroglio and the state's new World Heritage status would have charted a definitive course for Tasmania's ship of state. But the debate over development merely shifted to a new region -- that vast area of jagged mountains, glaciated valleys and nearly impenetrable jungle known as the southwest. Covering almost a quarter of Tasmania, this ancient region had avoided much human intervention, mainly because, for most of the island's human history, it was considered uninhabitable. When the ice sheets retreated 11,500 years ago and a warming climate spread forest across these mountains, the Aboriginal peoples who had previously hunted the southwest's grasslands retreated to the coast. When Lt. Matthew Flinders circumnavigated Tasmania in 1798, he took one look at the southwest and wrote: ''The mountains are the most stupendous works of nature I have ever beheld, and at the same time the most dismal that can be imagined. The eye ranges over these peaks and variously formed lumps of adamantine rock with astonishment and horror.''</p>
        <p>Today, of course, human engineering has made almost no landscape uninhabitable. Though large parts of the southwest lie within a national park, one sealed road and several dirt logging spurs now penetrate this feral land, used mostly by the 18-wheel trucks that come shuddering out of the mountains with loads of 10-ton logs. Lake Pedder, once the largest natural glacial outwash lake in the world (until the Hydro-Electric Commission inundated it), is now an artificial catchment holding 27 times the volume of water in Sydney Harbor. Lately, logging interests have been moving in force into the southwest, with its towering swamp gums and its 3,000-year-old Huon pines, particularly the area carved out by the Styx River, which is known as the ''Valley of the Giants'' for its 300-foot white-trunked eucalyptus, the tallest trees in the Southern Hemisphere and among the highest-standing hardwoods in the world.</p>
        <p>Until now, Tasmania has survived as one of the world's last wild places because of an unusual confluence of circumstances: its isolated geography and forbidding climate; an activist citizenry; an economy that gives it the luxury of picking and choosing among different forms of development; a tourist trade that values the environment; even its bloody history, which has led some Tasmanians to consider the preservation of its wilderness a matter of redemption. Nonetheless, for better or worse, Tasmania is back on the map, and ''rediscovery,'' like other palpitations of the heart, is in the eye of the beholder.</p>
        <p>On the trail up to the Mount Anne hut that stormy August day, I'd seen one possible vision of Tasmania -- the sheer, snow-covered rock face of Mount Anne itself moving in and out of clouds, performing a kind of Dance of the Seven Veils -- a reminder that this place still has the power to reveal itself only on its own terms.</p>
        <p>The following morning, when I climbed down from the frozen loft and shook the blood back into my toes, I saw another: down in the valley, in the diminishing mists, was the image of Lake Pedder, the Hydro-Electric Commission's artificial impoundment, which stretched to the horizon like an inland sea; inundated, the surrounding mountains had been reduced to hills, mere periscopes peering above the surface of the ''lake.''</p>
        <p>I recorded a few lines of my own in the logbook and stowed it in the tin container for the next castaway, then began the long return hike. All the way down, I could see them both: the ancient, stony mountain and the swampy, man-made lake, facing off across the valley.</p>
        <p>Essentials Tasmania</p>
        <p>BEFORE YOU GO Visas are required to visit Australia; applications can be submitted at www.immi.gov.au. Tasmania Tourism operates an excellent Web site that is an indispensable resource for planning a trip (www.discovertasmania.com.au).</p>
        <p>GETTING AROUND For both hikers and those who want to take it easy, a car is essential; Hertz, Avis and Thrifty all have rental offices on the island. Roads are generally good.</p>
        <p>HOTELS Avalon Coastal Retreat A stunning new waterfront rental property that sleeps up to six, with views of the Freycinet Peninsula. 011-61-13-0036-1136; www.avaloncoastal retreat.com.au; $415 a night. Bay of Fires Lodge One of the trendsetters in the ''new'' Tasmania, this sleek, luxe wilderness lodge on the island's northeast corner is reached as part of a four-day guided trek. The same company also operates six-day guided hikes (with overnights in private huts) in Cradle Mountain-Lake St. Clair National Park. 011-61-3-6391-9339; www.bayoffires.com.au; treks from $1,320. Cradle Mountain Lodge Full-service resort (fishing, canoeing, biking, guided hikes) on the edge of the Cradle Mountain-Lake St. Clair National Park. 011-61-2-8296-8010; www.cradlemountainlodge.com.au; doubles from $97. Edge of the Bay Resort Rustic-styled cottages, streamlined waterside suites and a fantastic restaurant on Coles Bay facing the Hazards. 011-61-3-6257-0102; www.edgeofthebay.com.au; doubles from $154. Henry Jones Art Hotel Stylish art-filled hotel (with a very good restaurant) on the Hobart waterfront. 25 Hunter Street; 011-61-3-6210-7700; www.thehenryjones.com; doubles from $220. Islington Hotel Small new boutique property -- a mix of period and modern styles -- with lovely gardens and views, minutes from Hobart's city center. 321 Davey Street; 011-61-3-6220-2123; www.islingtonhotel.com; doubles from $302.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS Outside the larger cities like Hobart, you'll generally eat in your hotel. In Hobart, restaurants to try include Gondwana, for creative cuisine using local produce (Corner Hampden Road and Francis Street; 011-61-3-6224-9900; entrees $16 to $26), and, at the Elizabeth Street Pier, T42X, for modern Australian dishes and a great wine list (011-61-3-6224-7742; entrees $8 to $13), and the local favorite Mures, for the freshest seafood (011-61-3-6231-1999; entrees $16 to $37).</p>
        <p>Sights And Activities Upon arrival, your first stop should be Service Tasmania in Hobart (134 Macquarie Street; 011-61-1300-13-55-13), where you can pick up detailed maps and guides to the island. Upstairs in the same building is an office of the Parks Department, which is extremely helpful in planning visits to any of the national parks. Hikers should be sure to visit the Web site of Australia's premier trekker, John Chapman (www.john.chapman.name), which provides detailed advice on hiking the island; you can also purchase his guidebooks online.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
