<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Pump or Not to Pump</title>
    <meta content="30boyle" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/30/opinion/30boyle.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1758269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyle, T C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Boyle, T Coraghessan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3D9103FF933A05757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Pump or Not to Pump</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Pump or Not to Pump</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By T. C. Boyle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boyle, T Coraghessan; Boyle, T C</byline>
      <dateline>Santa Barbara, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Author T C Boyle Op-Ed article holds that Californians would like to do their bit for environment and also drive less because of out-of-control gas prices, but they need their cars to commute to work; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST Sunday morning I took the Pacific Surfliner down the coast from Santa Barbara to San Diego, so as to be present for a book-signing early Monday. The trip, which included a half-hour layover at Union Station in Los Angeles, lasted approximately six hours, or about the time it would have taken to drive.</p>
        <p>If I'd opted to go by air, I might have shaved two or more hours off that total, driving 11 miles to our local airport and switching planes in Los Angeles, but that option never crossed my mind (flight delays, the cattle car, the indignities of the search and the Torquemadaean contortions of the ever-declining ratio of leg bone to seat-space). Nor did I consider driving. Not only would the drive have required two full tanks of gas costing approximately $80, but there was also the wear-and-tear on the mechanism to consider, not to mention on the driver himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In California, hearts and carburetors are at odds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST Sunday morning I took the Pacific Surfliner down the coast from Santa Barbara to San Diego, so as to be present for a book-signing early Monday. The trip, which included a half-hour layover at Union Station in Los Angeles, lasted approximately six hours, or about the time it would have taken to drive.</p>
        <p>If I'd opted to go by air, I might have shaved two or more hours off that total, driving 11 miles to our local airport and switching planes in Los Angeles, but that option never crossed my mind (flight delays, the cattle car, the indignities of the search and the Torquemadaean contortions of the ever-declining ratio of leg bone to seat-space). Nor did I consider driving. Not only would the drive have required two full tanks of gas costing approximately $80, but there was also the wear-and-tear on the mechanism to consider, not to mention on the driver himself.</p>
        <p>So the train it was. And the train was full, nearly every seat taken. The buzz, circulated by the conductor and humming freely from one seat to another, was that ever-escalating gas prices had resulted in an increased ridership along this particular line. This seemed perfectly reasonable to me -- until the return trip, when we pulled into Union Station at 7 p.m., just when you'd think commuters would be clamoring to head up the coast, and nobody got on. Five minutes later we were riding the gentle arc of the tracks alongside the Los Angeles River, admiring the titanic graffiti lining the walls of its concrete basin, six or seven mostly empty cars rattling on behind us.</p>
        <p>That's the conundrum out here in the land of the automobile. We'd all like to do our bit for the environment -- and out-of-control gas prices awaken in us a fervent desire to save at the pump through the simple expedient of driving less -- but while a leisurely Sunday meander down the coast aboard Amtrak is just fine, when Monday comes, we need our cars.</p>
        <p>We need to be first in line at the pump (remember the gas lines of the late 70's, cars lined up a hundred deep at 5 a.m., awaiting the arrival of the sad, slow-shuffling proprietor?), first off the freeway exit, lead car in the power lane and everybody look out! In the paper the other day, there was a letter from a concerned consumer suggesting that we go back to the draconian 55-mile-per-hour speed limit to conserve each precious pint, quart and gallon. What a dreamer.</p>
        <p>Right now we are averaging about 80 on the Ventura Freeway, with the eternally harassed and lead-footed up to 90 and better. No matter the cost of gas, we need to get to work, and each minute shaved off the commute is a minute -- golden and fat and glowing -- added to our real lives, the lives that begin after work, at home, in the bars and restaurants, with the children and the bills and the dog.</p>
        <p>I plead guilty to the above, as much a schizophrenic about the rift between environmental consciousness and the need, right and consuming passion for the automobile as any of my fellow Californians. My commute to the University of Southern California is an unholy 200 miles round-trip and it consumes time -- four and a half hours -- and fuel. I drive a powerful sports car because of the burning need to subdue and outrace all those other commuters, and though I make that trip only 39 days a year, still, I make it alone and I make it as expeditiously as I can, with little thought for what it is costing, on every level. (And yes, I've found myself buying gas half a tank at a time, fondly hoping that when I pull up to the next pump, prices will have plummeted to where they should be, or where we want them to be.)</p>
        <p>Gasoline prices in Santa Barbara have always been among the highest in the nation (and this has nothing to do, we are assured by the oil companies, with the protests over the 1969 oil spill from the rigs in the channel), but lately they seem punitive. The cheapest no-name gas at the four-pump station tucked under the freeway two blocks from the homeless shelter was recently going for $3.15 per gallon of regular. And who was willing to pay that price? I was. Certainly. And so was everyone else who has his personal needs and wants and to whom the conflagration in the Middle East is as remote as the refiners and distributors themselves.</p>
        <p>But there's another station here in town, in our toniest enclave, no more than three miles from the (formerly) cheap one. Here you don't get out of your car. Here you sit like a potentate behind the smoked windscreen of your sleek and gleaming vehicle while the attendant in his crisp blue shirt ministers to your needs because you don't want to dirty your hands or breathe the fumes or risk damage to your skin under the sun made all the fiercer by the depletion of the ozone layer. One morning last week, regular was going for $3.75, high-test for $3.96. I know, because I drove up there to find out.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor T. C. Boyle is the author of ''Tooth and Claw'' and the forthcoming ''Talk Talk.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">T. C. Boyle is the author of ''Tooth and Claw'' and the forthcoming ''Talk Talk.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
