<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Settling In, Glass In Hand, To Read Of Wine</title>
    <meta content="06pour" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/06/dining/06pour.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1809788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE POUR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3DE1631F935A35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Settling In, Glass In Hand, To Read Of Wine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Settling in, Glass in Hand, to Read of Wine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>USED to be you could tell the time of year in New York by the weather, but you can't always count on that anymore. This week's chill was preceded by a spell of humid muck that required other means for gauging the season. Like the Christmas trees on the streets, despite the salesmen in shorts. And, for me at least, the wine books that engulf my desk before the holidays.</p>
        <p>Not that I mind. Most people who love wine love reading about wine, the regions where it is made and the people who make it. Among this year's crop, here are six volumes that I found especially noteworthy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among this year’s crop of wine books, here are six volumes that are especially noteworthy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>USED to be you could tell the time of year in New York by the weather, but you can't always count on that anymore. This week's chill was preceded by a spell of humid muck that required other means for gauging the season. Like the Christmas trees on the streets, despite the salesmen in shorts. And, for me at least, the wine books that engulf my desk before the holidays.</p>
        <p>Not that I mind. Most people who love wine love reading about wine, the regions where it is made and the people who make it. Among this year's crop, here are six volumes that I found especially noteworthy.</p>
        <p>The third edition of The Oxford Companion to Wine (Oxford University Press, $65), edited by Jancis Robinson, is the one essential book for any wine-lover. The wine world has evolved since the last edition in 1999, and this encyclopedic work keeps pace with new information on issues like climate change, biodynamic viticulture and globalization, and emerging wine regions like Canada and eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robinson harnessed the talents of a battalion of contributors, which makes for expert perspectives but uneven writing, from lyrical to tongue-twistingly scientific. Nonetheless, the book is a necessity for those in the wine business, and it offers highly pleasurable browsing for anybody who is remotely curious about why wine is so compelling.</p>
        <p>With their emphasis on tasting notes and vintages, shopping guides can be hard slogging, but three new ones offer absorbing reading. Foremost among them is The Wines of France: The Essential Guide for Savvy Shoppers  (Ten Speed Press, $19.95) by Jacqueline Friedrich, whose last book, ''The Wine and Food Guide to the Loire,'' published in 1996, cries out for a new edition. In this book she embraces France region by region, offering opinionated reviews of producers and concise demystifications of the French nomenclature that bedevils American consumers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Friedrich does not try to be complete, but she clearly understands the trends that are reshaping the French wine industry. She shows a marked preference for what she calls hypernatural wines, those made with the least intervention possible, yet she is sympathetic to styles that would seem to be diametrically opposite, like the plush, oaky garagiste wines of St.-Émilion.</p>
        <p>Matt Kramer, the provocative Wine Spectator columnist, turns his attention to Italy in Making Sense of Italian Wine: Discovering Italy's Greatest Wines and Best Values (Running Press, $24.95). In previous volumes Mr. Kramer investigated in great detail the many facets of terroir in Burgundy and in California. In a departure, this book is a primer, intended for those only beginning to come under the spell of vino Italiano, who don't know their Barolos from their brunellos.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kramer can present even the most familiar thought in a stimulating guise. His brief essays on Italian wine culture are well grounded in history, while his critiques of styles and producers are clear and opinionated. Two quibbles: there are too many typos, and Mr. Kramer gives surprisingly short shrift to brunello di Montalcino. Given its importance in the marketplace, he should have explained his reasoning.</p>
        <p>Stephen Tanzer is the editor and publisher of International Wine Cellar, a newsletter. His controlled prose is overshadowed by that of the more flamboyant Robert M. Parker Jr.'s Wine Advocate. Sometimes it's hard to tell where Mr. Tanzer's tastes lie, as he conscientiously considers each wine. But in his new book, The WineAccess Buyer's Guide: The World's Best Wines and Where to Find Them (Sterling Publishing, $14.95), he loosens up and offers more personal evaluations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tanzer visits wine regions around the world and offers quick assessments of the producers he considers to be the best, without confining himself to hard-to-find cult winemakers. It is compact, concise and clear, and it couldn't be more useful.</p>
        <p>Much has already been written about Jay McInerney's book  A Hedonist in the Cellar: Adventures in Wine  (Alfred A. Knopf, $24), a collection of the monthly wine columns he writes for House &amp; Garden magazine. I will add only that it is a pleasure to see the wine world through a novelist's playful eyes, and to feel the infectious joy he finds in great wines, places and personalities from around the world.</p>
        <p>For all his skill as a writer, Mr. McInerney talks as an expert guiding his readers. Red, White, and Drunk All Over: A Wine-Soaked Journey From Grape to Glass (Bloomsbury, $23.95) by Natalie MacLean, a Canadian writer, takes another tack altogether. Ms. MacLean has made a name for herself on the Internet, where her site Nat Decants (nataliemaclean.com) has won numerous awards.</p>
        <p>Ms. MacLean is the disarming Everywoman. She loves wine, loves drinking and loves getting a little buzzed. But as she follows wine's journey from vineyard to cellar to retail shop, restaurant and dining room, she can't help feeling insecure.</p>
        <p>She fears embarrassing herself in front of Aubert de Villaine, the proprietor of the august Domaine de la Romanée-Conti, on a visit. Instead he opens a 1956 La Tâche for her. She takes a turn as a retail clerk and her shoes kill her. She invites friends to a tasting party, but sweats with anticipatory anxiety. She bursts into tears when confronted with an unsympathetic sommelier. ''Who knew that rejecting a bottle of wine involved the same arc of emotions as Greek tragedy?'' she writes.</p>
        <p>Ms. MacLean is also flirtatious. Great wines make her feel as if she's being undressed, while a properly uncorked bottle of Champagne opens with a ''postcoital sigh.'' And her point of view is distinctly female. On a glassware producer's discovery that ''content commands shape,'' she notes, ''But anyone who has ever bought a bra already knows that.''</p>
        <p>At times her enthusiasm gushes like Champagne opened improperly. But ultimately, it's a winning formula, aimed at women who are intimidated by wine, and at men who feel that way, too, but won't admit it.</p>
        <p>THE POUR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
