<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fallout | Sept. 10 - 16</title>
    <meta content="17week" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1790808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DB1331F934A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fallout | Sept. 10 - 16</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HEWLETT-PACKARD</p>
        <p>The News -- Patricia C. Dunn will step down as chairwoman of the Hewlett-Packard board, one of a series of moves intended to calm turmoil over a leak investigation.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The company still faces legal inquiries related to the investigation, in which surreptitious methods were used to obtain phone records of directors and reporters. But the board shake-up seemed to restore order in a company that has long set a standard for corporate behavior in Silicon Valley. Investors seemed satisfied as well: Hewlett-Packard's stock is at a five-year high.</p>
        <p>WORLD BANK</p>
        <p>The News -- Paul D. Wolfowitz, the head of the World Bank, has come under criticism within and outside the bank for a campaign against corruption in developing countries.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- Mr. Wolfowitz's efforts have led to the suspension of hundreds of millions of dollars of loans. Critics say under his approach lending may be shut off in an arbitrary way, jeopardizing the bank's goal of reducing poverty. But the criticism may also reflect lingering doubts about the selection of Mr. Wolfowitz, a neoconservative who as deputy defense secretary was a primary architect of the Iraq war.</p>
        <p>WAR ON TERROR</p>
        <p>The News -- Colin L. Powell, President Bush's former secretary of state, sided with some Republican senators in opposing the president's proposals for the trial and interrogation of terrorism suspects.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- Mr. Powell said the president's plan, which provides fewer protections for suspects, would encourage nations to question the ''moral basis of our fight against terrorism.'' It was a rare public disagreement by Mr. Powell. But he had long expressed reservations about White House claims it should not be bound by the Geneva Conventions in the war on terror.</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>The News -- Frankie Andreu, a former teammate of Lance Armstrong, admitted he had used performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The admission by Andreu and another anonymous former teammate that they had used the drug EPO in 1999, the first year Armstrong won the Tour de France, put pressure on the cycling star, who has said he never used banned substances. But both teammates said they did not see Armstrong use drugs, and Armstrong said he had never pushed his teammates to use them and had not known they had done so.</p>
        <p>THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
        <p>The News -- A new study showed that global warming is responsible for the rising ocean temperatures in tropical regions that spawn destructive storms.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The report found that the rising water temperatures could only be explained by the buildup of heat-trapping greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. The study did not address the issue of whether recent hurricanes have been stronger because of the warmer waters, but the researchers warned that continued warming might mean stronger storms in the coming decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HEWLETT-PACKARD</p>
        <p>The News -- Patricia C. Dunn will step down as chairwoman of the Hewlett-Packard board, one of a series of moves intended to calm turmoil over a leak investigation.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The company still faces legal inquiries related to the investigation, in which surreptitious methods were used to obtain phone records of directors and reporters. But the board shake-up seemed to restore order in a company that has long set a standard for corporate behavior in Silicon Valley. Investors seemed satisfied as well: Hewlett-Packard's stock is at a five-year high.</p>
        <p>WORLD BANK</p>
        <p>The News -- Paul D. Wolfowitz, the head of the World Bank, has come under criticism within and outside the bank for a campaign against corruption in developing countries.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- Mr. Wolfowitz's efforts have led to the suspension of hundreds of millions of dollars of loans. Critics say under his approach lending may be shut off in an arbitrary way, jeopardizing the bank's goal of reducing poverty. But the criticism may also reflect lingering doubts about the selection of Mr. Wolfowitz, a neoconservative who as deputy defense secretary was a primary architect of the Iraq war.</p>
        <p>WAR ON TERROR</p>
        <p>The News -- Colin L. Powell, President Bush's former secretary of state, sided with some Republican senators in opposing the president's proposals for the trial and interrogation of terrorism suspects.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- Mr. Powell said the president's plan, which provides fewer protections for suspects, would encourage nations to question the ''moral basis of our fight against terrorism.'' It was a rare public disagreement by Mr. Powell. But he had long expressed reservations about White House claims it should not be bound by the Geneva Conventions in the war on terror.</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>The News -- Frankie Andreu, a former teammate of Lance Armstrong, admitted he had used performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The admission by Andreu and another anonymous former teammate that they had used the drug EPO in 1999, the first year Armstrong won the Tour de France, put pressure on the cycling star, who has said he never used banned substances. But both teammates said they did not see Armstrong use drugs, and Armstrong said he had never pushed his teammates to use them and had not known they had done so.</p>
        <p>THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
        <p>The News -- A new study showed that global warming is responsible for the rising ocean temperatures in tropical regions that spawn destructive storms.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The report found that the rising water temperatures could only be explained by the buildup of heat-trapping greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. The study did not address the issue of whether recent hurricanes have been stronger because of the warmer waters, but the researchers warned that continued warming might mean stronger storms in the coming decades.  THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
