<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Revises Its Formula To Calculate Auto Mileage</title>
    <meta content="12mileage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/12/business/12mileage.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1811355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Consumer Reports</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Consumers Union</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bluewater Network</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0D71431F931A25751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Revises Its Formula To Calculate Auto Mileage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">E.P.A. Revises Its Formula to Calculate Auto Mileage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency rewrote one of the great fictions of American life on Monday by changing the formula for calculating miles-per-gallon numbers on the window stickers of new cars, to take account of higher speeds, more aggressive driving, more air-conditioning use and other factors not in the old system.</p>
        <p>The rules cover 2008 models, some of which will be on sale next month. It does not change the actual mileage, only the advice to consumers. Congress ordered the change 18 months ago because of widespread dissatisfaction with the accuracy of the old numbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new formula takes into account higher speeds, more aggressive driving, more air-conditioning use and other factors not in the old system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency rewrote one of the great fictions of American life on Monday by changing the formula for calculating miles-per-gallon numbers on the window stickers of new cars, to take account of higher speeds, more aggressive driving, more air-conditioning use and other factors not in the old system.</p>
        <p>The rules cover 2008 models, some of which will be on sale next month. It does not change the actual mileage, only the advice to consumers. Congress ordered the change 18 months ago because of widespread dissatisfaction with the accuracy of the old numbers.</p>
        <p>The system was last adjusted in 1984, when the E.P.A. cut the city values by 10 percent and the highway values by 22 percent. This one cuts the estimate of highway mileage another 8 percent, on average, and city mileage up to another 25 percent beyond the 1984 cut. Generally, the new formula narrows the gap between small cars and bigger vehicles, with small-car fuel economy estimates falling by more than the estimates for sport utility vehicles and other larger vehicles.</p>
        <p>Hybrid vehicles will take some of the biggest hits, according to the agency, because the new standards include use of heaters and air-conditioners. Most gas-electric hybrids shut down their engines at low speeds, and run on electric batteries, but if the vehicle occupants have turned on the air-conditioner or heater, the engine may not shut down.</p>
        <p>At Consumers Union, the nonprofit group that publishes Consumer Reports, Ann Wright, a senior policy analyst, said the new stickers would move the government estimates closer to reality. Consumer Reports does road tests on vehicles and its mileage results are generally much lower than the E.P.A.'s.</p>
        <p>At the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers, a trade group, officials also praised the new standard and said it would cut fuel economy estimates by 8 to 10 percent on average. The alliance had fought to make sure that the formula was used only on the sticker, and not on the Corporate Average Fuel Economy standard, the one that manufacturers must meet or pay a penalty.</p>
        <p>At the Bluewater Network, an environmental group that petitioned the E.P.A. in 2002 to recalculate the numbers, Russell Long, the executive director, said he had been told that the agency was also working on a new sticker for ''flexfuel'' vehicles, which can run on ethanol mixtures as high as 85 percent, known as E85. Those get about 30 percent fewer miles a gallon of E85 than on gasoline.</p>
        <p>When the E.P.A. began estimating mileage in the 1970s, the test covered speeds up to 60 miles an hour, and it expected that when drivers wanted to go faster, they increased their speeds by 3.3 miles per hour each second. But about 28 percent of driving is done above 60 miles per hour, the agency said, and actual acceleration rates are often 10 or 12 miles per hour each second.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year when it proposed the new standard, the E.P.A. said its test ''omitted many critical driving modes.''</p>
        <p>The fuel economy rating system is an afterthought to treadmill tests done by the E.P.A. to measure pollutants that cause smog and acid rain.</p>
        <p>The redesigned sticker puts the annual estimated fuel cost in big type in the center of the label, and locates the vehicle with an arrow on a horizontal bar, to show its position relative to competitors, as is done with refrigerators and air-conditioners.</p>
        <p>For most of 2007, both stickers, and both formulas, will be in use, the new ones on the cars designated as 2008 models, and the old ones on the 2007 models.</p>
        <p>Despite the changes, the EPA's label retains a phrase that has become a cliché: ''Actual mileage will vary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
