<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="05forsumms" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1773924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EED91230F936A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>North Korea Test Fires 6 Missiles, One Long-Range  North Korea test-fired at least six missiles over the Sea of Japan, including an intercontinental missile that apparently failed or was aborted 42 seconds after it was launched, White House and Pentagon officials said. The launchings came in defiance of warnings from President Bush and the governments of Japan, South Korea and China.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deaths of Iraqis Still on Rise  Baghdad's central morgue said it had received 1,595 bodies in June, 16 percent more than in May, in a tally that showed the pace of the killing in Baghdad has increased since the death of Abu Musab al-Zarqawi, Iraq's most wanted insurgent leader.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>The military investigation into soldiers suspected of raping an Iraqi woman and killing her and her family is looking at whether poor oversight within the soldiers' unit helped give them the chance to operate on their own, American military officials said.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>American commanders say they are planning to bulldoze about three blocks in the middle of Ramadi, the epicenter of the Iraqi insurgency, and convert them into a ''Green Zone,'' a version of the fortified and largely stable area that houses the Iraqi and American leadership in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Electoral Crisis Builds in Mexico  Mexico's electoral crisis deepened as the leftist candidate demanded a recount and election officials acknowledged that as many as three million votes had not been tallied in the preliminary results. The ballots counted so far showed the conservative, Felipe Calderón, with a lead of fewer than 400,000 votes over his opponent, Andrés Manuel López Obrador.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Rocket Hits Deep Into Israel  Defying Israel's military advances into Gaza to help free a captured Israeli soldier, Palestinian militants in Gaza lobbed a rocket deep into Israel, further infuriating the prime minister, Ehud Olmert, above, who called it ''an escalation of unprecedented gravity.'' There was no word on the fate of the soldier.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Georgian Leader Invited to U.S.  In a clear signal to Russia, President Bush has invited Georgian president, Mikheil Saakashvili, to Washington only 10 days before the Group of 8 summit meeting in St. Petersburg, which will be dedicated largely to energy security.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Malaysian Turns to Former Foe  Mahathir Mohamad, left, for 20 years the iron-fisted prime minister of Malaysia, has been ignored by the press he once controlled and has turned to the alternative Internet sites that he says he still despises to condemn his handpicked successor, who has been reversing some of his policies.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-14</p>
        <p>Bush Signals a Shift On Immigration Approach  In an attempt to revise his stalled immigration bill before Election Day, President Bush is demonstrating a new willingness to negotiate with House Republicans, showing interest in a so-called enforcement-first approach that would put new border security programs in place before creating a guest worker program or a path to citizenship for illegal aliens.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Speaking to hundreds of soldiers and their families at Fort Bragg, President Bush warned that setting an ''artificial timetable'' for a withdrawal from Iraq would be ''a terrible mistake.''</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A Debate Over Inmate Labor  Louisiana inmates are regularly used as cheap or free labor, digging graves and tending the athletic fields at local private schools. While many people say they could not get by without it, critics say that local sheriffs use inmate labor to curry political favor and to line their own pockets, taking a large cut from whatever pay the inmates might receive.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Homes for Destitute Alcoholics  Some of Seattle's ''unsympathetic homeless'' -- those who beg, drink, urinate and vomit in public -- now have brand-new, government-financed apartments where they can drink as much as they want, part of an experiment to ease the torment of drug and alcohol addiction while saving taxpayers' money. They do not have to promise to drink less, attend Alcoholics Anonymous or go to church.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Lady Liberty, Bearing a Cross  On Independence Day in Memphis, Lady Liberty was unveiled again, this time wearing ''Jehovah'' on her crown and carrying a cross instead of a torch. The Statue of Liberation Through Christ, as she is called, is the brainchild of a megachurch pastor to whom homosexuality is a sin and the destruction of Hurricane Katrina was God's retribution.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Man Kills Children and Himself  A California man shot and killed his four young children before killing himself less than an hour after a store owner had reported that the man and his wife were arguing in his store, the police said. The police said they found the man's wife uninjured outside the family's home in the San Joaquin Valley, and the father and children dead inside the home.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>SCIENCE</p>
        <p>Discovery Is Launched Safely  The space shuttle Discovery roared into orbit on schedule, beginning a 12-day mission that is the first flight in a year for the diminished shuttle fleet. Also considered the second and final test flight for the shuttle fleet since the loss of the Columbia in 2003, the Discovery's ascent was closely scrutinized for the kind of liftoff debris that caused that disaster.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Sharp Rise in Complaints Against Debt Collectors  The number of complaints about aggressive debt collectors has increased sharply nationwide, and more than doubled in three years in New York City, amid rising consumer debt and tightened bankruptcy laws.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Impasse Could Close Casinos  Although they worked through the July 4 holiday, New Jersey lawmakers and Gov. Jon S. Corzine remained at a stalemate over his proposal to raise the state sales tax, meaning that Atlantic City casinos and state parks will most likely shut down this morning.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Jim Crow Items Sell in Harlem  While selling racist memorabilia and items from the Jim Crow era in the heart of Harlem, America's most famous black neighborhood, might seem offensive, dealers say that blacks rather than whites now tend to be the ones collecting the most repellent objects.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SPORTSWEDNESDAY</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Italy Advances in World Cup  Italy won against Germany in the World Cup semifinals after a scoreless game broke open into a frantic, stunning 2-0 victory in overtime.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Crash Takes Out a Tour Favorite  The Tour de France lost another top rider as Alejandro Valverde of Spain, left, crashed on a broiling sunny day when riders traveled through three countries as part of a stage defined by spills.</p>
        <p>D2</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Wagner Gets a Turn at Festival  The Aix festival in France is, for the first time, presenting Wagner. Sir Simon Rattle is conducting the Berlin Philharmonic in his first stage version of Wagner's four-opera masterpiece, ''Der Ring des Nibelungen.''</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>DINING IN</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>Natural Hot Dogs Catch On  Sales of packaged organic hot dogs have increased sharply over the past four years, and, although they have been around for at least a decade, the new models on the market taste better, have healthier fat profiles and are made from animals that spend their lives eating nothing but pasture.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Lorraine Hunt Lieberson  The mezzo-soprano who won near universal praise from critics and audiences for her courageous, insightful and deeply affecting artistry, she was 52.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Homegrown Caviar Boom  Caviar businesses in California are booming since the United Nations Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species extended a temporary trade ban on most wild sturgeon. Chefs and consumers who once snubbed farmed sturgeon are more willing to serve caviar from farm-raised fish.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Turning Coal Into Diesel Fuel  The technology to turn coal into diesel fuel has attracted entrepreneurs and government officials who want domestic substitutes for foreign oil, but far more carbon dioxide is generated by producing fuels from coal instead of oil or natural gas. The projects moving forward have no incentive to capture carbon dioxide beyond the limited amount that companies can sell for industrial use.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Investigation Into Lone Star  South Korean authorities are continuing a high-profile investigation into Lone Star, the Dallas-based private-equity fund, fueling a public reaction to excessive profits made by foreign investment funds.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Smiley Face Trademark  A trademark dispute between Wal-Mart Stores and a company owned by a French family over American commercial rights to the ubiquitous yellow symbol for happiness, will be determined by the Patent and Trademark Office.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: The shuttle takes off; North Korea's folly; naming names at Ground Zero; hospital-caused deaths.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E2  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>North Korea Test Fires 6 Missiles, One Long-Range  North Korea test-fired at least six missiles over the Sea of Japan, including an intercontinental missile that apparently failed or was aborted 42 seconds after it was launched, White House and Pentagon officials said. The launchings came in defiance of warnings from President Bush and the governments of Japan, South Korea and China.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deaths of Iraqis Still on Rise  Baghdad's central morgue said it had received 1,595 bodies in June, 16 percent more than in May, in a tally that showed the pace of the killing in Baghdad has increased since the death of Abu Musab al-Zarqawi, Iraq's most wanted insurgent leader.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>The military investigation into soldiers suspected of raping an Iraqi woman and killing her and her family is looking at whether poor oversight within the soldiers' unit helped give them the chance to operate on their own, American military officials said.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>American commanders say they are planning to bulldoze about three blocks in the middle of Ramadi, the epicenter of the Iraqi insurgency, and convert them into a ''Green Zone,'' a version of the fortified and largely stable area that houses the Iraqi and American leadership in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Electoral Crisis Builds in Mexico  Mexico's electoral crisis deepened as the leftist candidate demanded a recount and election officials acknowledged that as many as three million votes had not been tallied in the preliminary results. The ballots counted so far showed the conservative, Felipe Calderón, with a lead of fewer than 400,000 votes over his opponent, Andrés Manuel López Obrador.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Rocket Hits Deep Into Israel  Defying Israel's military advances into Gaza to help free a captured Israeli soldier, Palestinian militants in Gaza lobbed a rocket deep into Israel, further infuriating the prime minister, Ehud Olmert, above, who called it ''an escalation of unprecedented gravity.'' There was no word on the fate of the soldier.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Georgian Leader Invited to U.S.  In a clear signal to Russia, President Bush has invited Georgian president, Mikheil Saakashvili, to Washington only 10 days before the Group of 8 summit meeting in St. Petersburg, which will be dedicated largely to energy security.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Malaysian Turns to Former Foe  Mahathir Mohamad, left, for 20 years the iron-fisted prime minister of Malaysia, has been ignored by the press he once controlled and has turned to the alternative Internet sites that he says he still despises to condemn his handpicked successor, who has been reversing some of his policies.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-14</p>
        <p>Bush Signals a Shift On Immigration Approach  In an attempt to revise his stalled immigration bill before Election Day, President Bush is demonstrating a new willingness to negotiate with House Republicans, showing interest in a so-called enforcement-first approach that would put new border security programs in place before creating a guest worker program or a path to citizenship for illegal aliens.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Speaking to hundreds of soldiers and their families at Fort Bragg, President Bush warned that setting an ''artificial timetable'' for a withdrawal from Iraq would be ''a terrible mistake.''</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A Debate Over Inmate Labor  Louisiana inmates are regularly used as cheap or free labor, digging graves and tending the athletic fields at local private schools. While many people say they could not get by without it, critics say that local sheriffs use inmate labor to curry political favor and to line their own pockets, taking a large cut from whatever pay the inmates might receive.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Homes for Destitute Alcoholics  Some of Seattle's ''unsympathetic homeless'' -- those who beg, drink, urinate and vomit in public -- now have brand-new, government-financed apartments where they can drink as much as they want, part of an experiment to ease the torment of drug and alcohol addiction while saving taxpayers' money. They do not have to promise to drink less, attend Alcoholics Anonymous or go to church.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Lady Liberty, Bearing a Cross  On Independence Day in Memphis, Lady Liberty was unveiled again, this time wearing ''Jehovah'' on her crown and carrying a cross instead of a torch. The Statue of Liberation Through Christ, as she is called, is the brainchild of a megachurch pastor to whom homosexuality is a sin and the destruction of Hurricane Katrina was God's retribution.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Man Kills Children and Himself  A California man shot and killed his four young children before killing himself less than an hour after a store owner had reported that the man and his wife were arguing in his store, the police said. The police said they found the man's wife uninjured outside the family's home in the San Joaquin Valley, and the father and children dead inside the home.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>SCIENCE</p>
        <p>Discovery Is Launched Safely  The space shuttle Discovery roared into orbit on schedule, beginning a 12-day mission that is the first flight in a year for the diminished shuttle fleet. Also considered the second and final test flight for the shuttle fleet since the loss of the Columbia in 2003, the Discovery's ascent was closely scrutinized for the kind of liftoff debris that caused that disaster.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Sharp Rise in Complaints Against Debt Collectors  The number of complaints about aggressive debt collectors has increased sharply nationwide, and more than doubled in three years in New York City, amid rising consumer debt and tightened bankruptcy laws.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Impasse Could Close Casinos  Although they worked through the July 4 holiday, New Jersey lawmakers and Gov. Jon S. Corzine remained at a stalemate over his proposal to raise the state sales tax, meaning that Atlantic City casinos and state parks will most likely shut down this morning.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Jim Crow Items Sell in Harlem  While selling racist memorabilia and items from the Jim Crow era in the heart of Harlem, America's most famous black neighborhood, might seem offensive, dealers say that blacks rather than whites now tend to be the ones collecting the most repellent objects.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SPORTSWEDNESDAY</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Italy Advances in World Cup  Italy won against Germany in the World Cup semifinals after a scoreless game broke open into a frantic, stunning 2-0 victory in overtime.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Crash Takes Out a Tour Favorite  The Tour de France lost another top rider as Alejandro Valverde of Spain, left, crashed on a broiling sunny day when riders traveled through three countries as part of a stage defined by spills.</p>
        <p>D2</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Wagner Gets a Turn at Festival  The Aix festival in France is, for the first time, presenting Wagner. Sir Simon Rattle is conducting the Berlin Philharmonic in his first stage version of Wagner's four-opera masterpiece, ''Der Ring des Nibelungen.''</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>DINING IN</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>Natural Hot Dogs Catch On  Sales of packaged organic hot dogs have increased sharply over the past four years, and, although they have been around for at least a decade, the new models on the market taste better, have healthier fat profiles and are made from animals that spend their lives eating nothing but pasture.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Lorraine Hunt Lieberson  The mezzo-soprano who won near universal praise from critics and audiences for her courageous, insightful and deeply affecting artistry, she was 52.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Homegrown Caviar Boom  Caviar businesses in California are booming since the United Nations Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species extended a temporary trade ban on most wild sturgeon. Chefs and consumers who once snubbed farmed sturgeon are more willing to serve caviar from farm-raised fish.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Turning Coal Into Diesel Fuel  The technology to turn coal into diesel fuel has attracted entrepreneurs and government officials who want domestic substitutes for foreign oil, but far more carbon dioxide is generated by producing fuels from coal instead of oil or natural gas. The projects moving forward have no incentive to capture carbon dioxide beyond the limited amount that companies can sell for industrial use.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Investigation Into Lone Star  South Korean authorities are continuing a high-profile investigation into Lone Star, the Dallas-based private-equity fund, fueling a public reaction to excessive profits made by foreign investment funds.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Smiley Face Trademark  A trademark dispute between Wal-Mart Stores and a company owned by a French family over American commercial rights to the ubiquitous yellow symbol for happiness, will be determined by the Patent and Trademark Office.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: The shuttle takes off; North Korea's folly; naming names at Ground Zero; hospital-caused deaths.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E2  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
