<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting Environmentalism on the Urban Map</title>
    <meta content="17leeds" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Business of Green" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/17/business/businessspecial2/17leeds.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1762248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="STANDARDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solaire (NYC Apartment Building)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Battery Park City (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Green Building Council</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EED9153EF934A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting Environmentalism on the Urban Map</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Putting Environmentalism on the Urban Map</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Solaire in Battery Park, first residential high-rise building in New York City to be certified by US Green Building Council, will be joined in next three years by seven other green residential buildings and green Goldman Sachs headquarters; all projects are expected to be certified gold, with three potentially rated platinum, under rating system called Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design, which council established to evaluate building's efforts to use renewable materials, conserve energy and water consumption and enhance indoor air quality; Battery Park City stands to become experiment in creating all-green neighborhood, which so far appears to be unmatched in US; photo; drawings; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YES, there are sweeping views of the Hudson River, 35 acres of parkland and waterfront promenades. But what gets James Cavanaugh especially jazzed about Battery Park City is the reclaimed toilet water, processed by a waste-treatment plant in the basement of an apartment building at 20 River Terrace.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Cavanaugh, the president and chief executive of the Battery Park City Authority, has tasted it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Battery Park City is insisting that developers retrofit their existing pre-guideline buildings to make them even greener.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YES, there are sweeping views of the Hudson River, 35 acres of parkland and waterfront promenades. But what gets James Cavanaugh especially jazzed about Battery Park City is the reclaimed toilet water, processed by a waste-treatment plant in the basement of an apartment building at 20 River Terrace.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Cavanaugh, the president and chief executive of the Battery Park City Authority, has tasted it.</p>
        <p>The plant is located in the base of the Solaire, the first residential high-rise building in New York City to be certified by the U.S. Green Building Council.</p>
        <p>The Solaire, certified in 2004, is still the exception in the city; only recently have architects, developers and construction managers begun to integrate so-called sustainable design into their high-rise projects. But in Battery Park City, the Solaire has become the rule.</p>
        <p>By 2009, when all the available sites on its 92 acres will be developed, Battery Park City will have eight green residential buildings and a green Goldman Sachs headquarters. All these projects are expected to be certified gold -- with three potentially rated platinum -- under the Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design ratings system.</p>
        <p>The LEED ratings were established by the Green Building Council to evaluate a building's efforts to use renewable materials, conserve energy and water consumption and enhance indoor air quality. This makes Battery Park City an experiment in creating an all-green neighborhood, which so far appears to be unmatched in the United States.</p>
        <p>''It's looking at the way an entire built community comes together -- Battery Park City is visionary in that regard,'' said S. Richard Fedrizzi, president and chief executive of the Green Building Council, a coalition of building industry leaders who promote environmentally responsible -- or sustainable -- design. ''It's a beacon for what communities all over the country and all over the world are doing.''</p>
        <p>The greening of Battery Park City started in 1999, when the authority -- a New York State public-benefit corporation -- drafted its own green building guidelines, which require that every residence in the area meet strict sustainability criteria. (The guidelines for commercial properties followed in 2002.)</p>
        <p>Battery Park City is now insisting that developers retrofit their existing pre-guideline buildings to make them green, a process under way at the New York Mercantile Exchange's building.</p>
        <p>''We have the opportunity in Battery Park City -- because our authority is in control -- where we can make it a condition for all future development,'' said Gov. George E. Pataki, in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>People have come from all over to learn from Battery Park City, including contingents from the Czech Republic, China and Korea. The authority recently made a presentation to the United States Conference of Mayors in Albuquerque and was part of an international green building challenge at the international Sustainable Building Conference in Oslo.</p>
        <p>''This is a movement that is taking hold and moving forward,'' said Timothy S. Carey, the former president and chief executive of the Battery Park City Authority.</p>
        <p>The visitors come not only because of the high concentration of green buildings there, but also because the authority's green guidelines are so stringent. In many cases, the guidelines exceed those of the Green Building Council. The buildings also have to be 30 percent more energy efficient than New York State building code demands for all types of construction.</p>
        <p>The authority requires photovoltaics, which capture heat from the sun and turn it into electricity. Green roofs are required for 75 percent of a building's nonmechanical roof area. All the parks are run organically, using horticultural soap instead of pesticides, and the ball fields feature waterless urinals and composting toilets.</p>
        <p>In evaluating developers' proposals, the authority gives almost as much weight to the environmental pitch as it does the financial. ''We expect potential developers to go beyond our guidelines and do even better,'' Mr. Cavanaugh said. ''We're not just looking for top dollar, but also sustainable design. The developers are really on notice. They've got to push the envelope every time we engage them to be as aggressive as they can.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey said that at first the authority's board did not know what to make of the idea. ''Some thought I meant green bricks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki said the initial resistance among developers was also strong; some New York City developers still have not joined the bandwagon. ''You really had to convince people that they weren't out of their minds to take this dramatic step,'' Mr. Pataki said.</p>
        <p>Russell C. Albanese, the president of the Albanese Organization, said he remembered being in a room with about a dozen other developers, listening to the requirements for the Solaire in 2000. ''It was new for all of us,'' he said, adding, ''It seemed to make sense as far as building for the future.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Albanese developed the Solaire, completed in 2003, and now has two more projects in Battery Park City -- one to be finished this year, another in 2008. Other developers building in the area are the Related Companies, Millennium Partners, the Sheldrake Organization and Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>Finding materials was more challenging six years ago than it is now. Battery Park City requires 35 percent certified wood in the buildings' interiors (wood that has been harvested sustainably). To meet this standard, Mr. Albanese said he had to marry a wood manufacturer in California with a cabinetmaker in Canada. He also had to find materials that would be environmentally acceptable but also aesthetically pleasing. Porcelain or ceramic tile, for example, ''didn't meet marketing criteria,'' Mr. Albanese said. ''It was environmentally O.K., but not what consumers would want.''</p>
        <p>These kinds of materials have become more widely available these days. While chemical-free paint was once hard to find, it is now used by the average consumer. Products that were custom made for the Solaire -- adhesives, appliances, enamels -- are now sold at Home Depot.</p>
        <p>The cost of making things green has also dropped. Whereas 15 to 17 percent of the $120 million Solaire went toward sustainability, Mr. Albanese's next building, the Verdesian -- also a rental -- has an added green cost of 8 percent, the developer said.</p>
        <p>Still, the extra cost of building green is higher in Battery Park City than the national average, which is now believed to be around 2 to 5 percent, in part because of the authority's tough guidelines. But developers, in turn, can get higher rents and sales prices. Green apartments sell at an estimated 5 percent higher than market, Mr. Cavanaugh said. A 2005 survey of Battery Park City residents found that almost half said they would be willing to pay a premium to live in a building with green features.</p>
        <p>''Pretty soon there will be no more 'green buildings,' because all buildings will be green,'' said James F. Gill, the chairman of the Battery Park City Authority. ''People are willing to pay up to live in a healthier environment.''</p>
        <p>The air is filtered twice -- outside the building and inside the apartment -- humidified in the winter and dehumidified in the summer. ''Nobody ever opens their windows,'' Mr. Cavanaugh said.</p>
        <p>In the Solaire, the tenants also save money, 50 to 60 percent of every air-conditioning bill, because the cooling source is centralized. Mr. Albanese said he was able to go beyond 35 percent energy efficiency using additional heat-recovery technologies. The building reuses heat exhausted by fans in the kitchens and bathrooms, which saves a lot on energy costs.</p>
        <p>The filtration plant in the Solaire treats all the water in the building as a large treatment plant would, with micro-organisms eating the waste. The building also has motion sensors in the corridors, where lights are dimmed by half from midnight to 6 a.m. When a door or an elevator opens during those hours, the lights go to full level.</p>
        <p>The Verdesian runs on a natural-gas microturbine that creates electricity, which helps power the building. The heat given off in this process is used to create the hot water. Mr. Albanese said this amounted to overall efficiency of 80 to 85 percent for the building. A typical power plant -- which burns fossil fuels like oil, gas or coal -- is about 30 percent efficient.</p>
        <p>Over the years, the authority has tightened its guidelines. Originally, 60 percent of all construction waste had to be recycled, for example. That requirement is now 80 percent. Buildings were first required to recycle gray water -- from the laundry or shower -- and reuse it for irrigation.</p>
        <p>Now all water must be recycled, including toilet -- or ''black'' -- water, which is reused for toilet flushing, air-conditioning, irrigation and central laundry. This has resulted in buildings that use about 50 percent less potable -- drinking -- water than standard buildings do.</p>
        <p>The authority has also toughened how it tracks construction. Now developers are required to educate their construction teams about why they are being asked to do things differently. Developers must demonstrate how they are meeting the green guidelines.</p>
        <p>After a project is done, developers must file annual reports that account for their energy and water savings.</p>
        <p>The green building movement is catching on in pockets nationwide. The Rose Smart Growth Investment Fund I, a real estate investment fund run by the developer Jonathan F. P. Rose, buys buildings and makes them green. Last month, the fund bought two buildings in downtown Seattle and planned to reduce their energy costs, operating expenses and improve the air quality for tenants.</p>
        <p>In October, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg signed into law in New York City the Green City Buildings Act, which requires that nonresidential projects costing $2 million or more meet silver LEED standards. (Schools have to be only LEED certified.) Still, mandating green building remains an emerging concept.</p>
        <p>''I still haven't seen that commitment to using government authority to have an entire community,'' Mr. Pataki said. ''There is still more to do to encourage governments to build these into their codes and standards, to encourage manufacturers to make materials and to encourage consumers to look for it.''</p>
        <p>STANDARDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
