<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pastor Chosen to Lead Christian Coalition Steps Down in Dispute Over Agenda</title>
    <meta content="28pastor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/28/us/28pastor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1807874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Christian Coalition</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7D7103EF93BA15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pastor Chosen to Lead Christian Coalition Steps Down in Dispute Over Agenda</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pastor Chosen to Lead Christian Coalition Steps Down in Dispute Over Agenda</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president-elect of the Christian Coalition of America, which has long served as a model for activism for the religious right, has stepped down, saying the group resisted his efforts to broaden its agenda to include reducing poverty and fighting global warming.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Joel C. Hunter, pastor of a Florida megachurch, was named the group's president-elect in July. He was to have taken over the presidency in January from Roberta Combs, who is also the chairwoman of the Christian Coalition's board. Mrs. Combs will continue in both positions now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rev. Joel C. Hunter said the Christian Coalition of America resisted his efforts to broaden its agenda to include reducing poverty and fighting global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The president-elect of the Christian Coalition of America, which has long served as a model for activism for the religious right, has stepped down, saying the group resisted his efforts to broaden its agenda to include reducing poverty and fighting global warming.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Joel C. Hunter, pastor of a Florida megachurch, was named the group's president-elect in July. He was to have taken over the presidency in January from Roberta Combs, who is also the chairwoman of the Christian Coalition's board. Mrs. Combs will continue in both positions now.</p>
        <p>Over the last few years, Dr. Hunter, senior pastor of Northland Church in Longwood, Fla., has gained a reputation as an evangelical leader seeking to expand the agenda of conservative Christian activists from issues like abortion and same-sex marriage.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Dr. Hunter said that although Mrs. Combs had indicated that the organization also wanted to expand its priorities to include the issues that concerned him, the board backed away from such a commitment during a conference call last Tuesday. By the end of the call, Dr. Hunter and the coalition had decided to part amicably, according to both sides.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hunter said, ''When we really got down to it, they said: 'This just isn't for us. It won't speak to our base, so we just can't go there.' ''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Combs contended that the split had less to do with Dr. Hunter's priorities than with his willingness to assert them without consulting the organization's members first.</p>
        <p>''We're a political organization, and there's a way to do things, like taking a survey of your members and seeing what they need,'' she said. ''Joel had a different way of doing things, so he just went out there.''</p>
        <p>The author of ''Right Wing, Wrong Bird: Why the Tactics of the Religious Right Won't Fly With Most Conservative Christians,'' Dr. Hunter has argued that a large number of conservative Christians feel that right-wing religious groups do not represent them, because they focus their energies too narrowly on what he calls moral issues, often to the exclusion of economic and environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>He said that many evangelical leaders hewed to narrow moral issues because they were ''deathly afraid of being labeled a liberal by other Christians, the media, talk radio.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hunter said his departure from the Christian Coalition indicated his belief in the rise of an evangelical Christian constituency that is less interested in the passage of certain laws and focused instead on ''living what Jesus would do.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hunter's departure is the latest difficulty to confront the Christian Coalition, which was founded 17 years ago by Pat Robertson and quickly became the chief lobbying group and voter organizer for the religious right. Since Mr. Robertson's resignation five years ago, the coalition has struggled with creditors, defections by state affiliates and a dwindling presence in the capital.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Combs asserted, however, that the group's debt had declined and its fortunes were changing.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure,'' she said, ''10 years from now, people will still be writing our obituary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
