<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shivering and Unsung, Scientists Monitor the Arctic Year After Year After Year</title>
    <meta content="09arct" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/09/science/09arct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1760325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Pole Environmental Observatory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Science Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Snorkeling and Diving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFDD163EF93AA35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shivering and Unsung, Scientists Monitor the Arctic Year After Year After Year</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shivering and Unsung, Scientists Monitor the Arctic Year After Year After Year</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>North Pole Environmental Observatory, National Science Foundation-funded project that is trying to establish continuing record of ocean conditions in and around North Pole, is in fifth year of gathering information; divers are used to extract two-mile-long strand of instruments that measure conditions and events under ice; difficult conditions in ever-changing region described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On April 22, two divers from the University of Washington entered a manhole-size opening in the veneer of floating sea ice around the North Pole.</p>
        <p>For the fifth year in a row they descended into the blue-green 29-degree water in pursuit of the least glorious, and perhaps most important, facet of earth and ocean science: the collection of basic information on conditions in the same place year after year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Careful environmental monitoring is unsung and underfinanced, but it has resulted in some of the most important discoveries about how the world is changing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On April 22, two divers from the University of Washington entered a manhole-size opening in the veneer of floating sea ice around the North Pole.</p>
        <p>For the fifth year in a row they descended into the blue-green 29-degree water in pursuit of the least glorious, and perhaps most important, facet of earth and ocean science: the collection of basic information on conditions in the same place year after year.</p>
        <p>Their task was to retrieve a two-mile-long strand of instruments that for a year had been anchored to the sea floor recording shifting currents, temperatures, salinity, ice thickness and other vital signs. Now, after an acoustic signal released it from the anchor, the strand was bunched in a tangle of floats and Kevlar line under the ice.</p>
        <p>The divers are part of a team of nearly two dozen researchers who have been trying to establish the first continuing record of changing ocean conditions near the North Pole.</p>
        <p>After this retrieval of a year's worth of data, the team would drop fresh instruments and a new anchor.</p>
        <p>Such monitoring, whether in unremarkable places or at the ends of the earth, is unsung and underfinanced, but it has resulted in some of the most important discoveries about how the world is changing under the increasingly global influence of humans, many scientists say.</p>
        <p>First came revelations about acid rain and the destruction of the ozone layer, with atmospheric monitoring over Antarctica revealing the surprising seasonal ''hole'' that etched the issue into the public consciousness in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>In the same way, quotidian efforts by Charles D. Keeling of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in San Diego to measure levels of atmospheric carbon dioxide -- month after month, year after year, decade after decade -- provided the first clear evidence that humans were sharply increasing the concentration of this heat-trapping greenhouse gas.</p>
        <p>Ralph Keeling, also at Scripps and the son of Charles Keeling (who died last June), has been trying to sustain his father's carbon dioxide monitoring project in a time of shrinking budgets.</p>
        <p>Although such work may seem inconsequential or boring to some outsiders, he said, it has its own special feeling of urgency. ''To keep up with the latest pulse of the planet in a warming world is quite exciting, similar to watching the charts of an unstable patient in the emergency room of a hospital,'' Dr. Keeling said.</p>
        <p>Trends in the Arctic so far have been reflected in readings of sea ice thickness and the area it covers, taken by satellites and nuclear submarines.</p>
        <p>While satellites have helped track increasing summer retreats of the ice over three decades, they cannot reveal the temperature, salinity and currents of the layered ocean below.</p>
        <p>Declassified information collected by submarines has shown that the ice has also been thinning but the data are limited to corridors used in the cold war.</p>
        <p>Glaring gaps persist in the data, and as a result scientists have had difficulty putting the recent big changes in air, ice and ocean conditions in the far north into context.</p>
        <p>The team that sets up what it calls the North Pole Environmental Observatory each spring is content to add one new data point each year to the big picture, right near the North Pole.</p>
        <p>Every such point counts because global-scale puzzles, like determining how accumulating greenhouse gases will alter climate and the oceans, are clearest when assessing the ''balance of evidence,'' not specific findings in one place.</p>
        <p>As with a pointillist painting, the picture is revealed only when a large array of dots is regarded as a whole.</p>
        <p>The challenge with monitoring the central Arctic Ocean is finding ways to take measurements precisely and consistently in a place where nothing is consistent -- where the only unchanging thing is the seabed below the ice, 10 Empire State Buildings deep. But the crunching, shifting frozen surface is in constant flux, often drifting up to 400 yards an hour.</p>
        <p>The researchers have endured such conditions since 2000, and the National Science Foundation has agreed to spend more than $1 million a year to support the project through 2008, because the top of the world is an important crossroads for currents and flowing ice that can help reveal bigger patterns as the Arctic Ocean responds to warming.</p>
        <p>There is no way, yet, to place instruments on the ice or sea floor that phone home year after year as they might do from a mountaintop or Antarctica. Although that continent has one of the harshest environments on earth, it is -- beneath its ice sheets -- solid ground so scientists can settle in for the long haul with no need to plunge into frigid depths.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the North Pole research team has stuck with it. The project was complicated this year by a fresh array of challenges, including unusual warmth and wind, thick fog and fragmented ice.</p>
        <p>In past years, the scientists usually enjoyed at least the illusion of being on a solid surface, with their man-made hole being the only open water for more than a thousand yards around.</p>
        <p>This time, said James Johnson, a University of Washington engineer who helped design the instrument chains, they were essentially camped on an ice raft not much larger than a football field that was surrounded by patches of black, steaming water. As the days passed, the ice beneath them became progressively laced with disconcerting cracks, Mr. Johnson said.</p>
        <p>Independent sea ice experts at the National Snow and Ice Data Center in Boulder, Colo., said the weaker ice, the fog and the open water seen by the team at the North Pole were consistent with their latest measurements of the overall conditions on the Arctic Ocean. They have measured big retreats in the floating ice in recent summers, including a modern record in 2005, and the ice did not rebuild in recent months as it usually does in the deep freeze and long nights of the Arctic winter, said Mark C. Serreze, a senior scientist at the center.</p>
        <p>In April the divers, who spent 42 minutes under the ice, faced challenges they had not encountered before. Among other issues, the instruments and attached floats were tangled amid ridges of broken ice under some ice floes.</p>
        <p>One diver, James Osse, said his knife, usually a pro forma accessory on these expeditions, suddenly became a vital tool as he was forced to hack through a cat's cradle of line.</p>
        <p>''And it was actually sharp enough to cut something, which was surprising but fortunate,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Osse is an engineer back at the university in Seattle, and there he has devoted much of his time in recent years to devising automated winged probes that he hopes will soon make his Arctic scuba work obsolete.</p>
        <p>The probes are meant to glide thousands of feet into the depths and surface, then glide and surface again and again, transmitting data each time they surface, staying at sea for up to seven months.</p>
        <p>There have been only preliminary tests of such gliders beneath sea ice, where they cannot surface and must keep track of their position using underwater beacons instead of the global positioning system network.</p>
        <p>For at least a few more years, then, someone will have to continue diving under the North Pole ice to get the job done.</p>
        <p>Andrew C. Revkin's new book, ''The North Pole Was Here: Puzzles and Perils at the Top of the World,'' is the first title in a new line of New York Times books for younger readers. Mr. Revkin is answering students' questions about the Arctic and global warming until May 14 at nytimes.com/learning/globalwarming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Andrew C. Revkin's new book, ''The North Pole Was Here: Puzzles and Perils at the Top of the World,'' is the first title in a new line of New York Times books for younger readers. Mr. Revkin is answering students' questions about the Arctic and global warming until May 14 at nytimes.com/learning/globalwarming.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
