<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saturn Moon Has Geysers, Hinting Life Is a Possibility</title>
    <meta content="10saturn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/10/science/space/10saturn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1745583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Saturn (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Solar System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Saturn (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DD1331F933A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saturn Moon Has Geysers, Hinting Life Is a Possibility</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Saturn Moon Has Geysers, Hinting Life Is a Possibility</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With newly discovered signs of liquid water, a moon of Saturn joins the small, highly select group of places in the solar system that could plausibly support life.</p>
        <p>The moon, Enceladus, is only 300 miles wide, and usually something that small is nothing more than a frozen chunk of ice and rock. Instead, NASA's Cassini spacecraft has spotted eruptions of icy crystals, which hint at pockets of liquid water near the surface.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With signs of liquid water, Enceladus joins the small group of places in the solar system that could plausibly support life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With newly discovered signs of liquid water, a moon of Saturn joins the small, highly select group of places in the solar system that could plausibly support life.</p>
        <p>The moon, Enceladus, is only 300 miles wide, and usually something that small is nothing more than a frozen chunk of ice and rock. Instead, NASA's Cassini spacecraft has spotted eruptions of icy crystals, which hint at pockets of liquid water near the surface.</p>
        <p>''It's startling,'' said Carolyn C. Porco of the Space Science Institute in Boulder, Colo., leader of the imaging team for Cassini. Nine scientific papers about Enceladus (pronounced en-SELL-ah-dus), appear in today's issue of Science. ''I wouldn't be surprised to see the planetary community clamoring for a future exploratory expedition to land on the south polar terrain of Enceladus,'' said Dr. Porco, lead author of one of the papers. ''We have found an environment that is potentially suitable for living organisms.''</p>
        <p>Life requires at least three ingredients -- water, heat and carbon-based molecules -- and Enceladus may possess all three. As Cassini flew through the plumes of vapor and ice crystals rising into space from the eruptions, it also detected simple carbon-based molecules like methane and carbon dioxide, which suggest more complicated carbon molecules may lie on the moon's surface.</p>
        <p>The lack of a crater suggests that the heat is not the result of a meteor's impact. Based on initial observations, some scientists think that this warm region near the south pole may have persisted for billions of years, sufficient time for life to arise.</p>
        <p>''It's an exciting place,'' said James W. Head III, a professor of geological sciences at Brown University, who was not involved with any of the research reported in today's Science. ''That's what exploration is all about. You go out there. It isn't A. It isn't B. It isn't C. It's D, none of the above.''</p>
        <p>Planetary scientists pointed to the discovery as an argument for continuing NASA's space science efforts. The agency's proposed budget would cut $3 billion from space science over the next five years to help pay for the completion of the space station and plans to send astronauts back to Earth's Moon. NASA's astrobiology institute, which finances research on the possibility of life elsewhere in the solar system and universe, is to see its budget cut in half.</p>
        <p>''They must provide sufficient funds for NASA to conduct both human flight and robotic exploration missions,'' Dr. Porco said. ''Right now, the funding is inadequate.''</p>
        <p>Cassini flew by Enceladus three times last year. For the first two flybys, Cassini's observations of Enceladus' equatorial region turned up nothing odd -- except that it seemed to be deflecting Saturn's magnetic fields, implying that Enceladus had a thin atmosphere of charged atoms.</p>
        <p>NASA tweaked the trajectory of Cassini's July flyby to pass within about 110 miles of Enceladus' surface. For the first time, the spacecraft got a look at the south pole, which turned out to be smooth compared with the pockmarked northern hemisphere. And it was warm.</p>
        <p>The expectation was that the temperature would be about minus-330 degrees Fahrenheit. It turned out more than 100 degrees warmer. ''Which is fairly dramatic and blew us away when we first saw it,'' said John R. Spencer, a planetary scientist at the Southwest Research Institute in Boulder and a team member working with a Cassini instrument that measures infrared emissions. ''It's a lot of heat to come out of such a tiny object.''</p>
        <p>Images of the moon also showed towering plumes of ice crystals coming off at high speed from the surface. The jets seem to originate from fissures near the south pole.</p>
        <p>Dr. Porco said calculations eliminated the possibility that the particles were produced by warm vapor rising off warm ice at the surface. The best explanation, she said, is that pockets of liquid water exist under high pressure below a few tens of yards of ice. When the ice ruptures, the water shoots out and immediately freezes into ice crystals.</p>
        <p>''We think we've got geysers,'' Dr. Porco said.</p>
        <p>A small body like Enceladus would be unlikely to hold enough radioactive elements to produce continuing warmth. A more likely explanation is that the gravitational tugging on Enceladus by Saturn and another moon, Dione, squishes Enceladus and that friction creates the heat. Another mystery is why the heat is concentrated around the south pole.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
