<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Port's Ice Is Thinning, and So Is Its Tourist Trade</title>
    <meta content="14japan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/14/international/asia/14japan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Mombetsu Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4D91031F937A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Port's Ice Is Thinning, and So Is Its Tourist Trade</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Port's Ice Is Thinning, and So Is Its Tourist Trade</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <dateline>MOMBETSU, Japan</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The icebreaker Garinko II cast off one recent morning with an apology.</p>
        <p>The loudspeaker told the four tourists aboard the ship, large enough for 195 passengers, what they had already deduced. Regrettably, the drift ice that drew them here, which usually descends on Japan's northern face this time of the year, was nowhere in sight -- a result, experts say, of warming waters in the Sea of Okhotsk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warmer water means less interest in taking a Japanese icebreaker cruise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The icebreaker Garinko II cast off one recent morning with an apology.</p>
        <p>The loudspeaker told the four tourists aboard the ship, large enough for 195 passengers, what they had already deduced. Regrettably, the drift ice that drew them here, which usually descends on Japan's northern face this time of the year, was nowhere in sight -- a result, experts say, of warming waters in the Sea of Okhotsk.</p>
        <p>Inside the control room, the captain, Shigeru Yamai, was making a beeline for a thin patch of ice in a corner of the harbor. It was hardly drift ice. Still, as the icebreaker's two powerful drills tore through the pitifully thin ice, perhaps the muted sound did give the tourists, in the captain's words, ''just a feel'' of the real thing.</p>
        <p>''It wouldn't do if all they saw on this trip was the sea's blue water,'' he said, steering the Garinko II toward just that.</p>
        <p>''It's an abnormal year,'' said the captain, who has navigated through the drift ice for 21 years. ''We've gotten so little ice.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, there was so little this winter of the majestic, often latticeshaped ice that normally drifts down the Sea of Okhotsk onto the northern coast of Hokkaido that the tourist association here is already talking of the post-drift-ice era. In its thinness, in its short duration and in every other measure, this winter's drift ice was considered the poorest in almost two decades.</p>
        <p>Next year, of course, the ice may be thicker and longer-lasting. But some experts say global warming is changing the temperature of the Sea of Okhotsk and shrinking the size of the drift ice the same way it is melting Greenland's glaciers.</p>
        <p>Masaaki Aota, director of the Okhotsk Sea Ice Museum of Hokkaido here, said records from the nearby city of Abashiri showed that the average temperature had risen 1.5 degrees Fahrenheit over the last century and that the amount of drift ice had shrunk by 40 percent.</p>
        <p>''It's clear that the force of the drift ice has become weaker and the average air temperature has become higher,'' Mr. Aota said. He said he believed that the most likely cause was global warming, though he added that there was no conclusive evidence. ''I don't think this is a problem particular to this place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Sea of Okhotsk is the southernmost body of water where drift ice can be seen in the Northern Hemisphere, a phenomenon tied to its twolayer water system. In early December the seawater in the northern Sea of Okhotsk reaches the freezing point as Siberian winds chill the air. At the same time, the Amur River in Russia flows into the sea, glossing the surface with fresh water, which freezes more easily than saltwater.</p>
        <p>Temperatures have long been cold enough to freeze the sea's southernmost edge, along the Hokkaido coast, for the first three months of each year. Archaeologists believe that in ancient times the ice allowed Asians from the mainland -- known as the Okhotsk people and related to the Inuit in North America -- to migrate to Hokkaido.</p>
        <p>Here in Mombetsu, a traditional fishing town with a smattering of stores catering to Russians engaging in the crab trade, the drift ice has usually appeared in mid-January and stayed strong until mid-March, often lingering until May. The drift ice made the sea impassable to all ships but icebreakers for an average of 40 days. This year, the sea remained locked for only 10 days.</p>
        <p>Takatoshi Hatakeyama, 71, a retired fisherman, remembered that when he was a boy the drift ice invaded the coast every winter. Children played atop the mounds of ice that piled up on the shore.</p>
        <p>''We'd put a board on the ice and walk on it,'' Mr. Hatakeyama said. ''When spring came we'd see hairy crabs showing their red shells on the sand here and there. We'd fill them into the bamboo baskets we carried on our backs. I'd collect them and go home before going to school.''</p>
        <p>He remembers being stuck in the drift ice when he worked on a fishing trawler as an adult.</p>
        <p>''We'd be caught in the drift ice, but it was all right,'' he said. ''If there was a storm and we'd go into the drift ice it'd be quiet, in the evening or in the daytime. We'd hear the sound of the drift ice. It has different kinds of cries, like 'giri giri.' We call it the cry of the drift ice. When the air comes in, it cries 'gu gu gu.' It changes according to the situation.''</p>
        <p>For fishermen -- especially before it was widely known that the drift ice acted as a lid and contributed to the growth of algae and plankton underneath, to the benefit of fish -- the drift ice was considered an enemy. It landlocked fishermen in the winter and forced them to find other jobs during those months. Or it forced large trawlers to break through the ice and seek open waters away from the Sea of Okhotsk.</p>
        <p>''The sea would be entirely frozen,'' said Kazuo Nawata, 69, another retired fisherman. ''You couldn't move forward, but you'd have to move forward. So you'd go back, then strike forward, go back, then forward.''</p>
        <p>It is only in the last 25 years that drift ice became a tourist attraction, said Masayoshi Hatanaka, president of the Mombetsu City Tourist Association. Mr. Hatanaka is now emphasizing the importance of finding another tourist attraction in Mombetsu's post-drift-ice era.</p>
        <p>Tourists were drawn to the severe beauty of the frozen sea, and scientists like Mr. Aota wrote essays on the poetry of the drift ice.</p>
        <p>''When the drift ice is pressing against the shore,'' Mr. Aota said, ''it cries like a cow. When it gets severely cold it goes 'biri.' It's a metallic sound. If you combine them, you could make a symphony.''</p>
        <p>The drift ice drew tourists like Mitsuhiro Nakamura, 35, one of the four aboard the Garinko II the other morning. Mr. Nakamura came every year from Tokyo to see the ice on his birthday.</p>
        <p>''I'll probably come again next year,'' Mr. Nakamura told Captain Yamai inside the control room.</p>
        <p>As he prepared to dock the Garinko II, the captain said, ''If you come again next year and see me, please say hello. I might not be here, though.''</p>
        <p>Mombetsu Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
