<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frozen in Time</title>
    <meta content="26will--williams" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/26/books/review/26williams.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1742433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="'The Ice Museum: In Search of the Lost Land of Thule,' by Joanna Kavenna"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Florence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kavenna, Joanna</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ice Museum, The: In Search of the Lost Land of Thule (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ice Museum, The: In Search of the Lost Land of Thule (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED8133EF935A15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frozen in Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Frozen in Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florence Williams reviews book The Ice Museum: In Search of the Lost Land of Thule by Joanna Kavenna; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ICE MUSEUM</p>
        <p>In Search of the Lost Land of Thule.</p>
        <p>By Joanna Kavenna.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 294 pp. Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The author set out to find the mythical, metaphorical northern land of Thule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ICE MUSEUM</p>
        <p>In Search of the Lost Land of Thule.</p>
        <p>By Joanna Kavenna.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 294 pp. Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>What is it about the polar North that has enraptured imaginations from the mariners of ancient Greece to the Romantic poets to modern tourists? It all started in the fourth century B.C., when Pytheas sailed six days from Scotland over floe-filled seas to a land he called Thule, a place surrounded by mists and lit by a midnight summer sun. His written account was lost, and Thule was never identified with any certainty, forever relegating it to the realm of speculation, imagination and mythology. Joanna Kavenna, a British journalist, travels by car, plane, helicopter and boat to places that have claimed the mantle over the ages, including Shetland, Iceland, Norway, Estonia, Greenland and Svalbard (formerly Spitsbergen).</p>
        <p>Thule, real or not, is ripe and beguiling material for a literary and geographic adventurer, and Kavenna is formidable on both fronts. She was fascinated by Arctic exploration and enticed by artistic allusions to Thule from an early age. Virgil had called the northern country ultima Thule, and it became a metaphor for extremity. Charlotte Brontë conjured Thule as one of those ''forlorn regions of dreary space.'' Edgar Allan Poe called it ''a wild weird clime that lieth, sublime / out of space . . . out of time!'' Christopher Columbus claimed to have reached it before sailing to America; the Norwegian explorer Fridtjof Nansen, long obsessed with the idea of Thule, tried to drift his ship, Fram, across the North Pole and failed in 1893.</p>
        <p>''The subject engrossed me,'' Kavenna writes in ''The Ice Museum,'' her first book. ''It kept me in a trance. . . . The questions and the northern lands themselves summoned me.'' She yearns for the emotional transport of emptiness, ''a crazy beauty, immeasurable and bizarre.'' Her mission is also highly cerebral, as she ferrets out the literary references and the individuals, often wonderfully eccentric, who support a particular theory of the real Thule. Many people she interviews in these desolate pockets are loosened by drink, including patrons of Shetland's Thule Bar and an Icelandic poet named Johannes. But her style is more bookish than loutish, and she spends equal time with the scribblings of Arctic seekers like Trollope and Auden.</p>
        <p>Although her writing can be prim (the glacier's edge ''declined onto the mud plains,'' and ''by morning I am tired and unkempt''), Kavenna makes no apologies for being erudite -- and in an age of flippant, self-indulgent travelogues, this in itself is refreshing. She gives us only as much of her reactions and background, including short scenes from an idyllic country childhood, as we need to know in order to understand her nostalgia for wilderness and reverie. Her quest is less about a place than about a metaphor.</p>
        <p>Today, Thule seems an obsolete puzzle. After all, planes buzz over the North Pole and tourists clink Champagne glasses there. Scientists have plumbed the polar ice cap, and even the Air Force uses the region for missile defense operations. But though the Thule quest may now seem ancient, it is far from irrelevant. Kavenna bridges the transition like a master. ''When B-52's flew across the pole, when nuclear waste rotted in the depths of the Arctic Ocean, what had happened to a dream of a pure place, a place apart from the ambiguities of the world below?'' she asks. The myth has only grown darker, clouded by exploitation.</p>
        <p>Much of her journey is eye-opening, as it entwines Nordic history, cold-war politics, nation-building and the rise of Nazism. After World War I, Aryan supremacists in Germany formed the crypto-fascist Thule Society, whose aim was to fetishize the northern races and to denounce Jews, foreigners and Bolsheviks. Its supporters included Adolf Hitler and Rudolf Hess. Kavenna visits their meeting places and devotes a chapter to an embittered woman born of the Nazi project to further the Aryan race, her father a German soldier, her mother a Norwegian villager. After the war, she and so many other children like her were ostracized and forsaken by their countries.</p>
        <p>The white, vast wilderness of Siberia turned into a landscape of prisons and oppression, and later the Arctic seas became a dumping ground of industrialization, with tragic consequences for people and wildlife. In a moment of daring worthy of the region's history of exploration, Kavenna begs her way onto a helicopter bound for Thule Air Base in northern Greenland. That forlorn spot was, it turned out, ''equidistant between New York and Moscow, as the bomber flies.''</p>
        <p>She fittingly ends her travels on Svalbard, where a scientific research station works to solve another Arctic puzzle: climate change. Thule and climate change are integrally related. As one finally comes close to being apprehended, the other imperils it. The coming world, Kavenna writes, may be one of melted ice and extinct polar bears, and Thule may once again be known only as myth.</p>
        <p>'The Ice Museum: In Search of the Lost Land of Thule,' by Joanna Kavenna Florence Williams is a contributing editor for Outside magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Florence Williams is a contributing editor for Outside magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
