<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: June 23 - June 29</title>
    <meta content="23thea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060624T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1771032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDA1F31F930A15755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="15137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: June 23 - June 29</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE BUSY WORLD IS HUSHED' Opens on Sunday. A minister played by Jill Clayburgh finds herself at odds with her estranged, wayward son in this new play by Keith Bunin (''The Credeaux Canvas''). Mark Brokaw directs (2:00). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'MACBETH' Opens on Wednesday. First at the Public in the park this year will be Moisés Kaufman's production of ''the Scottish play,'' starring Liev Schreiber, who went unto the breach at the Delacorte Theater in 2003 in ''Henry V'' (2:25). Delacorte Theater, Central Park West and 81st Street, (212) 539-8750.</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' Opens on Tuesday. The Roundabout Theater reunites part of the artistic team from ''Urinetown'' -- the playwright Greg Kotis and the director John Rando -- for this play about a couple struggling to hold onto their herd of pigs. Denis O'Hare stars (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'SCHOOL OF THE AMERICAS' In previews. Opens on July 6. Based on historical fact, José Rivera's new play is about two days that Che Guevera spent trapped in a one-room schoolhouse. A co-production with the Labyrinth Theater company. John Ortiz and Patricia Velasquez star. (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SECRETS' Opens on Sunday. Gerald Zipper's play takes place over the course of a dinner party that turns sour and vicious, threatening several long marriages. Directed by Ted Mornel. (1:30). Theater at St. Luke's, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SHAKESPEARE IS DEAD' In previews; opens on Wednesday. Two parents, a pair of artists, re-examine their seven-year-old relationship after the accidental death of their child in this play by Orran Farmer, directed by Chris Chaberski (1:00). Paradise Factory, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, Special Theatrical Event 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, Best Book of a Musical and Best Original Score 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, Best Play and Best Direction of a Play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' A dancing encyclopedia of clichés set to the music of Earth, Wind and Fire. Numbing (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'SHINING CITY' Quiet, haunting and absolutely glorious. Conor McPherson's impeccably assembled ghost story about being alone in the crowded city of Dublin has been brought to American shores with a first-rate cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Oliver Platt, Martha Plimpton and Peter Scanavino), directed by Robert Falls (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, Best Direction of a Musical 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ARABIAN NIGHT' A blonde in a German apartment building sleeps too much; the super takes an unexpected trip to the desert; and a peeping Tom is properly punished in this stylish comedy whose title turns out to make perfect sense (1:05). The East 13th Street Theater, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 279-4200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'BURLEIGH GRIME$' A feeble-witted comedy by Roger Kirby about dirty dealings on Wall Street, featuring a pair of skilled actors known for recent television work -- Wendie Malick of ''Just Shoot Me'' and Mark Moses of ''Desperate Housewives'' -- and incidental music by David Yazbek, who wrote the score for Broadway's ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels.'' These putative assets are painfully ill served by Mr. Kirby's play, which is long on ludicrous plot and short on fresh humor. (2:10). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'ELVIS AND JULIET'  This opposites-collide tale by Mary Willard and starring her husband, the television actor Fred Willard, looks like community theater and is just as unoriginal. The title characters are young lovers, he the son of an Elvis impersonator, she the daughter of overeducated snobs. Fred dons an Elvis suit, but it's not enough (2:15). Abingdon Theater Arts Complex, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'THE MOST WONDERFUL LOVE' Blue Coyote Theater Group has a rollicking good time with this inventive tale of domestic disintegration by Matthew Freeman. Mother (Lenni Benicaso) and Father (Frank Anderson), after long years together, decide to ''unmarry,'' which isn't quite the same as divorce but just as unsettling for their already unsettled youngest child (Josephine Stewart). But that doesn't begin to convey how nutty this play is. Access Theater, 380 Broadway, at White Street, TriBeCa; (212) 868-4444. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'NERVE' In Adam Szymkowicz's romantic comedy, an online couple's first date is a frightening but satisfyingly comic escalation of confessions and demands (1:00). 14th Street Y, 344 East 14th Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444.(Gates)</p>
        <p>'NOT A GENUINE BLACK MAN' Brian Copeland's solo memoir about his African-American family moving into a white suburb in the early 1970's is an engaging, if stiltedly performed, show (1:30). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'NOTHING' A morsel of catnip for Anglophiles, flavorfully adapted by Andrea Hart from the novel by Henry Green. Simon Dutton and Sophie Ward play onetime lovers contemplating the possible marriage of their children in this comedy of manners about the string of upheavals that a romance in one generation causes in another (1:40). The 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SANDRA BERNHARD: EVERYTHING BAD AND BEAUTIFUL' Sandra Bernhard was a proverbial rock star long before headline-making folks in even the most prosaic walks of life were being referred to as such. Her new show, a collection of songs interspersed with musings on her life and on public figures ranging from Britney Spears to Condoleezza Rice, is casual to the point of being offhand. That said, it's invigorating to be in the presence of a true original (2:00). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, at Union Square, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SATELLITES' This tough-minded, soft-hearted and very likable play by Diana Son (''Stop Kiss'') portrays a world in which traditional ethnic, social, economic and sexual boundaries have become so porous that people are never quite sure who or where they are. Sandra Oh and Kevin Carroll play a couple who move into a Brooklyn brownstone that refuses (literally) to stay still. Michael Greif directs the appropriately fluid ensemble. (1:40). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SOME GIRL(S)' A slight and sour comedy from Neil LaBute that once again puts a morally bankrupt man under the microscope and watches him squirm. The central specimen is here played by Eric McCormack, who as a thoughtless heterosexual gives much the same performance he did as a thoughtful homosexual on ''Will and Grace.'' Jo Bonney directs a cast that also includes Fran Drescher, Judy Reyes, Brooke Smith and Maura Tierney as women done wrong by the same man (1:40). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'STOPPING TRAFFIC' The actress Mary Pat Gleason's endearing one-woman show about making movies (and just getting through life) while bipolar is a play with both a message and some hearty laughs (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, (212) 353-0303. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE WATER'S EDGE' In a bold surgical endeavor that recalls the experiments of the mad Dr. Frankenstein, Theresa Rebeck has tried to transplant the big, blood-engorged heart of a Greek tragedy into the slender body of a modest American comic drama. The resulting hybrid runs amok in a stylishly acted production, directed by Will Frears and starring Kate Burton and Tony Goldwyn (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BACK OF THE THROAT' An Arab-American playwright, Yussef El Guindi, addressing the harassment of Arab-Americans after Sept. 11? Interesting. But the play would have been even more interesting if the harassers were something other than cardboard characters out of the J. Edgar Hoover closet (1:15). Flea Theater, 41 White Street, TriBeCa, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DOUBT, A PARABLE' John Patrick Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions in the clash between the head of a parochial school and the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge (1:30). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'AMERICANA ABSURDUM and THE COMPLETE LOST WORKS OF SAMUEL BECKETT  '  'The Complete Lost Works of Samuel Beckett ' consists of affectionate and hilarious short spoofs of Beckett's spare, rigorous and brooding dramas, as well as tedious segues involving mock threats of legal action against the spoofers. 'Americana Absurdum' is an interestingly glib, deeply cynical satire of stereotypical American greed, rapaciousness and narcissism whose serious purposes are unfortunately clouded by a production invested much more in style than in sense (1:45). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closing on Sunday. (Jonathan Kalb)</p>
        <p>'ASSISTED LOVING' This warm and witty monologue by Bob Morris, who contributes the Age of Dissonance column to the Sunday Styles section of The New York Times, is performed by the author, who chronicles his widowed father's and his own search for love in and around New York. Engaging, subtle and winning (1:10). Daryl Roth Theater, D-Lounge, 103 East 15th Street, at Union Square, (212) 239-6200; closing on Monday. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>* 'AWAKE AND SING!' (Tony Award, Best Play Revival 2006) Dreams and disappointments, hopes and fears, encouraging words and bitter putdowns clash by day and night in Clifford Odets's turbulent comedy-drama about a Jewish family struggling to stay afloat in the 1930's. A gifted roster of performers -- including Mark Ruffalo, Lauren Ambrose, Zoë Wanamaker and Ben Gazzara -- manage to locate the dreaming centers of their characters, buried beneath layers of political sloganeering, everyday gripes or street slang. And even when the focus occasionally blurs in Bartlett Sher's ultimately moving revival, Odets's zesty dialogue is a joy to hear (2:30). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CAGE LOVE' The new thriller by Christopher Denham -- star of ''Red Light Winter'' -- is a compulsively watchable, sometimes ridiculous drama about a man who becomes increasingly suspicious of his wife-to-be (1:30). Rattlestick Theater, 224 Waverly Place, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444; closing on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'IN THE MATTER OF J. ROBERT OPPENHEIMER'  In the title role, Thomas Jay Ryan makes morality, in its truest sense, look fashionable. This is a long but frequently gripping play of literate talk and real ideas (2:45). The Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444; closing on Tuesday. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'STUFF HAPPENS'  Daniel Sullivan's sharp, invigorating production of David Hare's journalistic drama about the road to war in Iraq is conducted on the modest scale of a town-hall meeting. The characters (who have names like Bush and Blair) seem less like destiny-shaping gods than the ego trippers in your office. If that means they're too close for comfort, then ''Stuff Happens'' is doing its job (2:50). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE THREEPENNY OPERA' Presented as a long, pansexual orgy, Scott Elliot's numbing revival of the Brecht-Weill classic feels like a party where the hangover begins almost as soon as the evening does. The starry cast includes Alan Cumming (as Mac the Knife) and a Dietrich-like Cyndi Lauper, though only Jim Dale and Nellie McKay appear to have a clue as to what the show is about (2:40). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'WAITING FOR GODOT' Vladimir (Wendell Pierce) and Estragon (J. Kyle Manzay) wait and wait, but in this version they're soaking wet, their desolate plot being surrounded by water. A familiar play is injected with surprises (2:00). Harlem School for the Arts, 645 St. Nicho las Avenue, near 141st Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 864-4444; closing tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'bombon-EL PERRO' (No rating, 96 minutes, in Spanish) A lonely, unemployed, middle-aged man finds a glimmer of hope when he acquires a purebred show dog in this sweet, gritty neo-realist fable from Argentina. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'DOWN IN THE VALLEY' (R, 114 minutes) This allegorical neo-western set in the San Fernando Valley has dreams as big as the fantasies that consume its protagonist, a Stetson-wearing suburban cowboy (Edward Norton) who is not what he appears to be. How much you like it will depend on your appetite for the kind of cultural metaphors that David Jacobson flings onto the screen with a reckless abandon. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LAND OF THE BLIND' (R, 111 minutes) Watching this simplistic Orwellian fable set in a composite Everycountry that swings politically from extreme right to extreme left is like poring over a quadruple exposure. It's a jumble of ideas and images. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'LOVERBOY' (R, 86 minutes) This cautionary mother-child drama, directed by Kevin Bacon, is a star vehicle for his wife, Kyra Sedgwick, who plays a pathologically possessive single mother. After starting out warm and fuzzy, this tonally uncertain film stealthily pulls out the rug until you suddenly find yourself standing on a cold stone floor, barefoot and shivering. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'LA MOUSTACHE' (No rating, 86 minutes, in French) Emmanuel Carrière's psychological mystery prepares you to bask in one of those sexy, bittersweet marital comedies that are a hallmark of sophisticated French cinema. Then, by degrees, it subverts those expectations to spiral down a rabbit hole of ambiguity and doubt. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE OMEN' (R, 110 minutes) The supremely unnecessary remake of ''The Omen,'' the 1976 horror show that, along with ''Rosemary's Baby'' and ''The Exorcist,'' plunked everyone's favorite baddie, Satan, into the Hollywood mainstream, wants to capitalize on the tabloid theology in the air. Except for a few contemporary touches (the World Trade Center in flames as a portent of Armageddon) it slavishly recycles the original. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>INDIEWIRE: UNDISCOVERED GEMS (Tuesday and Wednesday) This eight-month-long series presents film-festival features that have not found theatrical distributors. This month's movie is Arin Crumley and Susan Buice's ''Four Eyed Monsters,'' about a couple who take a new approach to romantic interactivity and truly become one person. Cinema Village, 12th Street between University Place and Fifth Avenue, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>STANLEY KUBRICK RETROSPECTIVE (Through July 9) The Museum of the Moving Image's five-week series continues this weekend with ''Lolita'' (1962), in which James Mason plays Vladimir Nabokov's Humbert Humbert, romancing an adolescent girl, and ''Dr. Strangelove, or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb'' (1963), Kubrick's nuclear-weapons comedy starring Peter Sellers. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues this weekend with ''Kagemusha'' (1980), starring Tatsuya Nakadai as a small-time thief hired to impersonate a medieval warlord. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ASIAN FILM FESTIVAL (Through July 1) Subway Cinema's fifth annual festival of high-grossing and/or award-winning new movies continues at Anthology Film Archives. The weekend's films, all from 2005, include ''The Great Yokai War,'' which has been described as Takashi Miike's ''Lord of the Rings''; ''Cromartie High School,'' a Japanese spoof of juvenile delinquent movies; and ''Linda Linda Linda,'' about Japanese high school girls (and one Korean) who form a band. 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, and ImaginAsian Theater, 239 East 59th Street, (212) 371-6682; $9. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NORDIC NOIR: CRIME DRAMAS FROM SWEDEN AND DENMARK (Through Aug. 10) The American Scandinavian Foundation is screening ''Henning Mankell's Kurt Wallander Mysteries,'' television films written by Mr. Mankell, the author of the internationally best-selling Wallander novels. In Wednesday's film, ''The African,'' a black man's body is found on a train that originated in Wallander's Swedish hometown. Scandinavia House, 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212) 879-9779; $8. (Gates)</p>
        <p>TOMORROWLAND: CAL ARTS IN MOVING PICTURES (Through Aug. 13) The Museum of Modern Art's three-decade survey of films and videos by former students at the California Institute of the Arts continues. This weekend's features include William Jones's ''Massillon'' (1991), a gay road movie, and ''Tony Oursler: Pioneering Videos,'' which includes ''Life of Phillis'' (1979), Mr. Oursler's psychosexual soap opera. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE VISION THAT CHANGED CINEMA: MICHELANGELO ANTONIONI (Through Thursday) BAMcinématek's tribute to Antonioni nears its end with three films this weekend. ''Zabriskie Point'' (1970) is his view of the American 1960's counterculture, complete with campus riots. ''L'Éclisse'' (1962) is a love story with angst, starring Monica Vitti and Alain Delon. ''Red Desert'' (1964) also stars Ms. Vitti, this time as a mentally ill housewife. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>AFI (Tonight) AFI gives its slithery, death-and-gloom-obsessed songs a jolt of fierce energy by reaching back to the anthemic hard-core punk of 1980's groups like Agnostic Front (as well as to 90's pop-punkers like Green Day). The recipe works: last week, on the strength of its catchy single ''Miss Murder,'' the band's new album, ''Decemberunderground'' (Interscope), went to No. 1. Also on the bill are Dillinger Escape Plan, which plays an impossibly complex kind of punk-jazz, and Nightmare of You. At 6:45, Roseland, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $25. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ALLMAN BROTHERS, DEREK TRUCKS BAND (Tuesday) Derek Trucks, who is starting to take on a role similar to the young Eric Clapton's -- that of a phenomenally gifted, graceful blues-rock guitarist whose presence makes anything better -- does double duty here, playing with the Southern-rock granddaddies the Allman Brothers and also opening the show with his own group. At 7 p.m., Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000; $20 to $65. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE (Monday) Atmosphere is a Minneapolis-based hip-hop group led by Slug, whose keenly written rhymes convey a gloomy sensibility more commonly associated with underground rock. With Brother Ali and Los Nativos. 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20. (Kelefa Sanneh)</p>
        <p>BLUE CHEER (Tonight) On a few gloriously untidy albums in the late 1960's and early 70's, Blue Cheer followed the blunter edges of Jimi Hendrix's sound into a bludgeoning kind of primordial heavy metal, and played it with an un-self-conscious glee that made the band sound like cavemen discovering fire. With Soldiers of Fortune and Titan. At 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAZILIAN GIRLS (Tuesday) Electronica, a live rhythm section and a wildly cosmopolitan spirit meet a charismatic and unpredictable singer, Sabina Sciubba, in the Brazilian Girls. The music dips into reggae, samba, funk and house, never staying in one place long. With Gold Streets and Adam Deitch Project. Pier 54, Hudson River at 13th Street; free. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>CALEXICO (Tuesday) This collective from Tucson, centered on the guitarist and singer Joey Burns and the drummer John Convertino, elegantly mingles dry alt-country with surf guitar, mariachi and a folk-flavored psychedelia like that of the 1960's band Love. With Jason Collett, a sometime member of the Toronto indie collective Broken Social Scene, who draws inspiration from Bob Dylan and the Allman Brothers, among others. At 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DEVOTCHKA (Tomorrow) DeVotchKa, from Denver, is the most musically versatile band of the Gypsy-punk trendlet of the last few years. It does its share of wild fiddling and rug-cutting, but also plays a lot of moody, carefully textured ballads that can recall the Tindersticks. The band has a new mini-album with versions of Velvet Underground and Frank Sinatra songs, and recorded the score to a film at Sundance this year. With Norfolk &amp; Western and the Mendoza Line. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $14. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ESPERS, BRIGHTBLACK MORNING LIGHT (Tonight) These two bands are part of a new wave that aims to revive the sound and the utopianism of 1960's folk. Espers, a mostly acoustic sextet from Philadelphia, plays airy English folk à la Fairport Convention, sometimes surrounding it with a foreboding drone. Brightblack Morning Light's sound is more intriguing because it's harder to place: an electric hum; warbling keyboards that evoke funk; and ecstatic, breathy chants. The songs on its new, self-titled album on Matador were written, the band has said, while living in tents in Northern California. With Mariee Souix. At 9:30, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FEIST, JASON COLLETT, BUCK 65 (Sunday) Central Park SummerStage's annual Canada Day concert (well, close enough: the holiday is actually July 1) includes two singers whose indie-rock bona fides includes time with the great Toronto collective Broken Social Scene. Leslie Feist, a k a Feist, is a cosmopolitan chanteuse who knows how to rock a club, playing bossa nova, folk, Françoise Hardy bonbons and her specialty, the sad disco ballad; Jason Collett draws inspiration from a narrower field, including Bob Dylan and the Allman Brothers. Also on the bill is Buck 65, a raspy rapper from Nova Scotia who rhymes about the backwoods life. At 3 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FIERY FURNACES (Thursday) In a smart scramble of eras and attitudes, the Fiery Furnaces back flippantly surreal lyrics with blues riffs, teetering analog synthesizers, parlor piano and punky noise, coming up with a 21st-century urban skiffle. With Man Man and Standing Nudes. At 6 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Wednesday and Thursday) There are no small emotions for Diamanda Galás, whose compositions are music theater with its rawest nerves exposed. She takes up fear and rage, mourning and vengeance; her voice can reach operatic heights or slice through a room with primal moans and shrieks and sobs. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* JOSÉ GONZÁLEZ, JUANA MOLINA, PSAPP (Thursday) Connoisseurs of hip television soundtracks might recognize some of the music on this bill. José González, an Argentinean Swede, plays haunting, austere guitar confessions with precision picking and a deadpan hush; his song ''Crosses'' was played in the soap-opera season finale of ''The OC'' this spring. Juana Molina is another whispery Argentine, whose gentle, swirling lullabies draw a listener directly into her reveries. The English duo Psapp places soft vocals over beats constructed from found sounds like splashing water, creaking floorboards and even squeaking cats, creating a kind of hyperintimate electronica; ''Grey's Anatomy'' uses one of Psapp's songs as its theme. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>I-THREES (Tomorrow) The I-Threes were the great reggae backup singers of the 1970's, formed to support Bob Marley and the Wailers. The members -- Rita Marley, Bob Marley's widow; Judy Mowatt, who was already a pop star in Jamaica when the group was founded; and Marcia Griffiths -- play a rare group date at the Apollo Theater. Also on the bill is Thandiswa, a singer in the trailblazing South African kwaito group Bongo Maffin, who on her new solo album, ''Zabalaza'' (Escondida), mingles traditional xhosa rhythms with hip-hop, gospel and reggae. At 8 p.m., 253 West 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 531-5305 or (212) 307-7171; $45 to $55. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOE JACKSON (Thursday) In songs like ''Is She Really Going Out With Him?'' and ''Steppin' Out'' in the late 1970's and early 80's, Joe Jackson made his reputation as a cold-eyed master of British soul, bringing a cutting new-wave minimalism to stories of lonely lovers who cry that they are ''so tired of all the darkness in our lives.'' Since then he has proved remarkably versatile, releasing, among other projects, settings of the Seven Deadly Sins and a Grammy-winning recording of his Symphony No. 1. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JAY-Z (Sunday) Three years ago Jay-Z, the rap prince turned record executive, announced his retirement from performing, but he keeps finding ways to stay in the game: albums with R. Kelly and Linkin Park, some guest spots, a big radio-sponsored concert or two. Here he shows that he does not need any ruse but himself. He celebrates the 10th anniversary of his debut album, ''Reasonable Doubt,'' by performing it beginning to end. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KEANE (Tonight) This British band consists of just a drummer, a singer and an awfully hard-working keyboardist, but manages to flesh out songs of yearning and self-pity with rich sonorities and sharp hooks that make you swear that there's a guitar in there somewhere. Keane has headlined Radio City Music Hall, but plays this much smaller show to promote its lush and mawkish new album, ''Under the Iron Sea'' (Island). At 8, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ARTHUR LEE BENEFIT (Tonight) In Los Angeles in the mid-1960's, the band Love, led by Arthur Lee, perfected a distinctly lyrical variety of psychedelia steeped in folk and garage-rock. Now 61, Mr. Lee is suffering from leukemia, and the roster of musicians at this benefit concert reveals some of his wide influence: Robert Plant, Ian Hunter, Ryan Adams, Nils Lofgren, Yo La Tengo, Garland Jeffreys and Flashy Python and the Body Snatchers, a new group featuring Alec Ounsworth of Clap Your Hands Say Yeah. At 8, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; $53.50 to $128.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LIARS (Tomorrow and Monday) The Liars are an avant-garde rock band the way all avant-garde rock bands should be: noisy, challenging and unpredictable. It began playing cold, paranoid punk-funk and has gradually moved into ever eerier and more disorienting territory, as if trying to eliminate any trace of conventional rock 'n' roll from its sound. Tomorrow the band plays with one of its stylistic ancestors, Alan Vega of the great 1970's noise-punk minimalists Suicide; tomorrow and Monday's shows also include the Apes, a chaos-loving band from Washington that always keeps one yeti-like foot in Black Sabbath stomps. Tomorrow at 9 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; Monday at 8 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780. Each show is $15 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NATALIE MacMASTER AND FRIENDS (Tonight) Ms. MacMaster, a fiddler whose repertory leans from Celtic music into bluegrass, leads a small group of musicians in a celebration of the Celtic music of her homeland, the Eastern Canadian island of Cape Breton. She performs with the powerful Irish-American Susan McKeown, the fiddler Donnell Leahy (who is also Ms. MacMaster's husband), the cellist Natalie Haas and the singer Catherine Russell. At 7:30, Celebrate Brooklyn, Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882; $3 suggested donation. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MADONNA (Wednesday and Thursday) Part 10 (or so), in which our heroine strikes such poses as Jesus on the cross, James Brown in his cape and John Travolta in his white disco suit, all while performing dance-floor hits in new remixes and reconfigurations. Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $64.50 to $354.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>AUDRA McDONALD (Thursday) Ms. McDonald sings Broadway fare with a 33-piece orchestra; her program is likely to include what she calls songs associated with the ''two Barbaras,'' Cook and Streisand. With the gospel singer Liz McComb. At 7 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TIM McGRAW AND FAITH HILL (Tonight and tomorrow night) The first couple of country-pop flash have recently acquired a slight and unexpected political edge -- though not much controversy -- by criticizing the government's response to Hurricane Katrina. At 8, Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $49.50 to $99.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ONE RING ZERO, LAS RUBIAS DEL NORTE, SLAVIC SOUL PARTY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Barbès, a cozy bar and cabaret in Park Slope, serves as an incubator for a group of smart and casually eclectic musicians, the type who might mingle a little Gypsy music with their norteño. Now the club has started a record label to extend its support (and brand name), and offers a showcase this weekend. One Ring Zero, tonight at 9, has set words by authors like Jonathan Lethem, Margaret Atwood and Rick Moody to kitchen-sink songs with toy piano and theremin. Las Rubias del Norte, at 10:30, play boleros, cumbias and other Latin styles, elegantly arranged for a small band and two songbird sopranos. Slavic Soul Party, tomorrow night at 10, plays a raucous mix of Eastern European music, funk and jazz. Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; $8 suggested donation. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PANIC! AT THE DISCO, DRESDEN DOLLS (Wednesday and Thursday) Panic! at the Disco, from Las Vegas, were discovered by Pete Wentz of Fall Out Boy, who quickly signed the band to his own label, Decaydence. It's not hard to see why: the group has the slick runway look of the Killers (also from Las Vegas); the muscular, gushy emo-rock sound of Fall Out Boy; and a knack for song titles that could be Oscar Wilde epigrams, like ''The Only Difference Between Martyrdom and Suicide Is Press Coverage'' and ''Lying Is the Most Fun a Girl Can Have Without Taking Her Clothes Off.'' The Dresden Dolls play elaborate, gender-bending cabaret-punk vamps and dress the part. At 7:30 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* REFUGEE ALL STARS OF SIERRA LEONE (Tonight) These six musicians, ranging from a teenage rapper to a guitarist in his 50's, fled civil war in their homeland for a refugee camp in rural Guinea. They formed a band there four years ago, and tell their stories in songs tinged with soul and reggae. A documentary about the group, made by Zach Niles and Banker White, will be shown after its performance. At 7 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRUCE SPRINGSTEEN WITH THE SEEGER SESSIONS BAND (Tomorrow and Sunday) A hootenanny of musicians, playing banjos, accordions, fiddles and guitars, accompanies Bruce Springsteen in folk songs of work, hardscrabble survival and political anger -- the Depression-era ''How Can a Poor Man Stand Such Times and Live'' gets a Hurricane Katrina rewrite -- from his latest album, ''We Shall Overcome: The Seeger Sessions'' (Columbia). At 7:30 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698; $46.25 to $91.75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* THE STREETS, LADY SOVEREIGN (Tuesday) The best and weirdest of new British hip-hop: the Streets, a k a Mike Skinner, is a loquacious rapper whose monotonous delivery can sometimes make him sound like a robot learning to rhyme, and Lady Sovereign, a k a Louise Harman, is a teenage firecracker who is one of the most entertaining exponents of grime, a hyperactive rap-plus-techno British subgenre. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Cabaret</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday) Even when swinging out, this Lady of a Thousand Songs remains an impressionist with special affinities for Thelonious Monk and bossa nova. At 2 p.m., the Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $58, including brunch at noon. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* Eartha Kitt (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday nights) The latest edition of an act Ms. Kitt has been performing for decades is the lightest, swiftest and funniest one to date, and that's all to the good. More than ever, the singer, now a glamorous 79, pauses to poke fun at her status as the greatest and wittiest of all singing tigresses. At 8:45, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 10:45, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600; $100. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* JESSICA MOLASKEY (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday nights) A theater singer with jazz chops, Ms. Molaskey combines sophisticated wit, fierce intelligence and a lightly swinging voice that hovers on the keen edge between happy and sad. A hybrid of the bossa nova standard ''Desafinado'' and Billy Joel's ''Summer, Highland Falls'' performed Brazilian style, is the pinnacle of a show whose material she describes as ''limbo songs.'' At 9, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, the Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $50 cover; $60 prix fixe dinner required at all 9 p.m. shows; $20 minimum at the late shows tonight and tomorrow night. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>TIM BERNE DUOS (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Berne, an adventurous alto saxophonist, has always had some of his strongest musical connections with drummers. Next week he goes head to head with two of them: the suggestive and fluid Gerald Cleaver (Wednesday) and the wry, responsive Tom Rainey (Thursday). On Wednesday at 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. On Thursday at 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDY BEY (Wednesday through July 1) Intimacy is a hallmark of Mr. Bey's vocal style, which alternates between a rich baritone and a burnished falsetto. He's also a fine pianist, as he'll surely demonstrate here. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BRAZIL NIGHTS (Tonight and tomorrow night) The superb guitarist Romero Lubambo leads two Brazilian jazz acts this weekend, and neither should be missed. Tonight it's Trio da Paz, with the bassist Nilson Matta and the drummer Duduka da Fonseca; the pianist Kenny Barron will join them as a special guest. Tomorrow the setting will be more intimate: just Mr. Lubambo and the singer Luciana Souza, as on her ''Brazilian Duos'' albums. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $30. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIM BLACK'S ALAS NO AXIS (Sunday) Noise rock, along with numerous strains of music made on laptops, exerts a heavy influence on Mr. Black's music, as his new album, ''Dogs of Great Indifference'' (Winter &amp; Winter), confirms. But tuneful lyricism and jazz improvisation also have a place in his working band, which features his drums and electronics, on the same plane as Chris Speed's tenor saxophone and clarinet, Skuli Sverrisson's electric bass and Hilmar Jensson's guitar. At 8 and 9:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* A SALUTE TO CACHAO: MASTER OF THE MAMBO (Tomorrow) In the 1940's Israel Lopez, known as Cachao, helped define modern Cuban music; he is the most influential Latin bassist of all time, and one of Cuban music's most important bandleaders. His signature descargas will serve as the common language of this tribute, which is well stocked with artists like the conga drummer Carlos Valdez, the trumpeter Alfredo Armenteros, the flutist Dave Valentin and the trombonist Jimmy Bosch. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $35 to $85. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY CHILDS JAZZ-CHAMBER ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) Mr. Childs, an accomplished pianist, composer and producer, favors a billowy sound in his own music, which sometimes drifts perilously close to New Age. But beneath a genteel atmosphere of piano, saxophone, harp, guitar and strings lurks the action-oriented rhythm team of Scott Colley on bass and Brian Blade on drums. At 8:30 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3303; $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AVISHAI COHEN BAND (Sunday) Mr. Cohen is an assertive trumpeter with a taste for modernism, and he keeps good company here: the alto saxophonist Yosvany Terry, the guitarist Lionel Loueke, the pianist Jason Lindner, the bassist Omer Avital and the drummer Daniel Freedman. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN COWHERD, JOHN PATITUCCI, BRIAN BLADE (Tuesday and Wednesday) Mr. Blade, the lithe and subtle drummer, serves as the fulcrum of this impressionistic trio, which features two of his frequent collaborators. Mr. Cowherd plays piano and writes music for Mr. Blade's Fellowship band, while Mr. Patitucci, the bassist, plays with Mr. Blade in the working band led by the saxophonist Wayne Shorter. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, near Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE DOUGLAS GROUP (Sunday) Mr. Douglas, the trumpeter and composer, taps an aggressive improvisational vein with this assembled quartet, which features the august Henry Grimes and Andrew Cyrille on bass and drums. J. D. Allen, a probing tenor saxophonist, rounds out the ensemble. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES FINN'S NDA NANAA (Thursday) On his recent album, ''Plaza de Toros'' (Clean Feed), the tenor saxophonist James Finn teased out a connection between bullfighting and free jazz, with appropriate doses of bravado and humor. Here he steps into the ring with the trombonist Steve Swell, the pianist Gordon Beeferman and the percussionist Jackson Krall. At 8 and 10 p.m., Jimmy's Restaurant, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL FRISELL TRIO/PETRA HADEN AND KELLY JOE PHELPS (Tonight) Rustic Americana is the prevailing atmosphere of this concert, thanks to Mr. Frisell, one of jazz's most imaginative guitarists, and to the duo of Ms. Haden, a singer, and Mr. Phelps, a guitarist and singer-songwriter. Given the overlapping histories onstage -- Mr. Frisell has recorded with both of his fellow headliners -- it should be a freewheeling evening. At 8, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, www.symphonyspace.org; $23 and $28. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIZZY GILLESPIE ALL-STAR BIG BAND (Through Sunday) Bebop's goateed ambassador did some of his best work with big bands, a fact that this repertory ensemble, led by his former trombonist and arranger Slide Hampton, happily exploits. The band includes other veterans of Gillespie's employ -- like the saxophonists James Moody, Frank Wess and Jimmy Heath -- as well as Roy Hargrove, the trumpeter enlisted here to fill his shoes. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAVION GLOVER &amp; THE OTHERZ /ROBERT GLASPER TRIO (Tomorrow) Mr. Glover, the dynamo of rhythmic tap dance, sees himself as a jazz percussionist, and plays the part in his ensemble the Otherz. Mr. Glasper is a pianist given to silvery modern flourishes and gospel intimations, and he leads a remarkably cohesive trio with the bassist Vicente Archer and the drummer Damion Reid. At 7:30 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell, Ninth Street and Prospect Park West, Park Slope, Brooklyn, www.celebratebrooklyn.org; free. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HAPPY APPLE (Sunday) This Minneapolis-based trio fashions a hardy yet elastic amalgam of indie-rock and post-bop, with doses of sardonic humor. Its sound is served equally by Michael Lewis's saxophones, Erik Fratzke's electric bass and David King's drums. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; cover, $12, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HERBIE'S WORLD: HERBIE HANCOCK AND FRIENDS (Tonight) Mr. Hancock is one of jazz's most successful chameleons, in addition to being one of its finest pianists. This impressive concert gives him the opportunity to dig into fluid pianism (in duets with Gonzalo Rubalcaba); ambitiously abstract chamber improvisation (in a quartet with the tenor saxophonist Wayne Shorter, the bassist Dave Holland and the drummer Brian Blade); earthy rhythm section work (in a trio with the bassist Ron Carter and the drummer Jack DeJohnette); and deep-rooted groove (in a band with the guitarist Lionel Loueke and the bassists Matt Garrison and Marcus Miller, among others). At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $40 to $100. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MAT MANERI QUINTET (Thursday) Mr. Maneri has a dark, hollow tone on viola and a generous approach to collective improvisation. His ensemble consists of Joe Carton on trumpet, Matt Moran on vibraphone, John Hebert on bass and Randy Peterson on drums. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* WYNTON MARSALIS SEXTET/SEPTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Marsalis is a ubiquitous presence at Frederick P. Rose Hall, but he doesn't often headline at its most intimate space. Tonight and tomorrow he plays Dizzy's Club with a six-piece band culled from the ranks of his Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra; on Sunday he leads a seven-piece, comprising Wycliffe Gordon on trombone, Wes Anderson and Victor Goines on saxophones, Richard Johnson on piano, Carlos Henriquez on bass and Herlin Riley on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIYA MASAOKA TRIO (Tomorrow) Ms. Masaoka brings an avant-garde sensibility to the koto, a Japanese zither; she also works with a laptop and with the cellist Okkyung Lee and the pianist Sylvie Courvoisier. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* PAUL MOTIAN BAND (Tuesday through July 2) This luminous ensemble consists of two contrasting pairs of improvisers (the tenor saxophonists Mark Turner and Chris Cheek, and the guitarists Steve Cardenas and Ben Monder); a couple of stabilizers (Jacob Bro and Jerome Harris, also guitarists); a lone anchor (the bassist Ben Street); and a mastermind (Mr. Motian, on drums). The band's last ECM album was excellent; its last Village Vanguard appearance, in January, was even better. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20; $25 on Friday and Saturday, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEWIS NASH QUINTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Nash is an engaging and subtle drummer who brings a crisp sense of swing to any setting. His ensemble consists of Jeremy Pelt on trumpet, Steve Wilson on alto and soprano saxophones, Gerald Clayton on piano and Peter Washington on bass. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $25 ($20 on Sunday), with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARTURO O'FARRILL TRIO (Tomorrow) Mr. O'Farrill, the pianist and bandleader of Lincoln Center's Afro-Latin Jazz Orchestra, knows how to energize smaller settings; in this trio he works with Alex Blake on bass, and Jamie Affoumado on drums. At 9:15 and 10:40 p.m. and midnight, Puppets Jazz Bar, 294 Fifth Avenue, at First Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 499-2627, www.puppetsjazz.com; $5, with a two-drink minimum (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EIVIND OPSVIK'S OVERSEAS (Wednesday) Mr. Opsvik is a Norwegian bassist and composer who carefully balances avant-gardism against a poplike lyricism, as he demonstrates here with a working band composed of Tony Malaby on tenor saxophone, Jacob Sacks on piano and Kenny Wollesen on drums. At 6:30 p.m., Scandinavia House. 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212) 879-9779, www.scandinaviahouse.org; cover, $7; members, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARIO PAVONE QUARTET (Wednesday) Mr. Pavone, a bassist and composer with an expansive worldview, leads a cadre of fellow colorists: Ron Horton on trumpet, Tony Malaby on saxophones and Gerald Cleaver on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HERLIN RILEY AND FRIENDS (Tuesday through July 2) Few contemporary jazz drummers groove as naturally as Mr. Riley, who presides here over a quartet composed of other strong musicians with ties to Wynton Marsalis: the tenor saxophonist and clarinetist Victor Goines, the pianist Eric Reed and the bassist Reginald Veal. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 p.m. set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL STEWART TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Though he is known primarily as a sideman, Mr. Stewart, a drummer, has a composer's vocabulary, as he proved with a pair of underrated Blue Note albums in the 1990's. He connects here with Larry Goldings on Hammond B-3 organ and Kevin Hayes on piano, mining a post-bop sound that owes more than a little to rhythm and blues. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BUSTER WILLIAMS AND SOMETHING MORE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Williams's bass playing is the anchor but not the focal point of this chamber-jazz quintet, with his longtime rhythm-section partner Lenny White on drums; Marcus Strickland on tenor and soprano saxophone; Stefon Harris on vibraphone; and on piano either George Colligan (tonight) or Anthony Wonsey (tomorrow). At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'THE BARBER OF SEVILLE' (Thursday) The Lake George Opera opens its season at the Saratoga Performing Arts Center with Rossini's hoary chestnut, sung in Italian with projected supertitles. Other offerings this summer include ''Pagliacci'' and Ned Rorem's ''Our Town.'' At 8 p.m., Spa Little Theater, Saratoga Springs, N.Y., (518) 587-3330; $48 to $70; $5 off for children and 65+. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'GLORY DENIED' (Monday) The invaluable Center for Contemporary Opera, which helps living composers place their operas, either completed or in-progress works, before the public, presents a staged reading of Tom Cipullo's ''Glory Denied.'' This Vietnam-era story is based on an oral history by the journalist Tom Philpott about Col. Jim Thompson, America's longest-held prisoner of war. When Act I was presented in 2004 as part of the New York City Opera's Vox readings, Mr. Cipullo's unsentimental handling of the story was complemented by his hard-edged, neo-Romantic musical style. Though this staged reading will present the complete opera, the cast will be accompanied only by piano. At 8 p.m., the Thalia at Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400; $20. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight the pianist Jeffrey Swann concludes the overview of Chopin he has been presenting all this month, with a program that includes the F minor Fantasy, the Sonata No. 2, the second and third Scherzos and the Ballade No. 4. Tomorrow the Amernet String Quartet takes over for a program of Shostakovich, Fredrick Kaufman and Brahms. On Sunday a more varied ensemble -- guitar, accordion, violin, piano and bass -- offers a program of Astor Piazzolla's music. And on Thursday Jeanne Mallow, a violist, and Vladimir Valjarevic, a pianist, collaborate on works by Brahms, Schumann, Rachmaninoff and William Keith Rogers. Tonight and tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30, Sunday at 4 p.m., Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35 for all but the Sunday concert, which is $40. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CARAMOOR (Tomorrow and Sunday) On the shady grounds of a former estate, this Westchester summer festival begins its season with its excellent resident orchestra, the Orchestra of St. Luke's, under Peter Oundjian, in a festive selection of music: the overture to the unfinished opera ''Pope Joan'' by Caramoor's composer-in-residence this year, John Musto; Beethoven's Eighth; and the ever-popular Mendelssohn Violin Concerto, with the ever-popular Joshua Bell. On Sunday Peter Schickele presents ''P. D. Q. Bach: His Life, Legacy and Leftovers.'' Tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday afternoon at 4:30, Venetian Theater, Caramoor, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-1252; $40 to $92.50 tomorrow, $19 to $49 on Sunday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* CONNECTICUT EARLY MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow) This annual festival offers consistently varied and enlightening programs. Tonight chamber works by Couperin are the focal points in a program of works from the court of Louis XIV. Tomorrow the superb wind ensemble Piffaro plays Spanish and Portuguese Baroque works. Tonight at 8, Mystic Arts Center, Mystic, Conn.; tomorrow at 8 p.m., Evans Hall, Connecticut College, New London, (860) 444-2419; $26 for a reserved seat, $20 general admission. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>FREE FOR ALL AT TOWN HALL (Sunday) The music is by the guitarist Sharon Isbin and the mezzo-soprano Susanne Mentzner, and the tickets are free. At 5 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 707-8787; tickets are available starting at noon. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL FESTIVAL OF ARTS AND IDEAS (Tonight) Each June since 1996, this festival in New Haven has brought together thinkers, creators and performers from the worlds of theater, dance, art, music, literature and letters. As in past years, music is an important component of this summer's festival, which ends this weekend. Tonight two fine artists, Sarah Rothenberg, playing piano, and John Gibbons, playing harpsichord, juxtapose preludes and fugues by Bach with those by Shostakovich, whose works in this genre were directly inspired by Bach's. At 8, Sprague Memorial Hall, Yale University, 470 College Street, (203) 562-5666 or (888) 736-2663; $35. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) In the spirit of its founder, the conductor Jens Nygaard, this ensemble brings together familiar works and scores from off the beaten path. Its guest this week is the violinist Anne Akiko Myers, who joins it for a program that includes the StamitzClarinet Quartet, the Rosetti Sextet and Dvorak's Quintet in G. At 8 p.m., the JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 799-1259; $15. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* MANNES INSTITUTE AND FESTIVAL OF CONTEMPORARY PERFORMANCE (Tonight through Thursday) Having just completed its extensive Beethoven Institute, the Mannes College of Music, the classical music division of the New School, turns its attention to new music. This festival attracts composers and performers, both renowned figures and adventurous students, for 10 days of workshops, master classes and concerts, all open to the public. Tonight the composer and pianist Frederic Rzewski, a galvanizing performer of his own ferocious works, joins the Amernet String Quartet for an all-Rzewski program. Tomorrow the pianist Wilhem Latchoumia, a new-music champion, and the percussionist Daniel Ciampolini, who spent 20 years playing in Pierre Boulez's cutting-edge ensemble, share a program. On Sunday evening the piano duo of Jean-Jacques Balet and Mayumi Kameda perform during the first half of a program that after intermission offers a memorial tribute to the composer Donald Martino, with a roster of performers participating. Tuesday's concert features the percussionist Matthew Gold, the pianist Stephen Gosling and the violinist Curtis Macomber. On Wednesday the percussionist Daniel Druckman, of the New York Philharmonic, joins the Speculum Musicae ensemble in works by Louis Andriessen, Salvatore Sciarrino, Milton Babbitt and others. On Thursday an ensemble from the institute plays works by the Moroccan-born French composer Yan Maresz. At 8 p.m., Mannes College, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 580-0210, Ext. 4884; concerts are $20; $10 for students; master classes and lectures are $8; a pass to all events is $150. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>MAVERICK CONCERTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) This concert series near Woodstock, N.Y., offers its performances in an open-backed barn that allows the sounds of nature to mingle with the music. Tomorrow the festival's director, Alexander Platt , leads the pianist Frederic Chiu and the Maverick Chamber Players in the chamber versions of Mozart's Piano Concertos Nos. 11, 12 and 13. On Sunday the American String Quartet plays Haydn's Quartet in E flat (Op. 76, No. 6), Shostakovich's Quartet No. 11 and Mozart's Quartet in F (K. 590). Tomorrow at 6 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m.; the Maverick Concert Hall, Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217; $20; $5 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MUSIC FESTIVAL OF THE HAMPTONS (Tomorrow and Sunday) A gala concert tomorrow kicks off the 11th season of this piano-loving festival that comes, this year, with a few caveats: its artistic director, Lukas Foss, is not actually taking part in any of the season's concerts (although his music will be played), and some of the tent events are listed as ''pending Town of Southampton permits.'' Permits or no, tomorrow's concert travels a colorful road from Vivaldi to Duke Ellington, with stops at Mozart, Ravel and others along the way. On Sunday afternoon the festival continues with a recital by the 12-year-old pianist and composer Drew Petersen; in the evening the director Daniel Anker will introduce his rather turgid film about the musicians of the Philadelphia Orchestra, ''Music From the Inside Out.'' Tomorrow night at 7:30 (cocktails at 6), Sunday afternoon at 3 and 7, East Hampton Studios, Wainscott, N.Y. (gala concert and Anker film), and Bellport, N.Y. (Petersen recital), (800) 644-4418; tomorrow, $75; $150 for concert and party; Sunday afternoon, $25; Sunday evening, $10; $7 for 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MUSIC MOUNTAIN (Tonight through Sunday) String quartets are a focus of this venerable institution in northwestern Connecticut, and on Sunday the Amernet Quartet performs the second of two weekend concerts, offering Shostakovich's Third, Beethoven's Op. 132 and Mozart's Oboe Quartet in F Major, with the oboist Humbert Lucarelli. Tonight the Saint John's Chorale, a small group 15 years old, makes its debut at the festival under its director, Richard Busch. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday afternoon at 3, Gordon Hall at Music Mountain, Falls Village, Conn., (860) 824-7126; $25 at the door; $22 in advance; $12 for students. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NAUMBURG ORCHESTRAL CONCERTS (Tuesday) This free series in Central Park begins its 101st-anniversary season with a concert that is not, strictly speaking, orchestral. The eclectic woodwind quintet Imani Winds, which describes itself as African-American/Latino, will be joined by the pianist André-Michel Shub for a program with Piazzolla and Paquito D'Rivera on the one hand, and an arrangement of Ravel's ''Tombeau de Couperin'' on the other; the third and fourth hands include a Mozart wind quintet and a piece called ''Umoja'' by the group's flutist, Valerie Coleman. At 7:30 p.m., Naumburg Bandshell, Central Park, midpark at 70th Street, (718) 340-3018. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN BALLET THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow; Monday through Thursday) The last three performances of Kenneth MacMillan's ''Manon'' are tonight and tomorrow, with Diana Vishneva and Vladimir Malakhov scheduled tonight. On Monday begins a weeklong run of ''Swan Lake.'' (The season continues until July 15.) Tonight and tomorrow night, and Monday through Thursday nights, at 8 p.m.; tomorrow and Wednesday at 2 p.m.; Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000 or abt.org; $23 to $163. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* BARD SUMMERSCAPE (Thursday) This summer arts festival opens on Thursday with two new dances by Donna Uchizono, performed by her company and by the guest artist Mikhail Baryshnikov, whose Hell's Kitchen arts center commissioned one piece. Through July 1. The festival runs through Aug. 20. At 8 p.m., Fisher Center, Sosnoff Theater, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y. (845) 758-7900 or summerscape.bard.edu; $25 to $55. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* KIMBERLY BARTOSIK (Tonight through Sunday night) Ms. Bartosik knows there is a world beyond the dance studio, which is what her new ''home in the neon heat,'' described as a meditation on fractured landscapes, addresses. Her company features current and former Merce Cunningham dancers, including Cédric Andrieux, Daniel Squire and Derry Swan. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CATALYST (Wednesday and Thursday) This Minneapolis-based dance company, making its New York debut, will perform ''Heat and Life,'' a multimedia dance about global warming by the company director Emily Johnson. At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; $12 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE: FREE THURSDAYS (Thursday) This first of three free programs will feature multimedia events created by the dancers and designers of the Cedar Lake Contemporary Ballet. At 6 p.m., Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444 (Smarttix) or cedarlakedance.com. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CELEBRATE BROOKLYN! SAVION GLOVER &amp; FRIENDS (Tomorrow) Mr. Glover will jam with guest dancers to music by his jazz band, The Otherz, on a program that also includes a performance by Robert Glasper's jazz trio. At 7:30 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 855-7882; suggested contribution, $3. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CORBINDANCES (Tonight through Sunday night) Patrick Corbin, a former dancer with the Paul Taylor Dance Company, offers the premiere of ''Bathing Jeff, Part I,'' a monologue with movement based on Mr. Corbin's experiences in the worst years of the AIDS epidemic. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $25. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>Fugate/Bahiri Ballet NY (Monday through July 2) Judith Fugate, a former New York City Ballet principal dancer, and her husband, Medhi Bahiri, a former principal at Boston Ballet, formed this chamber company in 1997. Their mission is to present contemporary ballets, and the company's longevity is testament to Ms. Fugate and Mr. Bahiri's shrewd selection of choreographers who make modern, appealing work. This season offers repertory pieces by Thaddeus Davis, Stanton Welch and Toni Pimble, with new works by Francis Patrelle and John Butler. Tuesday at 7.30 p.m., Wednesday through Friday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $36. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>GESTURES DANCE ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) This preprofessional group from the Harbor Conservatory for the Performing Arts presents an evening of work by an alumnus, Darrell Grand Moultrie, who has made pieces for dance companies around the country. At 7:30 p.m., Miller Theater, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 427-2244; $15. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>NEIL GREENBERG (Tonight through Sunday) A revival of ''Not-About-AIDS-Dance,'' a commentary on life, illness and loss, originally produced in 1994, shares the program with the new ''Quartet with Three Gay Men.'' Through June 25. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 4 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077; $25; $15 for students, 65+ and artists. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) There are usually two attractions per week in the main theaters of this bucolic, venerable festival, which runs until Aug. 27. On this opening weekend there is CND2, short for the second company of Nacho Duato's Compañía Nacional de Danza from Madrid. The other attraction is a screening of the acclaimed documentary ''Ballets Russes'' on Friday. On Wednesday and Thursday the Limón Dance Company will be at the larger Ted Shawn Theater, and starting Thursday at the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater is ASzURe &amp; Artists, devoted to the choreography of Aszure Barton. CND2 tonight and tomorrow night at 8, and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m.; and Limón on Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., Shawn Theater; $50. ''Ballet Russes'' tonight and ASzURe on Thursday night, Duke Theater, 8:15 p.m.; $10 for the film, $24 for ASzURe. Ten percent off all tickets for students, 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions can be found at jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>STEPHEN KOPLOWITZ (Today through Sunday) ''Revealed'' seeks to alter perspectives of place, site and scale with the aid of 10 dancers and the optical device known as the camera obscura. At noon, World Financial Center, 220 Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-0505 or worldfinancialcenter.com; free. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* LA MAMA MOVES! (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) This ambitious festival includes four different programs this weekend, in two of La MaMa's honeycombed little theaters. ''Children of Ur'' (tonight) features work by nine individuals and groups, among them Karinne Keithley, David Neumann and Nicky Paraiso. ''Duets'' (tomorrow) showcases dance by five duos, and ''Dancing Divas'' (Sunday) lives up to its name with work by Pat Catterson, Ellen Fisher, Keely Garfield, Sally Gross, Deborah Jowitt, Jodi Melnick, Yvonne Meier and Vicky Shick. And ''Mavericks in Motion'' (Thursday) features dance by Jonah Bokaer, Monica Bill Barnes and Tami Stronach. Tonight at 10, tomorrow and Sunday at 5:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MICHELA MARINO-LERMAN (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Marino-Lerman, a 19-year-old ''Sesame Street'' alumna, and her company will examine existence, public life and education in tap dance. At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736 or dixonplace.org; $12 or T.D.F.; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* THE NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) The closing weekend of the company's spring season, ending on Sunday afternoon with an all-Balanchine program of ''Symphony in C'' and ''Vienna Waltzes.'' All the programs will be conducted by Andrea Quinn, the departing music director. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, tomorrow at 2 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.org; $30 to $86; student rush tickets at $12. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of this winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, has settled into the intimate Theater 80 for this month and next, through July 30. Tonight and tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m.; Sunday at 5 p.m.; Theater 80, 80 St. Mark's Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>OF MOVING COLORS (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company, based in Baton Rouge, La., will perform dances by Pavel Zustiak, Ashleigh Leite, Nick Erickson and the company director, Garland Goodwin Wilson. At 8, Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200 or dnadance.org; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>OUT OF SPACE @ BRICSTUDIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) This occasional series, organized by Marya Wethers, is presented in collaboration with Danspace Project, which suggests a talent-scouting expedition might be in order. The new works on the program are by Keïty Anjoure, Faye Driscoll, Will Rawls and Tamar-kali. At 8:30, BRICstudio, 57 Rockwell Place, second Floor, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 855-7882; $12; $10 for students. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* PASCAL RIOULT DANCE THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Rioult, a former Martha Graham dancer, tends to give his larger-than-life themes and dances a Grahamesque heroism, this time in a program that includes ''If by Chance,'' a world premiere set to a score by Jacques Loussier, a French jazz composer, that reworks Mozart's Concerto No. 23. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org; $38. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SITELINES 2006: DOUGLAS DUNN AND ELKE RINDFLEISCH (Today and Monday through Thursday) This free avant-garde arts festival, also produced by River to River, features Mr. Dunn and Ms. Rindfleisch in paired pieces. At 12:30 p.m., Elevated Acres, 55 Water Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 219-9401. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Folk Art Museum: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' through Sept. 17. The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and cast-off clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,'  through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedekers, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them and souvenir platters, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'VERONESE'S ALLEGORIES: VIRTUE, LOVE AND EXPLORATION IN RENAISSANCE VENICE,' through July 16. Paolo Veronese (1528-88), a superb colorist and one of the most suavely sensuous of Renaissance Venetian painters, used the age-old device of allegory to make abstract concepts visual, often by means of human or mythological figures. In this five-painting show, the first to include all of his large-scale allegories from American collections, high ideals mingle with earthy and sometimes erotic physicality, as in the painting ''Venus and Mars United by Love.'' 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* METropolitan museum of art: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early 19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. (212) 535-7710.(Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. And wait till you see the painted ceramic vessel known as the ''Dazzler Vase,'' with its red and green patterns like jade on fire, you'll understand its name. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Morgan Library and Museum: 'Masterworks from the Morgan,'  through Sept. 10. Almost three years after closing to build an expansion, the Morgan is back and brilliant. What's new: Renzo Piano's splendid four-story glass-and-steel court, a sort of giant solarium with see-through elevators; two good-size second-floor galleries; and a neat little strongbox of an enclosure, called the Cube, for reliquaries and altar vessels, medieval objects made with so much silver and gold that they seem to give off heat. What's not new: almost everything in this exhibition, which fills every gallery with mini-exhibitions of master drawings and musical manuscripts, as well as illuminated gospels, devotional sculptures and historical and literary autograph manuscripts from the Brontës to Bob Dylan. 225 Madison Avenue, at East 36th Street, (212) 685-0008 or www.themorgan.org. (Individual show closings can be checked by telephone or through the Web site.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Arts AND Design: 'THE EAMES LOUNGE CHAIR: AN ICON OF MODERN DESIGN,' through Sept. 3 Celebrating the 50th anniversary of a chair whose combination of declarative modernist structure and sheer creature comfort was both innovative and a bit alien, this exhibition is a successful design object in its own right. It pays homage with drawings, advertising ephemera, precursors, vintage television clips, a wonderful documentary and three versions of the chair itself, enshrined, exploded and useable. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11 This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed a golden opportunity to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' through Aug. 18. Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* The Studio Museum In harlem: 'Energy/Experimentation: Black Artists and Abstraction, 1964-1980,' through July 2. During one of the most radical periods in 20th-century American politics, the Black Power era, a group of African-American artists was working in one of the most radical forms of 20th-century art: abstraction. This show is stylishly installed. (One gallery bursts with color, another has a cool platinum shimmer.) The 15 artists are intensely individualistic and part of an important history. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212, through July 7. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>Philippe Decrauzat: 'Plate 28' A conceptually perplexing but visually striking installation by a young Swiss artist includes a black and white grid painted on the walls; a sculpture based on a Russian Constructivist design, and a grainy, flickering black-and-white film showing glimpses of ominous landscapes from ''The Twilight Zone.'' Swiss Institute, 495 Broadway, at Broome Street, (212) 925-2035, through July 15. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* 'An Ongoing Low-Grade Mystery' Organized by the curator Bob Nickas, this excellent group show includes works in many different mediums and styles, related in that they are all predominantly red. Donald Judd, Sherrie Levine, Jim Drain, Wolfgang Tillmans and Dan Walsh are among more than 30 artists included. Paula Cooper, 534 West 21st Street, (212) 255-1105, through June 23. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Jackie Gendel: 'Portraits' With seemingly off-hand painterly verve, smudgy colors and a sweet sense of humor, Ms. Gendel creates smart and sensuous, semi-abstract riffs on Modernist portraiture. Jeff Bailey, 511 West 25th Street, (212) 989-0156, through July 1. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* NEW VIDEO, NEW EUROPE A selection of 49 tapes by 40 artists from 16 Eastern European countries, several of which did not exist before the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1989, presents bits and pieces of another world. Revolution, landmines, economic hardship and disappearing ways of life alternate with wit and artistic originality. The whole forms an inadvertent documentary, but many of the parts are well worth attention. The Kitchen, 512 East 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, through June 30. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* 'Artists Against the State: Perestroika Revisited' Satiric and subversive Pop and Conceptualist works by more than 50 artists working in the Soviet Union during the years leading up to the end of Communism. Ronald Feldman, 31 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 226-3232, closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Loretta Lux By means of subtle digital manipulations, Ms. Lux turns color photographs of children in empty rooms into hallucinatory portraits of angelic beings with slightly oversized heads; big, soulful eyes; and beautiful clothes. Yossi Milo, 525 West 25th Street, (212) 414-0370, closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* 'The Rest is Silence: James Lee Byars' New York only really started to wake up to James Lee Byars (1932-1997) when he died. This three-gallery survey has some early work but focuses on the large-scale sculptures of his later years. It is tempting to fit him into existing slots: performance art, Minimalism, Conceptualism, whatever. But his extravagance and his privacy combine to keep him outside the fold, as do his philosophical concerns: Big Ideas, or rather Big Questions, about perfection, death and eternity. Perry Rubenstein Gallery, 526 West 24th Street, (212) 627-8000; 534 West 24th Street and 527 West 23rd Street; Mary Boone Gallery, 541 West 24th Street and 745 Fifth Avenue, (212) 752-2929); Michael Werner, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623. All close tomorrow.(Cotter)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE BUSY WORLD IS HUSHED' Opens on Sunday. A minister played by Jill Clayburgh finds herself at odds with her estranged, wayward son in this new play by Keith Bunin (''The Credeaux Canvas''). Mark Brokaw directs (2:00). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'MACBETH' Opens on Wednesday. First at the Public in the park this year will be Moisés Kaufman's production of ''the Scottish play,'' starring Liev Schreiber, who went unto the breach at the Delacorte Theater in 2003 in ''Henry V'' (2:25). Delacorte Theater, Central Park West and 81st Street, (212) 539-8750.</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' Opens on Tuesday. The Roundabout Theater reunites part of the artistic team from ''Urinetown'' -- the playwright Greg Kotis and the director John Rando -- for this play about a couple struggling to hold onto their herd of pigs. Denis O'Hare stars (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'SCHOOL OF THE AMERICAS' In previews. Opens on July 6. Based on historical fact, José Rivera's new play is about two days that Che Guevera spent trapped in a one-room schoolhouse. A co-production with the Labyrinth Theater company. John Ortiz and Patricia Velasquez star. (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SECRETS' Opens on Sunday. Gerald Zipper's play takes place over the course of a dinner party that turns sour and vicious, threatening several long marriages. Directed by Ted Mornel. (1:30). Theater at St. Luke's, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SHAKESPEARE IS DEAD' In previews; opens on Wednesday. Two parents, a pair of artists, re-examine their seven-year-old relationship after the accidental death of their child in this play by Orran Farmer, directed by Chris Chaberski (1:00). Paradise Factory, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, Special Theatrical Event 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, Best Book of a Musical and Best Original Score 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, Best Play and Best Direction of a Play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' A dancing encyclopedia of clichés set to the music of Earth, Wind and Fire. Numbing (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'SHINING CITY' Quiet, haunting and absolutely glorious. Conor McPherson's impeccably assembled ghost story about being alone in the crowded city of Dublin has been brought to American shores with a first-rate cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Oliver Platt, Martha Plimpton and Peter Scanavino), directed by Robert Falls (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, Best Direction of a Musical 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ARABIAN NIGHT' A blonde in a German apartment building sleeps too much; the super takes an unexpected trip to the desert; and a peeping Tom is properly punished in this stylish comedy whose title turns out to make perfect sense (1:05). The East 13th Street Theater, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 279-4200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'BURLEIGH GRIME$' A feeble-witted comedy by Roger Kirby about dirty dealings on Wall Street, featuring a pair of skilled actors known for recent television work -- Wendie Malick of ''Just Shoot Me'' and Mark Moses of ''Desperate Housewives'' -- and incidental music by David Yazbek, who wrote the score for Broadway's ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels.'' These putative assets are painfully ill served by Mr. Kirby's play, which is long on ludicrous plot and short on fresh humor. (2:10). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'ELVIS AND JULIET'  This opposites-collide tale by Mary Willard and starring her husband, the television actor Fred Willard, looks like community theater and is just as unoriginal. The title characters are young lovers, he the son of an Elvis impersonator, she the daughter of overeducated snobs. Fred dons an Elvis suit, but it's not enough (2:15). Abingdon Theater Arts Complex, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'THE MOST WONDERFUL LOVE' Blue Coyote Theater Group has a rollicking good time with this inventive tale of domestic disintegration by Matthew Freeman. Mother (Lenni Benicaso) and Father (Frank Anderson), after long years together, decide to ''unmarry,'' which isn't quite the same as divorce but just as unsettling for their already unsettled youngest child (Josephine Stewart). But that doesn't begin to convey how nutty this play is. Access Theater, 380 Broadway, at White Street, TriBeCa; (212) 868-4444. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'NERVE' In Adam Szymkowicz's romantic comedy, an online couple's first date is a frightening but satisfyingly comic escalation of confessions and demands (1:00). 14th Street Y, 344 East 14th Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444.(Gates)</p>
        <p>'NOT A GENUINE BLACK MAN' Brian Copeland's solo memoir about his African-American family moving into a white suburb in the early 1970's is an engaging, if stiltedly performed, show (1:30). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'NOTHING' A morsel of catnip for Anglophiles, flavorfully adapted by Andrea Hart from the novel by Henry Green. Simon Dutton and Sophie Ward play onetime lovers contemplating the possible marriage of their children in this comedy of manners about the string of upheavals that a romance in one generation causes in another (1:40). The 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SANDRA BERNHARD: EVERYTHING BAD AND BEAUTIFUL' Sandra Bernhard was a proverbial rock star long before headline-making folks in even the most prosaic walks of life were being referred to as such. Her new show, a collection of songs interspersed with musings on her life and on public figures ranging from Britney Spears to Condoleezza Rice, is casual to the point of being offhand. That said, it's invigorating to be in the presence of a true original (2:00). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, at Union Square, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SATELLITES' This tough-minded, soft-hearted and very likable play by Diana Son (''Stop Kiss'') portrays a world in which traditional ethnic, social, economic and sexual boundaries have become so porous that people are never quite sure who or where they are. Sandra Oh and Kevin Carroll play a couple who move into a Brooklyn brownstone that refuses (literally) to stay still. Michael Greif directs the appropriately fluid ensemble. (1:40). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SOME GIRL(S)' A slight and sour comedy from Neil LaBute that once again puts a morally bankrupt man under the microscope and watches him squirm. The central specimen is here played by Eric McCormack, who as a thoughtless heterosexual gives much the same performance he did as a thoughtful homosexual on ''Will and Grace.'' Jo Bonney directs a cast that also includes Fran Drescher, Judy Reyes, Brooke Smith and Maura Tierney as women done wrong by the same man (1:40). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'STOPPING TRAFFIC' The actress Mary Pat Gleason's endearing one-woman show about making movies (and just getting through life) while bipolar is a play with both a message and some hearty laughs (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, (212) 353-0303. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE WATER'S EDGE' In a bold surgical endeavor that recalls the experiments of the mad Dr. Frankenstein, Theresa Rebeck has tried to transplant the big, blood-engorged heart of a Greek tragedy into the slender body of a modest American comic drama. The resulting hybrid runs amok in a stylishly acted production, directed by Will Frears and starring Kate Burton and Tony Goldwyn (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BACK OF THE THROAT' An Arab-American playwright, Yussef El Guindi, addressing the harassment of Arab-Americans after Sept. 11? Interesting. But the play would have been even more interesting if the harassers were something other than cardboard characters out of the J. Edgar Hoover closet (1:15). Flea Theater, 41 White Street, TriBeCa, (212) 352-3101. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DOUBT, A PARABLE' John Patrick Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions in the clash between the head of a parochial school and the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge (1:30). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'AMERICANA ABSURDUM and THE COMPLETE LOST WORKS OF SAMUEL BECKETT  '  'The Complete Lost Works of Samuel Beckett ' consists of affectionate and hilarious short spoofs of Beckett's spare, rigorous and brooding dramas, as well as tedious segues involving mock threats of legal action against the spoofers. 'Americana Absurdum' is an interestingly glib, deeply cynical satire of stereotypical American greed, rapaciousness and narcissism whose serious purposes are unfortunately clouded by a production invested much more in style than in sense (1:45). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closing on Sunday. (Jonathan Kalb)</p>
        <p>'ASSISTED LOVING' This warm and witty monologue by Bob Morris, who contributes the Age of Dissonance column to the Sunday Styles section of The New York Times, is performed by the author, who chronicles his widowed father's and his own search for love in and around New York. Engaging, subtle and winning (1:10). Daryl Roth Theater, D-Lounge, 103 East 15th Street, at Union Square, (212) 239-6200; closing on Monday. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>* 'AWAKE AND SING!' (Tony Award, Best Play Revival 2006) Dreams and disappointments, hopes and fears, encouraging words and bitter putdowns clash by day and night in Clifford Odets's turbulent comedy-drama about a Jewish family struggling to stay afloat in the 1930's. A gifted roster of performers -- including Mark Ruffalo, Lauren Ambrose, Zoë Wanamaker and Ben Gazzara -- manage to locate the dreaming centers of their characters, buried beneath layers of political sloganeering, everyday gripes or street slang. And even when the focus occasionally blurs in Bartlett Sher's ultimately moving revival, Odets's zesty dialogue is a joy to hear (2:30). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CAGE LOVE' The new thriller by Christopher Denham -- star of ''Red Light Winter'' -- is a compulsively watchable, sometimes ridiculous drama about a man who becomes increasingly suspicious of his wife-to-be (1:30). Rattlestick Theater, 224 Waverly Place, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444; closing on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'IN THE MATTER OF J. ROBERT OPPENHEIMER'  In the title role, Thomas Jay Ryan makes morality, in its truest sense, look fashionable. This is a long but frequently gripping play of literate talk and real ideas (2:45). The Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444; closing on Tuesday. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'STUFF HAPPENS'  Daniel Sullivan's sharp, invigorating production of David Hare's journalistic drama about the road to war in Iraq is conducted on the modest scale of a town-hall meeting. The characters (who have names like Bush and Blair) seem less like destiny-shaping gods than the ego trippers in your office. If that means they're too close for comfort, then ''Stuff Happens'' is doing its job (2:50). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE THREEPENNY OPERA' Presented as a long, pansexual orgy, Scott Elliot's numbing revival of the Brecht-Weill classic feels like a party where the hangover begins almost as soon as the evening does. The starry cast includes Alan Cumming (as Mac the Knife) and a Dietrich-like Cyndi Lauper, though only Jim Dale and Nellie McKay appear to have a clue as to what the show is about (2:40). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'WAITING FOR GODOT' Vladimir (Wendell Pierce) and Estragon (J. Kyle Manzay) wait and wait, but in this version they're soaking wet, their desolate plot being surrounded by water. A familiar play is injected with surprises (2:00). Harlem School for the Arts, 645 St. Nicho las Avenue, near 141st Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 864-4444; closing tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'bombon-EL PERRO' (No rating, 96 minutes, in Spanish) A lonely, unemployed, middle-aged man finds a glimmer of hope when he acquires a purebred show dog in this sweet, gritty neo-realist fable from Argentina. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'DOWN IN THE VALLEY' (R, 114 minutes) This allegorical neo-western set in the San Fernando Valley has dreams as big as the fantasies that consume its protagonist, a Stetson-wearing suburban cowboy (Edward Norton) who is not what he appears to be. How much you like it will depend on your appetite for the kind of cultural metaphors that David Jacobson flings onto the screen with a reckless abandon. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LAND OF THE BLIND' (R, 111 minutes) Watching this simplistic Orwellian fable set in a composite Everycountry that swings politically from extreme right to extreme left is like poring over a quadruple exposure. It's a jumble of ideas and images. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'LOVERBOY' (R, 86 minutes) This cautionary mother-child drama, directed by Kevin Bacon, is a star vehicle for his wife, Kyra Sedgwick, who plays a pathologically possessive single mother. After starting out warm and fuzzy, this tonally uncertain film stealthily pulls out the rug until you suddenly find yourself standing on a cold stone floor, barefoot and shivering. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'LA MOUSTACHE' (No rating, 86 minutes, in French) Emmanuel Carrière's psychological mystery prepares you to bask in one of those sexy, bittersweet marital comedies that are a hallmark of sophisticated French cinema. Then, by degrees, it subverts those expectations to spiral down a rabbit hole of ambiguity and doubt. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE OMEN' (R, 110 minutes) The supremely unnecessary remake of ''The Omen,'' the 1976 horror show that, along with ''Rosemary's Baby'' and ''The Exorcist,'' plunked everyone's favorite baddie, Satan, into the Hollywood mainstream, wants to capitalize on the tabloid theology in the air. Except for a few contemporary touches (the World Trade Center in flames as a portent of Armageddon) it slavishly recycles the original. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>INDIEWIRE: UNDISCOVERED GEMS (Tuesday and Wednesday) This eight-month-long series presents film-festival features that have not found theatrical distributors. This month's movie is Arin Crumley and Susan Buice's ''Four Eyed Monsters,'' about a couple who take a new approach to romantic interactivity and truly become one person. Cinema Village, 12th Street between University Place and Fifth Avenue, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>STANLEY KUBRICK RETROSPECTIVE (Through July 9) The Museum of the Moving Image's five-week series continues this weekend with ''Lolita'' (1962), in which James Mason plays Vladimir Nabokov's Humbert Humbert, romancing an adolescent girl, and ''Dr. Strangelove, or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb'' (1963), Kubrick's nuclear-weapons comedy starring Peter Sellers. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues this weekend with ''Kagemusha'' (1980), starring Tatsuya Nakadai as a small-time thief hired to impersonate a medieval warlord. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ASIAN FILM FESTIVAL (Through July 1) Subway Cinema's fifth annual festival of high-grossing and/or award-winning new movies continues at Anthology Film Archives. The weekend's films, all from 2005, include ''The Great Yokai War,'' which has been described as Takashi Miike's ''Lord of the Rings''; ''Cromartie High School,'' a Japanese spoof of juvenile delinquent movies; and ''Linda Linda Linda,'' about Japanese high school girls (and one Korean) who form a band. 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, and ImaginAsian Theater, 239 East 59th Street, (212) 371-6682; $9. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NORDIC NOIR: CRIME DRAMAS FROM SWEDEN AND DENMARK (Through Aug. 10) The American Scandinavian Foundation is screening ''Henning Mankell's Kurt Wallander Mysteries,'' television films written by Mr. Mankell, the author of the internationally best-selling Wallander novels. In Wednesday's film, ''The African,'' a black man's body is found on a train that originated in Wallander's Swedish hometown. Scandinavia House, 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212) 879-9779; $8. (Gates)</p>
        <p>TOMORROWLAND: CAL ARTS IN MOVING PICTURES (Through Aug. 13) The Museum of Modern Art's three-decade survey of films and videos by former students at the California Institute of the Arts continues. This weekend's features include William Jones's ''Massillon'' (1991), a gay road movie, and ''Tony Oursler: Pioneering Videos,'' which includes ''Life of Phillis'' (1979), Mr. Oursler's psychosexual soap opera. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE VISION THAT CHANGED CINEMA: MICHELANGELO ANTONIONI (Through Thursday) BAMcinématek's tribute to Antonioni nears its end with three films this weekend. ''Zabriskie Point'' (1970) is his view of the American 1960's counterculture, complete with campus riots. ''L'Éclisse'' (1962) is a love story with angst, starring Monica Vitti and Alain Delon. ''Red Desert'' (1964) also stars Ms. Vitti, this time as a mentally ill housewife. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>AFI (Tonight) AFI gives its slithery, death-and-gloom-obsessed songs a jolt of fierce energy by reaching back to the anthemic hard-core punk of 1980's groups like Agnostic Front (as well as to 90's pop-punkers like Green Day). The recipe works: last week, on the strength of its catchy single ''Miss Murder,'' the band's new album, ''Decemberunderground'' (Interscope), went to No. 1. Also on the bill are Dillinger Escape Plan, which plays an impossibly complex kind of punk-jazz, and Nightmare of You. At 6:45, Roseland, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $25. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ALLMAN BROTHERS, DEREK TRUCKS BAND (Tuesday) Derek Trucks, who is starting to take on a role similar to the young Eric Clapton's -- that of a phenomenally gifted, graceful blues-rock guitarist whose presence makes anything better -- does double duty here, playing with the Southern-rock granddaddies the Allman Brothers and also opening the show with his own group. At 7 p.m., Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000; $20 to $65. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE (Monday) Atmosphere is a Minneapolis-based hip-hop group led by Slug, whose keenly written rhymes convey a gloomy sensibility more commonly associated with underground rock. With Brother Ali and Los Nativos. 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20. (Kelefa Sanneh)</p>
        <p>BLUE CHEER (Tonight) On a few gloriously untidy albums in the late 1960's and early 70's, Blue Cheer followed the blunter edges of Jimi Hendrix's sound into a bludgeoning kind of primordial heavy metal, and played it with an un-self-conscious glee that made the band sound like cavemen discovering fire. With Soldiers of Fortune and Titan. At 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAZILIAN GIRLS (Tuesday) Electronica, a live rhythm section and a wildly cosmopolitan spirit meet a charismatic and unpredictable singer, Sabina Sciubba, in the Brazilian Girls. The music dips into reggae, samba, funk and house, never staying in one place long. With Gold Streets and Adam Deitch Project. Pier 54, Hudson River at 13th Street; free. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>CALEXICO (Tuesday) This collective from Tucson, centered on the guitarist and singer Joey Burns and the drummer John Convertino, elegantly mingles dry alt-country with surf guitar, mariachi and a folk-flavored psychedelia like that of the 1960's band Love. With Jason Collett, a sometime member of the Toronto indie collective Broken Social Scene, who draws inspiration from Bob Dylan and the Allman Brothers, among others. At 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DEVOTCHKA (Tomorrow) DeVotchKa, from Denver, is the most musically versatile band of the Gypsy-punk trendlet of the last few years. It does its share of wild fiddling and rug-cutting, but also plays a lot of moody, carefully textured ballads that can recall the Tindersticks. The band has a new mini-album with versions of Velvet Underground and Frank Sinatra songs, and recorded the score to a film at Sundance this year. With Norfolk &amp; Western and the Mendoza Line. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $14. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ESPERS, BRIGHTBLACK MORNING LIGHT (Tonight) These two bands are part of a new wave that aims to revive the sound and the utopianism of 1960's folk. Espers, a mostly acoustic sextet from Philadelphia, plays airy English folk à la Fairport Convention, sometimes surrounding it with a foreboding drone. Brightblack Morning Light's sound is more intriguing because it's harder to place: an electric hum; warbling keyboards that evoke funk; and ecstatic, breathy chants. The songs on its new, self-titled album on Matador were written, the band has said, while living in tents in Northern California. With Mariee Souix. At 9:30, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FEIST, JASON COLLETT, BUCK 65 (Sunday) Central Park SummerStage's annual Canada Day concert (well, close enough: the holiday is actually July 1) includes two singers whose indie-rock bona fides includes time with the great Toronto collective Broken Social Scene. Leslie Feist, a k a Feist, is a cosmopolitan chanteuse who knows how to rock a club, playing bossa nova, folk, Françoise Hardy bonbons and her specialty, the sad disco ballad; Jason Collett draws inspiration from a narrower field, including Bob Dylan and the Allman Brothers. Also on the bill is Buck 65, a raspy rapper from Nova Scotia who rhymes about the backwoods life. At 3 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FIERY FURNACES (Thursday) In a smart scramble of eras and attitudes, the Fiery Furnaces back flippantly surreal lyrics with blues riffs, teetering analog synthesizers, parlor piano and punky noise, coming up with a 21st-century urban skiffle. With Man Man and Standing Nudes. At 6 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Wednesday and Thursday) There are no small emotions for Diamanda Galás, whose compositions are music theater with its rawest nerves exposed. She takes up fear and rage, mourning and vengeance; her voice can reach operatic heights or slice through a room with primal moans and shrieks and sobs. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* JOSÉ GONZÁLEZ, JUANA MOLINA, PSAPP (Thursday) Connoisseurs of hip television soundtracks might recognize some of the music on this bill. José González, an Argentinean Swede, plays haunting, austere guitar confessions with precision picking and a deadpan hush; his song ''Crosses'' was played in the soap-opera season finale of ''The OC'' this spring. Juana Molina is another whispery Argentine, whose gentle, swirling lullabies draw a listener directly into her reveries. The English duo Psapp places soft vocals over beats constructed from found sounds like splashing water, creaking floorboards and even squeaking cats, creating a kind of hyperintimate electronica; ''Grey's Anatomy'' uses one of Psapp's songs as its theme. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>I-THREES (Tomorrow) The I-Threes were the great reggae backup singers of the 1970's, formed to support Bob Marley and the Wailers. The members -- Rita Marley, Bob Marley's widow; Judy Mowatt, who was already a pop star in Jamaica when the group was founded; and Marcia Griffiths -- play a rare group date at the Apollo Theater. Also on the bill is Thandiswa, a singer in the trailblazing South African kwaito group Bongo Maffin, who on her new solo album, ''Zabalaza'' (Escondida), mingles traditional xhosa rhythms with hip-hop, gospel and reggae. At 8 p.m., 253 West 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 531-5305 or (212) 307-7171; $45 to $55. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOE JACKSON (Thursday) In songs like ''Is She Really Going Out With Him?'' and ''Steppin' Out'' in the late 1970's and early 80's, Joe Jackson made his reputation as a cold-eyed master of British soul, bringing a cutting new-wave minimalism to stories of lonely lovers who cry that they are ''so tired of all the darkness in our lives.'' Since then he has proved remarkably versatile, releasing, among other projects, settings of the Seven Deadly Sins and a Grammy-winning recording of his Symphony No. 1. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JAY-Z (Sunday) Three years ago Jay-Z, the rap prince turned record executive, announced his retirement from performing, but he keeps finding ways to stay in the game: albums with R. Kelly and Linkin Park, some guest spots, a big radio-sponsored concert or two. Here he shows that he does not need any ruse but himself. He celebrates the 10th anniversary of his debut album, ''Reasonable Doubt,'' by performing it beginning to end. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KEANE (Tonight) This British band consists of just a drummer, a singer and an awfully hard-working keyboardist, but manages to flesh out songs of yearning and self-pity with rich sonorities and sharp hooks that make you swear that there's a guitar in there somewhere. Keane has headlined Radio City Music Hall, but plays this much smaller show to promote its lush and mawkish new album, ''Under the Iron Sea'' (Island). At 8, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ARTHUR LEE BENEFIT (Tonight) In Los Angeles in the mid-1960's, the band Love, led by Arthur Lee, perfected a distinctly lyrical variety of psychedelia steeped in folk and garage-rock. Now 61, Mr. Lee is suffering from leukemia, and the roster of musicians at this benefit concert reveals some of his wide influence: Robert Plant, Ian Hunter, Ryan Adams, Nils Lofgren, Yo La Tengo, Garland Jeffreys and Flashy Python and the Body Snatchers, a new group featuring Alec Ounsworth of Clap Your Hands Say Yeah. At 8, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070 or (212) 307-7171; $53.50 to $128.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LIARS (Tomorrow and Monday) The Liars are an avant-garde rock band the way all avant-garde rock bands should be: noisy, challenging and unpredictable. It began playing cold, paranoid punk-funk and has gradually moved into ever eerier and more disorienting territory, as if trying to eliminate any trace of conventional rock 'n' roll from its sound. Tomorrow the band plays with one of its stylistic ancestors, Alan Vega of the great 1970's noise-punk minimalists Suicide; tomorrow and Monday's shows also include the Apes, a chaos-loving band from Washington that always keeps one yeti-like foot in Black Sabbath stomps. Tomorrow at 9 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; Monday at 8 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780. Each show is $15 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NATALIE MacMASTER AND FRIENDS (Tonight) Ms. MacMaster, a fiddler whose repertory leans from Celtic music into bluegrass, leads a small group of musicians in a celebration of the Celtic music of her homeland, the Eastern Canadian island of Cape Breton. She performs with the powerful Irish-American Susan McKeown, the fiddler Donnell Leahy (who is also Ms. MacMaster's husband), the cellist Natalie Haas and the singer Catherine Russell. At 7:30, Celebrate Brooklyn, Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882; $3 suggested donation. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MADONNA (Wednesday and Thursday) Part 10 (or so), in which our heroine strikes such poses as Jesus on the cross, James Brown in his cape and John Travolta in his white disco suit, all while performing dance-floor hits in new remixes and reconfigurations. Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $64.50 to $354.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>AUDRA McDONALD (Thursday) Ms. McDonald sings Broadway fare with a 33-piece orchestra; her program is likely to include what she calls songs associated with the ''two Barbaras,'' Cook and Streisand. With the gospel singer Liz McComb. At 7 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TIM McGRAW AND FAITH HILL (Tonight and tomorrow night) The first couple of country-pop flash have recently acquired a slight and unexpected political edge -- though not much controversy -- by criticizing the government's response to Hurricane Katrina. At 8, Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $49.50 to $99.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ONE RING ZERO, LAS RUBIAS DEL NORTE, SLAVIC SOUL PARTY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Barbès, a cozy bar and cabaret in Park Slope, serves as an incubator for a group of smart and casually eclectic musicians, the type who might mingle a little Gypsy music with their norteño. Now the club has started a record label to extend its support (and brand name), and offers a showcase this weekend. One Ring Zero, tonight at 9, has set words by authors like Jonathan Lethem, Margaret Atwood and Rick Moody to kitchen-sink songs with toy piano and theremin. Las Rubias del Norte, at 10:30, play boleros, cumbias and other Latin styles, elegantly arranged for a small band and two songbird sopranos. Slavic Soul Party, tomorrow night at 10, plays a raucous mix of Eastern European music, funk and jazz. Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; $8 suggested donation. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PANIC! AT THE DISCO, DRESDEN DOLLS (Wednesday and Thursday) Panic! at the Disco, from Las Vegas, were discovered by Pete Wentz of Fall Out Boy, who quickly signed the band to his own label, Decaydence. It's not hard to see why: the group has the slick runway look of the Killers (also from Las Vegas); the muscular, gushy emo-rock sound of Fall Out Boy; and a knack for song titles that could be Oscar Wilde epigrams, like ''The Only Difference Between Martyrdom and Suicide Is Press Coverage'' and ''Lying Is the Most Fun a Girl Can Have Without Taking Her Clothes Off.'' The Dresden Dolls play elaborate, gender-bending cabaret-punk vamps and dress the part. At 7:30 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* REFUGEE ALL STARS OF SIERRA LEONE (Tonight) These six musicians, ranging from a teenage rapper to a guitarist in his 50's, fled civil war in their homeland for a refugee camp in rural Guinea. They formed a band there four years ago, and tell their stories in songs tinged with soul and reggae. A documentary about the group, made by Zach Niles and Banker White, will be shown after its performance. At 7 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRUCE SPRINGSTEEN WITH THE SEEGER SESSIONS BAND (Tomorrow and Sunday) A hootenanny of musicians, playing banjos, accordions, fiddles and guitars, accompanies Bruce Springsteen in folk songs of work, hardscrabble survival and political anger -- the Depression-era ''How Can a Poor Man Stand Such Times and Live'' gets a Hurricane Katrina rewrite -- from his latest album, ''We Shall Overcome: The Seeger Sessions'' (Columbia). At 7:30 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698; $46.25 to $91.75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* THE STREETS, LADY SOVEREIGN (Tuesday) The best and weirdest of new British hip-hop: the Streets, a k a Mike Skinner, is a loquacious rapper whose monotonous delivery can sometimes make him sound like a robot learning to rhyme, and Lady Sovereign, a k a Louise Harman, is a teenage firecracker who is one of the most entertaining exponents of grime, a hyperactive rap-plus-techno British subgenre. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Cabaret</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday) Even when swinging out, this Lady of a Thousand Songs remains an impressionist with special affinities for Thelonious Monk and bossa nova. At 2 p.m., the Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $58, including brunch at noon. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* Eartha Kitt (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday nights) The latest edition of an act Ms. Kitt has been performing for decades is the lightest, swiftest and funniest one to date, and that's all to the good. More than ever, the singer, now a glamorous 79, pauses to poke fun at her status as the greatest and wittiest of all singing tigresses. At 8:45, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 10:45, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600; $100. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* JESSICA MOLASKEY (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday nights) A theater singer with jazz chops, Ms. Molaskey combines sophisticated wit, fierce intelligence and a lightly swinging voice that hovers on the keen edge between happy and sad. A hybrid of the bossa nova standard ''Desafinado'' and Billy Joel's ''Summer, Highland Falls'' performed Brazilian style, is the pinnacle of a show whose material she describes as ''limbo songs.'' At 9, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, the Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $50 cover; $60 prix fixe dinner required at all 9 p.m. shows; $20 minimum at the late shows tonight and tomorrow night. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>TIM BERNE DUOS (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Berne, an adventurous alto saxophonist, has always had some of his strongest musical connections with drummers. Next week he goes head to head with two of them: the suggestive and fluid Gerald Cleaver (Wednesday) and the wry, responsive Tom Rainey (Thursday). On Wednesday at 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. On Thursday at 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDY BEY (Wednesday through July 1) Intimacy is a hallmark of Mr. Bey's vocal style, which alternates between a rich baritone and a burnished falsetto. He's also a fine pianist, as he'll surely demonstrate here. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BRAZIL NIGHTS (Tonight and tomorrow night) The superb guitarist Romero Lubambo leads two Brazilian jazz acts this weekend, and neither should be missed. Tonight it's Trio da Paz, with the bassist Nilson Matta and the drummer Duduka da Fonseca; the pianist Kenny Barron will join them as a special guest. Tomorrow the setting will be more intimate: just Mr. Lubambo and the singer Luciana Souza, as on her ''Brazilian Duos'' albums. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $30. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIM BLACK'S ALAS NO AXIS (Sunday) Noise rock, along with numerous strains of music made on laptops, exerts a heavy influence on Mr. Black's music, as his new album, ''Dogs of Great Indifference'' (Winter &amp; Winter), confirms. But tuneful lyricism and jazz improvisation also have a place in his working band, which features his drums and electronics, on the same plane as Chris Speed's tenor saxophone and clarinet, Skuli Sverrisson's electric bass and Hilmar Jensson's guitar. At 8 and 9:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* A SALUTE TO CACHAO: MASTER OF THE MAMBO (Tomorrow) In the 1940's Israel Lopez, known as Cachao, helped define modern Cuban music; he is the most influential Latin bassist of all time, and one of Cuban music's most important bandleaders. His signature descargas will serve as the common language of this tribute, which is well stocked with artists like the conga drummer Carlos Valdez, the trumpeter Alfredo Armenteros, the flutist Dave Valentin and the trombonist Jimmy Bosch. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $35 to $85. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY CHILDS JAZZ-CHAMBER ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) Mr. Childs, an accomplished pianist, composer and producer, favors a billowy sound in his own music, which sometimes drifts perilously close to New Age. But beneath a genteel atmosphere of piano, saxophone, harp, guitar and strings lurks the action-oriented rhythm team of Scott Colley on bass and Brian Blade on drums. At 8:30 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3303; $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AVISHAI COHEN BAND (Sunday) Mr. Cohen is an assertive trumpeter with a taste for modernism, and he keeps good company here: the alto saxophonist Yosvany Terry, the guitarist Lionel Loueke, the pianist Jason Lindner, the bassist Omer Avital and the drummer Daniel Freedman. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN COWHERD, JOHN PATITUCCI, BRIAN BLADE (Tuesday and Wednesday) Mr. Blade, the lithe and subtle drummer, serves as the fulcrum of this impressionistic trio, which features two of his frequent collaborators. Mr. Cowherd plays piano and writes music for Mr. Blade's Fellowship band, while Mr. Patitucci, the bassist, plays with Mr. Blade in the working band led by the saxophonist Wayne Shorter. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, near Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE DOUGLAS GROUP (Sunday) Mr. Douglas, the trumpeter and composer, taps an aggressive improvisational vein with this assembled quartet, which features the august Henry Grimes and Andrew Cyrille on bass and drums. J. D. Allen, a probing tenor saxophonist, rounds out the ensemble. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES FINN'S NDA NANAA (Thursday) On his recent album, ''Plaza de Toros'' (Clean Feed), the tenor saxophonist James Finn teased out a connection between bullfighting and free jazz, with appropriate doses of bravado and humor. Here he steps into the ring with the trombonist Steve Swell, the pianist Gordon Beeferman and the percussionist Jackson Krall. At 8 and 10 p.m., Jimmy's Restaurant, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL FRISELL TRIO/PETRA HADEN AND KELLY JOE PHELPS (Tonight) Rustic Americana is the prevailing atmosphere of this concert, thanks to Mr. Frisell, one of jazz's most imaginative guitarists, and to the duo of Ms. Haden, a singer, and Mr. Phelps, a guitarist and singer-songwriter. Given the overlapping histories onstage -- Mr. Frisell has recorded with both of his fellow headliners -- it should be a freewheeling evening. At 8, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, www.symphonyspace.org; $23 and $28. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIZZY GILLESPIE ALL-STAR BIG BAND (Through Sunday) Bebop's goateed ambassador did some of his best work with big bands, a fact that this repertory ensemble, led by his former trombonist and arranger Slide Hampton, happily exploits. The band includes other veterans of Gillespie's employ -- like the saxophonists James Moody, Frank Wess and Jimmy Heath -- as well as Roy Hargrove, the trumpeter enlisted here to fill his shoes. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAVION GLOVER &amp; THE OTHERZ /ROBERT GLASPER TRIO (Tomorrow) Mr. Glover, the dynamo of rhythmic tap dance, sees himself as a jazz percussionist, and plays the part in his ensemble the Otherz. Mr. Glasper is a pianist given to silvery modern flourishes and gospel intimations, and he leads a remarkably cohesive trio with the bassist Vicente Archer and the drummer Damion Reid. At 7:30 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell, Ninth Street and Prospect Park West, Park Slope, Brooklyn, www.celebratebrooklyn.org; free. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HAPPY APPLE (Sunday) This Minneapolis-based trio fashions a hardy yet elastic amalgam of indie-rock and post-bop, with doses of sardonic humor. Its sound is served equally by Michael Lewis's saxophones, Erik Fratzke's electric bass and David King's drums. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; cover, $12, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HERBIE'S WORLD: HERBIE HANCOCK AND FRIENDS (Tonight) Mr. Hancock is one of jazz's most successful chameleons, in addition to being one of its finest pianists. This impressive concert gives him the opportunity to dig into fluid pianism (in duets with Gonzalo Rubalcaba); ambitiously abstract chamber improvisation (in a quartet with the tenor saxophonist Wayne Shorter, the bassist Dave Holland and the drummer Brian Blade); earthy rhythm section work (in a trio with the bassist Ron Carter and the drummer Jack DeJohnette); and deep-rooted groove (in a band with the guitarist Lionel Loueke and the bassists Matt Garrison and Marcus Miller, among others). At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $40 to $100. JVC Jazz Festival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MAT MANERI QUINTET (Thursday) Mr. Maneri has a dark, hollow tone on viola and a generous approach to collective improvisation. His ensemble consists of Joe Carton on trumpet, Matt Moran on vibraphone, John Hebert on bass and Randy Peterson on drums. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* WYNTON MARSALIS SEXTET/SEPTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Marsalis is a ubiquitous presence at Frederick P. Rose Hall, but he doesn't often headline at its most intimate space. Tonight and tomorrow he plays Dizzy's Club with a six-piece band culled from the ranks of his Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra; on Sunday he leads a seven-piece, comprising Wycliffe Gordon on trombone, Wes Anderson and Victor Goines on saxophones, Richard Johnson on piano, Carlos Henriquez on bass and Herlin Riley on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIYA MASAOKA TRIO (Tomorrow) Ms. Masaoka brings an avant-garde sensibility to the koto, a Japanese zither; she also works with a laptop and with the cellist Okkyung Lee and the pianist Sylvie Courvoisier. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* PAUL MOTIAN BAND (Tuesday through July 2) This luminous ensemble consists of two contrasting pairs of improvisers (the tenor saxophonists Mark Turner and Chris Cheek, and the guitarists Steve Cardenas and Ben Monder); a couple of stabilizers (Jacob Bro and Jerome Harris, also guitarists); a lone anchor (the bassist Ben Street); and a mastermind (Mr. Motian, on drums). The band's last ECM album was excellent; its last Village Vanguard appearance, in January, was even better. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20; $25 on Friday and Saturday, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEWIS NASH QUINTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Nash is an engaging and subtle drummer who brings a crisp sense of swing to any setting. His ensemble consists of Jeremy Pelt on trumpet, Steve Wilson on alto and soprano saxophones, Gerald Clayton on piano and Peter Washington on bass. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $25 ($20 on Sunday), with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARTURO O'FARRILL TRIO (Tomorrow) Mr. O'Farrill, the pianist and bandleader of Lincoln Center's Afro-Latin Jazz Orchestra, knows how to energize smaller settings; in this trio he works with Alex Blake on bass, and Jamie Affoumado on drums. At 9:15 and 10:40 p.m. and midnight, Puppets Jazz Bar, 294 Fifth Avenue, at First Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 499-2627, www.puppetsjazz.com; $5, with a two-drink minimum (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EIVIND OPSVIK'S OVERSEAS (Wednesday) Mr. Opsvik is a Norwegian bassist and composer who carefully balances avant-gardism against a poplike lyricism, as he demonstrates here with a working band composed of Tony Malaby on tenor saxophone, Jacob Sacks on piano and Kenny Wollesen on drums. At 6:30 p.m., Scandinavia House. 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212) 879-9779, www.scandinaviahouse.org; cover, $7; members, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARIO PAVONE QUARTET (Wednesday) Mr. Pavone, a bassist and composer with an expansive worldview, leads a cadre of fellow colorists: Ron Horton on trumpet, Tony Malaby on saxophones and Gerald Cleaver on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HERLIN RILEY AND FRIENDS (Tuesday through July 2) Few contemporary jazz drummers groove as naturally as Mr. Riley, who presides here over a quartet composed of other strong musicians with ties to Wynton Marsalis: the tenor saxophonist and clarinetist Victor Goines, the pianist Eric Reed and the bassist Reginald Veal. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 p.m. set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL STEWART TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Though he is known primarily as a sideman, Mr. Stewart, a drummer, has a composer's vocabulary, as he proved with a pair of underrated Blue Note albums in the 1990's. He connects here with Larry Goldings on Hammond B-3 organ and Kevin Hayes on piano, mining a post-bop sound that owes more than a little to rhythm and blues. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BUSTER WILLIAMS AND SOMETHING MORE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Williams's bass playing is the anchor but not the focal point of this chamber-jazz quintet, with his longtime rhythm-section partner Lenny White on drums; Marcus Strickland on tenor and soprano saxophone; Stefon Harris on vibraphone; and on piano either George Colligan (tonight) or Anthony Wonsey (tomorrow). At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'THE BARBER OF SEVILLE' (Thursday) The Lake George Opera opens its season at the Saratoga Performing Arts Center with Rossini's hoary chestnut, sung in Italian with projected supertitles. Other offerings this summer include ''Pagliacci'' and Ned Rorem's ''Our Town.'' At 8 p.m., Spa Little Theater, Saratoga Springs, N.Y., (518) 587-3330; $48 to $70; $5 off for children and 65+. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'GLORY DENIED' (Monday) The invaluable Center for Contemporary Opera, which helps living composers place their operas, either completed or in-progress works, before the public, presents a staged reading of Tom Cipullo's ''Glory Denied.'' This Vietnam-era story is based on an oral history by the journalist Tom Philpott about Col. Jim Thompson, America's longest-held prisoner of war. When Act I was presented in 2004 as part of the New York City Opera's Vox readings, Mr. Cipullo's unsentimental handling of the story was complemented by his hard-edged, neo-Romantic musical style. Though this staged reading will present the complete opera, the cast will be accompanied only by piano. At 8 p.m., the Thalia at Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400; $20. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight the pianist Jeffrey Swann concludes the overview of Chopin he has been presenting all this month, with a program that includes the F minor Fantasy, the Sonata No. 2, the second and third Scherzos and the Ballade No. 4. Tomorrow the Amernet String Quartet takes over for a program of Shostakovich, Fredrick Kaufman and Brahms. On Sunday a more varied ensemble -- guitar, accordion, violin, piano and bass -- offers a program of Astor Piazzolla's music. And on Thursday Jeanne Mallow, a violist, and Vladimir Valjarevic, a pianist, collaborate on works by Brahms, Schumann, Rachmaninoff and William Keith Rogers. Tonight and tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30, Sunday at 4 p.m., Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35 for all but the Sunday concert, which is $40. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CARAMOOR (Tomorrow and Sunday) On the shady grounds of a former estate, this Westchester summer festival begins its season with its excellent resident orchestra, the Orchestra of St. Luke's, under Peter Oundjian, in a festive selection of music: the overture to the unfinished opera ''Pope Joan'' by Caramoor's composer-in-residence this year, John Musto; Beethoven's Eighth; and the ever-popular Mendelssohn Violin Concerto, with the ever-popular Joshua Bell. On Sunday Peter Schickele presents ''P. D. Q. Bach: His Life, Legacy and Leftovers.'' Tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday afternoon at 4:30, Venetian Theater, Caramoor, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-1252; $40 to $92.50 tomorrow, $19 to $49 on Sunday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* CONNECTICUT EARLY MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow) This annual festival offers consistently varied and enlightening programs. Tonight chamber works by Couperin are the focal points in a program of works from the court of Louis XIV. Tomorrow the superb wind ensemble Piffaro plays Spanish and Portuguese Baroque works. Tonight at 8, Mystic Arts Center, Mystic, Conn.; tomorrow at 8 p.m., Evans Hall, Connecticut College, New London, (860) 444-2419; $26 for a reserved seat, $20 general admission. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>FREE FOR ALL AT TOWN HALL (Sunday) The music is by the guitarist Sharon Isbin and the mezzo-soprano Susanne Mentzner, and the tickets are free. At 5 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 707-8787; tickets are available starting at noon. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL FESTIVAL OF ARTS AND IDEAS (Tonight) Each June since 1996, this festival in New Haven has brought together thinkers, creators and performers from the worlds of theater, dance, art, music, literature and letters. As in past years, music is an important component of this summer's festival, which ends this weekend. Tonight two fine artists, Sarah Rothenberg, playing piano, and John Gibbons, playing harpsichord, juxtapose preludes and fugues by Bach with those by Shostakovich, whose works in this genre were directly inspired by Bach's. At 8, Sprague Memorial Hall, Yale University, 470 College Street, (203) 562-5666 or (888) 736-2663; $35. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) In the spirit of its founder, the conductor Jens Nygaard, this ensemble brings together familiar works and scores from off the beaten path. Its guest this week is the violinist Anne Akiko Myers, who joins it for a program that includes the StamitzClarinet Quartet, the Rosetti Sextet and Dvorak's Quintet in G. At 8 p.m., the JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 799-1259; $15. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* MANNES INSTITUTE AND FESTIVAL OF CONTEMPORARY PERFORMANCE (Tonight through Thursday) Having just completed its extensive Beethoven Institute, the Mannes College of Music, the classical music division of the New School, turns its attention to new music. This festival attracts composers and performers, both renowned figures and adventurous students, for 10 days of workshops, master classes and concerts, all open to the public. Tonight the composer and pianist Frederic Rzewski, a galvanizing performer of his own ferocious works, joins the Amernet String Quartet for an all-Rzewski program. Tomorrow the pianist Wilhem Latchoumia, a new-music champion, and the percussionist Daniel Ciampolini, who spent 20 years playing in Pierre Boulez's cutting-edge ensemble, share a program. On Sunday evening the piano duo of Jean-Jacques Balet and Mayumi Kameda perform during the first half of a program that after intermission offers a memorial tribute to the composer Donald Martino, with a roster of performers participating. Tuesday's concert features the percussionist Matthew Gold, the pianist Stephen Gosling and the violinist Curtis Macomber. On Wednesday the percussionist Daniel Druckman, of the New York Philharmonic, joins the Speculum Musicae ensemble in works by Louis Andriessen, Salvatore Sciarrino, Milton Babbitt and others. On Thursday an ensemble from the institute plays works by the Moroccan-born French composer Yan Maresz. At 8 p.m., Mannes College, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 580-0210, Ext. 4884; concerts are $20; $10 for students; master classes and lectures are $8; a pass to all events is $150. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>MAVERICK CONCERTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) This concert series near Woodstock, N.Y., offers its performances in an open-backed barn that allows the sounds of nature to mingle with the music. Tomorrow the festival's director, Alexander Platt , leads the pianist Frederic Chiu and the Maverick Chamber Players in the chamber versions of Mozart's Piano Concertos Nos. 11, 12 and 13. On Sunday the American String Quartet plays Haydn's Quartet in E flat (Op. 76, No. 6), Shostakovich's Quartet No. 11 and Mozart's Quartet in F (K. 590). Tomorrow at 6 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m.; the Maverick Concert Hall, Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217; $20; $5 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MUSIC FESTIVAL OF THE HAMPTONS (Tomorrow and Sunday) A gala concert tomorrow kicks off the 11th season of this piano-loving festival that comes, this year, with a few caveats: its artistic director, Lukas Foss, is not actually taking part in any of the season's concerts (although his music will be played), and some of the tent events are listed as ''pending Town of Southampton permits.'' Permits or no, tomorrow's concert travels a colorful road from Vivaldi to Duke Ellington, with stops at Mozart, Ravel and others along the way. On Sunday afternoon the festival continues with a recital by the 12-year-old pianist and composer Drew Petersen; in the evening the director Daniel Anker will introduce his rather turgid film about the musicians of the Philadelphia Orchestra, ''Music From the Inside Out.'' Tomorrow night at 7:30 (cocktails at 6), Sunday afternoon at 3 and 7, East Hampton Studios, Wainscott, N.Y. (gala concert and Anker film), and Bellport, N.Y. (Petersen recital), (800) 644-4418; tomorrow, $75; $150 for concert and party; Sunday afternoon, $25; Sunday evening, $10; $7 for 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MUSIC MOUNTAIN (Tonight through Sunday) String quartets are a focus of this venerable institution in northwestern Connecticut, and on Sunday the Amernet Quartet performs the second of two weekend concerts, offering Shostakovich's Third, Beethoven's Op. 132 and Mozart's Oboe Quartet in F Major, with the oboist Humbert Lucarelli. Tonight the Saint John's Chorale, a small group 15 years old, makes its debut at the festival under its director, Richard Busch. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday afternoon at 3, Gordon Hall at Music Mountain, Falls Village, Conn., (860) 824-7126; $25 at the door; $22 in advance; $12 for students. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NAUMBURG ORCHESTRAL CONCERTS (Tuesday) This free series in Central Park begins its 101st-anniversary season with a concert that is not, strictly speaking, orchestral. The eclectic woodwind quintet Imani Winds, which describes itself as African-American/Latino, will be joined by the pianist André-Michel Shub for a program with Piazzolla and Paquito D'Rivera on the one hand, and an arrangement of Ravel's ''Tombeau de Couperin'' on the other; the third and fourth hands include a Mozart wind quintet and a piece called ''Umoja'' by the group's flutist, Valerie Coleman. At 7:30 p.m., Naumburg Bandshell, Central Park, midpark at 70th Street, (718) 340-3018. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN BALLET THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow; Monday through Thursday) The last three performances of Kenneth MacMillan's ''Manon'' are tonight and tomorrow, with Diana Vishneva and Vladimir Malakhov scheduled tonight. On Monday begins a weeklong run of ''Swan Lake.'' (The season continues until July 15.) Tonight and tomorrow night, and Monday through Thursday nights, at 8 p.m.; tomorrow and Wednesday at 2 p.m.; Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000 or abt.org; $23 to $163. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* BARD SUMMERSCAPE (Thursday) This summer arts festival opens on Thursday with two new dances by Donna Uchizono, performed by her company and by the guest artist Mikhail Baryshnikov, whose Hell's Kitchen arts center commissioned one piece. Through July 1. The festival runs through Aug. 20. At 8 p.m., Fisher Center, Sosnoff Theater, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y. (845) 758-7900 or summerscape.bard.edu; $25 to $55. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* KIMBERLY BARTOSIK (Tonight through Sunday night) Ms. Bartosik knows there is a world beyond the dance studio, which is what her new ''home in the neon heat,'' described as a meditation on fractured landscapes, addresses. Her company features current and former Merce Cunningham dancers, including Cédric Andrieux, Daniel Squire and Derry Swan. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CATALYST (Wednesday and Thursday) This Minneapolis-based dance company, making its New York debut, will perform ''Heat and Life,'' a multimedia dance about global warming by the company director Emily Johnson. At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; $12 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CEDAR LAKE: FREE THURSDAYS (Thursday) This first of three free programs will feature multimedia events created by the dancers and designers of the Cedar Lake Contemporary Ballet. At 6 p.m., Cedar Lake Theater, 547 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444 (Smarttix) or cedarlakedance.com. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CELEBRATE BROOKLYN! SAVION GLOVER &amp; FRIENDS (Tomorrow) Mr. Glover will jam with guest dancers to music by his jazz band, The Otherz, on a program that also includes a performance by Robert Glasper's jazz trio. At 7:30 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 855-7882; suggested contribution, $3. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CORBINDANCES (Tonight through Sunday night) Patrick Corbin, a former dancer with the Paul Taylor Dance Company, offers the premiere of ''Bathing Jeff, Part I,'' a monologue with movement based on Mr. Corbin's experiences in the worst years of the AIDS epidemic. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $25. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>Fugate/Bahiri Ballet NY (Monday through July 2) Judith Fugate, a former New York City Ballet principal dancer, and her husband, Medhi Bahiri, a former principal at Boston Ballet, formed this chamber company in 1997. Their mission is to present contemporary ballets, and the company's longevity is testament to Ms. Fugate and Mr. Bahiri's shrewd selection of choreographers who make modern, appealing work. This season offers repertory pieces by Thaddeus Davis, Stanton Welch and Toni Pimble, with new works by Francis Patrelle and John Butler. Tuesday at 7.30 p.m., Wednesday through Friday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $36. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>GESTURES DANCE ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) This preprofessional group from the Harbor Conservatory for the Performing Arts presents an evening of work by an alumnus, Darrell Grand Moultrie, who has made pieces for dance companies around the country. At 7:30 p.m., Miller Theater, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 427-2244; $15. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>NEIL GREENBERG (Tonight through Sunday) A revival of ''Not-About-AIDS-Dance,'' a commentary on life, illness and loss, originally produced in 1994, shares the program with the new ''Quartet with Three Gay Men.'' Through June 25. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 4 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077; $25; $15 for students, 65+ and artists. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) There are usually two attractions per week in the main theaters of this bucolic, venerable festival, which runs until Aug. 27. On this opening weekend there is CND2, short for the second company of Nacho Duato's Compañía Nacional de Danza from Madrid. The other attraction is a screening of the acclaimed documentary ''Ballets Russes'' on Friday. On Wednesday and Thursday the Limón Dance Company will be at the larger Ted Shawn Theater, and starting Thursday at the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater is ASzURe &amp; Artists, devoted to the choreography of Aszure Barton. CND2 tonight and tomorrow night at 8, and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m.; and Limón on Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., Shawn Theater; $50. ''Ballet Russes'' tonight and ASzURe on Thursday night, Duke Theater, 8:15 p.m.; $10 for the film, $24 for ASzURe. Ten percent off all tickets for students, 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions can be found at jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>STEPHEN KOPLOWITZ (Today through Sunday) ''Revealed'' seeks to alter perspectives of place, site and scale with the aid of 10 dancers and the optical device known as the camera obscura. At noon, World Financial Center, 220 Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-0505 or worldfinancialcenter.com; free. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* LA MAMA MOVES! (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) This ambitious festival includes four different programs this weekend, in two of La MaMa's honeycombed little theaters. ''Children of Ur'' (tonight) features work by nine individuals and groups, among them Karinne Keithley, David Neumann and Nicky Paraiso. ''Duets'' (tomorrow) showcases dance by five duos, and ''Dancing Divas'' (Sunday) lives up to its name with work by Pat Catterson, Ellen Fisher, Keely Garfield, Sally Gross, Deborah Jowitt, Jodi Melnick, Yvonne Meier and Vicky Shick. And ''Mavericks in Motion'' (Thursday) features dance by Jonah Bokaer, Monica Bill Barnes and Tami Stronach. Tonight at 10, tomorrow and Sunday at 5:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MICHELA MARINO-LERMAN (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Marino-Lerman, a 19-year-old ''Sesame Street'' alumna, and her company will examine existence, public life and education in tap dance. At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736 or dixonplace.org; $12 or T.D.F.; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* THE NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) The closing weekend of the company's spring season, ending on Sunday afternoon with an all-Balanchine program of ''Symphony in C'' and ''Vienna Waltzes.'' All the programs will be conducted by Andrea Quinn, the departing music director. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, tomorrow at 2 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.org; $30 to $86; student rush tickets at $12. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of this winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, has settled into the intimate Theater 80 for this month and next, through July 30. Tonight and tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m.; Sunday at 5 p.m.; Theater 80, 80 St. Mark's Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>OF MOVING COLORS (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company, based in Baton Rouge, La., will perform dances by Pavel Zustiak, Ashleigh Leite, Nick Erickson and the company director, Garland Goodwin Wilson. At 8, Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200 or dnadance.org; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>OUT OF SPACE @ BRICSTUDIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) This occasional series, organized by Marya Wethers, is presented in collaboration with Danspace Project, which suggests a talent-scouting expedition might be in order. The new works on the program are by Keïty Anjoure, Faye Driscoll, Will Rawls and Tamar-kali. At 8:30, BRICstudio, 57 Rockwell Place, second Floor, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 855-7882; $12; $10 for students. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* PASCAL RIOULT DANCE THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Rioult, a former Martha Graham dancer, tends to give his larger-than-life themes and dances a Grahamesque heroism, this time in a program that includes ''If by Chance,'' a world premiere set to a score by Jacques Loussier, a French jazz composer, that reworks Mozart's Concerto No. 23. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org; $38. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SITELINES 2006: DOUGLAS DUNN AND ELKE RINDFLEISCH (Today and Monday through Thursday) This free avant-garde arts festival, also produced by River to River, features Mr. Dunn and Ms. Rindfleisch in paired pieces. At 12:30 p.m., Elevated Acres, 55 Water Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 219-9401. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Folk Art Museum: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' through Sept. 17. The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and cast-off clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,'  through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedekers, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them and souvenir platters, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'VERONESE'S ALLEGORIES: VIRTUE, LOVE AND EXPLORATION IN RENAISSANCE VENICE,' through July 16. Paolo Veronese (1528-88), a superb colorist and one of the most suavely sensuous of Renaissance Venetian painters, used the age-old device of allegory to make abstract concepts visual, often by means of human or mythological figures. In this five-painting show, the first to include all of his large-scale allegories from American collections, high ideals mingle with earthy and sometimes erotic physicality, as in the painting ''Venus and Mars United by Love.'' 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* METropolitan museum of art: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early 19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. (212) 535-7710.(Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. And wait till you see the painted ceramic vessel known as the ''Dazzler Vase,'' with its red and green patterns like jade on fire, you'll understand its name. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Morgan Library and Museum: 'Masterworks from the Morgan,'  through Sept. 10. Almost three years after closing to build an expansion, the Morgan is back and brilliant. What's new: Renzo Piano's splendid four-story glass-and-steel court, a sort of giant solarium with see-through elevators; two good-size second-floor galleries; and a neat little strongbox of an enclosure, called the Cube, for reliquaries and altar vessels, medieval objects made with so much silver and gold that they seem to give off heat. What's not new: almost everything in this exhibition, which fills every gallery with mini-exhibitions of master drawings and musical manuscripts, as well as illuminated gospels, devotional sculptures and historical and literary autograph manuscripts from the Brontës to Bob Dylan. 225 Madison Avenue, at East 36th Street, (212) 685-0008 or www.themorgan.org. (Individual show closings can be checked by telephone or through the Web site.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Arts AND Design: 'THE EAMES LOUNGE CHAIR: AN ICON OF MODERN DESIGN,' through Sept. 3 Celebrating the 50th anniversary of a chair whose combination of declarative modernist structure and sheer creature comfort was both innovative and a bit alien, this exhibition is a successful design object in its own right. It pays homage with drawings, advertising ephemera, precursors, vintage television clips, a wonderful documentary and three versions of the chair itself, enshrined, exploded and useable. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11 This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed a golden opportunity to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' through Aug. 18. Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* The Studio Museum In harlem: 'Energy/Experimentation: Black Artists and Abstraction, 1964-1980,' through July 2. During one of the most radical periods in 20th-century American politics, the Black Power era, a group of African-American artists was working in one of the most radical forms of 20th-century art: abstraction. This show is stylishly installed. (One gallery bursts with color, another has a cool platinum shimmer.) The 15 artists are intensely individualistic and part of an important history. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212, through July 7. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>Philippe Decrauzat: 'Plate 28' A conceptually perplexing but visually striking installation by a young Swiss artist includes a black and white grid painted on the walls; a sculpture based on a Russian Constructivist design, and a grainy, flickering black-and-white film showing glimpses of ominous landscapes from ''The Twilight Zone.'' Swiss Institute, 495 Broadway, at Broome Street, (212) 925-2035, through July 15. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* 'An Ongoing Low-Grade Mystery' Organized by the curator Bob Nickas, this excellent group show includes works in many different mediums and styles, related in that they are all predominantly red. Donald Judd, Sherrie Levine, Jim Drain, Wolfgang Tillmans and Dan Walsh are among more than 30 artists included. Paula Cooper, 534 West 21st Street, (212) 255-1105, through June 23. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Jackie Gendel: 'Portraits' With seemingly off-hand painterly verve, smudgy colors and a sweet sense of humor, Ms. Gendel creates smart and sensuous, semi-abstract riffs on Modernist portraiture. Jeff Bailey, 511 West 25th Street, (212) 989-0156, through July 1. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* NEW VIDEO, NEW EUROPE A selection of 49 tapes by 40 artists from 16 Eastern European countries, several of which did not exist before the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1989, presents bits and pieces of another world. Revolution, landmines, economic hardship and disappearing ways of life alternate with wit and artistic originality. The whole forms an inadvertent documentary, but many of the parts are well worth attention. The Kitchen, 512 East 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, through June 30. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* 'Artists Against the State: Perestroika Revisited' Satiric and subversive Pop and Conceptualist works by more than 50 artists working in the Soviet Union during the years leading up to the end of Communism. Ronald Feldman, 31 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 226-3232, closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Loretta Lux By means of subtle digital manipulations, Ms. Lux turns color photographs of children in empty rooms into hallucinatory portraits of angelic beings with slightly oversized heads; big, soulful eyes; and beautiful clothes. Yossi Milo, 525 West 25th Street, (212) 414-0370, closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* 'The Rest is Silence: James Lee Byars' New York only really started to wake up to James Lee Byars (1932-1997) when he died. This three-gallery survey has some early work but focuses on the large-scale sculptures of his later years. It is tempting to fit him into existing slots: performance art, Minimalism, Conceptualism, whatever. But his extravagance and his privacy combine to keep him outside the fold, as do his philosophical concerns: Big Ideas, or rather Big Questions, about perfection, death and eternity. Perry Rubenstein Gallery, 526 West 24th Street, (212) 627-8000; 534 West 24th Street and 527 West 23rd Street; Mary Boone Gallery, 541 West 24th Street and 745 Fifth Avenue, (212) 752-2929); Michael Werner, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623. All close tomorrow.(Cotter)</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 24, 2006, Saturday  An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday about ''Artists Against the State: Perestroika Revisited,'' at the Ronald Feldman gallery in Soho, included an outdated closing date. It is July 28, not today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 24, 2006, Saturday</p>
        <p>An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday about ''Artists Against the State: Perestroika Revisited,'' at the Ronald Feldman gallery in Soho, included an outdated closing date. It is July 28, not today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
