<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="08obse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/08/science/08observ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1781575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4D71E3FF93BA3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Comeback Story Proves a Cautionary Tale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Henry Fountain</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New in the 'Old and Cold'</p>
        <p>About a decade ago, Japanese scientists exploring the seafloor near the Japan Trench in the northwestern Pacific made a surprising finding.</p>
        <p>Using a remotely operated submersible, they collected a bit of volcanic rock only about five million years old. Yet this was on the 135-million-year-old Pacific plate, which was not considered an active volcanic area, but rather an ''old and cold'' bit of the Earth's crust.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saving endangered Caribbean sea turtles, volcano hunting on the seafloor, oil-eating bacteria and more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New in the 'Old and Cold'</p>
        <p>About a decade ago, Japanese scientists exploring the seafloor near the Japan Trench in the northwestern Pacific made a surprising finding.</p>
        <p>Using a remotely operated submersible, they collected a bit of volcanic rock only about five million years old. Yet this was on the 135-million-year-old Pacific plate, which was not considered an active volcanic area, but rather an ''old and cold'' bit of the Earth's crust.</p>
        <p>Intrigued, Naoto Hirano of the Tokyo Institute of Technology and the Scripps Institution of Oceanography and colleagues spent several years using sonar to map the ocean floor in the region, hunting for volcanoes. In an online report published in late July by Science, they say they have found very small young undersea volcanoes in two areas about 350 miles apart.</p>
        <p>The researchers call them ''petit spot'' volcanoes and say they occur in areas where the Pacific plate has cracked as it bends and slides under the Japan Trench, in a process called subduction.</p>
        <p>Analysis of the lava that oozes from them showed that it came from the asthenosphere, the shallow zone between the crust and the upper mantle. This is in contrast to ''hot spot'' volcanoes like those in Hawaii, in which the molten rock is thought to rise in plumes from much deeper in the mantle.</p>
        <p>The researchers say there may be many more of these petit spot volcanoes around the world, in areas where subduction occurs and old plates are flexed enough to crack and let the lava through.</p>
        <p>Where Rays Do the Rotting</p>
        <p>People who live in wet climates know all about rot. Moisture creates fertile ground for bacteria and other organisms of decay to do their thing. So dead vegetation quickly turns into rotting vegetation.</p>
        <p>But what about more arid regions, where there is little water to go around?</p>
        <p>A study conducted on the Patagonian steppes in southern South America shows that in this semiarid region, sunlight is the controlling factor in decomposition of dead plant matter. The sun's rays, particularly ultraviolet-B ones, break down the organic carbon compounds in plant tissue, releasing carbon directly to the atmosphere in the form of carbon dioxide and other gases.</p>
        <p>In the study, Amy T. Austin and Lucía Vivanco of the University of Buenos Aires exposed plots of dead native grasses to the sun, using various filters and controlling other elements like bacterial activity. Their results, reported last week in the journal Nature, showed that after nearly two years the organic matter was reduced by up to 40 percent.</p>
        <p>But the only variable that affected decomposition, the researchers found, was the solar radiation. Filtering out some of the UV-B radiation reduced the amount of decay. But altering the biological activity in the plots had no significant effect.</p>
        <p>The researchers say this direct photodegradation of organic carbon acts as a short circuit in the carbon cycle, as carbon travels directly from plant tissue to the atmosphere without passing through the soil. The finding also has climate-change implications, since long-term changes in cloud cover and ozone in the high atmosphere can affect the amount of ultraviolet light reaching the ground, and thus the amount of decomposition that takes place.</p>
        <p>The Root of Oil-Eaters' Hunger</p>
        <p>Of course, it's not just dead plants that decompose. Just about everything does -- even oil, which can be broken down by some bacteria.</p>
        <p>Scientists in Germany have announced that they have sequenced the genome of one of these oil-eaters, Alcanivorax borkumensis. It is a voracious degrader -- in cases of oil spills or other hydrocarbon pollution it quickly becomes the dominant microbe -- and the genome, reported in the journal Nature Biotechnology, shows why.</p>
        <p>Among other characteristics, the bacterium has genes that enable it to act on a variety of hydrocarbons, others responsible for the production of surfactants that emulsify the oils and enhance degradation, and still others involved in making biofilms that keep the bacterium just where it can do its best work, at the point where the oil and the water meet.</p>
        <p>A Comeback Story Proves a Cautionary Tale</p>
        <p>Thanks to publicity about their plight and the efforts of conservation groups, some endangered Caribbean sea turtles have made comebacks in recent decades. Nesting beaches have been protected, and a result has been large population increases in green turtles and other species.</p>
        <p>But researchers at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography argue in a new study that the situation is more dire. Using an approach that blends history and ecology, the researchers say that both the number of nesting sites and the overall populations of green and hawksbill turtles have been greatly reduced from historical levels. Conservation efforts, they say, need to focus not just on a few large nesting sites, but also on marginal ones just holding on.</p>
        <p>''We need to at least get these beaches on the radar,'' said Marah J. H. Newman, an author of the study, which appears this month in the journal Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment. She is a graduate student at Scripps, which is part of the University of California, San Diego.</p>
        <p>Ms. Newman, with the study's lead author, Loren McClenachan, and Jeremy B. C. Jackson, used historical sources like traders' records and pirates' journals to compile a list of nesting sites. Hawksbills were prized for their shells; greens were hunted for their flesh (flipping them over renders them helpless, so they were a ready source of fresh meat).</p>
        <p>The researchers found evidence of 59 nesting beaches for green turtles and 55 for hawksbills. Then, given all these known beaches, they used several approaches to estimate the historical population sizes of the two species. The estimates vary widely, but even the most conservative ones are many times current levels.</p>
        <p>''There was incredibly extensive cover throughout the Caribbean,'' Ms. Newman said. ''Wherever there was a beach, there were turtles. You just don't see that now.''</p>
        <p>The researchers found that about 20 percent of the historical sites had been lost, and half of the remaining ones were home to very small populations.</p>
        <p>But smaller sites, Ms. Newman said, are ''how a species hedges its bets'' in case a major nesting beach is destroyed by a hurricane or another disaster. ''It's really a weakness in conservation strategy not to put some effort into restoring these satellite beaches,'' she said. ''It's important to bulk those up.''</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
