<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Weigh New Power as Leaders</title>
    <meta content="10cong" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061114T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1803683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2006 ELECTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DA1F3FF933A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Weigh New Power as Leaders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Democrats take control of the Senate in January, they will immediately assume far more power to influence President Bush's agenda, particularly his choice of executive and judicial nominations that must pass through the chamber.</p>
        <p>By virtue of their de facto 51-to-49 majority, Democrats will now control the committees and the floor schedule -- a factor Mr. Bush will have to weigh in his selection of high-level candidates. (The Senate split 49 to 49, but tipping the scales toward the Democrats are Senator-elect Bernard Sanders of Vermont, an independent who caucuses with Democrats, and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, a Democrat who ran as an independent after losing in the primary.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Democrats take control of the Senate in January, they will immediately assume far more power to influence President Bush's agenda, particularly his choice of executive and judicial nominations that must pass through the chamber.</p>
        <p>By virtue of their de facto 51-to-49 majority, Democrats will now control the committees and the floor schedule -- a factor Mr. Bush will have to weigh in his selection of high-level candidates. (The Senate split 49 to 49, but tipping the scales toward the Democrats are Senator-elect Bernard Sanders of Vermont, an independent who caucuses with Democrats, and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, a Democrat who ran as an independent after losing in the primary.)</p>
        <p>''It means send us more moderate people or don't waste your time,'' said Senator Richard J. Durbin of Illinois, the second-in-command and a member of the Judiciary Committee, which considers judicial nominees.</p>
        <p>Republicans acknowledge that the shift will be a significant factor in high-profile nominations, such as any to fill Supreme Court vacancies, in the remainder of the president's term. But they also say that the Senate tradition of respecting the rights of the minority gives them the same opportunities to influence the agenda that Democrats used during their years out of power.</p>
        <p>''It is clearly going to be harder to get his people through, not easier,'' said Senator John Cornyn, a Texas Republican and White House ally who also sits on the Judiciary Committee. ''But the Senate is different from the House, and 49 Republican senators can certainly shape a piece of legislation that goes through, or if they feel it is bad enough, they have the power to kill it.''</p>
        <p>The new majority leader, Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, promised Thursday to have a more collegial relationship with the minority Republicans than he said was shown to the Democrats over the past four years of partisanship and procedural gamesmanship.</p>
        <p>''They've set a bad example in not working with us,'' Mr. Reid told cheering supporters who gathered across from the Capitol to celebrate the Democrat victory. ''We're not following that example.''</p>
        <p>In contrast to the House, the Senate has experienced more regular shifts in party control over the years -- Democrats were last in the majority in 2002 -- and many current members are accustomed to suddenly going from committee chairman to ranking minority member. In fact, many of the Democrats in line to take over important committees have wielded the gavel before, sometimes alongside the Republican who will be leaving the chairmanship.</p>
        <p>For instance, Senator Carl Levin, a Michigan Democrat and a leading party voice on military issues, has led the Armed Services Committee and has a good working relationship with senior Republicans on the panel. He will now play a major role in determining the approach on Iraq.</p>
        <p>But there are pronounced ideological differences between the incoming leaders and those they will be replacing, as well as other lingering issues. On the Intelligence Committee, Senator John D. Rockefeller IV of West Virginia, the top Democrat, has feuded with Senator Pat Roberts of Kansas, the Republican chairman, over Mr. Roberts' reluctance to challenge the administration's handling of intelligence preceding the Iraq war.</p>
        <p>In what could be the biggest policy divide on the panels, Senator Barbara Boxer, the liberal California Democrat and environmental advocate, is in line to take control of the Environment and Public Works Committee from Senator James M. Inhofe of Oklahoma, who has disputed the existence of global warming.</p>
        <p>''He thinks global warming is a hoax and I think it is the challenge of our generation,'' said Ms. Boxer, who said she has a cordial working relationship with Mr. Inhofe. ''We have to move on it.''</p>
        <p>In other notable changes, Senator Robert C. Byrd, 88, the West Virginia Democrat elected to his ninth term, is expected to resume his role as chairman of the Appropriations Committee. Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts, also re-elected, will be back at the Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee. Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr. of Delaware will be at the helm of the Foreign Relations Committee.</p>
        <p>With new power, Senate Republicans said Democrats will now have to do more than criticize. ''Now that Democrats will have control of Congress for the next two years, they have a new responsibility for one of the most important issues of our time,'' said Amy Call, a spokeswoman for Senator Bill Frist of Tennessee, the majority leader who is retiring at the end of the year. ''Quite simply, how shall we win the war on terror?''</p>
        <p>While there will no doubt be clashes with Mr. Bush, there are also some issues where he could find the new Senate easier to work with than the old one. Democrats have been much more supportive than Republicans of Mr. Bush's broad approach on immigration and that issue could get new traction.</p>
        <p>Democrats have been cheered by Mr. Bush's new bipartisan tone in recent days and say they are willing to reciprocate. But some also noted that the president laid out a very ambitious agenda for the post-election session scheduled to begin Monday under Republican control, including seeking approval of the nomination of John R. Bolton as ambassador to the United Nations. Mr. Bolton is serving as ambassador under an interim appointment after his nomination stalled in the Senate.</p>
        <p>''The president has indicated that he understands the significance of Tuesday's election and the need to work in a bipartisan fashion to move our nation forward,'' said Senator Christopher J. Dodd, Democrat of Connecticut and a Bolton critic.</p>
        <p>''But,'' he added, ''trying to jam this nomination through during a lame-duck session may indicate that the president didn't fully hear the voice of the American public -- and that is troubling.''</p>
        <p>Democrats have complained for years that Republicans have run roughshod over the minority party in both the House and Senate, and they promise to restore more traditional processes, including having open negotiations between the House and Senate over major legislation.</p>
        <p>With the pickup of six Senate seats that even he did not anticipate, Mr. Reid is more than secure in his post as party leader, with Mr. Durbin as the assistant leader. The party is exploring ways to recognize the leadership role of Senator Charles E. Schumer of New York. Mr. Schumer, the architect of the Democrats' triumph as head of the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, has been invited to lead that group for the 2008 elections if he chooses.</p>
        <p>In the House, Representative Rahm Emanuel of Illinois, who led the successful campaign effort there, announced Thursday that he would seek to lead the Democratic conference -- the fourth-ranking leadership slot. The decision could earn Mr. Emanuel, 47, further goodwill by averting a potentially divisive contest for the majority whip position with Representative James E. Clyburn of South Carolina.</p>
        <p>''I seek this post, and not any other, because I believe what we need now is a unified Democratic caucus, focused squarely on the business of moving this country forward,'' Mr. Emanuel said in a statement.</p>
        <p>THE 2006 ELECTIONS</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 14, 2006, Tuesday  An article on Friday about expected leadership changes in Congress misstated the position on global warming taken by Senator James M. Inhofe, the Oklahoma Republican who will be losing the chairmanship of the Environment and Public Works Committee. Senator Inhofe has said that it is a hoax to suggest that human activity is the cause of global warming; he does not dispute the idea that the earth is getting warmer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 14, 2006, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about expected leadership changes in Congress misstated the position on global warming taken by Senator James M. Inhofe, the Oklahoma Republican who will be losing the chairmanship of the Environment and Public Works Committee. Senator Inhofe has said that it is a hoax to suggest that human activity is the cause of global warming; he does not dispute the idea that the earth is getting warmer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
