<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Searching for the Sex Appeal in a Hybrid</title>
    <meta content="25torn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/25/automobiles/autospecial/25torn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1799743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="GAS AND ELECTRIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D81130F936A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Searching for the Sex Appeal in a Hybrid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Searching for the Sex Appeal in a Hybrid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Alex</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FEW weekends ago, I was rumbling through an intersection in Greenwich Village in a yellow convertible when a fashionable young couple -- she walking a small designer dog -- blithely strolled into my path, defying the light and forcing me to stomp on my brakes to avoid flattening both the couple and their easy-to-accessorize canine companion. The man and I exchanged words and gestures. But in the end, I let my car do the talking.</p>
        <p>And because my car was a 4.6-liter V8 Ford Mustang with a five-speed transmission and dual exhaust, it won, in decisive fashion. A quick foot to the gas pedal, and the couple quickly vanished in my rearview mirror, the man's final verbal parry drowned by the roar of a full-throated Detroit engine winding out in second gear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since we are moving toward a hybrid, if not an electric, era, I know I must evolve. I must relearn my concept of what makes a car a car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FEW weekends ago, I was rumbling through an intersection in Greenwich Village in a yellow convertible when a fashionable young couple -- she walking a small designer dog -- blithely strolled into my path, defying the light and forcing me to stomp on my brakes to avoid flattening both the couple and their easy-to-accessorize canine companion. The man and I exchanged words and gestures. But in the end, I let my car do the talking.</p>
        <p>And because my car was a 4.6-liter V8 Ford Mustang with a five-speed transmission and dual exhaust, it won, in decisive fashion. A quick foot to the gas pedal, and the couple quickly vanished in my rearview mirror, the man's final verbal parry drowned by the roar of a full-throated Detroit engine winding out in second gear.</p>
        <p>It felt great, but it also felt, I confess, a bit wrong. I consider myself an environmentalist, at least a pale green one. I worry about global warming, air pollution and oil dependency. Whenever I see someone driving a hybrid automobile, I am heartened: there's hope.</p>
        <p>The problem is, I still love muscle cars. I love the tingle of sensuality and power. They make me feel 17. They make me feel alive. Still, I feel as if the tide of history is against me. We are moving toward a hybrid, if not an electric, era. So I know I must evolve. I must relearn my concept of what makes a car a car.</p>
        <p>So a few weeks ago, I test-drove a Toyota Prius as part of my re-education. I wanted to go deep inside my own head, and convince the inner boy in me, the one who always wanted to be Steve McQueen, that it was just as cool to be Larry David.</p>
        <p>It didn't start well. When I pulled up to my first stoplight on Eighth Avenue in Manhattan, the Prius stalled, just like my college roommate's old Triumph TR6 used to.</p>
        <p>But wait. It's supposed to do that. That is the car's Hybrid Synergy Drive hybrid powertrain in action. It's no secret that the Prius runs on dual power plants, gas and electric, and is always distributing power around the car, in one direction or another -- from the engine to the battery, the battery to the brakes, the brakes to the battery. This is why it gets 55 miles a gallon, combined city and highway.</p>
        <p>It is also why it shuts down at every stop. That is impressively intelligent. But it feels odd. You feel a few inches shorter, and your biceps just a little skinnier, sitting amid idling cars in traffic with your car turned off. Indeed, what is remarkable about the Prius is absence: noise, engine rattle, fumes. At low speeds, it glides around, almost noiselessly, as if on ice skates.</p>
        <p>It feels like a stealth car. But while stealth is great in a bomber, it's not what I look for in a car. One joy of a car, after all, is the peacock experience. Being seen. This point was driven home while I was idling at a red light in a factory-fresh yellow convertible Mustang I test-drove on a later weekend.</p>
        <p>At every stoplight in the Mustang you feel as if you are actually at the starting line of a top-fuel drag race, waiting for green. In the Mustang, you feel the car even when it's not moving. The rumble of the engine bubbles up through your seat and rattles your spine. The heat from the engine massages your thighs.</p>
        <p>In the Mustang, moreover, you are noticed. I pulled up to a stoplight in Chinatown, and a doe-eyed young woman in a lowered white Nissan with gold rims gave me a lingering look. Idling at a stoplight on Fourth Avenue in Brooklyn, two lanky teenage boys in baggy basketball shorts gave me rock-on! smiles, one flashing a thumbs-up.</p>
        <p>That kind of automotive experience is satisfying on a primal level. As Richard M. Ryan, a professor of psychology, psychiatry and education at the University of Rochester, later explained: ''That's part of the fantasy -- you imagine yourself to be stronger or tougher as you drive a muscle car.''</p>
        <p>A Prius is more about Silicon Valley chic. It is as much a tech gizmo as it is a car. And there is a joy to showing off in 21st-century fashion that even muscle-car enthusiasts can appreciate.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Perkowitz, a co-founder of an ecology-focused catalog company in Charlotte, N.C., has owned a Porsche and a Maserati, he said, but his latest delight is being seen around town in his wife's Prius.</p>
        <p>''I realized I was turning more heads in that'' than he was in his Maserati, Mr. Perkowitz said. It was like showing up at a party with the latest 80-gig iPod.</p>
        <p>''I've lost the ego for bigger cars,'' he added. ''I realized I'm not getting there any faster. It's just a status symbol. And now there's status in the hybrid.''</p>
        <p>But my concerns go beyond status. A car should act like a car, I believe. Performance counts. In a hybrid, you have to learn to savor something other than neck-jolting acceleration.</p>
        <p>Another recent convert to hybrids helped show me the way. Dave Severns, who runs a philanthropic foundation in Sunnyvale, Calif., is a self-professed Jekyll and Hyde when it comes to cars. He recently traveled to the Chevrolet factory in Bowling Green, Ky., to buy a Corvette Z06, which has a 7.0 liter engine cranking out 505 horsepower. But he also drives a Prius to keep his Sierra Club guilt pangs at bay.</p>
        <p>''I get just as much kick out of driving the Prius as I do the Corvette,'' he said. ''It's just a whole different game.''</p>
        <p>Which he means literally. Mr. Severns turns his time behind the wheel of his Prius into a competition, with the car and the forces of physics. He's always trying to save power, in acceleration, in turns, in trying to keep the car humming above a 50 mile-a-gallon average, which he can keep track of, moment by moment, on the video monitor built into the dashboard.</p>
        <p>''You're trying to stay above the 50 mile-per-gallon level, and it's usually just out of reach -- 'Okay, the light is turning yellow up there, turn, better ease off the gas and let the brakes regenerate,' '' he said, adding, ''It's so fun to watch it, and see if you can maximize.''</p>
        <p>Out on the road in the Prius, I did start to appreciate the drive. It was so clean, so elegant and yes, even nimble.</p>
        <p>Still, one thing nagged at me. As I headed down Fifth Avenue in the Prius on a warm, late September evening -- presumably one of the last of the year where you might see short skirts and low-cut tops -- I was noticing an absence of glances from women. This was rarely a problem in the Mustang.</p>
        <p>After all, said David M. Buss, a professor of evolutionary psychology at the University of Texas in Austin, women are almost hard-wired to notice a car like the Mustang. ''Men with the muscle cars and sports cars tend to be signaling that they have extravagant resources, and sufficient excess to lavish those resources on nonnecessities,'' he said in an e-mail message. ''These are precisely the qualities that women look for in a short-term mate -- extravagant display of resources that can be devoted to them.</p>
        <p>But that does not mean that manhood must be sacrificed in a Prius, he said. ''Men driving the prudent, fuel efficient cars, in contrast, are signaling that they are not short-term mating strategies, but rather long-term mating strategies,'' he added. ''They are signaling dependability, reliability, conscientiousness, long-term planning and willingness to commit.''</p>
        <p>Maybe he was right. Maybe the Prius is simply the thinking man's chick magnet. Maybe I could learn to radiate masculinity in it -- just a different sort.</p>
        <p>Then it happened. Just outside Rockefeller Center, a Champagne-colored Lexus suddenly pulled away from the curb and started drifting straight into me. The driver, a balding man probably in his 50's, was talking on a cellphone, paying no attention to his impending collision with me. I punched the horn. It bleated weakly. I mouthed a few choice words. He glanced over, looking unthreatened and perhaps a bit bemused.</p>
        <p>The only thing left was to peel out and leave him in the dust. So I stomped on the gas -- or whatever it is you're stomping on in a Prius. Instead of lunging forward, the car inched away politely, its engine not roaring but purring, like an overstimulated kitten.</p>
        <p>Yes, I thought, I could learn to be a different man in a hybrid. Maybe a better man.</p>
        <p>But this was going to take time.</p>
        <p>GAS AND ELECTRIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
