<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="14biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1789876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DF1231F937A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERIOR AGENCY CRITICIZED -- The inspector general of the Interior Department accused top agency officials of tolerating widespread ethical failures, from cronyism to cover-ups of incompetence, and then dismissing criticisms with ''a promise not to do it again.'' [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>GOOGLE'S APPROACH TO CHARITY -- Larry Page, left, and Sergey Brin, founders of Google, have set up a philanthropy, giving it seed money of about $1 billion and a mandate to tackle poverty, disease and global warming. But unlike most charities, this one will be for-profit, allowing it to fund start-up companies, form partnerships with venture capitalists, and even lobby Congress. It will also pay taxes. [A1.]</p>
        <p>WOLFOWITZ'S CORRUPTION FIGHT -- As president of the World Bank, Paul D. Wolfowitz has made the fight against corruption in poor countries a hallmark issue, and he has drawn criticism for an aggressive campaign that has led to the suspension of hundreds of millions of dollars in loans and contracts to countries including India, Chad and Bangladesh. [C1.]</p>
        <p>U.S. WARNS CHINA -- In the administration's toughest warning yet to China on economic issues, Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr. said that Chinese leaders were imperiling their nation's future by engaging in policies that Americans and others see as unfair. [C3.]</p>
        <p>NINTENDO TO RELEASE CONSOLE -- Nintendo of Japan plans to announce that it will release its new Wii video game console in North America and South America on Nov. 19, just as the holiday shopping season begins, and that the machine will cost $250 in the United States. The move may allow Nintendo to take advantage of stumbles by its main rival, Sony. [C1.]</p>
        <p>MICROSOFT VS. HACKER -- A solitary computer hacker has entangled Microsoft in a battle of wits by repeatedly releasing a free program to strip away the software lock that the company created to protect digital movies and songs from being freely copied by Internet users. [C5.]</p>
        <p>HIGH HOPES FOR ONLINE GAME -- AOL and Mark Burnett, producer for reality television, kicked off an ambitious online game called ''Gold Rush,'' which they hope will become a national sensation somewhat on par with the one Mr. Burnett created six years ago with the ''Survivor'' series. [C3.]</p>
        <p>STRONG EARNINGS AT LEHMAN -- Lehman posted strong third-quarter results amid weak markets, lackluster deal flow and higher global interest rates, and its shares surged. [C13.]</p>
        <p>MARKETS RISE -- Stocks rose, sending major indexes to their highest levels since May, as battered energy shares like Exxon Mobil rebounded and investors bet that interest rates would not rise any time soon. [C13.]</p>
        <p>ROUGH TIME FOR NISSAN CHIEF -- Despite Carlos Ghosn's gilded reputation, his companies, Renault and its partner, Nissan Motor Corporation, are not performing well right now -- a fact their boss readily acknowledges. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CHICAGO WAGE EFFORT FAILS -- The first attempt in the nation to impose minimum wage regulations on big-box stores like Wal-Mart unraveled as Chicago's City Council fell three votes short of overriding Mayor Richard M. Daley's veto. [A18.]</p>
        <p>PLAN FOR JOBLESS INSURANCE -- The unemployment insurance system, which has hardly changed since its inception in 1935, should be revamped to aid more workers displaced by a transforming economy, economists said as they released overhaul plans. [A21.]</p>
        <p>HELP FOR WHITE-COLLAR WORKERS -- Barbara Ehrenreich, author of ''Nickel and Dimed,'' has started an organization called United Professionals to help white-collar workers, be they unemployed, uninsured, downsized, stressed out or merely anxious. [A21.]</p>
        <p>H.P. AND SPYING CASE -- California prosecutors looking into the Hewlett-Packard spying case are focusing on a small private investigation firm operating out of a house in suburban Boston. It is not clear how such a tiny firm ended up handling work for H.P., one of the largest technology companies. But other private investigators said it was not surprising, because corporations who are in need of such services often end rely on subcontractors. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TRIAL SET FOR DIRECT MARKETER -- The lawsuit in which the coupon company Valassis Communications seeks to cancel its $1.3 billion merger agreement with the direct-mail marketer Advo will go to trial in December, a judge ruled. [C5.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>A BANK REBUILDS -- Gary Rivlin of The Times spoke with chief executive of Liberty Bank, Alden J. McDonald Jr., about struggling to rebuild after Hurricane Katrina. An audio report is at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>ETHANOL USE -- As proponents of ethanol push for its use, Alexei Barrionuevo of The Times went on a road trip through the Midwest to find out how available the fuel is to the American driver. His report is at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>ONLINE: DEALBOOK -- A report on mergers and acquisitions, up-to-the-minute news on Wall Street and a look at the behind-the-scenes maneuvering is at nytimes.com/dealbook.</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>AIRBUS MAY DELAY DELIVERY of its A380 airliner by more than a year amid rising production costs, said Mike Turner, chief executive of BAE Systems, which owns 20 percent of Airbus. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>THE SUN-TIMES MEDIA GROUP, formerly Hollinger International Inc., said its chief executive, Gordon Paris, would step down at the end of the year as the newspaper publishing company shifts all of its New York-based corporate functions to Chicago. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERIOR AGENCY CRITICIZED -- The inspector general of the Interior Department accused top agency officials of tolerating widespread ethical failures, from cronyism to cover-ups of incompetence, and then dismissing criticisms with ''a promise not to do it again.'' [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>GOOGLE'S APPROACH TO CHARITY -- Larry Page, left, and Sergey Brin, founders of Google, have set up a philanthropy, giving it seed money of about $1 billion and a mandate to tackle poverty, disease and global warming. But unlike most charities, this one will be for-profit, allowing it to fund start-up companies, form partnerships with venture capitalists, and even lobby Congress. It will also pay taxes. [A1.]</p>
        <p>WOLFOWITZ'S CORRUPTION FIGHT -- As president of the World Bank, Paul D. Wolfowitz has made the fight against corruption in poor countries a hallmark issue, and he has drawn criticism for an aggressive campaign that has led to the suspension of hundreds of millions of dollars in loans and contracts to countries including India, Chad and Bangladesh. [C1.]</p>
        <p>U.S. WARNS CHINA -- In the administration's toughest warning yet to China on economic issues, Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr. said that Chinese leaders were imperiling their nation's future by engaging in policies that Americans and others see as unfair. [C3.]</p>
        <p>NINTENDO TO RELEASE CONSOLE -- Nintendo of Japan plans to announce that it will release its new Wii video game console in North America and South America on Nov. 19, just as the holiday shopping season begins, and that the machine will cost $250 in the United States. The move may allow Nintendo to take advantage of stumbles by its main rival, Sony. [C1.]</p>
        <p>MICROSOFT VS. HACKER -- A solitary computer hacker has entangled Microsoft in a battle of wits by repeatedly releasing a free program to strip away the software lock that the company created to protect digital movies and songs from being freely copied by Internet users. [C5.]</p>
        <p>HIGH HOPES FOR ONLINE GAME -- AOL and Mark Burnett, producer for reality television, kicked off an ambitious online game called ''Gold Rush,'' which they hope will become a national sensation somewhat on par with the one Mr. Burnett created six years ago with the ''Survivor'' series. [C3.]</p>
        <p>STRONG EARNINGS AT LEHMAN -- Lehman posted strong third-quarter results amid weak markets, lackluster deal flow and higher global interest rates, and its shares surged. [C13.]</p>
        <p>MARKETS RISE -- Stocks rose, sending major indexes to their highest levels since May, as battered energy shares like Exxon Mobil rebounded and investors bet that interest rates would not rise any time soon. [C13.]</p>
        <p>ROUGH TIME FOR NISSAN CHIEF -- Despite Carlos Ghosn's gilded reputation, his companies, Renault and its partner, Nissan Motor Corporation, are not performing well right now -- a fact their boss readily acknowledges. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CHICAGO WAGE EFFORT FAILS -- The first attempt in the nation to impose minimum wage regulations on big-box stores like Wal-Mart unraveled as Chicago's City Council fell three votes short of overriding Mayor Richard M. Daley's veto. [A18.]</p>
        <p>PLAN FOR JOBLESS INSURANCE -- The unemployment insurance system, which has hardly changed since its inception in 1935, should be revamped to aid more workers displaced by a transforming economy, economists said as they released overhaul plans. [A21.]</p>
        <p>HELP FOR WHITE-COLLAR WORKERS -- Barbara Ehrenreich, author of ''Nickel and Dimed,'' has started an organization called United Professionals to help white-collar workers, be they unemployed, uninsured, downsized, stressed out or merely anxious. [A21.]</p>
        <p>H.P. AND SPYING CASE -- California prosecutors looking into the Hewlett-Packard spying case are focusing on a small private investigation firm operating out of a house in suburban Boston. It is not clear how such a tiny firm ended up handling work for H.P., one of the largest technology companies. But other private investigators said it was not surprising, because corporations who are in need of such services often end rely on subcontractors. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TRIAL SET FOR DIRECT MARKETER -- The lawsuit in which the coupon company Valassis Communications seeks to cancel its $1.3 billion merger agreement with the direct-mail marketer Advo will go to trial in December, a judge ruled. [C5.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>A BANK REBUILDS -- Gary Rivlin of The Times spoke with chief executive of Liberty Bank, Alden J. McDonald Jr., about struggling to rebuild after Hurricane Katrina. An audio report is at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>ETHANOL USE -- As proponents of ethanol push for its use, Alexei Barrionuevo of The Times went on a road trip through the Midwest to find out how available the fuel is to the American driver. His report is at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>ONLINE: DEALBOOK -- A report on mergers and acquisitions, up-to-the-minute news on Wall Street and a look at the behind-the-scenes maneuvering is at nytimes.com/dealbook.</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>AIRBUS MAY DELAY DELIVERY of its A380 airliner by more than a year amid rising production costs, said Mike Turner, chief executive of BAE Systems, which owns 20 percent of Airbus. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>THE SUN-TIMES MEDIA GROUP, formerly Hollinger International Inc., said its chief executive, Gordon Paris, would step down at the end of the year as the newspaper publishing company shifts all of its New York-based corporate functions to Chicago. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
