<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saving Both Money and Energy</title>
    <meta content="10mort" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/10/realestate/10mort.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1788927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="MORTGAGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6D71731F933A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saving Both Money and Energy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Saving Both Money and Energy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB TEDESCHI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOMEOWNERS who are tired of worrying about high utility bills, or who want to minimize their homes' effect on the environment, are turning to an often overlooked type of loan for relief.</p>
        <p>So-called Energy Efficient Mortgages, which were introduced in the 1980's to help existing owners and prospective buyers pay for energy-saving home improvements, have gained more attention recently, even as mortgage activity has slumped as interest rates have risen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Homeowners are turning to so-called Energy Efficient Mortgages to help minimize their high utility bills, as well as their homes’ effect on the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOMEOWNERS who are tired of worrying about high utility bills, or who want to minimize their homes' effect on the environment, are turning to an often overlooked type of loan for relief.</p>
        <p>So-called Energy Efficient Mortgages, which were introduced in the 1980's to help existing owners and prospective buyers pay for energy-saving home improvements, have gained more attention recently, even as mortgage activity has slumped as interest rates have risen.</p>
        <p>''We've seen a tremendous increase in interest in these over the past year,'' said Joel Wiese, the manager of the Indigo Financial Group, a mortgage broker in Lansing, Mich. ''More people are becoming concerned about the energy performance of their homes.''</p>
        <p>There are a few flavors of Energy Efficient Mortgages, or E.E.M.'s. The one most widely available to mortgage applicants, industry executives said, is Fannie Mae's product, which is offered by many big lenders.</p>
        <p>With Fannie Mae's Energy Efficient Mortgage, which is sometimes referred to as the ''conventional E.E.M.,'' homeowners can spend up to 15 percent of the appraised value of the home on energy improvements and thereby qualify for a loan that is 15 percent greater than they would have received under normal underwriting conditions. Lenders also guarantee that the appraised value of the home will increase by the amount the borrower spends on those improvements, which typically include insulation, new windows and efficient heating and cooling systems.</p>
        <p>To qualify, homeowners must submit the house or their construction plans to an energy audit, arranged by the prospective lender. The lender will then use the audit to determine which energy improvements will save more money than they cost.</p>
        <p>For instance, if a homeowner plans to increase his mortgage by $10,000 for energy improvements, that would add roughly $60 per month to his loan payment (assuming a 30-year fixed mortgage at 6 percent).</p>
        <p>If the lender's energy audit determines that those improvements would save $60 or more a month, the loan would be approved.</p>
        <p>In most cases, Mr. Wiese said, the savings are considerably greater. The average Energy Efficient Mortgage loan recipient, he said, spends $10,000 on improvements and reduces his annual utility costs by 30 percent to 50 percent.</p>
        <p>The Federal Housing Administration and the Department of Veterans Affairs also offer such mortgages, but both have lower ceilings for energy improvement expenditures.</p>
        <p>One possible downside to the program is that although the home's appraised value increases by the amount the owner spends on improvements, that value may not be reflected in the ultimate resale price. Mr. Wiese said that many real estate agents do not take a house's energy performance into consideration. ''We advise our clients to contact us so we can train their Realtors on how to approach this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some lenders are doing more to encourage borrowers to consider these loans. For those who are building new homes, for instance, Wells Fargo will guarantee a mortgage interest rate for up to two years if they agree to take out an Energy Efficient Mortgage and will also lower the rate to reflect declines within 60 days of settlement.</p>
        <p>''If you have lower overall household expenses, you're a better credit risk,'' said Stuart Tyrie, a vice president of Wells Fargo Home Mortgage. ''So we'll allow you to purchase slightly more home.''</p>
        <p>Currently, fewer than 1 percent of all loans are Energy Efficient Mortgages, according to industry executives. But environmentalists, among others, are hoping that the recent interest in such loans will continue, even if fuel prices drop. ''Two different forces lead you to the same solution,'' said Jeremy Symons, the director of the National Wildlife Federation's global warming campaign. ''Saving energy is good for the pocketbook, but also for your kids because you're saving the environment.''</p>
        <p>MORTGAGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
