<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saving the Planet, One Book at a Time</title>
    <meta content="09donadio" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/09/books/review/09donadio.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1774586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DB1430F93AA35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saving the Planet, One Book at a Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Saving the Planet, One Book at a Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rachel Donadio</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Donadio, Rachel</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH its flowcharts and glossy photos of wilderness and industrial blight, the companion volume to Al Gore's environmental documentary, ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' is basically a Power Point presentation on paper. Appleton Green Power Utopia 80# Matte, to be precise, a recycled paper with a sanctimonious name befitting a book that also says it's -- brace yourself -- ''carbon neutral,'' the first book ever to offset 100 percent of the carbon dioxide generated in publishing it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Publishers are jumping on the eco-books bandwagon. But how green can a product made of felled trees and toxic ink be?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH its flowcharts and glossy photos of wilderness and industrial blight, the companion volume to Al Gore's environmental documentary, ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' is basically a Power Point presentation on paper. Appleton Green Power Utopia 80# Matte, to be precise, a recycled paper with a sanctimonious name befitting a book that also says it's -- brace yourself -- ''carbon neutral,'' the first book ever to offset 100 percent of the carbon dioxide generated in publishing it.</p>
        <p>Gore's publisher, the gardening and health giant Rodale, took steps to use carbon offsets, a system by which you help finance the production of relatively clean sources of energy to make up for the less clean sources you've relied on. While ''carbon neutral'' may be a stretch, Rodale said the offsets would go toward three renewable energy projects run by NativeEnergy, ''a privately held Native American energy company,'' which estimates that 37.5 tons of carbon dioxide were generated in the production of the book's first edition, including the use of office machines and lights, printing equipment, and the trucks used to transport the book to distribution centers. The book is No. 2 on the paperback best-seller list, with 225,000 copies in print. (Paramount Classics also used carbon offsets for some of the energy used for the documentary.)</p>
        <p>While this is the kind of environmental consciousness we've come to expect from the former passenger of Air Force Two, Gore's is not the only effort afoot to produce greener books. In recent weeks, Random House, which estimates it buys 120,000 tons of paper a year for its 88 imprints, announced a four-year plan to increase its use of recycled paper. Some trade publishers, including Chronicle Books, and a number of leading university presses have signed on to a treatise aimed at shifting the book industry's ''collective average use of postconsumer recycled fiber'' -- paper made with previously used material -- to a 30 percent average in 2011 from a 5 percent average today. According to the Green Press Initiative, the nonprofit organization shepherding the effort, this would conserve an estimated 524 million pounds of greenhouse gases annually -- the equivalent of keeping 45,800 cars off the road -- and save 4.9 million trees, 2.1 billion gallons of water and 264 million pounds of solid waste each year.</p>
        <p>Among other things, the treatise also sets guidelines for the provenance of nonrecycled paper, or ''virgin sheets,'' in greenie nomenclature. ''Large publishers and others have been debating the issues for years now,'' said Tyson Miller, the director of the Green Press Initiative. He said the treatise ''sets goals and a process for actually doing something about the book industry's social and environmental impacts.'' If more publishers bought in bulk, market demand would drive the price of recycled paper down. ''We want to see an economy of scale develop,'' Miller said.</p>
        <p>But how green can an industry ever be whose product depends on felled trees and toxic ink? While hardly strip mining, the publishing industry's sales strategy is famously based on waste. Return rates for books average 25 percent, which means bookstores return one in four books unsold to publishers, who pay to have them pulped. And in a business with relatively small profit margins, how much are publishers willing to pay to be virtuous? It's hard to imagine carbon offsetting becoming widespread -- except as part of the publicity strategy for select titles. While the Green Press Initiative cites a study showing that some buyers, especially women, would be willing to pay as much as $1 more for a book printed on recycled paper, publishers aren't always willing to pay the extra cost up front. It's difficult to get clear estimates of the price difference, but industry experts say it typically runs 4 to 6 percent higher. In recent years, several companies have developed lines of book-quality recycled paper, which is generally made by bleaching the ink out of once-virgin fiber and reconstituting it into new paper.</p>
        <p>Random House, which has not signed the Green Press Initiative's treatise, describes its own recycled-paper push as ''a multimillion dollar investment'' it's prepared to shoulder without raising book prices. Peter Olson, the company's chief executive, decided the time had come ''to stop making eye-rolling excuses about how burdensome and expensive environmental initiatives are,'' Stuart Applebaum, the chief spokesman for Random House, said in an e-mail message. The company has pledged that 10 percent of the paper it uses will ''derive from recycled paper fibers'' by 2007, rising to 30 percent in 2010 -- though the percentage of recycled content in its papers will vary. (The New York Times Company uses an average of 27 percent recycled content in its newsprint.) Random House says its nonrecycled paper will come from ''well-managed forests credibly certified by a third party.''</p>
        <p>Some powerful authors, including Alice Walker, Barbara Kingsolver and Alice Munro, have insisted their books be published on paper with recycled content. But not all writers have as much sway with their publishers. In her 2005 book, ''Garbage Land,'' about what happens to the things we throw away, the science writer Elizabeth Royte described her unsuccessful efforts to persuade her publisher, Little, Brown, to print the book on recycled paper. ''It just goes to show how hard it is to move the bottom-line culture, even with a book that's a natural fit for recycled paper,'' Royte said. (Little, Brown didn't return requests for comment.)</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, the greenest book on the market may be one made not from paper, but from -- the horror! -- plastic. In their 2002 environmental manifesto, ''Cradle to Cradle,'' William McDonough, the green architecture pioneer, and Michael Braungart, a German chemist, argue that traditional recycling just delays the trip to the landfill, and push for developing reusable materials. (Paper can be recycled only about three times before it's no longer high enough quality to use for books; lower quality papers can be recycled about seven times.) To prove their point, they had the book published on plastic -- DuraBook, a patented material developed by Melcher Media, a book packager and publisher in New York that also produced Al Gore's book. ''The medium is the message,'' McDonough said in a telephone interview. ''The planet is awash in plastic, literally . . . so why not use plastic for books instead of paper?'' The book can be melted down and used to make new books or other products, which themselves could be melted down again. ''We need plastics. We're not going to go back to nature,'' McDonough said. ''We're not going back to being hunter-gatherers. The best thing is to use them.''</p>
        <p>Published by North Point Press and printed in China, ''Cradle to Cradle'' has sold steadily, and now has 100,000 copies in print in its English edition. It cost one-third more to produce than a traditional book, McDonough said, so the authors agreed to take lower royalties. (The foreign-language editions are printed on paper.) For their next book, which will further elaborate their ideas on green design and reusable materials, McDonough said he and Braungart are experimenting with ''a surprising new material,'' also synthetic, as well as inks safe for use with food. He declined to be more specific. Time will tell whether McDonough and Braungart will make eco-skeptics eat their words.</p>
        <p>ESSAY Rachel Donadio is a writer and editor at the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Rachel Donadio is a writer and editor at the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
