<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Solar Power Where You Might Not Expect It</title>
    <meta content="04njsola" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1766600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Verona (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prout, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Joachim, David S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E0D91631F937A35755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Solar Power Where You Might Not Expect It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID S. JOACHIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Joachim, David S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Bob Prout, funeral home director in Verona, NJ, who, along with other individuals and business owners, is taking advantage of solar rebates, part of New Jersey's Clean Energy Program; more than half of state's $165 million budget for program went to solar rebate program last year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BOB PROUT just spent $340,000 for a solar electric system to power his family's third-generation funeral home in Verona. He also turned an old smoking room in the basement into a miniature green museum, with his solar conversion equipment encased in glass for visitors to see.</p>
        <p>This is no futuristic vanity project for Mr. Prout, 50, who drives a hybrid car and has been a member of the Hudson-Essex-Passaic Soil Conservation District since 1979. He said it was a shrewd business move.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BOB PROUT just spent $340,000 for a solar electric system to power his family's third-generation funeral home in Verona. He also turned an old smoking room in the basement into a miniature green museum, with his solar conversion equipment encased in glass for visitors to see.</p>
        <p>This is no futuristic vanity project for Mr. Prout, 50, who drives a hybrid car and has been a member of the Hudson-Essex-Passaic Soil Conservation District since 1979. He said it was a shrewd business move.</p>
        <p>That is because of a New Jersey program that paid about $200,000 of Mr. Prout's costs and allowed him to sell surplus power back to his utility, the Public Service Electric and Gas Company, producing income of up to $10,000 a year. He plans to use the money and the savings on his energy bill to pay off the $140,000 he borrowed for the system, which he says will take seven or eight years. Then it will be all profit.</p>
        <p>He said he had been keeping an eye on solar technology since roof panels appeared in the 1980's. ''I had looked 18 months ago, and I thought, 'Well, the efficiencies really aren't great. Should I wait?' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Then, he said, he thought about the rising cost of energy, the turmoil in oil-rich countries and global warming. ''I said, 'I have to act on this belief now,' '' Mr. Prout said. The state incentives, introduced in their current form in 2003, pushed him over the top.</p>
        <p>Now he is using his business, which experts say has energy needs typical of small companies with public spaces, including its heavy use of refrigeration, to promote renewable energy. He created a 45-minute presentation for children, which includes a video on renewable energy, a tour of the roof panels and a question-and-answer period on what children can do for the cause. During a recent week, he gave the presentation to 150 children from science classes and scout troops.</p>
        <p>''You have to expose the next generation to this technology if you want it to be mainstream in the future,'' Mr. Prout said.</p>
        <p>Experts say New Jersey is thinking long term, too. It has set an aggressive schedule for making renewable energy -- wind, water, geothermal -- contribute a large portion of the state's power needs, with an emphasis on solar power produced at the point of consumption, like a home or an office building. More than half of the $165 million budget for its Clean Energy Program went to the solar rebate program last year, said Michael Winka, director of New Jersey's Office of Clean Energy.</p>
        <p>About 3.5 percent of New Jersey's energy comes from renewable sources. The timetable calls for an increase to 5.5 percent by 2008 and 20 percent by 2020. ''We're on a path to do that,'' said Jeanne M. Fox, president of the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities.</p>
        <p>As promising as solar power is, it is much more expensive per watt than other renewable energy sources, like wind, Ms. Fox said. For that reason, wind farms that are operated by power companies, not only in New Jersey but also throughout the larger power grid that touches 14 states, will represent the bulk of the new clean energy, she said. Only about one-tenth will come from solar.</p>
        <p>Still, for homeowners and business owners like Mr. Prout, the large rebates are recasting the math.</p>
        <p>''New Jersey has the best set of regulations and incentives to encourage the use of solar energy in the country,'' said Rhone Resch, president of the Solar Energy Industries Association, a lobbying group.</p>
        <p>The rebate program has also kick-started the solar industry in the state. Dan Lichtman, an owner of Absolutely Energized Solar Electric in Millstone Township, N.J., which installed the solar system at the Prout Funeral Home, said he had two or three competitors when he started three and a half years ago. Now there are too many to count, and large retailers like Home Depot have gotten into the act.</p>
        <p>The rebate program will not last forever. Ms. Fox, of the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, said it was intended only to prime the local solar market and would be phased out in 5 to 10 years. By then, it is anticipated that the price of solar panels will be so low that people will switch without subsidies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prout said he would keep doing his part by showing off his funeral home. ''I'm hoping to expose that if a very traditional business like a funeral home can thrive with this technology, it must be moving toward the mainstream,'' he said. ''It's not just for leftover hippies and tree huggers from the 60's.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
