<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Warming: Let's Do Better</title>
    <meta content="l01warm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1801366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D6123FF932A35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Warming: Let's Do Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Budgets Falling in Race to Fight Global Warming'' (''The Energy Challenge'' series, front page, Oct. 30):</p>
        <p>As the evidence for global warming continues to mount, it still never breaks into the top 10 issues that concern voters.</p>
        <p>Yet if the growing consensus of scientists is correct, global warming represents a greater threat to the future of our children than any of the issues that place well above it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Budgets Falling in Race to Fight Global Warming'' (''The Energy Challenge'' series, front page, Oct. 30):</p>
        <p>As the evidence for global warming continues to mount, it still never breaks into the top 10 issues that concern voters.</p>
        <p>Yet if the growing consensus of scientists is correct, global warming represents a greater threat to the future of our children than any of the issues that place well above it.</p>
        <p>The Republicans, with their heavy indebtedness to the energy industry, would like nothing better than to keep it that way. The Democrats, who seem to fear offending any potential voter, aren't saying much about it either.</p>
        <p>Those who advocate doing nothing, or very little, like to point out that there is a lack of certainty in the global warming debate. But this lack of certainty should be a call for action, not inaction.</p>
        <p>My daughter will soon be celebrating her fifth birthday. I can't look at her without thinking that before long she will be a young adult. I fear for the state of planet she will inherit if we continue to do nothing to protect it.</p>
        <p>We cannot continue to place the weight of our excesses today on the backs of our children tomorrow. They deserve better, and we can do better.</p>
        <p>Bob Rosenbluth  Lincolndale, N.Y., Oct. 30, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>We can't wait for government or industry to finance searches for alternative energy sources. We have to take it upon ourselves as citizens of the earth to act now to reduce carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Why can't we drive less, walk more, put out unneeded lights, lower thermostats, and so on, as well as reduce consumption, and reuse and recycle goods?</p>
        <p>All it takes is a conscious effort by each of us to begin to slow global warming. Think about it. We can begin to do it now. We don't have to wait.</p>
        <p>Eve Winer  Flushing, Queens, Oct. 30, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It is disheartening enough, from an ecological viewpoint, to note that our government devotes a shrinking budget to solving the puzzles of energy conservation and alternative energy sources. Our dependence on foreign oil is another big dimension of this issue.</p>
        <p>Washington would rather commit an endless flow of war dollars to ensure the flow of Middle East oil than to find a long-term solution to our energy needs. We seem to speak of oil only when we moan about the price of it. Yet it is oil that drives much of American foreign policy, and that will not change until we find efficient ways to use less of it.</p>
        <p>Bruce J. Bloom  Southold, N.Y., Oct. 30, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Despite the gloom, at least there is a public discussion about the causes and effects of global warming and the need for developing alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>Missing entirely is a public discussion of how we prepare for the effects of rising ocean levels, an accelerating phenomenon well under way.</p>
        <p>The melting of Arctic Sea ice cannot be stopped under the most hopeful of conditions for at least several decades, and perhaps a century or more.</p>
        <p>Consider New Orleans. Why are we rebuilding that city when we know that there is a high likelihood that the Atlantic Ocean will rise three feet during the next 100 years?</p>
        <p>John V. Kjellman  Henniker, N.H., Oct. 30, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The widespread use of clean energy -- from wind, solar and hydropower -- is one of the solutions we need to fight global warming.</p>
        <p>While we must continue pushing for more federal financing for the research and development of low-emission energies to counter global warming, we need to look at a more powerful mechanism for catalyzing long-term change, the market.</p>
        <p>In particular, we need to look at demand.</p>
        <p>Stoking demand for clean energy will develop fertile markets that will inspire companies to capitalize on the opportunity and attract private-sector financing and investment, fostering additional innovation.</p>
        <p>If demand is there and people know that money can be made, that will drive the change, creating the economy that will attract the money that will support the innovation.</p>
        <p>As the saying goes, money goes to money.</p>
        <p>Brian F. Keane  Hartford, Oct. 31, 2006</p>
        <p>The writer is president of SmartPower, a nonprofit marketing group that promotes clean, renewable energy.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Scandal Below the Surface,'' by Nicholas D. Kristof (column, Oct. 31):</p>
        <p>At the risk of sounding like a wide-eyed naïf, I'd like to suggest that those worried about the costs of a fight against the damage done by greenhouse emissions consider how much is being spent against another nebulous ''enemy,'' terrorism.</p>
        <p>In fact, they are powerfully connected, in that increased alternative energy sources will reduce our need for oil found in the Middle East, and thus reduce our need to have a presence there.</p>
        <p>A global war on climate change might not sound as masculine as the war being marketed, but it is ultimately more important, and is actually one we could all win.</p>
        <p>For politicians without the will to curb crony capitalism, it would afford a means of doing some good while still bringing home the pork.</p>
        <p>We can beat swords into solar cells.</p>
        <p>David Schwartz  Baltimore, Oct. 31, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
