<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: August 4 - August 10</title>
    <meta content="04thea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060805T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1780507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7DF113FF937A3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="14723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: August 4 - August 10</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' In previews; opens on Aug. 16. If you were one of the people who missed the 17,162 performances of this show the last time around, good news: Harvey Schmidt and Tom Jones's romantic musical, which closed in 2002, is back (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'INDIAN BLOOD' In previews; opens on Thursday. Primary Stages presents A. R. Gurney's new comedy about a rebellious boy coming of age in the 1940's. Mark Lamos directs (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' In previews; opens on Aug. 17. This musical sendup of biographical shows features Martin Short and an ensemble telling the story of his life. Mr. Short's beloved old characters, like Ed Grimley and Jiminy Glick, make appearances (2:15). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>MIDTOWN INTERNATIONAL THEATER FESTIVAL Through Sunday. This seventh annual showcase can all too easily get lost in the shuffle, despite its large and diverse collection of shows. There should be more than 60 productions this season, at four locations on 36th Street. Schedules and information: (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'MOTHER COURAGE AND HER CHILDREN' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Aug. 21. Meryl Streep plays the title character in Tony Kushner's translation of Brecht's seminal play about a world at war. Kevin Kline also stars, and George C. Wolfe directs (2:30). Delacorte Theater, Central Park. Free. Ticket information: (212) 539-8750.</p>
        <p>'SEVEN GUITARS' In previews; opens Aug. 24. Signature Theater presents its first August Wilson revival since the playwright's death last year. Ruben Santiago-Hudson, who starred in the 1996 Broadway production, directs (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER' An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ALL THIS INTIMACY' In this not-very-deep comedy-drama by Rajiv Joseph, a 30-year-old poet impregnates not only his girlfriend, but also two other women, within two weeks. The women, once they meet, are surprisingly unimpressed with his notable virility (1:45). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 246-4422. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' Tormenting memories dissolve into soaring music, and pain is salved by a collective embrace in this heartfelt, powerfully performed theater piece about life under apartheid. The recollections of the five cast members and authors are woven together with a cappella performances of spirituals from the apartheid years and vignettes performed by the full cast. The actors all but glow with a sense of mission, as if telling their stories has given them new purpose and power (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School. Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200 (1:10). (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOUT!' A mini-skirted, go-go booted zombie of a musical about women searching for love in London in the 1960's. You won't see anything this groovy, this far-out, this with-it outside of, oh, maybe the show room of a Carnival Cruise ship (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A STONE CARVER' Despite the high cliché factor, William Mastrosimone's play about an Italian immigrant who is losing his house to a highway exit is timely and sporadically touching, in large part because of Dan Lauria's over-the-top performance as the title character and old-world patriarch who makes a mean barrel of wine and never talks when he can shout (1:40). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'IF YOU GIVE A MOUSE A COOKIE &amp; OTHER STORY BOOKS' This children's musical, made up of 10 sketches based on 8 books, is diverse, adorable and free. Also, the adults laugh (1:00). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village; (212) 642-9033. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NEVER TELL' The computer-involved characters in James Christy's intriguing drama about trust, video art and a society-changing application can be irritating but they're never boring (1:50). Michael Weller Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' Another excavation of what seems to have become Broadway's favorite musical terrain -- call it Scamalot, where con men are king (see ''The Producers''). Now starring Keith Carradine and Brian D'Arcy James as the mismatched swindlers (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CLOUD TECTONICS' A solid rendition of Jose Rivera's thin fable about time, centering on a hitchhiking woman who has been pregnant for two years. Luis Vega is particularly good as the man who gives her a ride and shelter for the night (1:30). Culture Project-45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this old comedy from the 1930's, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). Bank Street Theater, 155 Bank Street, West Village, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200; closes tomorrow. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ANT BULLY' (PG, 90 minutes) A young boy goes to live among the ants, who talk remarkably like Academy Award-winning actors. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'BEEN RICH ALL MY LIFE' (No rating, 80 minutes) This admiring documentary portrait of the Silver Belles, an indefatigable troupe of veteran Harlem tap dancers between the ages of 84 and 96, is a valuable historical footnote and a useful how-to movie about making the most of old age. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'CLERKS II' (R, 98 minutes) More than a decade later, Kevin Smith's New Jersey underachievers have moved from a convenience store to a fast-food franchise. The humor is reliably filthy and frequently hilarious, and the filmmaking is a few steps above rudimentary, but the movie's poignant sweetness is disarming. It has a dirty mind, but its heart is remarkably pure. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'Gabrielle' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haute bourgeois Parisian marriage, about 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems that Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over, and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'I Like Killing Flies' (R, 79 minutes) The documentary filmmaker Matt Mahurin paints an engaging if glib portrait of Kenny Shopsin, of the legendary or notorious, depending on your experience, Greenwich Village eatery that bears his name. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'LADY IN THE WATER' (PG-13, 108 minutes) In this watchable folly, Paul Giamatti plays a building manager who encounters a menagerie of otherworldly creatures, most important Bryce Dallas Howard's water nymph. The writer and director M. Night Shyamalan wants us to believe, mostly in the myth of his own genius. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>* Little Miss Sunshine (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MIAMI VICE' (R, 133 minutes) This updating of the 1980's television series cost more than the annual budget of the real-life Miami Police Department, making it the most expensive experimental art film ever made. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. A trio of intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband, and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PEACEFUL WARRIOR' (PG-13, 120 minutes) As ludicrous as the title promises, yet supremely unembarrassed, this New Age enlightenment parable has its heart in the right place, but a mind of corny mush. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'The Photographer, His Wife, Her Lover' (Not rated, 79 minutes) Art, adultery, divorce, lawyers and pots of money. Paul Yule's documentary wades unproductively through the mess surrounding the estate of the Brooklyn-born photographer O. Winston Link, who died in 2001. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' (PG-13, 151 minutes) Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)  * 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* Scoop (PG-13, 96 minutes) A not especially funny yet oddly appealing comedy in which Woody Allen and Scarlett Johansson make like Nick and Nora, but with more shtick and no martinis (or Asta). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SHADOWBOXER' (R, 93 minutes) This garish thriller starring Helen Mirren and Cuba Gooding Jr. as contract killers and lovers is an extravagance that leaves you with your mouth hanging open -- partly in admiration of its audacity and partly in disbelief at its preposterousness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'13 Tzameti'  (No rating, 90 minutes) The flashy black-and-white directorial debut of the Georgian filmmaker Gela Babluani is a sadistic, arty thriller that suggests a French new wave film infected by a virulent strain of Eastern European nihilism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>You, Me and Dupree' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>THE BEST OF BUSTER: KEATON COMEDY CLASSICS (Through Sept. 25) Film Forum's eight-week festival of the silent comedies of the brilliantly stone-faced Keaton (1895-1966) begins on Monday night. ''The General'' (1926), his version of the great Civil War locomotive chase, will be shown, along with three early-1920's shorts. Other films in the series include ''Sherlock Jr.'' (1924) and ''The Cameraman'' (1928). 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8110; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) The 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962) continues at the Museum of the Moving Image with four films this weekend. They include two World War I love stories with literary pedigrees: ''A Farewell to Arms'' (1932), starring Gary Cooper and Helen Hayes, and ''Three Comrades'' (1938), with Robert Taylor and Margaret Sullavan. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NOW THAT'S HIP! (Through Aug. 29) As part of the River to River arts festival, the HIP Health Plan of New York is sponsoring outdoor screenings of movies set in New York, preceded by shorts from New York filmmakers. The four-movie August series begins on Tuesday with ''Barefoot in the Park'' (1967), in which Robert Redford and Jane Fonda play mismatched newlyweds in a minuscule downtown apartment. The other films, all to be shown on Tuesday nights, are ''Pickup on South Street'' (1953), ''Mr. Deeds Goes to Town'' (1936) and ''Rear Window'' (1954). Elevated Acre, 55 Water Street, (212) 835-2789; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>PLAY IT LOUD: ROCK DOCS 2006 (Through Thursday) The Film Society of Lincoln Center's nine-film series of rock-music documentaries rocks on. This weekend's films include ''Everyone Stares: The Police Inside Out'' (2005), the history of the band as seen by its drummer, Stewart Copeland; and ''No Direction Home: Bob Dylan'' (2005), Martin Scorsese's portrait of the young Dylan. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RAISING HELL: SAM PECKINPAH (Through Aug. 29) BAMcinématek's monthlong tribute to Peckinpah (1925-84) continues. Monday night's feature is ''The Getaway'' (1972), in which Steve McQueen and Ali McGraw rob a bank, badly. Tuesday night's is ''The Ballad of Cable Hogue'' (1970), starring Jason Robards as an entrepreneurial prospector. BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SUMMER SWASHBUCKLERS (Through Aug. 24) Film Forum's 36-movie celebration of old-style action pictures begins this weekend with two double features. ''Captain Blood'' (1935), with Errol Flynn, and ''The Scarlet Pimpernel'' (1935), with Leslie Howard, are on the bill for Friday and Saturday, to be shown with ''The Scarlet Pumpernickel'' (1950), starring the dashing Daffy Duck. Sunday's films are ''The Prisoner of Zenda'' (1937), with Ronald Colman and Douglas Fairbanks Jr., and ''The Mark of Zorro'' (1920), with the other Fairbanks -- Douglas Sr. (See above.) (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* CELEBRATE BROOKLYN AFRICAN FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) One of the highlights of the Celebrate Brooklyn schedule each summer is its daylong African concert, any 10 minutes of which is well worth the $3 suggested donation. This year features Kekele, a supergroup of Congolese rumba elders gathered à la ''Buena Vista Social Club,'' and Lagbaja, a Nigerian bandleader who plays muscular Afro-funk and hides his face in a scarf to symbolize Africa's political anonymity. (His name means ''anybody'' in Yoruban.) Others on the bill include Razia, a singer born in Madagascar and raised in Gabon; the African Underground All-Stars, a pan-African hip-hop collective whose M.C.'s include Chosan, from Sierra Leone, and Dola, of Tanzania; and Martino Atangana, a Cameroonian guitarist who lives in New York. From 2 to 9 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882, brooklynx.org. Lagbaja also plays at 8 and 11 p.m. on Wednesday at S.O.B.'s., 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARSHALL CRENSHAW (Tuesday and Wednesday) Marshall Crenshaw's songs seem to roll off the guitar in a casual blend of pre-1970's styles -- folk-rock, surf-rock, country and above all, the Beatles -- that put melody first. With his winsome tenor, he delves into the ways love goes right and goes wrong, from distant yearning to the aftermath of infidelity, hiding turmoil within the chiming tunes. At 10 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500, rodeobar.com; no cover. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133, dannysgrandseapalace.com; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>HAZEL DICKENS; BONNY BILLY AND CAPTAIN ANOMOANON (Tomorrow and Sunday) The daughter of a West Virginia coal miner, Hazel Dickens sings sharp and unadorned bluegrass songs about hardship and defiant proletarian pride. (''They'll never shoot that union out of me.'') Nineteen years ago she appeared in John Sayles's film ''Matewan'' alongside Will Oldham, who has since developed a postmodern Appalachian folk style. He performs as Bonny Billy (one of his many pseudonyms), along with his brother Ned, who appears as Captain Anomoanon. Tomorrow at 7 and 9:30 p.m., Sunday at 4 and 6:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200, joespub.com; sold out tomorrow, $30 on Sunday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIRTY DOZEN BRASS BAND (Tuesday) The magnificent ensemble that revitalized New Orleans brass-band music. It swaggers through the city's whole musical heritage: parades, rumba, swing, be-bop and modern jazz, for starters. Solos can head for the far side of tonality, but the band never loses touch with gutbucket, danceable funk. At 8:15 p.m., Josie Robertson Plaza at Lincoln Center, Columbus Avenue at 64th Street, (212) 875-5766, lincolncenter.org; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>FORRÓ IN THE DARK (Wednesday) For more than three years now, this group has been leading one of New York's best and lowest-tech dance parties at the East Village bar Nublu. The groove is a humble and sexy two-beat dance from northeastern Brazil called forró, made with accordion, hand-held percussion and, since this is New York, whiffs of distorted electric guitar. At 11 p.m. and 12:30 a.m., 62 Avenue C, between Fourth and Fifth Streets, East Village, nublu.net; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Thursday) She is invariably dressed in black, her face in witchy streaks of makeup, but Diamanda Galás needs only her voice to terrify, seduce and beguile. She slides from a low, sensual growl to painful yet musically precise shrieks, and has a vast repertory that ranges from darkened Johnny Cash ballads to her own chilling AIDS Masses. In the first of four shows at the new Spiegeltent downtown, she offers ''Long Black Veil,'' a program of morbid music by Screamin' Jay Hawkins, Ornette Coleman and others. At 6 p.m., Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* HOT CHIP (Tonight) With wobbly electronic rhythms that seem to be made of melting jelly, and a strong command of the drippy disco ballad, this English group plays a kind of wistful but still snarky dance music. Get too lost in the beats and you'll miss smart gags like the oh-so-art-rock countdown of nonsense words in descending numbers of letters (''S-E-X-I-N-G, C-A-S-I-O, P-O-K-E''). With Oppenheimer. At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789, seaportmusicfestival.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) This two-week multidisciplinary and multinational series in Queens winds up this weekend. The gritty, deep-voiced Cuban singer Albita performs tonight. Tomorrow features Inti-Illimani, a veteran Chilean group that plays traditional Andean songs, as well as African and Spanish hybrids. On Sunday Peru Negro, a big troupe of dancers and singers, traverses three centuries of Afro-Peruvian music. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 and 7 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $35 tonight and Sunday, $30 tomorrow; $5 off when bought in advance. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LATIN ALTERNATIVE MUSIC CONFERENCE (Tonight and tomorrow) This annual series of concerts and discussion panels began six years ago, when a few Latin pop stars stood atop the charts (Ricky Martin, Jennifer Lopez), a varied rock and electronic scene flourished underground, and ''rock en Español'' was a marketing buzzword.The situation now is much the same, with fewer buzzwords: Shakira is an international phenomenon, while most Latin rock artists remain largely unknown to English-speaking American audiences. This will be mulled extensively at the daytime panels, but the best proof of the scene's vitality is the music itself. This weekend offers two free shows: Tonight at Celebrate Brooklyn are the Venezuelan groove-rockers Los Amigos Invisibles; Los Bunkers, from Chile; and Belanova, an electro-pop group from Mexico. Tomorrow afternoon at Central Park SummerStage are Gustavo Cerati, the former leader of the Argentine rock heroes Soda Stereo; Calle 13, a Puerto Rican reggaetón group; and the Mexican Institute of Sound. Tonight at 7:30, Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882; $3 suggested donation. Tomorrow at 3, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. Information: latinalternative.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LL COOL J (Monday) One of the first bigger-than-the-block personalities of rap, LL Cool J still follows the same few guidelines of self-representation that have served him throughout his long career: appear shirtless as often as possible for photographers, title all your albums either after yourself (''Todd Smith,'' his latest, refers to his given name, James Todd Smith) or some superlative that Muhammad Ali might have used (''Phenomenon,'' ''Greatest of All Time''), and perform in as sweatily vigorous a way as you can. At 7:30 p.m., Wingate Field, Winthrop Street, between Brooklyn and Kingston Avenues, East Flatbush, Brooklyn, (718) 469-1912, brooklynconcerts.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MANU CHAO (Monday) This great globalist rocker makes a rare appearance. In the 1980's, Manu Chao, a musical omnivore born in France to Spanish parents, led the pioneering Latin rock band Mano Negra, which fused the angry political punk of the Clash with flamenco and Algerian rai. Since the late 90's, despite minimal output, he has been a celebrated and inspirational symbol of high-minded, do-it-yourself multiculturalism: he dabbles in reggae and dub, rap, salsa, calypso and rock, and recently produced the eclectic Malian duo Amadou and Mariam. He plays a benefit concert for Celebrate Brooklyn, with Plastilina Mosh as the opening act. At 7 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell (see above); sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAVE MATTHEWS BAND (Tomorrow and Sunday) His own private Bonnaroo: Dave Matthews has programmed two days of kindred spirits at Randalls Island, a minifestival with a much more manageable seven bands instead of seven dozen. Both days feature the Dave Matthews Band, the robotically virtuosic banjoing of Bela Fleck and the Flecktones, the three-cheers-for-marijuana ska of Slightly Stoopid, and the Grateful Dead-influenced Tea Leaf Green. Tomorrow also has the mighty Southern rockers Gov't Mule, and on Sunday David Gray, the British singer-songwriter whose ballads mingle acoustic guitar and gentle electronica, will perform. At noon, Randalls Island, near Icahn Stadium, 1 Randalls Island, randallsislandconcerts.com, (212) 307-7171; sold out tomorrow, $55 and $62.50 on Sunday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE MIGHTY SPARROW (Tuesday) With wry lyrics and supple melodies, the Mighty Sparrow, who was born Slinger Francisco, made the carnival music of Trinidad and Tobago a political force and a pop phenomenon with a string of competition-winning hit songs that stretches back to the mid-1950's in which he comments on everything from the Shah to the first black Miss Universe. At 7 p.m., Queensbridge Park, Queens, (212) 360-8290, cityparksfoundation.org; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>NEWPORT FOLK FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) In a way, this veteran festival, home of ''We Shall Overcome'' singalongs and Bob Dylan's 1965 electric crossing, is one of the most creatively programmed in the country. To expand the idea of folk music -- or at least to fill up the weekend at a time when folk groups are in small supply -- Newport folds in jazz, soul, even greasy funk. Tonight's concert has more traditional fare, with Ronan Tynan and Cherish the Ladies, both from Ireland. On tomorrow's roster are David Gray, Rosanne Cash, Bettye LaVette, Sonny Landreth, Sonya Kitchell, Mary Gauthier and others; Sunday features the Indigo Girls, the veteran New Orleans funk group the Meters, Madeleine Peyroux, Keller Williams and Odetta. Absent: any representation of the vital, young and underground ''freak folk'' movement. Tonight at 8, at the International Tennis Hall of Fame; tomorrow and Sunday from 11:30 a.m. to 7 p.m. at Fort Adams State Park, Newport, R.I., (401) 847-3700, newportfolk.com; $30 to $75 tonight; $59 tomorrow and Sunday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ONE RING ZERO (Monday) This Brooklyn band has set words by authors like Jonathan Lethem, Margaret Atwood and Rick Moody to kitchen-sink songs with toy piano and theremin. The group offers a screening of ''As Smart as They Are,'' a documentary about its formation. At 8 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $20; $10 for members. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GRANT-LEE PHILLIPS (Thursday) Mr. Phillips harks back to the earnest ambitions and expansive melodies of Bob Dylan and John Lennon, singing with the conviction that rock can still be heroic. Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $15. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>THE RED KRAYOLA (Tuesday) The first album of the Red Crayola (as it was originally spelled) appeared in 1967, and Mayo Thompson has held on to its skewed psychedelic perspective ever since; he also spent some years as a member of Pere Ubu. He's fond of dissolving song structures, crypto-Marxist messages and woozy sounds, and when he reconvened the Red Krayola (the spelling was changed to avoid trademark problems) in 1994, he found fans and collaborators among progressive- and post-rock musicians. With Coyote, featuring members of the bands Vaz and Man Man. At 8 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* CANDI STATON (Wednesday) She has been a disco queen, a raw-voiced soul belter and, for much of the last two decades, a gospel singer. But Ms. Staton's greatest success has been with record collectors, who have kept her strong legacy of secular R &amp; B alive and may have persuaded her to return to it: she recently released ''His Hands'' (Honest Jon's/Astralwerks), a stirring album of broken-heart songs and rich Southern blues that is her first such recording in decades. This concert is billed as Ms. Staton's first in New York in more than 20 years. With Stephanie McKay. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WARPED TOUR (Tomorrow) Now 12 years old, this skateboards-punk-and-tattoos circus includes Thursday, From Autumn to Ashes, Against Me!, Helmet, Joan Jett and the Blackhearts, the Sounds, Motion City Soundtrack, NOFX, Bouncing Souls, Damone, Saves the Day, Senses Fail and the Academy Is  , Every Time I Die and many, many more. Best band name: Gym Class Heroes. Worst: Gatsby's American Dream. At noon, Nassau Coliseum, 1255 Hempstead Turnpike, Uniondale, N.Y., (631) 888-9000, warpedtour.com; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>MONTY ALEXANDER JAZZ AND ROOTS ENSEMBLE (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Alexander's most recent album, ''Concrete Jungle'' (Telarc), pays tribute to his celebrated countryman Bob Marley. He travels similar territory here, featuring his piano and melodica playing in a buoyant ensemble with Wendel Ferraro on guitar and vocals, Hassan Shakur on bass and George Fludas on drums. Through Aug. 13. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEFF BALLARD AND MARK TURNER (Tonight) Mr. Ballard, a drummer, and Mr. Turner, a tenor saxophonist, constitute two-thirds of Fly, a brainy yet earthy group that seeks adventure in collective interplay. Without a bassist or any harmonic accompaniment, their rapport at this performance should be stark and inspired. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARDFELD'S STUFF SMITH PROJECT (Thursday) Mr. Bardfeld is a violinist with a wide-ranging résumé who spent all of June on tour with Bruce Springsteen's ''Seeger Sessions'' band. Here he pays tribute to a swing-era hero of his instrument, with help from the pianist Anthony Coleman and the bassist Brad Jones. 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARSH (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Barsh is a keyboardist with a gift for groove, as he has demonstrated on recent albums by the bassist Avishai Cohen and the guitarist Jeff Parker. Performing on a new jazz series with a Hudson River view, he enlists Tim Collins on vibraphone, Ari Folman-Cohen on bass and Jaimeo Brown on drums. At 9 and 10:30, the River Room, Riverbank State Park, Riverside Drive at 145th Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 491-1500, theriverroomofharlem.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEDROCK (Tonight) The keyboardist Uri Caine, the bassist Tim Lefebvre and the drummer Zach Danziger make up this trio, which absorbs elements of fusion, funk and drum-and-bass into its own deliriously groovy style. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVEN BERNSTEIN'S MILLENNIAL TERRITORY ORCHESTRA (Tonight) This little big band, led by the irrepressible slide trumpeter Steven Bernstein, has a new album called ''MTO Volume 1'' (Sunnyside) that's full of signature touches, like effervescent swing arrangements and covers of hits by Prince and Stevie Wonder. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID BINNEY (Tuesday and Wednesday) This alto saxophonist pursues an avant-gardism that embraces harmony, melody and rhythm, along with amplification. He performs in two different settings next week, first with his group Balance (on Tuesday) and then with a more experimental crew (on Wednesday). Tuesday at 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. Wednesday at 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CARAMOOR JAZZ FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Roughly 50 miles upstate, this festival offers some smartly simple programming in a tented open-air environment. First up is the Paris-based pianist Kirk Lightsey, in a tribute to the recently departed John Hicks; then a quartet led by the trumpeter Jeremy Pelt; then the pianist Steve Kuhn, presenting his Third Stream compositions for a 12-piece string ensemble. After a dinner break, the pianist McCoy Tyner leads the final group, conceived as a tribute to the legacy of Impulse Records; his all-star lineup includes David Liebman and Donald Harrison on saxophones, Nicholas Payton on trumpet and Steve Turre on trombone. Starts at 2:30 p.m., with hourly sets until a dinner break at 6:30; the final set begins at 8. Caramoor, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-1252, caramoor.org; $45 and $55. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RON CARTER QUARTET (Tonight) Mr. Carter is a deeply literate bassist and composer whose ensembles usually give off light but little heat. That's fitting, in a way, for this appearance in a luminous, glass-enclosed planetarium, a ''Starry Nights'' performance to be broadcast live on WBGO. At 7:30 p.m., Rose Center for Earth and Space, American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 81st Street, (212) 313-7278, amnh.org. Suggested admission: $14; $10.50 for students; $8 for children. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAQUITO D'RIVERA SEXTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. D'Rivera, a clarinetist, alto saxophonist and longtime Cuban exile, favors bright extroversion in his music, which usually incorporates Latin rhythms. His band includes the trumpeter Diego Urcola, the pianist Alon Yavnai, the bassist Oscar Stagnaro and the percussionists Mark Walker and Pernell Saturnino. Through Aug. 13. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EHRAN ELISHA'S KINETIC MUSIC (Sunday) In the late 1990's, the percussionist Ehran Elisha recorded an album called ''Lowdown'' (CIMP) featuring a suitelike composition for a group that included Roy Campbell Jr. on trumpet, David Bindman on tenor saxophone, Sam Bardfeld on violin and Bill Lowe on tuba. Add Ken Filiano on bass, and you've got the same personnel here, though probably not the same music. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN GERSTEIN COLLECTIVE (Wednesday) Boisterous free improvisation from bright young players with a history of collaboration: Mr. Gerstein on trombone, Jacob Sacks on keyboards, Jacob Garchik on accordion and electronics, Thomas Morgan and Dave D'Ambrosio on bass and Dan Weiss on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JONATHON HAFFNER QUARTET (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mr. Haffner, an adventurous young alto saxophonist, performs tomorrow night with Bob Hoffnar on pedal steel guitar, Chris Lightcap on bass and Dan Weiss on drums. On Sunday Mr. Haffner ventures into a more exposed setting, with no accompaniment whatsoever. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. Sunday at 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARTHUR KELL QUARTET (Monday) On ''Traveller'' (Fresh Sound New Talent), the bassist and composer Arthur Kell pursues a searching strain of modern jazz; he has worthy partners here in the saxophonist Donny McCaslin, the guitarist Brad Shepik and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. At 7 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FRANCISCO MELA (Monday) Mr. Mela is a subtly dynamic drummer, attuned to the rhythmic depth of his native Cuba but adaptable to seemingly any sort of modern jazz. He's also an unassumingly good composer, as he demonstrates on ''Melao'' (Avya), the debut album that he celebrates with a quintet and several special guests, including the clarinetist and alto saxophonist Paquito D'Rivera, the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner and the pianist Jason Moran. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $10 at tables, $5 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES MOODY QUARTET (Thursday) Like his mentor Dizzy Gillespie, the saxophonist James Moody is a stalwart bebopper and one of jazz's most ebullient entertainers. He leads a solid working group consisting of the pianist Renee Rosnes, the bassist Todd Coolman and the drummer Adam Nussbaum. Through Aug. 13. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHOKO NAGAI'S EPHEMERAL (Tuesday) Playing piano, organ and sho, a bamboo pipe instrument, Ms. Nagai leads a five-piece ensemble in a new work inspired by premodern Japanese traditions, including Noh theater. Her collaborators are Ned Rothenberg on reeds, Jennifer Choi on violin and the brotherly rhythm section of Stomu Takeishi on bass and Satoshi Takeishi on percussion and electronics. 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>OZ NOY TRIO (Through Sunday) Oz Noy is an Israeli guitarist with a penchant for funk, as he demonstrates on his new album, ''Ha!'' (Magnatude). The audacious tone of that single-syllable title is just about right for Mr. Noy, who will play here, as on the album, with a rhythm team on loan from the CBS ''Late Show'' band: Will Lee on bass and Anton Fig on drums. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with a midnight show tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $27.50, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GRETCHEN PARLATO (Tonight and Monday) Ms. Parlato's lilting voice has earned her a good many casual admirers, but a continuing deluge of critical acclaim has more to do with her musicianship, underscored here by her rapport with the guitarist Lage Lund, the bassist Alan Hampton and the drummer Jamire Williams. Tonight at 6, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. Monday at 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $15, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEREMY PELT QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) The clarion tone and preternatural poise of Mr. Pelt's trumpet playing have earmarked him as a rising star in the jazz mainstream. As on his most recent album, ''Identity'' (MaxJazz), he is scheduled to play with the pianist Frank LoCrasto, the bassist Vicente Archer and the drummer Eric McPherson. Through Aug. 13. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANGELICA SANCHEZ QUINTET (Thursday) In her piano playing as well as in her composing, Ms. Sanchez seeks out the lyrical heartbeat within any avant-garde storm. Her working quintet includes the trumpeter Herb Robertson, the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, the bassist Mark Helias and the drummer Ches Smith. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHADES OF JAZZ (Wednesday and Thursday) This collective ensemble bears a strong resemblance to the Joe Lovano Quartet of 1990's vintage, which is almost certainly a good thing. In addition to Mr. Lovano on tenor and soprano saxophones, it includes Tom Harrell on trumpet, Cameron Brown on bass and Jimmy Cobb on drums. Through Aug. 12. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TODD SICKAFOOSE's BLOOD ORANGE  (Tuesday) Mr. Sickafoose is a bassist and composer equally fond of rough edges and rounded forms, as he demonstrated on his last album, ''Blood Orange'' (Secret Hatch). He showcases his atmospheric compositions in an improvising chamber ensemble that includes Russ Johnson and Josh Roseman on trumpet and trombone, Adam Levy and Mike Gamble on guitars, Jenny Scheinman on violin and Ches Smith on drums. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN STETCH TRIO (Tuesday) As on his new album, ''Bruxin' '' (Justin Time), Mr. Stetch upholds an effervescent school of pianism, expertly backed by Sean Smith on bass and Rodney Green on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BOB STEWART TRIO FEATURING BILLY HART (Tomorrow) Mr. Stewart brings agility and wit to the art of jazz tuba playing, and he responds well to assertive yet sensitive drummers like Mr. Hart, who fully deserves his featured billing. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEW TABACKIN TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Tabackin is an expansive tenor saxophonist and a highly lyrical flutist who never sounds freer than in a trio setting, backed by only a bassist and a drummer -- here, Boris Kozlov and Mark Taylor. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CEDAR WALTON QUINTET FEATURING STEVE TURRE (Tuesday through Thursday) As a pianist and composer, Mr. Walton practices an articulate, almost courtly variety of hard bop; he's at his best when his forms spark solos from collaborators like Mr. Turre, a trombonist, and Vincent Herring, an alto saxophonist. Through Aug. 13. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIM ZIESMER'S AMPERSAND (Sunday) Mr. Ziesmer's guitar playing is fluid and clearly rock-influenced, and his compositions feel sleekly modern, especially in the capable hands of the saxophonist and clarinetist Chris Speed, the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Take Toriyama. At 8 and 10 p.m., Bar 4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, bar4.net; suggested cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>BARD SUMMERSCAPE (Tonight through Thursday) This festival at Bard College continues tonight with a repeat performance of ''Genoveva,'' Schumann's only opera. Leon Botstein leads the American Symphony Orchestra in what is being billed as its first American production. Kasper Bech Holten, the dynamic young director of the Royal Danish Opera, directs a cast that includes the soprano Ylva Kihlberg in the title role of the young wife. Her husband, the crusading knight Siegfried, will be sung by the baritone Johannes Mannov; Golo, whose love for her is unrequited, will be performed by the tenor Philippe Castagner. Lighter fare is scheduled for the afternoon: the director-choreographer Ken Roht will stage three Offenbach's operettas, ''Les Deux Aveugles,'' ''L'Île de Tulipatan'' and ''Ba-ta-clan.'' Offenbach, today at 5 p.m., tomorrow and Sunday at 3 p.m., and Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., $45; ''Genoveva,'' tonight and tomorrow night at 8, $35 to $85. Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7900, summerscape.bard.edu. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tonight through Thursday) Three operas are in this week's rotation: Rossini's ''Barber of Seville'' (tonight at 8, Monday at 1:30 p.m., and Thursday at 8 p.m.); Janacek's ''Jenufa'' (tomorrow night at 8 and Tuesday at 1:30 p.m.); Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' (tomorrow and Sunday, both at 1:30 p.m.). The ''Barber'' is a beauty. Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255, glimmerglass.org; $41 to $117. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* ASTON MAGNA (Tonight and tomorrow) This esteemed early-music festival closes its summer programming -- the Aston Magna ensemble picks up again in the winter -- with a performance of Monteverdi's magnificent first opera, ''Orfeo.'' The cast includes the tenor Frank Kelley in the title role, as well as Roberta Anderson, Sharon Baker, Laurie Monahan and Deborah Rentz-Moore, sopranos; Jeffrey Gall, countertenor; William Hite, tenor; David Ripley, baritone; and Robert Honeysucker, bass. Daniel Stepner will conduct. Tonight at 8, Olin Humanities Building, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7425; tomorrow at 5 p.m., Arts Center at Simon's Rock College, Great Barrington, Mass., (800) 875-7156; astonmagna.org; $35. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall (a former coffee barge) on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight Bargemusic offers two gems of the chamber repertory. The first, Schubert's ''Two Cellos'' Quintet, will be a video recording from 1967, with the cellists Pablo Casals and Gregor Piatigorsky, the violinists Alexander Schneider and Isadore Cohen, and the violist Milton Thomas. After the intermission, Mark Peskanov on violin, Maurycy Banaszek on viola and Marie-Elisabeth Hecker on cello will perform Mozart's Divertimento in E flat (K. 563). Tomorrow and Sunday, Mr. Peskanov and Ms. Hecker are joined by José Ramos Santana, a pianist, in trios by Mozart (the E major, K. 542) and Dvorak (the ''Dumky'') and Brahms's Cello Sonata in F. And on Thursday, Steven Beck, a pianist, offers three Mozart sonatas (K. 279, 280 and 281), as well as preludes and fugues by Bach and Shostakovich. Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35; $20 for students; $30 for 65+, Thursdays and Fridays only. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BERKSHIRE CHORAL FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Robert Page, music director emeritus of the Mendelssohn Choir of Pittsburgh, returns to this festival to lead an enthusiastic group of choristers who have gathered from across the country for an intense week of training. They will perform Verdi's Requiem, the work Mr. Page conducted at the festival's opening in 1982. The soloists are the soprano Natalya Kraevsky, the mezzo-soprano Karen Brunssen, the tenor Douglas Ahlstedt and the baritone Timothy Noble. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., the Berkshire School, Route 41, Sheffield, Mass., (413) 229-1999, chorus.org; $25 to $40. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>CARAMOOR (Tonight and Sunday) The festival offers some prime chamber music this weekend. Tonight Trio Solisti plays Haydn's Trio in G, Schubert's Trio in B flat and Brahms's Trio in B in Caramoor's lovely Spanish Courtyard. On Sunday the estimable Tokyo String Quartet returns to the festival to perform Mozart's Quartet in C, Brahms's Quartet in A minor and ''A Way Alone'' by Takemitsu in the Venetian Theater. Tonight at 8, Sunday at 4:30 p.m., Katonah, N.Y.; (914) 232-1252, caramoor.org; $27 to $37 tonight, $19 to $49 on Sunday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) This energetic young ensemble, joined by Roman Rabinovich, a pianist who was born in Uzbekistan and now lives in Israel, offers a varied program that includes Mozart's arrangement of a Bach Adagio and Fugue; Hoffmeister's arrangement, for flute quartet, of a Mozart piano sonata (K. 331); a piano quartet by Beethoven; and Zemlinsky's Clarinet Trio. At 8 p.m., JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 799-1259, jupitersymphony.com; $15. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MARLBORO MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) Richard Goode and Mitsuko Uchida's prestigious chamber music retreat in rural Vermont kicks off this weekend with a benefit concert tonight featuring Saint-Saëns's Fantaisie for Violin and Harp, Reger's Piano Trio in E minor and Schumann's Quartet in A. Tomorrow's program includes selections from Dvorak's ''Cypresses: Songs for String Quartet,'' Schoenberg's String Quartet No. 3 and Chausson's ''Chanson Perpétuelle.'' On Sunday the lineup includes Bartok's String Quartet No. 3, Mozart's Divertimento No. 7 in D and Dvorak's Quartet in D minor. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, and Sunday at 2:30, Marlboro Music School and Festival, Marlboro, Vt., (802) 254-2394, marlboromusic.org; $15 to $30; $5 for canopy areas. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MOZART (Tonight through Thursday) Tonight's concert features Osmo Vanska conducting Frank Martin's ''Overture in Homage to Mozart,'' Mozart's Symphony No. 35 and Beethoven's ever-popular Violin Concerto, with Sergey Khachatryan as the soloist. The program repeats tomorrow. Tomorrow night the violinist Gidon Kremer and members of his Kremerata Baltica play Shostakovich, Sofia Gubaidulina and Mozart at the Kaplan Penthouse. On Sunday the Kremerata, fresh from performing the complete Mozart violin concertos at Tanglewood, bring the works to Lincoln Center, with Nos. 1 to 3 on Sunday and Nos. 4 and 5 on Monday; the second program also includes Alexander Raskatov's ''Five Minutes in the Life of W.A.M.'' The festival orchestra returns on Tuesday with Douglas Boyd, making his New York conducting debut with Ibert's ''Hommage à Mozart''; Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 21, with the soloist Alexei Lubimov; and the Symphony No. 38. That program repeats on Wednesday. The opera ''Zaide,'' opening Wednesday, should be a highlight of the festival. Mozart set the work as a clash between European slaves and Turkish sultans in the Ottoman Empire; the director Peter Sellars, an old hand at updating operas, uses contemporary Muslim-Western relations. Louis Langrée leads the period-instrument ensemble Concerto Köln. On Thursday evening the pianist Christian Zacharias plays Mozart and Ravel in the Kaplan Penthouse. Orchestral concerts: Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 5 p.m., and Monday through Wednesday at 8 p.m., in Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center ($35 to $55); tomorrow and Thursday nights at 10:30 p.m., Kaplan Penthouse, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, ($35); ''Zaide,'' Wednesday at 8 p.m., Rose Theater, Broadway at 60th Street ($35 to $75), (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>ST. LAWRENCE STRING QUARTET (Tomorrow and Sunday) This dynamic ensemble contributes to the Mozart festivities with his Quartet in B flat (K. 159), followed by Debussy's Quartet and Franck's Piano Quintet in F minor, with Stephen Prutsman. The St. Lawrence's concert in the intimate barn at the Mount Lebanon Shaker Village (as part of the Tannery Pond Concerts series) will be followed on Sunday with a concert in another atmospheric barn, this time the open-backed Maverick Concert Hall, near Woodstock, N.Y., where the group will play Mozart's Quartet No. 21 in D (''Prussian No. 1''), Schumann's Quartet No. 1 and Shostakovich's Quartet No. 3. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., New Lebanon, N.Y., (888) 820-9441, tannerypondconcerts.org, $25 and $30; Sunday at 3 p.m., Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217, maverickconcerts.org; $20; $5 for students. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* SUMMERGARDEN (Sunday) The student ensembles from the Juilliard School who play these concerts tend to be devoted to contemporary music and play it with virtuosity and polish. The works, all new to New York, include Tigran Ayvazyan's String Quartet (2003); Ben-Zion Orgad's ''Arsalgia'' (2004); Carl Vine's String Quartet No. 3 (1994); John Psathas's ''Kartsigar'' (2004); Lera Auerbach's ''Epilogue'' (2005); and Elliott Sharp's ''Eye in the Sky'' (2006), which was composed for this concert. At 8 p.m., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Sculpture Garden at the Museum of Modern Art, 15 West 54th Street, (212) 708-9491, moma.org; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday) The centerpiece of this busy weekend is Seiji Ozawa's return to Tanglewood, tomorrow evening, to lead the Boston Symphony Orchestra and the Tanglewood Festival Chorus in Mahler's huge Symphony No. 2, the ''Resurrection.'' His soloists are the soprano Heidi Grant Murphy and the contralto Nathalie Stutzmann, and for listeners who can't get enough, there is also an open rehearsal tomorrow morning. Surrounding Mr. Ozawa's Mahler are programs led by Donald Runnicles. Tonight Yo-Yo Ma is his soloist in concertos by Haydn and Osvaldo Golijov, on a program that begins with Janacek's ''Idyll'' and ends with Elgar's ''Enigma Variations.'' On Sunday afternoon Mr. Runnicles is joined by the pianist Lars Vogt in the Beethoven ''Emperor'' Concerto. The program also includes Mozart's Symphony No. 38 and a suite from Strauss's ''Rosenkavalier.'' On Sunday evening the well-trained students of the Tanglewood Music Center play Dvorak's ''Carnival'' Overture, Babbitt's ''From the Psalter,'' Fauré's ''Pelléas et Mélisande'' Suite, Sibelius's ''Luonnotar'' and Ravel's ''Daphnis and Chloé'' Suite No. 2. Stefan Asbury is the conductor, and Dawn Upshaw the soprano soloist. Boston Symphony: tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday afternoon at 2:30. Mahler rehearsal: tomorrow at 10:30 a.m. Tanglewood Music Center Orchestra: Sunday at 8:30 p.m. Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; tonight, $18 to $50, with $8.50 lawn tickets; sold out tomorrow night, except for lawn tickets at $17; rehearsal tomorrow morning, $17; Sunday afternoon, $18 to $50; Sunday evening, $11 to $36. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>* CENTRAL PARK SUMMERSTAGE 2006: LIMÓN DANCE COMPANY (Tonight) Lyrical and dramatic, dancing by the Limón company tends to stir the soul. This free 60th-anniversary program includes a performance by Raphael Boumaila of Daniel Nagrin's rarely seen ''Dance in the Sun,'' as well as works by José Limón, Jiri Kylian and Donald McKayle. At 8, Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-1777, or summerstage.org. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* CENTRAL PARK SUMMERSTAGE 2006: 'FROM MAMBO TO HIP HOP'  (Monday) This sounds like the place to be for sheer fun. This free program includes a preview screening of ''From Mambo to Hip Hop,'' a PBS documentary that explores the rich cultural history of the South Bronx. Veteran hip-hop, salsa and mambo dancers will perform before the movie is shown. The film will be followed by a question-and-answer session with Henry Chalfant, the documentary's director; the mambo dancer Peanut; the hip-hop dancer and historian PopMaster Fabel; and others. 7 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, Central Park, (212) 360-2777, or summerstage.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ENTRESUEÑO (Wednesday) This new flamenco production by Edwin Aparicio is formed around the states of mind before entering sleep and awakening. The dancers include Óscar Valero and La Genoveva. At 7:30 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, or symphonyspace.org; $25 to $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>HOT! THE NYC CELEBRATION OF QUEER CULTURE: HENRY HILL AND KELLY BARTNIK (Tonight and tomorrow night) Friends and collaborators, Mr. Hill and Ms. Bartnik will perform solos and group pieces in a program endearingly entitled ''Believe the Hype.'' Well, why not, just this once? At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, or dixonplace.org; $10 to $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) The Trey McIntyre Project, a contemporary ballet company, will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend, followed there on Wednesday and Thursday (and next weekend) by Shen Wei Dance Arts. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, Armitage Gone! (Karole Armitage's new New York-based company) plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is MoveOpolis, the company formed by Richard Move, who made his name as a Martha Graham impersonator. McIntyre tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., $45; Shen Wei Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, $50. Armitage tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15; tomorrow at 2:15 p.m.; and Sunday at 5 p.m.; $24. MoveOpolis on Thursday at 8:15 p.m., $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, ages 65+ and children. Details: jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL: PERU NEGRO (Sunday) The company celebrates black Peruvian culture in dance, playful multigenerational stage business and music performed on quijadas de buro (donkey jaw-bone rattles) and other exotic traditional instruments. At 3 and 7 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens, (718) 760-0064 or QueensTheatre.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER OUT OF DOORS (Tonight through Aug. 27) O.K., so being outside in New York City in August feels as if you're in a soup bowl, but there's a bright side: free dance to be had all month at Lincoln Center. The action begins tomorrow with ''Playday,'' lessons and demonstrations involving African, Middle Eastern and Irish folk dance. Thursday's lineup looks particularly promising: first, ''We B*Girlz,'' hip-hop challenges among various female crews, and then a double bill, ''Double Trouble: Dancin' the Blues,'' with the sublime Reggie Wilson/Fist &amp; Heel Performance Group and the Lula Washington Dance Theater of Los Angeles. Performances take place on stages erected throughout the Lincoln Center campus, from 62nd to 65th Streets, between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues. Complete schedule: (212) 546-2656, or lincolncenter.org. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless but enormously popular for people of all ages. Three programs alternate for the run, ending Aug. 12. Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday at 8 p.m., and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, or joyce.org; $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>KANG SUN YOUNG DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday) Ms. Young is said to be the sole successor to Han Seong Jun, a pioneer in the preservation of traditional Korean dance. Her 60-member troupe of dancers and musicians will perform pieces from that repertory in a program called ''A Legacy in Tradition.'' 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, or www.kangsunyoungarts.org; $25 to $95.(Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and castoff clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States in a garrulous, very personal way. One particularly intense work, based on the belief that Abubakari II, ruler of Mali, crossed the Atlantic nearly 200 years before Columbus to discover the Americas, links the past with the present and Africa with the beloved Columbus of Ms. Robinson's childhood. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 or brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606 or daheshmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700 or frick.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestoes and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500 or guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* INternational Center of Photography: 'On Air,' through Aug. 27. The South Korean artist Atta Kim's best-known body of work is a series called ''The Museum Project'' (1995-2002), for which he photographed his human subjects -- families, nude couples, maimed war veterans -- locked inside plexiglass exhibition cases like specimens on display. The series eventually took a religious turn, with models posing as Buddhist deities. The pictures here, in his first major American solo show, continue this spiritual trajectory. Filmed using long exposure times, figures, landscapes and religious icons have been turned into apparitions. People, art and museums may last for a while, Mr. Kim seems to say, but all things eventually melt away. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000 or icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* metropolitan museum of art: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early-19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. History is full of shifty characters, antique visionaries, cusp figures and half-crazy oddball innovators, later overlooked because they're hard to pigeonhole. Their independent cast of mind is the truest expression of how civilization advances. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 4 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of a kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. Many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500 or mobia.org. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer, , through Sept. 18. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200 or neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden: Chihuly at the New York Botanical Garden, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700 or nybg.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. A large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, (212) 873-3400 or nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' through Aug. 19. Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. Concentrating on books, but also including prints and drawings, it retells the tale of the French avant-garde on a relatively egalitarian playing field. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089 or nypl.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084 or ps1.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Rubin Museum of Art : 'What is it? HimalAyan Art' For a basic guide to the art of Tibet and Nepal, you will do no better than to take a slow walk through this new show, which, using an array of gorgeous objects, distills knotty visual and spiritual systems to a soothing but stimulating entry-level form. 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000 or rmanyc.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676 or whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* A BROKEN ARM The title is a tribute to Duchamp. The works review various strategies of using found objects or images in photography, painting and sculpture. The seven artists include Gedi Sibony, Arnold Odermatt and Karen Kalimnik. All has been orchestrated by Mari Spirito, the gallery's director. 303 Gallery, 525 West 22nd Street, (212) 255-1121, 303gallery.com, through Aug. 18. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* DERECONSTRUCTION Matthew Higgs, director of the alternative space White Columns, has assembled a handsome show that in typical Higgs fashion brings together outsider, emerging, hip and formerly hip artists. Variations on collage and assemblage predominate without feeling stale. The larger point: deconstruction has had its day, and it is time to start putting things back together again. The putters range from A. R. Penck and Lucas Samaras to Carter and Alexandra Bircken. Gladstone Gallery, 515 West 24th Street, (212) 206-9301, gladstonegallery.com, through Aug. 18. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* J. Bennett Fitts: 'No Lifeguard on Duty' Symbolically resonant photographs of mostly derelict motel swimming pools by a young Californian. Julie Saul, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 627-2410, saulgallery.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FOUNTAINS A summery theme is tweaked by energetic efforts. High points include Daniel Lefcourt's eye-popping photograph of studio tools, Sanford Bigger's video of a disco ball and Gibb Slife's television set, whose do-it-yourself antenna suggests spreading vines or brain waves. The low points seem to have been left out. D'Amelio Terras, 525 West 22nd Street, (212) 352-9460, damelioterras.com, through Aug. 11. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field with Sculptures' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West 22nd Street, (212) 243-0200, matthewmarks.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* GALERIE DANIEL BUCHHOLZ AT METRO PICTURES The well-known Cologne art gallery presents a surprisingly sweeping view of current art that includes Americans and Europeans and, despite its Conceptual slant, an impressive range of mediums and sensibilities. That may be the point. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, (212) 206-7100, metropicturesgallery.com, through Sept. 16. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Michael Heizer Sculptures in concrete representing prehistoric hand tools much enlarged so that they resemble Modernist sculptures by a follower of Brancusi. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 421-3292 or pacewildenstein.com, through Sept. 23. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Materiality' Inventive works made of all sorts of materials in this show include a stuffed leather-and-plywood tree by Carolyn Salas; a geometric landscape with a slowing-moving, wartlike kinetic element, covered in reflective Mylar, by Charlotte Becket; a neat display of more than 200 pieces of breakfast cereal by Tom Friedman; and a sumptuous stuffed object resembling a much-enlarged amoeba by Ernesto Neto. Kravets/Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238, kravetswehbygallery.com, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>MEN This show of 10 paintings of men by 10 women, organized by the painter Ellen Altfest, covers a lot of stylistic ground and includes an only partly tongue-in-cheek denunciation from the lesbian collective Redykeulous. Realism makes the strongest impression. I-20, 557 West 23rd Street, (212) 645-1100, I-20.com, through Aug. 18. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Howardena Pindell: 'In My Lifetime' Thirty years ago, Howardena Pindell was well known for meditative, process-based abstract work, though her art has always had two aspects. In the 1970's and 80's it assumed and maintained an overtly political direction in large-scale pieces that combined abstraction, words and figures to deal with social and political issues, from AIDS and homelessness to the present war in Iraq. Both types are in this informal gallery retrospective, which makes clear how thoroughly they are based on -- emerge from, are fueled and inflected by -- the individual experiences and memories of the artist herself. G. R. N'Namdi Gallery, 526 West 26th Street, Suite 316, (212) 929-6645, grnnamdi.com, through Aug. 31. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>A RABBIT AS KING OF THE GHOSTS With a title lifted from Wallace Stevens, this elegant show posits photography as the leading ghost in the machine of contemporary art and draws visually telling analogies from 140 years of the medium's life span. It has been organized by the photographers Justine Kurland and Dan Torop. Mitchell-Innes &amp; Nash, 534 West 26th Street, (212) 744-7400, miandn.com, through Aug. 11. (Smith)</p>
        <p>TWO FRIENDS AND SO ON Selected by asking one artist to invite another, who asked another, until a group of 30 had accrued, this show winds from Conceptual-based work through abstract painting and sculpture, and back again, presenting a random cross-section of the art world and displaying a network of style-based alliances. It is a quite a ride. Andrew Kreps Gallery, 525 West 22nd Street, (212) 741-8849, andrewkreps.com, through Aug. 12. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'WAR ON 45/MY MIRRORS ARE PAINTED BLACK (FOR YOU)' The latest word from the boys in black is a show of six artists organized by the head boy, Banks Violette. The stark glamour of it cannot be denied, but it looks too much like graphic design. Bortolami Dayan, 510 West 25th Street, (212) 727-2050, bortolamidayan.com, through Sept. 2. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'Gifts Go in One Direction' With art selling so briskly these days, isn't it time for the art world to hand out some gift bags, some freebies? After all, artists, as members of an intensively networked and mutually supportive community, have been giving one another gifts. That is the subject of this charming summer show, which takes the form of a round-robin of generosity, with artists on both the giving and receiving ends. Apexart, 291 Church Street, near Walker Street, TriBeCa, (212) 431-5270, through Aug. 12. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* Rudy Burckhardt: 'New York Paintings' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Mr. Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, near 57th Street, (212) 262-5050 or tibordenagy.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' In previews; opens on Aug. 16. If you were one of the people who missed the 17,162 performances of this show the last time around, good news: Harvey Schmidt and Tom Jones's romantic musical, which closed in 2002, is back (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'INDIAN BLOOD' In previews; opens on Thursday. Primary Stages presents A. R. Gurney's new comedy about a rebellious boy coming of age in the 1940's. Mark Lamos directs (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' In previews; opens on Aug. 17. This musical sendup of biographical shows features Martin Short and an ensemble telling the story of his life. Mr. Short's beloved old characters, like Ed Grimley and Jiminy Glick, make appearances (2:15). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>MIDTOWN INTERNATIONAL THEATER FESTIVAL Through Sunday. This seventh annual showcase can all too easily get lost in the shuffle, despite its large and diverse collection of shows. There should be more than 60 productions this season, at four locations on 36th Street. Schedules and information: (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'MOTHER COURAGE AND HER CHILDREN' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Aug. 21. Meryl Streep plays the title character in Tony Kushner's translation of Brecht's seminal play about a world at war. Kevin Kline also stars, and George C. Wolfe directs (2:30). Delacorte Theater, Central Park. Free. Ticket information: (212) 539-8750.</p>
        <p>'SEVEN GUITARS' In previews; opens Aug. 24. Signature Theater presents its first August Wilson revival since the playwright's death last year. Ruben Santiago-Hudson, who starred in the 1996 Broadway production, directs (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER' An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ALL THIS INTIMACY' In this not-very-deep comedy-drama by Rajiv Joseph, a 30-year-old poet impregnates not only his girlfriend, but also two other women, within two weeks. The women, once they meet, are surprisingly unimpressed with his notable virility (1:45). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 246-4422. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' Tormenting memories dissolve into soaring music, and pain is salved by a collective embrace in this heartfelt, powerfully performed theater piece about life under apartheid. The recollections of the five cast members and authors are woven together with a cappella performances of spirituals from the apartheid years and vignettes performed by the full cast. The actors all but glow with a sense of mission, as if telling their stories has given them new purpose and power (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School. Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200 (1:10). (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOUT!' A mini-skirted, go-go booted zombie of a musical about women searching for love in London in the 1960's. You won't see anything this groovy, this far-out, this with-it outside of, oh, maybe the show room of a Carnival Cruise ship (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A STONE CARVER' Despite the high cliché factor, William Mastrosimone's play about an Italian immigrant who is losing his house to a highway exit is timely and sporadically touching, in large part because of Dan Lauria's over-the-top performance as the title character and old-world patriarch who makes a mean barrel of wine and never talks when he can shout (1:40). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'IF YOU GIVE A MOUSE A COOKIE &amp; OTHER STORY BOOKS' This children's musical, made up of 10 sketches based on 8 books, is diverse, adorable and free. Also, the adults laugh (1:00). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village; (212) 642-9033. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NEVER TELL' The computer-involved characters in James Christy's intriguing drama about trust, video art and a society-changing application can be irritating but they're never boring (1:50). Michael Weller Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' Another excavation of what seems to have become Broadway's favorite musical terrain -- call it Scamalot, where con men are king (see ''The Producers''). Now starring Keith Carradine and Brian D'Arcy James as the mismatched swindlers (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CLOUD TECTONICS' A solid rendition of Jose Rivera's thin fable about time, centering on a hitchhiking woman who has been pregnant for two years. Luis Vega is particularly good as the man who gives her a ride and shelter for the night (1:30). Culture Project-45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this old comedy from the 1930's, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). Bank Street Theater, 155 Bank Street, West Village, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200; closes tomorrow. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ANT BULLY' (PG, 90 minutes) A young boy goes to live among the ants, who talk remarkably like Academy Award-winning actors. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'BEEN RICH ALL MY LIFE' (No rating, 80 minutes) This admiring documentary portrait of the Silver Belles, an indefatigable troupe of veteran Harlem tap dancers between the ages of 84 and 96, is a valuable historical footnote and a useful how-to movie about making the most of old age. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'CLERKS II' (R, 98 minutes) More than a decade later, Kevin Smith's New Jersey underachievers have moved from a convenience store to a fast-food franchise. The humor is reliably filthy and frequently hilarious, and the filmmaking is a few steps above rudimentary, but the movie's poignant sweetness is disarming. It has a dirty mind, but its heart is remarkably pure. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'Gabrielle' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haute bourgeois Parisian marriage, about 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems that Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over, and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'I Like Killing Flies' (R, 79 minutes) The documentary filmmaker Matt Mahurin paints an engaging if glib portrait of Kenny Shopsin, of the legendary or notorious, depending on your experience, Greenwich Village eatery that bears his name. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'LADY IN THE WATER' (PG-13, 108 minutes) In this watchable folly, Paul Giamatti plays a building manager who encounters a menagerie of otherworldly creatures, most important Bryce Dallas Howard's water nymph. The writer and director M. Night Shyamalan wants us to believe, mostly in the myth of his own genius. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>* Little Miss Sunshine (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MIAMI VICE' (R, 133 minutes) This updating of the 1980's television series cost more than the annual budget of the real-life Miami Police Department, making it the most expensive experimental art film ever made. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. A trio of intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband, and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PEACEFUL WARRIOR' (PG-13, 120 minutes) As ludicrous as the title promises, yet supremely unembarrassed, this New Age enlightenment parable has its heart in the right place, but a mind of corny mush. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'The Photographer, His Wife, Her Lover' (Not rated, 79 minutes) Art, adultery, divorce, lawyers and pots of money. Paul Yule's documentary wades unproductively through the mess surrounding the estate of the Brooklyn-born photographer O. Winston Link, who died in 2001. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' (PG-13, 151 minutes) Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)  * 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* Scoop (PG-13, 96 minutes) A not especially funny yet oddly appealing comedy in which Woody Allen and Scarlett Johansson make like Nick and Nora, but with more shtick and no martinis (or Asta). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SHADOWBOXER' (R, 93 minutes) This garish thriller starring Helen Mirren and Cuba Gooding Jr. as contract killers and lovers is an extravagance that leaves you with your mouth hanging open -- partly in admiration of its audacity and partly in disbelief at its preposterousness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'13 Tzameti'  (No rating, 90 minutes) The flashy black-and-white directorial debut of the Georgian filmmaker Gela Babluani is a sadistic, arty thriller that suggests a French new wave film infected by a virulent strain of Eastern European nihilism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>You, Me and Dupree' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>THE BEST OF BUSTER: KEATON COMEDY CLASSICS (Through Sept. 25) Film Forum's eight-week festival of the silent comedies of the brilliantly stone-faced Keaton (1895-1966) begins on Monday night. ''The General'' (1926), his version of the great Civil War locomotive chase, will be shown, along with three early-1920's shorts. Other films in the series include ''Sherlock Jr.'' (1924) and ''The Cameraman'' (1928). 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8110; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) The 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962) continues at the Museum of the Moving Image with four films this weekend. They include two World War I love stories with literary pedigrees: ''A Farewell to Arms'' (1932), starring Gary Cooper and Helen Hayes, and ''Three Comrades'' (1938), with Robert Taylor and Margaret Sullavan. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NOW THAT'S HIP! (Through Aug. 29) As part of the River to River arts festival, the HIP Health Plan of New York is sponsoring outdoor screenings of movies set in New York, preceded by shorts from New York filmmakers. The four-movie August series begins on Tuesday with ''Barefoot in the Park'' (1967), in which Robert Redford and Jane Fonda play mismatched newlyweds in a minuscule downtown apartment. The other films, all to be shown on Tuesday nights, are ''Pickup on South Street'' (1953), ''Mr. Deeds Goes to Town'' (1936) and ''Rear Window'' (1954). Elevated Acre, 55 Water Street, (212) 835-2789; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>PLAY IT LOUD: ROCK DOCS 2006 (Through Thursday) The Film Society of Lincoln Center's nine-film series of rock-music documentaries rocks on. This weekend's films include ''Everyone Stares: The Police Inside Out'' (2005), the history of the band as seen by its drummer, Stewart Copeland; and ''No Direction Home: Bob Dylan'' (2005), Martin Scorsese's portrait of the young Dylan. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RAISING HELL: SAM PECKINPAH (Through Aug. 29) BAMcinématek's monthlong tribute to Peckinpah (1925-84) continues. Monday night's feature is ''The Getaway'' (1972), in which Steve McQueen and Ali McGraw rob a bank, badly. Tuesday night's is ''The Ballad of Cable Hogue'' (1970), starring Jason Robards as an entrepreneurial prospector. BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SUMMER SWASHBUCKLERS (Through Aug. 24) Film Forum's 36-movie celebration of old-style action pictures begins this weekend with two double features. ''Captain Blood'' (1935), with Errol Flynn, and ''The Scarlet Pimpernel'' (1935), with Leslie Howard, are on the bill for Friday and Saturday, to be shown with ''The Scarlet Pumpernickel'' (1950), starring the dashing Daffy Duck. Sunday's films are ''The Prisoner of Zenda'' (1937), with Ronald Colman and Douglas Fairbanks Jr., and ''The Mark of Zorro'' (1920), with the other Fairbanks -- Douglas Sr. (See above.) (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* CELEBRATE BROOKLYN AFRICAN FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) One of the highlights of the Celebrate Brooklyn schedule each summer is its daylong African concert, any 10 minutes of which is well worth the $3 suggested donation. This year features Kekele, a supergroup of Congolese rumba elders gathered à la ''Buena Vista Social Club,'' and Lagbaja, a Nigerian bandleader who plays muscular Afro-funk and hides his face in a scarf to symbolize Africa's political anonymity. (His name means ''anybody'' in Yoruban.) Others on the bill include Razia, a singer born in Madagascar and raised in Gabon; the African Underground All-Stars, a pan-African hip-hop collective whose M.C.'s include Chosan, from Sierra Leone, and Dola, of Tanzania; and Martino Atangana, a Cameroonian guitarist who lives in New York. From 2 to 9 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882, brooklynx.org. Lagbaja also plays at 8 and 11 p.m. on Wednesday at S.O.B.'s., 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARSHALL CRENSHAW (Tuesday and Wednesday) Marshall Crenshaw's songs seem to roll off the guitar in a casual blend of pre-1970's styles -- folk-rock, surf-rock, country and above all, the Beatles -- that put melody first. With his winsome tenor, he delves into the ways love goes right and goes wrong, from distant yearning to the aftermath of infidelity, hiding turmoil within the chiming tunes. At 10 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500, rodeobar.com; no cover. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133, dannysgrandseapalace.com; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>HAZEL DICKENS; BONNY BILLY AND CAPTAIN ANOMOANON (Tomorrow and Sunday) The daughter of a West Virginia coal miner, Hazel Dickens sings sharp and unadorned bluegrass songs about hardship and defiant proletarian pride. (''They'll never shoot that union out of me.'') Nineteen years ago she appeared in John Sayles's film ''Matewan'' alongside Will Oldham, who has since developed a postmodern Appalachian folk style. He performs as Bonny Billy (one of his many pseudonyms), along with his brother Ned, who appears as Captain Anomoanon. Tomorrow at 7 and 9:30 p.m., Sunday at 4 and 6:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200, joespub.com; sold out tomorrow, $30 on Sunday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIRTY DOZEN BRASS BAND (Tuesday) The magnificent ensemble that revitalized New Orleans brass-band music. It swaggers through the city's whole musical heritage: parades, rumba, swing, be-bop and modern jazz, for starters. Solos can head for the far side of tonality, but the band never loses touch with gutbucket, danceable funk. At 8:15 p.m., Josie Robertson Plaza at Lincoln Center, Columbus Avenue at 64th Street, (212) 875-5766, lincolncenter.org; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>FORRÓ IN THE DARK (Wednesday) For more than three years now, this group has been leading one of New York's best and lowest-tech dance parties at the East Village bar Nublu. The groove is a humble and sexy two-beat dance from northeastern Brazil called forró, made with accordion, hand-held percussion and, since this is New York, whiffs of distorted electric guitar. At 11 p.m. and 12:30 a.m., 62 Avenue C, between Fourth and Fifth Streets, East Village, nublu.net; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIAMANDA GALÁS (Thursday) She is invariably dressed in black, her face in witchy streaks of makeup, but Diamanda Galás needs only her voice to terrify, seduce and beguile. She slides from a low, sensual growl to painful yet musically precise shrieks, and has a vast repertory that ranges from darkened Johnny Cash ballads to her own chilling AIDS Masses. In the first of four shows at the new Spiegeltent downtown, she offers ''Long Black Veil,'' a program of morbid music by Screamin' Jay Hawkins, Ornette Coleman and others. At 6 p.m., Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* HOT CHIP (Tonight) With wobbly electronic rhythms that seem to be made of melting jelly, and a strong command of the drippy disco ballad, this English group plays a kind of wistful but still snarky dance music. Get too lost in the beats and you'll miss smart gags like the oh-so-art-rock countdown of nonsense words in descending numbers of letters (''S-E-X-I-N-G, C-A-S-I-O, P-O-K-E''). With Oppenheimer. At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789, seaportmusicfestival.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) This two-week multidisciplinary and multinational series in Queens winds up this weekend. The gritty, deep-voiced Cuban singer Albita performs tonight. Tomorrow features Inti-Illimani, a veteran Chilean group that plays traditional Andean songs, as well as African and Spanish hybrids. On Sunday Peru Negro, a big troupe of dancers and singers, traverses three centuries of Afro-Peruvian music. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 and 7 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $35 tonight and Sunday, $30 tomorrow; $5 off when bought in advance. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LATIN ALTERNATIVE MUSIC CONFERENCE (Tonight and tomorrow) This annual series of concerts and discussion panels began six years ago, when a few Latin pop stars stood atop the charts (Ricky Martin, Jennifer Lopez), a varied rock and electronic scene flourished underground, and ''rock en Español'' was a marketing buzzword.The situation now is much the same, with fewer buzzwords: Shakira is an international phenomenon, while most Latin rock artists remain largely unknown to English-speaking American audiences. This will be mulled extensively at the daytime panels, but the best proof of the scene's vitality is the music itself. This weekend offers two free shows: Tonight at Celebrate Brooklyn are the Venezuelan groove-rockers Los Amigos Invisibles; Los Bunkers, from Chile; and Belanova, an electro-pop group from Mexico. Tomorrow afternoon at Central Park SummerStage are Gustavo Cerati, the former leader of the Argentine rock heroes Soda Stereo; Calle 13, a Puerto Rican reggaetón group; and the Mexican Institute of Sound. Tonight at 7:30, Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882; $3 suggested donation. Tomorrow at 3, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. Information: latinalternative.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LL COOL J (Monday) One of the first bigger-than-the-block personalities of rap, LL Cool J still follows the same few guidelines of self-representation that have served him throughout his long career: appear shirtless as often as possible for photographers, title all your albums either after yourself (''Todd Smith,'' his latest, refers to his given name, James Todd Smith) or some superlative that Muhammad Ali might have used (''Phenomenon,'' ''Greatest of All Time''), and perform in as sweatily vigorous a way as you can. At 7:30 p.m., Wingate Field, Winthrop Street, between Brooklyn and Kingston Avenues, East Flatbush, Brooklyn, (718) 469-1912, brooklynconcerts.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MANU CHAO (Monday) This great globalist rocker makes a rare appearance. In the 1980's, Manu Chao, a musical omnivore born in France to Spanish parents, led the pioneering Latin rock band Mano Negra, which fused the angry political punk of the Clash with flamenco and Algerian rai. Since the late 90's, despite minimal output, he has been a celebrated and inspirational symbol of high-minded, do-it-yourself multiculturalism: he dabbles in reggae and dub, rap, salsa, calypso and rock, and recently produced the eclectic Malian duo Amadou and Mariam. He plays a benefit concert for Celebrate Brooklyn, with Plastilina Mosh as the opening act. At 7 p.m., Prospect Park Bandshell (see above); sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAVE MATTHEWS BAND (Tomorrow and Sunday) His own private Bonnaroo: Dave Matthews has programmed two days of kindred spirits at Randalls Island, a minifestival with a much more manageable seven bands instead of seven dozen. Both days feature the Dave Matthews Band, the robotically virtuosic banjoing of Bela Fleck and the Flecktones, the three-cheers-for-marijuana ska of Slightly Stoopid, and the Grateful Dead-influenced Tea Leaf Green. Tomorrow also has the mighty Southern rockers Gov't Mule, and on Sunday David Gray, the British singer-songwriter whose ballads mingle acoustic guitar and gentle electronica, will perform. At noon, Randalls Island, near Icahn Stadium, 1 Randalls Island, randallsislandconcerts.com, (212) 307-7171; sold out tomorrow, $55 and $62.50 on Sunday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE MIGHTY SPARROW (Tuesday) With wry lyrics and supple melodies, the Mighty Sparrow, who was born Slinger Francisco, made the carnival music of Trinidad and Tobago a political force and a pop phenomenon with a string of competition-winning hit songs that stretches back to the mid-1950's in which he comments on everything from the Shah to the first black Miss Universe. At 7 p.m., Queensbridge Park, Queens, (212) 360-8290, cityparksfoundation.org; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>NEWPORT FOLK FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) In a way, this veteran festival, home of ''We Shall Overcome'' singalongs and Bob Dylan's 1965 electric crossing, is one of the most creatively programmed in the country. To expand the idea of folk music -- or at least to fill up the weekend at a time when folk groups are in small supply -- Newport folds in jazz, soul, even greasy funk. Tonight's concert has more traditional fare, with Ronan Tynan and Cherish the Ladies, both from Ireland. On tomorrow's roster are David Gray, Rosanne Cash, Bettye LaVette, Sonny Landreth, Sonya Kitchell, Mary Gauthier and others; Sunday features the Indigo Girls, the veteran New Orleans funk group the Meters, Madeleine Peyroux, Keller Williams and Odetta. Absent: any representation of the vital, young and underground ''freak folk'' movement. Tonight at 8, at the International Tennis Hall of Fame; tomorrow and Sunday from 11:30 a.m. to 7 p.m. at Fort Adams State Park, Newport, R.I., (401) 847-3700, newportfolk.com; $30 to $75 tonight; $59 tomorrow and Sunday. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ONE RING ZERO (Monday) This Brooklyn band has set words by authors like Jonathan Lethem, Margaret Atwood and Rick Moody to kitchen-sink songs with toy piano and theremin. The group offers a screening of ''As Smart as They Are,'' a documentary about its formation. At 8 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $20; $10 for members. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GRANT-LEE PHILLIPS (Thursday) Mr. Phillips harks back to the earnest ambitions and expansive melodies of Bob Dylan and John Lennon, singing with the conviction that rock can still be heroic. Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $15. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>THE RED KRAYOLA (Tuesday) The first album of the Red Crayola (as it was originally spelled) appeared in 1967, and Mayo Thompson has held on to its skewed psychedelic perspective ever since; he also spent some years as a member of Pere Ubu. He's fond of dissolving song structures, crypto-Marxist messages and woozy sounds, and when he reconvened the Red Krayola (the spelling was changed to avoid trademark problems) in 1994, he found fans and collaborators among progressive- and post-rock musicians. With Coyote, featuring members of the bands Vaz and Man Man. At 8 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103, northsix.com; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* CANDI STATON (Wednesday) She has been a disco queen, a raw-voiced soul belter and, for much of the last two decades, a gospel singer. But Ms. Staton's greatest success has been with record collectors, who have kept her strong legacy of secular R &amp; B alive and may have persuaded her to return to it: she recently released ''His Hands'' (Honest Jon's/Astralwerks), a stirring album of broken-heart songs and rich Southern blues that is her first such recording in decades. This concert is billed as Ms. Staton's first in New York in more than 20 years. With Stephanie McKay. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WARPED TOUR (Tomorrow) Now 12 years old, this skateboards-punk-and-tattoos circus includes Thursday, From Autumn to Ashes, Against Me!, Helmet, Joan Jett and the Blackhearts, the Sounds, Motion City Soundtrack, NOFX, Bouncing Souls, Damone, Saves the Day, Senses Fail and the Academy Is  , Every Time I Die and many, many more. Best band name: Gym Class Heroes. Worst: Gatsby's American Dream. At noon, Nassau Coliseum, 1255 Hempstead Turnpike, Uniondale, N.Y., (631) 888-9000, warpedtour.com; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>MONTY ALEXANDER JAZZ AND ROOTS ENSEMBLE (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Alexander's most recent album, ''Concrete Jungle'' (Telarc), pays tribute to his celebrated countryman Bob Marley. He travels similar territory here, featuring his piano and melodica playing in a buoyant ensemble with Wendel Ferraro on guitar and vocals, Hassan Shakur on bass and George Fludas on drums. Through Aug. 13. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEFF BALLARD AND MARK TURNER (Tonight) Mr. Ballard, a drummer, and Mr. Turner, a tenor saxophonist, constitute two-thirds of Fly, a brainy yet earthy group that seeks adventure in collective interplay. Without a bassist or any harmonic accompaniment, their rapport at this performance should be stark and inspired. At 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARDFELD'S STUFF SMITH PROJECT (Thursday) Mr. Bardfeld is a violinist with a wide-ranging résumé who spent all of June on tour with Bruce Springsteen's ''Seeger Sessions'' band. Here he pays tribute to a swing-era hero of his instrument, with help from the pianist Anthony Coleman and the bassist Brad Jones. 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARSH (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Barsh is a keyboardist with a gift for groove, as he has demonstrated on recent albums by the bassist Avishai Cohen and the guitarist Jeff Parker. Performing on a new jazz series with a Hudson River view, he enlists Tim Collins on vibraphone, Ari Folman-Cohen on bass and Jaimeo Brown on drums. At 9 and 10:30, the River Room, Riverbank State Park, Riverside Drive at 145th Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 491-1500, theriverroomofharlem.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEDROCK (Tonight) The keyboardist Uri Caine, the bassist Tim Lefebvre and the drummer Zach Danziger make up this trio, which absorbs elements of fusion, funk and drum-and-bass into its own deliriously groovy style. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVEN BERNSTEIN'S MILLENNIAL TERRITORY ORCHESTRA (Tonight) This little big band, led by the irrepressible slide trumpeter Steven Bernstein, has a new album called ''MTO Volume 1'' (Sunnyside) that's full of signature touches, like effervescent swing arrangements and covers of hits by Prince and Stevie Wonder. At 10 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID BINNEY (Tuesday and Wednesday) This alto saxophonist pursues an avant-gardism that embraces harmony, melody and rhythm, along with amplification. He performs in two different settings next week, first with his group Balance (on Tuesday) and then with a more experimental crew (on Wednesday). Tuesday at 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. Wednesday at 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CARAMOOR JAZZ FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Roughly 50 miles upstate, this festival offers some smartly simple programming in a tented open-air environment. First up is the Paris-based pianist Kirk Lightsey, in a tribute to the recently departed John Hicks; then a quartet led by the trumpeter Jeremy Pelt; then the pianist Steve Kuhn, presenting his Third Stream compositions for a 12-piece string ensemble. After a dinner break, the pianist McCoy Tyner leads the final group, conceived as a tribute to the legacy of Impulse Records; his all-star lineup includes David Liebman and Donald Harrison on saxophones, Nicholas Payton on trumpet and Steve Turre on trombone. Starts at 2:30 p.m., with hourly sets until a dinner break at 6:30; the final set begins at 8. Caramoor, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-1252, caramoor.org; $45 and $55. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RON CARTER QUARTET (Tonight) Mr. Carter is a deeply literate bassist and composer whose ensembles usually give off light but little heat. That's fitting, in a way, for this appearance in a luminous, glass-enclosed planetarium, a ''Starry Nights'' performance to be broadcast live on WBGO. At 7:30 p.m., Rose Center for Earth and Space, American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 81st Street, (212) 313-7278, amnh.org. Suggested admission: $14; $10.50 for students; $8 for children. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAQUITO D'RIVERA SEXTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. D'Rivera, a clarinetist, alto saxophonist and longtime Cuban exile, favors bright extroversion in his music, which usually incorporates Latin rhythms. His band includes the trumpeter Diego Urcola, the pianist Alon Yavnai, the bassist Oscar Stagnaro and the percussionists Mark Walker and Pernell Saturnino. Through Aug. 13. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EHRAN ELISHA'S KINETIC MUSIC (Sunday) In the late 1990's, the percussionist Ehran Elisha recorded an album called ''Lowdown'' (CIMP) featuring a suitelike composition for a group that included Roy Campbell Jr. on trumpet, David Bindman on tenor saxophone, Sam Bardfeld on violin and Bill Lowe on tuba. Add Ken Filiano on bass, and you've got the same personnel here, though probably not the same music. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN GERSTEIN COLLECTIVE (Wednesday) Boisterous free improvisation from bright young players with a history of collaboration: Mr. Gerstein on trombone, Jacob Sacks on keyboards, Jacob Garchik on accordion and electronics, Thomas Morgan and Dave D'Ambrosio on bass and Dan Weiss on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JONATHON HAFFNER QUARTET (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mr. Haffner, an adventurous young alto saxophonist, performs tomorrow night with Bob Hoffnar on pedal steel guitar, Chris Lightcap on bass and Dan Weiss on drums. On Sunday Mr. Haffner ventures into a more exposed setting, with no accompaniment whatsoever. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. Sunday at 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARTHUR KELL QUARTET (Monday) On ''Traveller'' (Fresh Sound New Talent), the bassist and composer Arthur Kell pursues a searching strain of modern jazz; he has worthy partners here in the saxophonist Donny McCaslin, the guitarist Brad Shepik and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. At 7 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FRANCISCO MELA (Monday) Mr. Mela is a subtly dynamic drummer, attuned to the rhythmic depth of his native Cuba but adaptable to seemingly any sort of modern jazz. He's also an unassumingly good composer, as he demonstrates on ''Melao'' (Avya), the debut album that he celebrates with a quintet and several special guests, including the clarinetist and alto saxophonist Paquito D'Rivera, the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner and the pianist Jason Moran. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $10 at tables, $5 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAMES MOODY QUARTET (Thursday) Like his mentor Dizzy Gillespie, the saxophonist James Moody is a stalwart bebopper and one of jazz's most ebullient entertainers. He leads a solid working group consisting of the pianist Renee Rosnes, the bassist Todd Coolman and the drummer Adam Nussbaum. Through Aug. 13. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHOKO NAGAI'S EPHEMERAL (Tuesday) Playing piano, organ and sho, a bamboo pipe instrument, Ms. Nagai leads a five-piece ensemble in a new work inspired by premodern Japanese traditions, including Noh theater. Her collaborators are Ned Rothenberg on reeds, Jennifer Choi on violin and the brotherly rhythm section of Stomu Takeishi on bass and Satoshi Takeishi on percussion and electronics. 8 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>OZ NOY TRIO (Through Sunday) Oz Noy is an Israeli guitarist with a penchant for funk, as he demonstrates on his new album, ''Ha!'' (Magnatude). The audacious tone of that single-syllable title is just about right for Mr. Noy, who will play here, as on the album, with a rhythm team on loan from the CBS ''Late Show'' band: Will Lee on bass and Anton Fig on drums. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with a midnight show tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $27.50, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GRETCHEN PARLATO (Tonight and Monday) Ms. Parlato's lilting voice has earned her a good many casual admirers, but a continuing deluge of critical acclaim has more to do with her musicianship, underscored here by her rapport with the guitarist Lage Lund, the bassist Alan Hampton and the drummer Jamire Williams. Tonight at 6, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; no cover. Monday at 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $15, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEREMY PELT QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) The clarion tone and preternatural poise of Mr. Pelt's trumpet playing have earmarked him as a rising star in the jazz mainstream. As on his most recent album, ''Identity'' (MaxJazz), he is scheduled to play with the pianist Frank LoCrasto, the bassist Vicente Archer and the drummer Eric McPherson. Through Aug. 13. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANGELICA SANCHEZ QUINTET (Thursday) In her piano playing as well as in her composing, Ms. Sanchez seeks out the lyrical heartbeat within any avant-garde storm. Her working quintet includes the trumpeter Herb Robertson, the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, the bassist Mark Helias and the drummer Ches Smith. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHADES OF JAZZ (Wednesday and Thursday) This collective ensemble bears a strong resemblance to the Joe Lovano Quartet of 1990's vintage, which is almost certainly a good thing. In addition to Mr. Lovano on tenor and soprano saxophones, it includes Tom Harrell on trumpet, Cameron Brown on bass and Jimmy Cobb on drums. Through Aug. 12. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TODD SICKAFOOSE's BLOOD ORANGE  (Tuesday) Mr. Sickafoose is a bassist and composer equally fond of rough edges and rounded forms, as he demonstrated on his last album, ''Blood Orange'' (Secret Hatch). He showcases his atmospheric compositions in an improvising chamber ensemble that includes Russ Johnson and Josh Roseman on trumpet and trombone, Adam Levy and Mike Gamble on guitars, Jenny Scheinman on violin and Ches Smith on drums. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN STETCH TRIO (Tuesday) As on his new album, ''Bruxin' '' (Justin Time), Mr. Stetch upholds an effervescent school of pianism, expertly backed by Sean Smith on bass and Rodney Green on drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BOB STEWART TRIO FEATURING BILLY HART (Tomorrow) Mr. Stewart brings agility and wit to the art of jazz tuba playing, and he responds well to assertive yet sensitive drummers like Mr. Hart, who fully deserves his featured billing. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEW TABACKIN TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Tabackin is an expansive tenor saxophonist and a highly lyrical flutist who never sounds freer than in a trio setting, backed by only a bassist and a drummer -- here, Boris Kozlov and Mark Taylor. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CEDAR WALTON QUINTET FEATURING STEVE TURRE (Tuesday through Thursday) As a pianist and composer, Mr. Walton practices an articulate, almost courtly variety of hard bop; he's at his best when his forms spark solos from collaborators like Mr. Turre, a trombonist, and Vincent Herring, an alto saxophonist. Through Aug. 13. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIM ZIESMER'S AMPERSAND (Sunday) Mr. Ziesmer's guitar playing is fluid and clearly rock-influenced, and his compositions feel sleekly modern, especially in the capable hands of the saxophonist and clarinetist Chris Speed, the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Take Toriyama. At 8 and 10 p.m., Bar 4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, bar4.net; suggested cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>BARD SUMMERSCAPE (Tonight through Thursday) This festival at Bard College continues tonight with a repeat performance of ''Genoveva,'' Schumann's only opera. Leon Botstein leads the American Symphony Orchestra in what is being billed as its first American production. Kasper Bech Holten, the dynamic young director of the Royal Danish Opera, directs a cast that includes the soprano Ylva Kihlberg in the title role of the young wife. Her husband, the crusading knight Siegfried, will be sung by the baritone Johannes Mannov; Golo, whose love for her is unrequited, will be performed by the tenor Philippe Castagner. Lighter fare is scheduled for the afternoon: the director-choreographer Ken Roht will stage three Offenbach's operettas, ''Les Deux Aveugles,'' ''L'Île de Tulipatan'' and ''Ba-ta-clan.'' Offenbach, today at 5 p.m., tomorrow and Sunday at 3 p.m., and Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., $45; ''Genoveva,'' tonight and tomorrow night at 8, $35 to $85. Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7900, summerscape.bard.edu. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tonight through Thursday) Three operas are in this week's rotation: Rossini's ''Barber of Seville'' (tonight at 8, Monday at 1:30 p.m., and Thursday at 8 p.m.); Janacek's ''Jenufa'' (tomorrow night at 8 and Tuesday at 1:30 p.m.); Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' (tomorrow and Sunday, both at 1:30 p.m.). The ''Barber'' is a beauty. Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255, glimmerglass.org; $41 to $117. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* ASTON MAGNA (Tonight and tomorrow) This esteemed early-music festival closes its summer programming -- the Aston Magna ensemble picks up again in the winter -- with a performance of Monteverdi's magnificent first opera, ''Orfeo.'' The cast includes the tenor Frank Kelley in the title role, as well as Roberta Anderson, Sharon Baker, Laurie Monahan and Deborah Rentz-Moore, sopranos; Jeffrey Gall, countertenor; William Hite, tenor; David Ripley, baritone; and Robert Honeysucker, bass. Daniel Stepner will conduct. Tonight at 8, Olin Humanities Building, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7425; tomorrow at 5 p.m., Arts Center at Simon's Rock College, Great Barrington, Mass., (800) 875-7156; astonmagna.org; $35. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall (a former coffee barge) on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight Bargemusic offers two gems of the chamber repertory. The first, Schubert's ''Two Cellos'' Quintet, will be a video recording from 1967, with the cellists Pablo Casals and Gregor Piatigorsky, the violinists Alexander Schneider and Isadore Cohen, and the violist Milton Thomas. After the intermission, Mark Peskanov on violin, Maurycy Banaszek on viola and Marie-Elisabeth Hecker on cello will perform Mozart's Divertimento in E flat (K. 563). Tomorrow and Sunday, Mr. Peskanov and Ms. Hecker are joined by José Ramos Santana, a pianist, in trios by Mozart (the E major, K. 542) and Dvorak (the ''Dumky'') and Brahms's Cello Sonata in F. And on Thursday, Steven Beck, a pianist, offers three Mozart sonatas (K. 279, 280 and 281), as well as preludes and fugues by Bach and Shostakovich. Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35; $20 for students; $30 for 65+, Thursdays and Fridays only. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BERKSHIRE CHORAL FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Robert Page, music director emeritus of the Mendelssohn Choir of Pittsburgh, returns to this festival to lead an enthusiastic group of choristers who have gathered from across the country for an intense week of training. They will perform Verdi's Requiem, the work Mr. Page conducted at the festival's opening in 1982. The soloists are the soprano Natalya Kraevsky, the mezzo-soprano Karen Brunssen, the tenor Douglas Ahlstedt and the baritone Timothy Noble. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., the Berkshire School, Route 41, Sheffield, Mass., (413) 229-1999, chorus.org; $25 to $40. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>CARAMOOR (Tonight and Sunday) The festival offers some prime chamber music this weekend. Tonight Trio Solisti plays Haydn's Trio in G, Schubert's Trio in B flat and Brahms's Trio in B in Caramoor's lovely Spanish Courtyard. On Sunday the estimable Tokyo String Quartet returns to the festival to perform Mozart's Quartet in C, Brahms's Quartet in A minor and ''A Way Alone'' by Takemitsu in the Venetian Theater. Tonight at 8, Sunday at 4:30 p.m., Katonah, N.Y.; (914) 232-1252, caramoor.org; $27 to $37 tonight, $19 to $49 on Sunday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) This energetic young ensemble, joined by Roman Rabinovich, a pianist who was born in Uzbekistan and now lives in Israel, offers a varied program that includes Mozart's arrangement of a Bach Adagio and Fugue; Hoffmeister's arrangement, for flute quartet, of a Mozart piano sonata (K. 331); a piano quartet by Beethoven; and Zemlinsky's Clarinet Trio. At 8 p.m., JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 799-1259, jupitersymphony.com; $15. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MARLBORO MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) Richard Goode and Mitsuko Uchida's prestigious chamber music retreat in rural Vermont kicks off this weekend with a benefit concert tonight featuring Saint-Saëns's Fantaisie for Violin and Harp, Reger's Piano Trio in E minor and Schumann's Quartet in A. Tomorrow's program includes selections from Dvorak's ''Cypresses: Songs for String Quartet,'' Schoenberg's String Quartet No. 3 and Chausson's ''Chanson Perpétuelle.'' On Sunday the lineup includes Bartok's String Quartet No. 3, Mozart's Divertimento No. 7 in D and Dvorak's Quartet in D minor. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, and Sunday at 2:30, Marlboro Music School and Festival, Marlboro, Vt., (802) 254-2394, marlboromusic.org; $15 to $30; $5 for canopy areas. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MOZART (Tonight through Thursday) Tonight's concert features Osmo Vanska conducting Frank Martin's ''Overture in Homage to Mozart,'' Mozart's Symphony No. 35 and Beethoven's ever-popular Violin Concerto, with Sergey Khachatryan as the soloist. The program repeats tomorrow. Tomorrow night the violinist Gidon Kremer and members of his Kremerata Baltica play Shostakovich, Sofia Gubaidulina and Mozart at the Kaplan Penthouse. On Sunday the Kremerata, fresh from performing the complete Mozart violin concertos at Tanglewood, bring the works to Lincoln Center, with Nos. 1 to 3 on Sunday and Nos. 4 and 5 on Monday; the second program also includes Alexander Raskatov's ''Five Minutes in the Life of W.A.M.'' The festival orchestra returns on Tuesday with Douglas Boyd, making his New York conducting debut with Ibert's ''Hommage à Mozart''; Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 21, with the soloist Alexei Lubimov; and the Symphony No. 38. That program repeats on Wednesday. The opera ''Zaide,'' opening Wednesday, should be a highlight of the festival. Mozart set the work as a clash between European slaves and Turkish sultans in the Ottoman Empire; the director Peter Sellars, an old hand at updating operas, uses contemporary Muslim-Western relations. Louis Langrée leads the period-instrument ensemble Concerto Köln. On Thursday evening the pianist Christian Zacharias plays Mozart and Ravel in the Kaplan Penthouse. Orchestral concerts: Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 5 p.m., and Monday through Wednesday at 8 p.m., in Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center ($35 to $55); tomorrow and Thursday nights at 10:30 p.m., Kaplan Penthouse, 165 West 65th Street, Manhattan, ($35); ''Zaide,'' Wednesday at 8 p.m., Rose Theater, Broadway at 60th Street ($35 to $75), (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>ST. LAWRENCE STRING QUARTET (Tomorrow and Sunday) This dynamic ensemble contributes to the Mozart festivities with his Quartet in B flat (K. 159), followed by Debussy's Quartet and Franck's Piano Quintet in F minor, with Stephen Prutsman. The St. Lawrence's concert in the intimate barn at the Mount Lebanon Shaker Village (as part of the Tannery Pond Concerts series) will be followed on Sunday with a concert in another atmospheric barn, this time the open-backed Maverick Concert Hall, near Woodstock, N.Y., where the group will play Mozart's Quartet No. 21 in D (''Prussian No. 1''), Schumann's Quartet No. 1 and Shostakovich's Quartet No. 3. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., New Lebanon, N.Y., (888) 820-9441, tannerypondconcerts.org, $25 and $30; Sunday at 3 p.m., Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217, maverickconcerts.org; $20; $5 for students. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* SUMMERGARDEN (Sunday) The student ensembles from the Juilliard School who play these concerts tend to be devoted to contemporary music and play it with virtuosity and polish. The works, all new to New York, include Tigran Ayvazyan's String Quartet (2003); Ben-Zion Orgad's ''Arsalgia'' (2004); Carl Vine's String Quartet No. 3 (1994); John Psathas's ''Kartsigar'' (2004); Lera Auerbach's ''Epilogue'' (2005); and Elliott Sharp's ''Eye in the Sky'' (2006), which was composed for this concert. At 8 p.m., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Sculpture Garden at the Museum of Modern Art, 15 West 54th Street, (212) 708-9491, moma.org; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday) The centerpiece of this busy weekend is Seiji Ozawa's return to Tanglewood, tomorrow evening, to lead the Boston Symphony Orchestra and the Tanglewood Festival Chorus in Mahler's huge Symphony No. 2, the ''Resurrection.'' His soloists are the soprano Heidi Grant Murphy and the contralto Nathalie Stutzmann, and for listeners who can't get enough, there is also an open rehearsal tomorrow morning. Surrounding Mr. Ozawa's Mahler are programs led by Donald Runnicles. Tonight Yo-Yo Ma is his soloist in concertos by Haydn and Osvaldo Golijov, on a program that begins with Janacek's ''Idyll'' and ends with Elgar's ''Enigma Variations.'' On Sunday afternoon Mr. Runnicles is joined by the pianist Lars Vogt in the Beethoven ''Emperor'' Concerto. The program also includes Mozart's Symphony No. 38 and a suite from Strauss's ''Rosenkavalier.'' On Sunday evening the well-trained students of the Tanglewood Music Center play Dvorak's ''Carnival'' Overture, Babbitt's ''From the Psalter,'' Fauré's ''Pelléas et Mélisande'' Suite, Sibelius's ''Luonnotar'' and Ravel's ''Daphnis and Chloé'' Suite No. 2. Stefan Asbury is the conductor, and Dawn Upshaw the soprano soloist. Boston Symphony: tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday afternoon at 2:30. Mahler rehearsal: tomorrow at 10:30 a.m. Tanglewood Music Center Orchestra: Sunday at 8:30 p.m. Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; tonight, $18 to $50, with $8.50 lawn tickets; sold out tomorrow night, except for lawn tickets at $17; rehearsal tomorrow morning, $17; Sunday afternoon, $18 to $50; Sunday evening, $11 to $36. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>* CENTRAL PARK SUMMERSTAGE 2006: LIMÓN DANCE COMPANY (Tonight) Lyrical and dramatic, dancing by the Limón company tends to stir the soul. This free 60th-anniversary program includes a performance by Raphael Boumaila of Daniel Nagrin's rarely seen ''Dance in the Sun,'' as well as works by José Limón, Jiri Kylian and Donald McKayle. At 8, Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-1777, or summerstage.org. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* CENTRAL PARK SUMMERSTAGE 2006: 'FROM MAMBO TO HIP HOP'  (Monday) This sounds like the place to be for sheer fun. This free program includes a preview screening of ''From Mambo to Hip Hop,'' a PBS documentary that explores the rich cultural history of the South Bronx. Veteran hip-hop, salsa and mambo dancers will perform before the movie is shown. The film will be followed by a question-and-answer session with Henry Chalfant, the documentary's director; the mambo dancer Peanut; the hip-hop dancer and historian PopMaster Fabel; and others. 7 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, Central Park, (212) 360-2777, or summerstage.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ENTRESUEÑO (Wednesday) This new flamenco production by Edwin Aparicio is formed around the states of mind before entering sleep and awakening. The dancers include Óscar Valero and La Genoveva. At 7:30 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, or symphonyspace.org; $25 to $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>HOT! THE NYC CELEBRATION OF QUEER CULTURE: HENRY HILL AND KELLY BARTNIK (Tonight and tomorrow night) Friends and collaborators, Mr. Hill and Ms. Bartnik will perform solos and group pieces in a program endearingly entitled ''Believe the Hype.'' Well, why not, just this once? At 8, Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, or dixonplace.org; $10 to $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) The Trey McIntyre Project, a contemporary ballet company, will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend, followed there on Wednesday and Thursday (and next weekend) by Shen Wei Dance Arts. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, Armitage Gone! (Karole Armitage's new New York-based company) plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is MoveOpolis, the company formed by Richard Move, who made his name as a Martha Graham impersonator. McIntyre tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., $45; Shen Wei Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, $50. Armitage tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15; tomorrow at 2:15 p.m.; and Sunday at 5 p.m.; $24. MoveOpolis on Thursday at 8:15 p.m., $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, ages 65+ and children. Details: jacobspillow.org. Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL: PERU NEGRO (Sunday) The company celebrates black Peruvian culture in dance, playful multigenerational stage business and music performed on quijadas de buro (donkey jaw-bone rattles) and other exotic traditional instruments. At 3 and 7 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens, (718) 760-0064 or QueensTheatre.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER OUT OF DOORS (Tonight through Aug. 27) O.K., so being outside in New York City in August feels as if you're in a soup bowl, but there's a bright side: free dance to be had all month at Lincoln Center. The action begins tomorrow with ''Playday,'' lessons and demonstrations involving African, Middle Eastern and Irish folk dance. Thursday's lineup looks particularly promising: first, ''We B*Girlz,'' hip-hop challenges among various female crews, and then a double bill, ''Double Trouble: Dancin' the Blues,'' with the sublime Reggie Wilson/Fist &amp; Heel Performance Group and the Lula Washington Dance Theater of Los Angeles. Performances take place on stages erected throughout the Lincoln Center campus, from 62nd to 65th Streets, between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues. Complete schedule: (212) 546-2656, or lincolncenter.org. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless but enormously popular for people of all ages. Three programs alternate for the run, ending Aug. 12. Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday at 8 p.m., and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, or joyce.org; $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>KANG SUN YOUNG DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday) Ms. Young is said to be the sole successor to Han Seong Jun, a pioneer in the preservation of traditional Korean dance. Her 60-member troupe of dancers and musicians will perform pieces from that repertory in a program called ''A Legacy in Tradition.'' 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, or www.kangsunyoungarts.org; $25 to $95.(Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and castoff clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States in a garrulous, very personal way. One particularly intense work, based on the belief that Abubakari II, ruler of Mali, crossed the Atlantic nearly 200 years before Columbus to discover the Americas, links the past with the present and Africa with the beloved Columbus of Ms. Robinson's childhood. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 or brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606 or daheshmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700 or frick.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestoes and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500 or guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* INternational Center of Photography: 'On Air,' through Aug. 27. The South Korean artist Atta Kim's best-known body of work is a series called ''The Museum Project'' (1995-2002), for which he photographed his human subjects -- families, nude couples, maimed war veterans -- locked inside plexiglass exhibition cases like specimens on display. The series eventually took a religious turn, with models posing as Buddhist deities. The pictures here, in his first major American solo show, continue this spiritual trajectory. Filmed using long exposure times, figures, landscapes and religious icons have been turned into apparitions. People, art and museums may last for a while, Mr. Kim seems to say, but all things eventually melt away. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000 or icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* metropolitan museum of art: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early-19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. History is full of shifty characters, antique visionaries, cusp figures and half-crazy oddball innovators, later overlooked because they're hard to pigeonhole. Their independent cast of mind is the truest expression of how civilization advances. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 4 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of a kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. Many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500 or mobia.org. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer, , through Sept. 18. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200 or neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden: Chihuly at the New York Botanical Garden, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700 or nybg.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. A large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, (212) 873-3400 or nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' through Aug. 19. Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. Concentrating on books, but also including prints and drawings, it retells the tale of the French avant-garde on a relatively egalitarian playing field. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089 or nypl.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084 or ps1.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Rubin Museum of Art : 'What is it? HimalAyan Art' For a basic guide to the art of Tibet and Nepal, you will do no better than to take a slow walk through this new show, which, using an array of gorgeous objects, distills knotty visual and spiritual systems to a soothing but stimulating entry-level form. 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000 or rmanyc.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676 or whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* A BROKEN ARM The title is a tribute to Duchamp. The works review various strategies of using found objects or images in photography, painting and sculpture. The seven artists include Gedi Sibony, Arnold Odermatt and Karen Kalimnik. All has been orchestrated by Mari Spirito, the gallery's director. 303 Gallery, 525 West 22nd Street, (212) 255-1121, 303gallery.com, through Aug. 18. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* DERECONSTRUCTION Matthew Higgs, director of the alternative space White Columns, has assembled a handsome show that in typical Higgs fashion brings together outsider, emerging, hip and formerly hip artists. Variations on collage and assemblage predominate without feeling stale. The larger point: deconstruction has had its day, and it is time to start putting things back together again. The putters range from A. R. Penck and Lucas Samaras to Carter and Alexandra Bircken. Gladstone Gallery, 515 West 24th Street, (212) 206-9301, gladstonegallery.com, through Aug. 18. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* J. Bennett Fitts: 'No Lifeguard on Duty' Symbolically resonant photographs of mostly derelict motel swimming pools by a young Californian. Julie Saul, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 627-2410, saulgallery.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FOUNTAINS A summery theme is tweaked by energetic efforts. High points include Daniel Lefcourt's eye-popping photograph of studio tools, Sanford Bigger's video of a disco ball and Gibb Slife's television set, whose do-it-yourself antenna suggests spreading vines or brain waves. The low points seem to have been left out. D'Amelio Terras, 525 West 22nd Street, (212) 352-9460, damelioterras.com, through Aug. 11. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field with Sculptures' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West 22nd Street, (212) 243-0200, matthewmarks.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* GALERIE DANIEL BUCHHOLZ AT METRO PICTURES The well-known Cologne art gallery presents a surprisingly sweeping view of current art that includes Americans and Europeans and, despite its Conceptual slant, an impressive range of mediums and sensibilities. That may be the point. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, (212) 206-7100, metropicturesgallery.com, through Sept. 16. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Michael Heizer Sculptures in concrete representing prehistoric hand tools much enlarged so that they resemble Modernist sculptures by a follower of Brancusi. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 421-3292 or pacewildenstein.com, through Sept. 23. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Materiality' Inventive works made of all sorts of materials in this show include a stuffed leather-and-plywood tree by Carolyn Salas; a geometric landscape with a slowing-moving, wartlike kinetic element, covered in reflective Mylar, by Charlotte Becket; a neat display of more than 200 pieces of breakfast cereal by Tom Friedman; and a sumptuous stuffed object resembling a much-enlarged amoeba by Ernesto Neto. Kravets/Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238, kravetswehbygallery.com, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>MEN This show of 10 paintings of men by 10 women, organized by the painter Ellen Altfest, covers a lot of stylistic ground and includes an only partly tongue-in-cheek denunciation from the lesbian collective Redykeulous. Realism makes the strongest impression. I-20, 557 West 23rd Street, (212) 645-1100, I-20.com, through Aug. 18. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Howardena Pindell: 'In My Lifetime' Thirty years ago, Howardena Pindell was well known for meditative, process-based abstract work, though her art has always had two aspects. In the 1970's and 80's it assumed and maintained an overtly political direction in large-scale pieces that combined abstraction, words and figures to deal with social and political issues, from AIDS and homelessness to the present war in Iraq. Both types are in this informal gallery retrospective, which makes clear how thoroughly they are based on -- emerge from, are fueled and inflected by -- the individual experiences and memories of the artist herself. G. R. N'Namdi Gallery, 526 West 26th Street, Suite 316, (212) 929-6645, grnnamdi.com, through Aug. 31. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>A RABBIT AS KING OF THE GHOSTS With a title lifted from Wallace Stevens, this elegant show posits photography as the leading ghost in the machine of contemporary art and draws visually telling analogies from 140 years of the medium's life span. It has been organized by the photographers Justine Kurland and Dan Torop. Mitchell-Innes &amp; Nash, 534 West 26th Street, (212) 744-7400, miandn.com, through Aug. 11. (Smith)</p>
        <p>TWO FRIENDS AND SO ON Selected by asking one artist to invite another, who asked another, until a group of 30 had accrued, this show winds from Conceptual-based work through abstract painting and sculpture, and back again, presenting a random cross-section of the art world and displaying a network of style-based alliances. It is a quite a ride. Andrew Kreps Gallery, 525 West 22nd Street, (212) 741-8849, andrewkreps.com, through Aug. 12. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'WAR ON 45/MY MIRRORS ARE PAINTED BLACK (FOR YOU)' The latest word from the boys in black is a show of six artists organized by the head boy, Banks Violette. The stark glamour of it cannot be denied, but it looks too much like graphic design. Bortolami Dayan, 510 West 25th Street, (212) 727-2050, bortolamidayan.com, through Sept. 2. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'Gifts Go in One Direction' With art selling so briskly these days, isn't it time for the art world to hand out some gift bags, some freebies? After all, artists, as members of an intensively networked and mutually supportive community, have been giving one another gifts. That is the subject of this charming summer show, which takes the form of a round-robin of generosity, with artists on both the giving and receiving ends. Apexart, 291 Church Street, near Walker Street, TriBeCa, (212) 431-5270, through Aug. 12. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* Rudy Burckhardt: 'New York Paintings' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Mr. Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, near 57th Street, (212) 262-5050 or tibordenagy.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 5, 2006, Saturday  A theater entry in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday for ''Indian Blood,'' which is in previews at Primary Stages, misstated the opening date. It will open on Wednesday, not Thursday.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 18, 2006, Friday  An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Aug. 4 and Aug. 11 for the group exhibition ''A Broken Arm'' at the 303 Gallery in Chelsea misspelled the surname of an artist. She is Karen Kilimnik, not Kalimnik.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 5, 2006, Saturday</p>
        <p>A theater entry in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday for ''Indian Blood,'' which is in previews at Primary Stages, misstated the opening date. It will open on Wednesday, not Thursday.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: August 18, 2006, Friday</p>
        <p>An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Aug. 4 and Aug. 11 for the group exhibition ''A Broken Arm'' at the 303 Gallery in Chelsea misspelled the surname of an artist. She is Karen Kilimnik, not Kalimnik.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
