<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Surfers vs. Turf as Long Beach Votes on Plan to Build New Dunes</title>
    <meta content="04beaches" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/04/nyregion/04beaches.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1759186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Beach (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1E3FF937A35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Surfers vs. Turf as Long Beach Votes on Plan to Build New Dunes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It's Surfers vs. Turf as Long Beach Votes on Plan to Build New Dunes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>LONG BEACH, N.Y., May 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Beach (NY) Council members will vote on whether to support Army Corp of Engineers $98.5 million storm-protection project for beachfront; city's share of cost would be $7 million; decades of erosion have left beach flat from waterline to boardwalk, leaving town vulnerable to flooding; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Storm experts predict a turbulent season this year. They have also long warned that Long Island is overdue for another really ''big one,'' like the devastating hurricane of 1938.</p>
        <p>Ground zero could well be this vulnerable barrier island that is home to 50,000 people, most of whom live in the city of Long Beach. Apartment towers along the ocean here have created the most densely populated waterfront on Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG BEACH, N.Y., May 3  Storm experts predict a turbulent season this year. They have also long warned that Long Island is overdue for another really</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Storm experts predict a turbulent season this year. They have also long warned that Long Island is overdue for another really ''big one,'' like the devastating hurricane of 1938.</p>
        <p>Ground zero could well be this vulnerable barrier island that is home to 50,000 people, most of whom live in the city of Long Beach. Apartment towers along the ocean here have created the most densely populated waterfront on Long Island.</p>
        <p>But decades of erosion have eaten away the beach, leaving it flat from the waterline to the Boardwalk and putting hundreds of millions of dollars of property at risk. Even in ordinary storms, surging surf sometimes covers the entire beach, spilling into adjacent streets.</p>
        <p>And if storm waves ever breach the barrier island, the next danger would be to the low-lying South Shore suburbs and their hundreds of thousands of residents.</p>
        <p>Now, the Army Corps of Engineers is proposing a $98.5 million storm-protection project along six miles of Long Beach and neighboring Lido Beach and Point Lookout. It calls for fortifying the shore with 6.6 million cubic yards of dredged sand, building new dunes, strengthening 18 rock jetties and adding seven new ones.</p>
        <p>''You'd think it would be a no-brainer to jump at the chance to do this,'' said Bruce Nyman, who worked on earlier plans as the Long Beach city supervisor and later city manager.</p>
        <p>But Long Beach, a diverse community with a tradition of infighting, is in an uproar.</p>
        <p>After two decades of debate, the showdown comes Thursday night. Facing a ''take it or leave it'' deadline from the corps, the City Council is supposed to cast its long-delayed vote on whether to join the project and pay the city's $7 million share. Council members have not tipped their hand as to how they will vote.</p>
        <p>The other governments that would share in the project -- the state, Nassau County and Hempstead Town, which oversees Lido Beach and Point Lookout -- are also awaiting the city's decision. All support the project, but if Long Beach does not go along, the corps will have to decide whether to scale back the work to just Lido and Point Lookout. Communities west of Long Beach, including Atlantic Beach, are not affected because their beaches are stronger.</p>
        <p>Proponents invoke scary memories of Katrina and the prospect of rising waters from global warming. But opponents question the plan's cost and effectiveness. Surfers claim the project would jeopardize the waves they love, and some people even argue over the size and color of the sand to be dredged.</p>
        <p>On the Boardwalk, a sampling of walkers, bikers and surfers on Wednesday found wide support for the plan. But hundreds of organized critics have packed recent hearings to voice adamant opposition. Mail to City Hall is running overwhelmingly against the project.</p>
        <p>''Look at that!'' Harvey Weisenberg said, pointing to a blotchy brown discoloration along the sand, a few feet from the Boardwalk. ''That's the high-water mark from the tides -- on a calm day!'' A storm would be disastrous, he said. Mr. Weisenberg, an assemblyman and for nearly half a century, a lifeguard, added, ''We have to protect ourselves, or we'll be Long Beach without a beach.''</p>
        <p>One environmental advocate, Morris H. Kramer, has written to apartment owners and even the clergy, pleading for the project. Without it, a moderate storm ''would damage nearly every structure'' in the city, and in a big storm, ''lives will be lost,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the Surfrider Foundation, an advocacy group, argues that the plan would spoil the beach and the sport of surfing even though the Army Corps project manager, Clifford Jones, has said: ''We don't see a long-term impact on the surfability,'' since the dredging would be done further east.</p>
        <p>Critics also complain that dredged sand would be darker and coarser than the light, fine-grain ''sugar'' sand that makes up the beach now. But Mr. Jones said that samples from the dredge site ''show that what we have is the same sand.'' Organic material in it may be dark, but that would soon bleach in the sun, he said.</p>
        <p>An earlier version of the plan drew objections that the proposed dunes would have obstructed ocean views from apartments on lower floors. Other critics said the dunes would not have left enough space for popular volleyball tournaments.</p>
        <p>''We did work with them to move the dune back,'' Mr. Jones said. The plan now calls for a 15-foot-high dune tucked under the Boardwalk, with a 10-foot berm extending out another 110 feet, planted with beach grass, then sloping down to the water.</p>
        <p>One resident, Michael Dunne, a retired postal worker, supports that approach, saying, ''I'd rather be safe than sorry.'' Three women on their daily Boardwalk stroll agreed. ''We all feel that way,'' said one of them, Rita Smith. ''It's called preventive medicine.''</p>
        <p>A biker, Norman Meschkow, supports the planned dunes ''as long as they don't come above the Boardwalk'' where he lives and block his view. A biking friend, Gil Meyer, said: '' I think it's crazy not to do it. A bunch of surfers who are not from the area came in and influenced the Council. It was a travesty.''</p>
        <p>One of the surfers, James Dolny, a New York City firefighter from Suffolk, opposes the project. ''Let nature refill itself,'' he said. ''The storms take, and they give back.'' Another surfer, Christopher Quinn, a college student, said: ''It's going to ruin the surf. There won't be any waves for years.'' He acknowledged, however, that the beach was eroded and the buildings would be endangered.</p>
        <p>Part of Long Beach already has man-made dunes, where the two-mile Boardwalk ends. ''Hurricane Gloria in 1985 did a lot of damage in the West End,'' recalled Mr. Kramer. ''People saw their furniture floating in the street and wanted to do something about it.''</p>
        <p>As City Council president then, Mr. Weisenberg oversaw the dune-building. Some people objected to blocked views, he said. ''But after the first northeaster, when they didn't get water in their basements for the first time, they said it was the greatest thing we ever did.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weisenberg called that pilot project living proof that dunes could prevent flooding. Noting that Long Beach's official motto is ''the City by the Sea,'' he said, ''We don't want to be the City in the Sea.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
