<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Something Borrowed, Something Renewed</title>
    <meta content="28wedd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/28/theater/reviews/28wedd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1757579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lynch, Stephen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Benanti, Laura</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beguelin, Chad</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sandler, Adam</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Spanger, Amy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cahoon, Kevin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gardner, Rita</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Wedding Singer, The (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EED9133FF93BA15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Something Borrowed, Something Renewed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Something Borrowed, Something Renewed: The Return of the 80's in 'The Wedding Singer'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW quickly our dreary yesterdays become bright, cute and endlessly repackageable. The 1980's, it seems, are to today what the 1950's were to the 1970's (and to part of the 1980's): a supposedly more innocent, picturesquely dopey time when people wore quaint clothes, listened to infectiously inane music and danced goofy tribal dances. Ah, how we laughed.</p>
        <p>Hence the return of big hair and shoulders to fashion's runways; the preponderance of Web sites with names like ''inthe80s.com''; and animated television scrapbooks, like ''I Love the 80's'' on VH1, where third-tier celebrities provide snarky commentary about their favorite period bands, movies and celebrities. And now, mining the same much-plundered vein, is ''The Wedding Singer,'' the assembly-kit musical that opened last night at the Al Hirschfeld Theater and might as well be called ''That 80's Show.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called "That 80s Show," this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotes from the era of big hair and junk bonds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW quickly our dreary yesterdays become bright, cute and endlessly repackageable. The 1980's, it seems, are to today what the 1950's were to the 1970's (and to part of the 1980's): a supposedly more innocent, picturesquely dopey time when people wore quaint clothes, listened to infectiously inane music and danced goofy tribal dances. Ah, how we laughed.</p>
        <p>Hence the return of big hair and shoulders to fashion's runways; the preponderance of Web sites with names like ''inthe80s.com''; and animated television scrapbooks, like ''I Love the 80's'' on VH1, where third-tier celebrities provide snarky commentary about their favorite period bands, movies and celebrities. And now, mining the same much-plundered vein, is ''The Wedding Singer,'' the assembly-kit musical that opened last night at the Al Hirschfeld Theater and might as well be called ''That 80's Show.''</p>
        <p>This transformation of a Hollywood movie into a Broadway musical, a trend that appears as irreversible as global warming, is an example of recycled recycling, or second-hand nostalgia. The film ''The Wedding Singer,'' which became a big hit, thanks largely to its romantic leads, Adam Sandler and Drew Barrymore, was also set in the mid-1980's, but it was made in the late 1990's. Remember the 1990's? Ah, how we laughed. Would that we could recapture the charm and innocence of how we looked at the 1980's in those days.</p>
        <p>In fairness, ''The Wedding Singer'' -- which features songs by Matthew Sklar and Chad Beguelin and a book by Tim Herlihy (who also wrote the screenplay for the movie) and Mr. Beguelin -- is hardly a low point in a Broadway season that has given us ''Lennon,'' ''In My Life'' and ''Lestat.'' True, it consists of little more than winks and nods and quotations. Entire stretches of dialogue are composed of titles of vintage songs, which are imitated as dutifully as copyright law allows in Mr. Sklar's pastiche score. And Rob Ashford's choreography is replete with literal-minded tributes to 1980's music videos for era-defining songs like ''Thriller,'' ''Material Girl'' and ''Flashdance.''</p>
        <p>But the show has at least a flutter of a hedonist's pulse. And if its formulaic catering to an established public appetite feels cynical, the cast members exude earnestness and good nature. They are a personable enough lot, which is not the same as saying that they have personality.</p>
        <p>For, as so often happens when good (or even not-so-good) films turn into stage shows, the first things to be jettisoned are sharp edges and authentically quirky characters. (Decades ago, when Broadway still had a mind of its own, the same process occurred when stage shows were made into Hollywood musicals.) I need utter only three words to make my case: ''Saturday Night Fever.''</p>
        <p>The plot of this ''Wedding Singer,'' directed with bland peppiness by John Rando, sticks closely to that of the movie. The title character, Robbie Hart (played here by Stephen Lynch), is a would-be rock star who makes do by fronting a band that plays wedding receptions in Ridgefield, N.J. He's good at his job because he's in love with love and the notion of happily ever after -- that is, until he is left standing at the altar by his skanky fiancée (the enjoyably trashy Felicia Finley). His only hope of salvation lies in the form of Julia Sullivan (Laura Benanti), a sweet, clumsy waitress who unfortunately already has a boyfriend, a Wall Street junk bonds whiz kid (Richard H. Blake).</p>
        <p>It's a wispy plot, even by the standards of romantic comedy. What made the movie more or less bearable was Mr. Sandler, a king of low comedy, subduing his frat-house instincts to create a surprisingly gentle portrait of a loser. Plus there was the dewier-than-daybreak Ms. Barrymore, who managed to make even vomit jokes smell like roses. (The vomit jokes, by the way, have been nixed for the stage version. The four-letter words remain.)</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Lynch nor Ms. Benanti, though obviously gifted, shows much original presence here. Mr. Lynch is best known as a performer of self-subverting comic songs that move from conventional prettiness to shock-effect humor. This would seem to make him a natural replacement for Mr. Sandler.</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Lynch is charming as Robbie in an angry or depressed mood (he does especially well by the two oddball songs retained from the movie, written by Mr. Sandler with Mr. Herlihy), he is more often called upon to be appealingly boyish, bringing to mind a less vain, less glib Ryan Seacrest. Ms. Benanti, a dark-haired enchantress in the revival of ''Into the Woods,'' goes Barrymore blond for ''The Wedding Singer'' and winds up looking like that sharp-featured beacon of on-screen efficiency, Helen Hunt. This Julia has a shrewd, calculating look that makes her less than convincing as a starry-eyed klutz.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, characterization is clearly secondary in ''The Wedding Singer,'' which is why a supporting cast stocked with sui generis talents tends to turn into a pasteboard parade. That includes Amy Spanger (a standout in the revival of ''Kiss Me, Kate'') as Julia's cousin, a Madonna wannabe ; Kevin Cahoon (the Childcatcher in ''Chitty Chitty Bang Bang'') as a member of Robbie's band and a Boy George wannabe; and Rita Gardner (the -- gasp! -- original Girl in ''The Fantasticks'') as a sweet little old grandmother who raps, break-dances and talks dirty.</p>
        <p>Despite these performers' game efforts, most of their characters feel only a hair's breadth away from the posse of celebrity impersonators (dressed up as Billy Idol, Cyndi Lauper, Tina Turner, Ronald Reagan and Imelda Marcos, among others) who are rounded up for the show's climax in a Las Vegas wedding chapel. Only the excellent Matthew Saldivar, as Robbie's best friend (a Van Halen wannabe), registers as a bona fide character, authentically defined by his time and place.</p>
        <p>That place, of course, is Ridgefield, which has been reconstructed with affectionate cartoon tackiness in Scott Pask's sets. (Gregory Gale's even tackier costumes should by rights single-handedly put a stop to an 80's revival in fashion.) ''The Wedding Singer'' makes no bones about appealing directly to nearby out-of-towners. ''New York is reserved for the rich and proud,/ But here comes the bridge and tunnel crowd,'' sings the ensemble in a number set in a Manhattan disco.</p>
        <p>But Jerseyphilia must take a back seat to the show's broader raison d'être: to create a singing, dancing version of ''Trivial Pursuit: 80's Edition.'' This ambition filters through sight gags (Julia's fiancé totes a cellphone with an oversized battery and drives a DeLorean with a license plate that says ''XMAS BONUS'') and little-did-we-know jokes about subjects like Starbucks and the New Coke.</p>
        <p>It says everything about this musical's priorities that it brings down its first-act curtain not on a suspenseful or emotional moment between Robbie and Julia but on the image of a scantily dressed woman in profile in a chair (Ms. Spanger) being doused with a bucket of water. If that image doesn't make you think ''What a feeling!,'' then ''The Wedding Singer'' is probably not your show.</p>
        <p>The Wedding Singer</p>
        <p>Music by Matthew Sklar; book by Chad Beguelin and Tim Herlihy; lyrics by Mr. Beguelin; based on the New Line Cinema film written by Mr. Herlihy. Choreographed by Rob Ashford; directed by John Rando; sets by Scott Pask; costumes by Gregory Gale; lighting by Brian MacDevitt; sound by Peter Hylenski; hair design, David Brian Brown; makeup design, Joe Dulude II; orchestrations, Irwin Fisch; incidental and dance music arranger, David Chase; music director-conductor, James Sampliner; executive producer, Mark Kaufman; production manager, Juniper Street Productions; associate choreographer, Joann M. Hunter; production stage manager, Rolt Smith; music coordinator, John Miller; general management, the Charlotte Wilcox Company. Presented by Margo Lion, New Line Cinema, the Araca Group, Roy Furman, Douglas L. Meyer/James D. Stern, Rick Steiner/the Staton/Bell/Osher/Mayerson Group, Jam Theatricals, in association with Jujamcyn Theaters and Jay Furman, Michael Gill, Dr. Lawrence Horowitz, Rhoda Mayerson, Marisa Sechrest, Gary Winnick, Dancap Productions Inc., Élan V. McAllister/Allan S. Gordon/Adam Epstein. At the Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. Running time: 2 hours 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Stephen Lynch (Robbie Hart), Laura Benanti (Julia Sullivan), Matthew Saldivar (Sammy), Kevin Cahoon (George), Amy Spanger (Holly), Richard H. Blake (Glen Guglia), Rita Gardner (Rosie), Felicia Finley (Linda) and Adinah Alexander (Angie).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
