<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Wild Zones</title>
    <meta content="WE--Corridor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/12/opinion/nyregionopinions/WE_Corridor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1739015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2D7143EF931A25751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Wild Zones</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Wild Zones</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sneaky thing about the suburban landscape is how natural it looks. The trees turn green, then brown and then green again, there are always leaves to blow and grass to mow, and something is keeping all those greedy deer and evil geese alive. It all looks good, but something is not right. All those highways, sidewalks and housing developments, the products of planning decisions that revolve mainly around people and their cars, keep nature off-balance. They pay little heed to the needs of all the other residents of suburbia -- the wild things that live, move, work and play entirely off the grid.</p>
        <p>Sprawl is bad for wildlife because it cuts habitat into isolated chunks. Plots of undeveloped land become biological islands, melancholy archipelagoes of green. Species that can't easily swim, crawl, flutter or fly from one to another become stranded. Their habits of migration, mating and feeding are disrupted. Biodiversity suffers, and the health of ecosystems declines. According to biologists like Michael Klemens, sprawl is as big a threat to some species as pesticides or global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a wise community that willingly subordinates its needs to accommodate those of a turtle, a salamander or a frog.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sneaky thing about the suburban landscape is how natural it looks. The trees turn green, then brown and then green again, there are always leaves to blow and grass to mow, and something is keeping all those greedy deer and evil geese alive. It all looks good, but something is not right. All those highways, sidewalks and housing developments, the products of planning decisions that revolve mainly around people and their cars, keep nature off-balance. They pay little heed to the needs of all the other residents of suburbia -- the wild things that live, move, work and play entirely off the grid.</p>
        <p>Sprawl is bad for wildlife because it cuts habitat into isolated chunks. Plots of undeveloped land become biological islands, melancholy archipelagoes of green. Species that can't easily swim, crawl, flutter or fly from one to another become stranded. Their habits of migration, mating and feeding are disrupted. Biodiversity suffers, and the health of ecosystems declines. According to biologists like Michael Klemens, sprawl is as big a threat to some species as pesticides or global warming.</p>
        <p>Dr. Klemens is a herpetologist and the director of the Metropolitan Conservation Alliance, a program of the Wildlife Conservation Society (Bronx Zoo, to you, although its purview extends far beyond that borough). As Debra West explained in these pages, the alliance (www.wcs.org/international/northamerica/mca) is a leader in promoting ''biotic corridors,'' stretches of protected land that respect animals' habitats and movements. They are an innovative way to confront the problem of threatened environment along what the alliance calls the ''suburban/rural frontier.''</p>
        <p>Northern Westchester is nothing if not the suburban/rural frontier. It is here -- in the towns of Lewisboro, Pound Ridge and North Salem -- that town officials have hired consultants to try to put Dr. Klemens's principles into practice over a 22,000-acre territory. Nothing has been decided yet, but zoning changes could include restrictions on what types of fences and walls go up, how big or tightly clustered housing units should be, and how close development can encroach on wetlands.</p>
        <p>New zoning restrictions, of course, are the last thing that many residents and local officials want, particularly in areas stung by housing shortages and the need to develop and nurture a tax base. But there's a powerful case to be made for ecologically sensible development, for doing more than simply roping off random patches of unpaved turf. Among the arguments that environmental groups have mustered against a large housing complex proposed along the Hudson River in Kingston, in Ulster County, is that it threatens biodiversity. In their view, a responsible plan would take into account the mobility of turtles as well as of cars.</p>
        <p>Biotic corridors are an innovation that arrived too late for many parts of the region. But where they have been proposed, residents and officials have been remarkably open to the idea. Planners and government officials are showing an increasing willingness to give the advocates a hearing. Cortland, New Castle and Yorktown may be getting in on the idea, Dr. Klemens says, as are other communities in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut. People who hear about biotic corridors, he says, tend to want to be included in them, unaware that wild things, not government boards, set their boundaries.</p>
        <p>If Dr. Klemens is right, biotic corridors could become the land-use planning vogue. We hope they do. It is a wise community that willingly subordinates its needs to accommodate those of a turtle, a salamander or a frog.</p>
        <p>Westchester</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
