<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Love-Hate Relationship Bears a 50-State Diesel</title>
    <meta content="15DIESEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/15/automobiles/15DIESEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1797287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="GREEN TECH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cameron, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Honda Motor Company Limited</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5D71030F936A25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Love-Hate Relationship Bears a 50-State Diesel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Love-Hate Relationship Bears a 50-State Diesel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN CAMERON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cameron, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Honda announces development of ultraclean diesel engine that will be sold in its cars in 2009; says engine will meet emissions standards in United States; photos; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASSIGNMENTS this juicy are rare in the career of an automotive engineer: the opportunity to develop a new generation of high-efficiency diesel engines that would lead a major company into a fuel-sipping low-emissions future.</p>
        <p>It was a challenge that Kenichi Nagahiro, whose portfolio as a Honda senior engineer included Formula One racing engines and the company's VTEC variable valve timing technology, should have relished. Instead, he turned it down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Honda, the company whose clean-burning CVCC Civic model did the seemingly impossible in the 1970’s by meeting emissions standards, has not lost its knack for innovation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASSIGNMENTS this juicy are rare in the career of an automotive engineer: the opportunity to develop a new generation of high-efficiency diesel engines that would lead a major company into a fuel-sipping low-emissions future.</p>
        <p>It was a challenge that Kenichi Nagahiro, whose portfolio as a Honda senior engineer included Formula One racing engines and the company's VTEC variable valve timing technology, should have relished. Instead, he turned it down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nagahiro eventually relented, agreeing to head the program -- but only if he had a free hand to design an engine that would overcome his disdain for the noisy, smelly diesels previously on the market.</p>
        <p>The initial product of the program -- the first diesel engine designed entirely by Honda -- was introduced in 2003 to power a European version of the Accord. A British advertising campaign played off Mr. Nagahiro's reluctance, asking, ''What if a diesel engine was built by someone who hates them?'' Television commercials featured Garrison Keillor singing a tune called ''Hate Something, Change Something.''</p>
        <p>The project did far more than simply tame a problematic alternative to gasoline engines. Last month, Honda announced that it would bring the 2.2-liter diesel, which it calls the i-CTDi engine, to the United States within three years. The company says that the engine will meet the demanding Tier II Bin 5 regulations, allowing it to be sold in America's largest auto markets -- California and the Northeast states that have adopted California's regulations -- where new diesel cars have not been sold since tailpipe pollutant levels were tightened beyond the reach of available engine technology.</p>
        <p>Honda is not the only automaker to promise a 50-state diesel; Mercedes-Benz has said it plans to sell diesel versions of its sport utility vehicles across the country in 2008. The first phase of the Mercedes emissions-control system, known as Bluetec, is used in the 2007 E320; next year's 50-state version for three sport utility models will also be equipped with AdBlue, a process that injects liquid urea into the exhaust, enabling a chemical reaction that reduces the output of smog-forming nitrogen oxides. Neither the Honda and nor the Mercedes systems have been through the certfication process.</p>
        <p>But Honda, the company whose clean-burning CVCC Civic model did the seemingly impossible in the 1970's by meeting emissions standards, has not lost its knack for innovation. The company says the i-CTDi turbodiesel engine will meet the regulations using a much simpler emissions-control system; it requires no added fluids to keep emissions in check.</p>
        <p>Diesel engines achieve high fuel economy by a combination of high compression ratio (16.7:1 in this Honda), lean combustion (a high proportion of air to fuel) and low pumping loss (because they have no throttle). But diesel tailpipes spew higher amounts of nitrogen oxides than comparable gasoline engines, and they are harder to clean up. The three-way catalytic converter, a technology highly effective on gasoline engines, eliminating up to 99 percent of nitrogen oxides, can cut those emissions by only 10 percent or so on diesels -- not nearly enough.</p>
        <p>Ben Knight, vice president for research and development of American Honda, said that the major components of the i-CTDi engine's emissions-control strategy were improved combustion within the engine and effective aftertreatment -- an industry buzzword for the devices that chemically convert exhaust pollutants to harmless gases.</p>
        <p>The engine uses common-rail fuel injection at very high pressure, about 30,000 pounds per square inch. Such pressures deliver the fuel more quickly, giving it more time to evaporate. It also breaks the fuel into smaller droplets, increasing its total surface area. High injection velocity -- close to the speed of sound -- ensures that the droplets penetrate deeply into the highly compressed air in the cylinder. The more uniformly fuel and air are mixed during diesel injection, the lower the output of nitrogen oxides.</p>
        <p>Cooled exhaust gas is recirculated to the cylinders, also reducing combustion temperature and further cutting the production of nitrogen oxides.</p>
        <p>Exhaust gas from the cylinders is piped first to an oxidation catalyst in which carbon monoxide and any unburned hydrocarbons are combined with oxygen to complete their combustion into carbon dioxide and water. Next, the exhaust gases pass through a particulate filter, which removes the carbon particles that in older models made diesel exhaust smoky. The last step, new and crucial to passing the toughest regulations, is cutting nitrogen oxides.</p>
        <p>Instead of adding liquid from an onboard reservoir to produce the ammonia needed to clean up the nitrogen oxides, as the Mercedes Bluetec system does, the Honda makes its own ammonia as it goes, combining hydrogen with nitrogen inside a two-layer catalyst. Honda's catalyst for scrubbing out nitrogen oxides operates in two stages. In normal operation, when the fuel mixture is lean, nitrogen oxides in the exhaust are trapped, or adsorbed, onto the lower layer of the catalyst. When the engine's control computer switches it to rich combustion for a few seconds, hydrogen is released from the exhaust gases. This reacts with the nitrogen from the adsorbed gases to form ammonia, which is stored by adsorption in the catalyst's upper layer.</p>
        <p>Then, as the engine returns to lean operation, the ammonia reacts with nitrogen oxides in the exhaust stream to produce water and nitrogen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Knight said that the 2.2-liter turbocharged engine developed 138 horsepower at 4,000 r.p.m., with peak torque of 251 pound-feet at 2,000 r.p.m. Asked what the ratio of lean to rich operation might be, he gave the example of a 60-mile-an-hour cruise, at which the engine would operate lean for three minutes, then rich for five seconds. This system is effective for the light loads of passenger car use, and in the relatively low temperature of diesel exhaust.</p>
        <p>Will this system work with larger engines? Mr. Knight said a V-6 application was being studied.</p>
        <p>Honda says that with the i-CTDi, it is hard to tell by the sound that the car is diesel-powered. Combined city/highway fuel economy is projected at nearly 42 miles a gallon for the Accord sedan; 0-60 acceleration takes 9.2 seconds.</p>
        <p>GREEN TECH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
