<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Sues 6 Automakers Over Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="21auto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/21/business/21auto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1791623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFDD1131F932A1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Sues 6 Automakers Over Global Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">California Sues 6 Automakers Over Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK BUNKLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>California, which has battled the automotive industry over new global warming regulations for years, sued the world's six-largest automakers yesterday, demanding that they pay for environmental damage caused by the emissions of their vehicles.</p>
        <p>''Global warming is causing significant harm to California's environment, economy, agriculture and public health,'' said the state's attorney general, Bill Lockyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The suit is the first attempt to hold automakers accountable for the greenhouse gases that vehicles produce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>California, which has battled the automotive industry over new global warming regulations for years, sued the world's six-largest automakers yesterday, demanding that they pay for environmental damage caused by the emissions of their vehicles.</p>
        <p>''Global warming is causing significant harm to California's environment, economy, agriculture and public health,'' said the state's attorney general, Bill Lockyer.</p>
        <p>''Vehicle emissions are the single most rapidly growing source of the carbon emissions contributing to global warming, yet the federal government and automakers have refused to act.''</p>
        <p>The suit, filed in United States District Court in Northern California, is the first such attempt to hold automakers accountable for the greenhouse gases that vehicles produce. It accuses General Motors, Toyota, Ford, Honda, Chrysler and Nissan of creating a public nuisance by building millions of vehicles that collectively discharge 289 million metric tons of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere annually.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lockyer contends that the products of the six companies are responsible for a fifth of the carbon dioxide emissions nationwide and nearly a third of the emissions in California, which has more vehicles than any other state.</p>
        <p>He said he would seek at least ''tens of millions'' in damages for past, current and future contributions to air pollution, beach erosion and reduced water supplies.</p>
        <p>The automakers named in the suit declined to comment on it directly, but a trade group representing them labeled the accusations a ''nuisance suit'' similar to an unsuccessful attempt by several Northeastern states to hold utilities liable for environmental damages.</p>
        <p>''Automakers are already building cleaner, more fuel-efficient vehicles,'' the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers, based in Washington, said in a statement. ''Today's autos are 99 percent cleaner than a generation ago, and every model of auto is now available with some type of fuel-efficient technology.''</p>
        <p>Dave Barthmuss, a G.M. spokesman in Los Angeles, said the automaker was working toward the eventual goal of selling clean, hydrogen-powered vehicles and, as an interim step, had invested in technology like flex-fuel engines.</p>
        <p>''We are spending significant financial and human resources to commercialize alternatives,'' Mr. Barthmuss said.</p>
        <p>James D. Marston, director of the energy program at the nonprofit Environmental Defense, said G.M., Ford and Chrysler could improve their bottom lines by reducing emissions. He cited a study released this week by transportation researchers at the University of Michigan that suggested the three automakers would sell more cars, adding $2 billion in annual profits, by raising the fuel economy of their vehicles only a few miles per gallon.</p>
        <p>The industry is ''wasting a lot of money paying lawyers to fight, and we ought to be spending that money on engineering,'' Mr. Marston said. ''Automobile manufacturers need to get the message that they've got to do something different. ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lockyer, a Democrat, is campaigning this fall to become California's treasurer. Some industry observers believe the suit to be merely a ploy to attract votes, but Mr. Lockyer disputed that in an interview yesterday. ''What am I supposed to do, not do my job because there's an election?'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also said the suit was not an attempt to persuade automakers to back off their legal challenges to rules enacted by the state aimed at cutting greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>In 2004, the state enacted similar requirements for auto emissions, which the automakers sought to throw out in federal court. That law was aimed at reducing pollution created by cars and light trucks by 25 percent and from sport utility vehicles by 18 percent.</p>
        <p>Last month, the California Legislature passed a measure designed to regulate industries' production of greenhouse gases. Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger is expected to sign the bill into law this month.</p>
        <p>Marc H. Ross, a professor of physics at the University of Michigan who has studied automobile emissions, said automakers set themselves up to become a target of environmentalists as they worked to maximize sales of sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>''Regardless of the negative social aspects of those vehicles, they proceeded to develop that market as much as they could,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
