<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fractured Fairy Tale Set in Boogie Wonderland</title>
    <meta content="01hot" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1758471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DE113FF932A35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fractured Fairy Tale Set in Boogie Wonderland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has not been a vintage season for the jukebox musical.</p>
        <p>Which I realize is a bit like lamenting that this year's acid rain just hasn't been up to snuff. But still. Even this little-loved genre has been around long enough for standards to be set, for beloved highs -- the nitwit glory that is ''Mamma Mia!'' -- and notorious lows (take your pick).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has not been a vintage season for the jukebox musical.</p>
        <p>Which I realize is a bit like lamenting that this year's acid rain just hasn't been up to snuff. But still. Even this little-loved genre has been around long enough for standards to be set, for beloved highs -- the nitwit glory that is ''Mamma Mia!'' -- and notorious lows (take your pick).</p>
        <p>Future historians of musical theater may point to April 30, 2006, as a tell-tale turning point, a harbinger of fatal decline. Or so one can hope. That date -- also known as yesterday -- saw both the closing of the ill-received Johnny Cash show ''Ring of Fire'' at the Barrymore Theater and the opening of ''Hot Feet,'' a dire dance musical set to a soundtrack of songs by Earth, Wind and Fire, at the Hilton Theater.</p>
        <p>Coincidence or fate? Who is to say?</p>
        <p>Who is to care? Those shows will probably be memories -- as will the risible ''Lennon'' -- long before the season's one respectable entry in the genre, ''Jersey Boys,'' has closed.</p>
        <p>For the books, then, let it be noted that ''Hot Feet,'' conceived, directed and choreographed by Maurice Hines, is a dancing encyclopedia of clichés culled from tattered tales of dreamy-eyed youngsters seeking fame and fortune in showbiz. Awkwardly lurching between frenzied, uninspired dance sequences and listless stock scenes of turmoil backstage, it is about as gripping as a two-and-a-half-hour episode of ''Soul Train.''</p>
        <p>The gifted ingénue is the lovely, limber Kalimba, an aspiring dancer from the mean streets played by Vivian Nixon. (Trivia note: a kalimba is an African thumb piano, a signature instrument in Earth, Wind and Fire songs.) Kalimba comes outfitted with one of the usual accessories, a loving and protective mama (Ann Duquesnay) seeking to inoculate her daughter against the toxins of a life onstage.</p>
        <p>These are personified by the domineering Victor Serpentine (Keith David), a hip-hop Diaghilev, who exploits Kalimba's brilliance for his own dark ends, and the fire-breathing diva Naomi (Wynonna Smith, acting with her hair and hips), who puts crushed glass in Kalimba's dance shoes in the hopes of sabotaging her younger rival. A more beneficent if less lively presence in Kalimba's new world is the choreographer Anthony (Michael Balderrama), who loves her and tries to persuade her to flee the consuming fires of showbiz before she is destroyed.</p>
        <p>That all will not end happily for this eager youngster will be obvious to most, since these cardboard figures are crudely deployed by the book writer, Heru Ptah, to enact a contemporary retelling of the Hans Christian Andersen fairy tale ''The Red Shoes.'' Kalimba is groomed by Victor to star in the ambitious ballet that gives the musical both its title and its numbingly overwrought dance climax. Had she spent more time at the library, or watching old movies, Kalimba would know that red is an ill-omened color for Capezios. (Although it is not credited, the stylish Powell and Pressburger movie from 1948, with Moira Shearer as a ballet dancer torn between her man and her art, seems a more direct influence than the original fairy tale.)</p>
        <p>To supplement the score of old Earth, Wind and Fire hits, Maurice White, the group's founder, has collaborated on several new musical-theater-style songs of little distinction, which are sung onstage by the actors. (Only Ms. Duquesnay, with her husky belt, makes anything of this material.) The much more enjoyable songs from the back catalog are relegated to the role of anonymous backup tracks. They blare from nowhere -- the band could be playing at the Hilton at Kennedy Airport, for all we know -- whenever the stage fills with the beaming dancers of the Serpentine Fire Dance Company, as Victor's troupe is called.</p>
        <p>These dance segments consume a fair portion of the evening's running time. A busy but mostly undistinguished amalgam of ballet, modern dance and street styles, Mr. Hines's choreography draws on two decades of trends, from head-wagging moves that were last cool when Janet Jackson performed them in music videos in the 1980's, to krumping, the jiggly hip-hop offshoot from Southern California that was all the rage 15 minutes ago.</p>
        <p>The dancers, at least, deserve celebration. They exude excitement, focus, drive and occasionally real joy when they are cutting loose to radio hits like ''September'' and ''Boogie Wonderland.'' Their robust technique and physical prowess dazzles despite the garish assortment of costumes by Paul Tazewell, some of which might be disdained by Russian ice dancers as being a little tacky.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nixon, the daughter of the dancer and choreographer Debbie Allen and the basketball player Norm Nixon, is a beautifully proportioned, well-trained dancer with sharp, exciting technique. (The genes came through, spectacularly.) She deserves a far better showcase than Mr. Hines's elaborate but aimless, often punishing routines. The exuberance of her performance is at once exciting, touching and sad: rarely can so much energy have been expended on a Broadway stage to such dubious ends.</p>
        <p>Speaking of dubious ends, this dreary enterprise hits a smirk-inducing note of steamy camp when the climactic ''Hot Feet'' ballet finally arrives. With the dancers leaping, twirling and writhing around the stage in body-hugging, flesh-baring getups to little coherent purpose, this sequence may bring to mind memorably atrocious dance spectaculars from the movies, like the ''Satan's Alley'' number in the ''Saturday Night Fever'' sequel ''Staying Alive'' or the candy-colored volcanic extravaganza from ''Showgirls.'' It is that ludicrous.</p>
        <p>It is also interminable. As poor Ms. Nixon churns through Mr. Hines's endless steps, pantomiming Kalimba's possession by the demonic powers in those infernal shoes, you may find it hard to muster the requisite compassion for her doom, even though you know it's coming. You are more likely to be preoccupied by your own.</p>
        <p>Hot Feet</p>
        <p>Conceived, directed and choreographed by Maurice Hines; book by Heru Ptah; music and lyrics by Maurice White; new songs, additional music and lyrics by Cat Gray, Brett Laurence, Bill Meyers, Mr. Ptah and Allee Willis; sets by James Noone; costumes by Paul Tazewell; lighting by Clifton Taylor; sound by Acme Sound Partners; hair design, Qodi Armstrong; music director and conductor, Jeffrey Klitz; arrangements and orchestrations, Bill Meyers; music coordinator, John Miller; production manager, Arthur Siccardi; assistant director, Ricardo Khan; production stage manager, Michael E. Harrod; general management, Leonard Soloway and Steven M. Levy. Presented by Transamerica, Rudy Durand in association with Kalimba Entertainment Inc., Meir A &amp; Eli C, LLC, Polymer Global Holdings and Godley Morris Group, LLC. At the Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. Running time: 2 hours 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Allen Hidalgo (Louie), Samantha Pollino (Emma), Vivian Nixon (Kalimba), Ann Duquesnay (Mom), Michael Balderrama (Anthony), Keith David (Victor) and Wynonna Smith (Naomi).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
