<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Government Report Calls for Broad Effort on Climate Issues</title>
    <meta content="30stern" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/30/business/worldbusiness/30stern.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1800933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Observer (British Newspaper)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Greenpeace</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DF123FF933A05753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Government Report Calls for Broad Effort on Climate Issues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">British Government Report Calls for Broad Effort on Climate Issues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report commissioned by British government calls for substantial international cooperation to combat global warming and doubling public spending on research into low-carbon technologies; report is being heavily promoted as one of most authoritative reviews of climate costs; British newspaper Observer reports study cites figure of $6.98 trillion as cost to society of failing to start blunting global warming within decade (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A report commissioned by the British government and scheduled for release Monday calls for substantial international cooperation to combat global warming and doubling public spending on research into low-carbon technologies.</p>
        <p>The main findings of the 16-month study, led by Sir Nicholas Stern, the chief of Britain's economic service, were described over the weekend in several British news reports. The Reuters news agency quoted the report's 27-page summary as saying, ''The evidence gathered by the review leads to a simple conclusion: the benefits of strong, early action considerably outweigh the costs.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The report calls for substantial international cooperation to combat global warming and doubling public spending on research into low-carbon technologies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A report commissioned by the British government and scheduled for release Monday calls for substantial international cooperation to combat global warming and doubling public spending on research into low-carbon technologies.</p>
        <p>The main findings of the 16-month study, led by Sir Nicholas Stern, the chief of Britain's economic service, were described over the weekend in several British news reports. The Reuters news agency quoted the report's 27-page summary as saying, ''The evidence gathered by the review leads to a simple conclusion: the benefits of strong, early action considerably outweigh the costs.''</p>
        <p>The report, prepared for Tony Blair, the prime minister, and Gordon Brown, the finance minister, has been heavily promoted by Britain and environmental groups as one of the most authoritative reviews of climate costs, although some economists and energy experts at anti-regulatory research groups saw it as understating the cost of an accelerated transition away from the fossil fuels that provide nearly 90 percent of the world's energy today.</p>
        <p>The report, called the Stern Review on the Economics of Climate Change, will be published online at sternreview.org.uk.</p>
        <p>If emissions are not cut and temperatures rise as many scientists project, the Reuters agency quoted the report as saying that, among various impacts, melting glaciers would threaten one sixth of the world population by raising sea levels and drying up river sources.</p>
        <p>The Observer, a British newspaper, reported that the study cited a figure of £3.68 trillion (the equivalent of $6.98 trillion) as the cost to society of failing to start blunting global warming within a decade.</p>
        <p>''Our actions over the coming few decades could create risks of major disruption to economic and social activity, later in this century and in the next, on a scale similar to those associated with the great wars and the economic depression of the first half of the 20th century,'' the report said, according to Reuters.</p>
        <p>The study estimated that the cost of cutting emissions in 2050 to 60 percent to 80 percent below 1990 levels would be about 1 percent of total global economic activity by then, Reuters and The Observer said. If emissions cannot be cut to those levels, the cost from climatic impacts could be 5 to 20 times higher, The Observer cited the study as saying.</p>
        <p>The study, according to the news reports, said that progress would best be accomplished by doubling global investment in research on climate-friendly energy technologies and placing a rising cost on further emissions of the greenhouse gases, led by carbon dioxide, to propel the shift toward non-polluting options.</p>
        <p>The news reports on the study are consistent with presentations by Sir Nicholas, including a speech last January at Oxford University.</p>
        <p>Other recent estimates of the eventual annual costs of stabilizing concentrations of greenhouse gases over the 21st century have ranged from 1 percent of global gross domestic product to 16 percent by around 2100, not counting any savings from averted damage.</p>
        <p>By comparison, the world is currently spending just over $1 trillion a year, or about 2.5 percent of global gross global domestic product, on defense, according to a yearly survey by the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute. (Military spending in the United States is about 3.7 percent of gross domestic product.)</p>
        <p>''This confirms what we've seen for a long time,'' said Kert Davies, a climate-policy coordinator for Greenpeace. ''The longer we take to act, the greater the costs will be.''</p>
        <p>Jerry Taylor, an expert on energy and climate policy at the Cato Institute, a libertarian research group in Washington, said the wide range of cost estimates for cutting emissions ''basically tells you we're guessing.''</p>
        <p>Overall, he said, he put more faith in academic analyses than one produced at a government's request, particularly at a time when the public appears eager to see signs of action on the issue.</p>
        <p>The release of the 700-page report, which was 16 months in the making, will come one week before the start of the latest round of talks on the Kyoto Protocol, the first international pact requiring cuts in heat-trapping emissions.</p>
        <p>The United States has not ratified the Kyoto pact but is a party to the voluntary treaty that preceded it, which requires all signatories to seek to avoid a dangerous buildup of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto Protocol, an addendum to the original treaty, requires three dozen participating industrialized countries to cut their combined emissions 5 percent below 1990 levels between 2008 and 2012.</p>
        <p>At the moment, many of the three dozen industrialized countries bound by the pact are not on track to meet targets. And there are few indications of a shift toward accepting binding restrictions in the United States, the world's biggest emitter of greenhouse gases, or China and India, which are projected to be the dominant source of emissions in a couple of decades.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
