<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grand Broadway Voices, Yours For a Song</title>
    <meta content="16cast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/16/theater/16cast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1769406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Brian Stokes Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Michael John Lachiusa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, Brian Stokes</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McDonald, Audra</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Connick, Harry Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Luker, Rebecca</person>
        <person class="online_producer">LaChanze</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cerveris, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">LuPone, Patti</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Young, John Lloyd</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Jason Robert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">LaChiusa, Michael John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Ricky Ian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0D81031F935A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="2202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grand Broadway Voices, Yours For a Song</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Grand Broadway Voices, Yours for a Song</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden Critic's Notebook on current Broadway cast albums; says major record labels are leery of putting out such albums because of their financial gamble and slow payoff; notes that despite this fear, cast albums are still being produced and Broadway talents are branching out to make their own recordings of classic Broadway tunes; roundup of traditional cast albums and related solo projects; list of all albums mentioned in article; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEMON chiffon confections don't come any lighter than ''The Drowsy Chaperone,'' the hit musical whose affable narrator, the Man in Chair (Bob Martin), gleefully extols the quaint Broadway values embodied by this imaginary 1928 show. ''It does what a musical is supposed to do,'' he declares. ''It takes you to another world, and it gives you a little tune to carry in your head when you're feeling blue.''</p>
        <p>''As We Stumble Along,'' the show's signature ditty, is a peppy little march whose lyrics exalt a willful flight into fantasy from ''a dismal little world'' of ''seven overrated wonders, seven underwhelming seas and six excruciating continents.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is both the best and worst of times for theater music on and off Broadway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEMON chiffon confections don't come any lighter than ''The Drowsy Chaperone,'' the hit musical whose affable narrator, the Man in Chair (Bob Martin), gleefully extols the quaint Broadway values embodied by this imaginary 1928 show. ''It does what a musical is supposed to do,'' he declares. ''It takes you to another world, and it gives you a little tune to carry in your head when you're feeling blue.''</p>
        <p>''As We Stumble Along,'' the show's signature ditty, is a peppy little march whose lyrics exalt a willful flight into fantasy from ''a dismal little world'' of ''seven overrated wonders, seven underwhelming seas and six excruciating continents.''</p>
        <p>Global warming? Bring it on! That might be the attitude of this world-weary fantasist who prefers the twittering Jazz Age never-never land in his mind to the scary real world outside his New York apartment.</p>
        <p>The success of this charming trifle of a show -- which just won five Tony Awards, including best score -- illustrates the paradoxical state of theater music on and off Broadway, where it is both the best and worst of times.</p>
        <p>If you're an admirer of Broadway-ready singing actors, it is a time of feast; there's never been more potentially showstopping talent. Brian Stokes Mitchell, Audra McDonald, Harry Connick Jr., Hugh Jackman, Rebecca Luker, Lillias White, Bernadette Peters, Betty Buckley: the list of reliable marquee names and major emerging talents would make any casting director salivate.</p>
        <p>But what new shows are worthy of such talents? Not even the most die-hard Broadway nostalgist could describe Lisa Lambert and Greg Morrison's Charleston-flavored score for ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' as more than a serviceable pastiche of Jazz Age froth.</p>
        <p>The musical theater's flagging artistic health has, in turn, affected the future of the traditional Broadway cast album, making major record labels increasingly leery of the financial gamble and slow payoff such albums involve. It's a telling sign that the ''Drowsy Chaperone'' cast album was recorded on the boutique label Ghostlight.</p>
        <p>But if the commitment of major labels to recording cast albums is shakier than it used to be, the tradition persists. The albums for the three other shows nominated for best score -- ''The Color Purple'' (Angel), ''The Wedding Singer'' (Sony BMG) and ''The Woman in White'' (EMI) -- are on major labels, as are the albums for the season's competing revivals, ''Sweeney Todd'' (Nonesuch) and ''The Pajama Game'' (Columbia). And small record companies like Ghostlight, its sister label Sh-K-Boom, and PS Classics have rushed to fill any breach left by the majors.</p>
        <p>Some of those gifted performers, meanwhile, have been driven by the dearth of musical substance in Broadway shows to strut their talents at all-star benefits, in cabarets, in concert series like Town Hall's Broadway by the Year, Lincoln Center's American Songbook and the Encores! series at City Center, and especially in solo recordings.</p>
        <p>A great solo record can do wonders. For Mr. Mitchell, who hasn't starred in a Broadway show since ''Man of La Mancha'' in 2002-3, this has been a year of personal triumph with the nearly simultaneous release of his long-gestating first solo record (on Playbill, a new label distributed by Sony-BMG-Legacy) and of last year's thrilling concert version of ''South Pacific.''</p>
        <p>Here is a selective roundup of recent traditional cast albums and related solo projects, followed by a look at some of the more specialized fare available from the new, smaller record labels.</p>
        <p>The Color Purple -- The solid but under-appreciated pop-soul score, recorded with an augmented string section and featuring pungent performances by LaChanze and Elisabeth Withers-Mendes, would probably have won the Tony had audiences not fallen in love with ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' for extra-musical reasons. ''The Color Purple'' writing team of Brenda Russell, Allee Willis and Stephen Bray, three seasoned pop professionals, effectively glosses Southern blues and gospel styles from the first half of the 20th century and throws in two crowd-pleasing post-Motown ballads, ''What About Love?'' and the title song.</p>
        <p>The Wedding Singer -- ''Grease'' redux, but with the ''Happy Days'' innocence curdled into name-dropping 80's cynicism, dispensed in catchy, personality-free songs performed with aggressive perkiness. The musical quotations run from Spandau Ballet to Madonna. The list-heavy lyrics allude to everything from A Flock of Seagulls haircuts to Michael Milken; the jingly songwriting by Matthew Sklar and Chad Beguelin is as generically 80's as that of ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' is generically 20's. The song ''All About the Green'' (money, that is) sums up its values.</p>
        <p>Harry on Broadway Act 1 -- ''The Pajama Game'' is packaged with a second disc of songs Mr. Connick wrote for his 2002 show ''Thou Shalt Not'' (not to be confused with the 2002 cast album). On the ''Pajama Game'' disc Mr. Connick's cottony crooning voice, dripping with sex, reinvents the role of Sid Sorokin, originated in 1954 by the stentorian John Raitt. Mr. Connick's charismatic seducer may not mesh with his character, but the steam heat he generates with his co-star Kelli O'Hara outweighs any sacrifice of realism. ''Hernando's Hideaway'' becomes a pop-jazz star turn, and Mr. Connick treats the show's most substantial ballad, ''A New Town Is a Blue Town,'' as a Sinatra-style saloon song. The discipline of Broadway elicits his strongest, most articulate singing to date.</p>
        <p>Mr. Connick also arranged and orchestrated the material for ''Thou Shalt Not,'' which he performs with Ms. O'Hara. The disc suggests that Mr. Connick, a phenomenal talent of unlimited but still untapped artistic potential, has sabotaged his own development by spreading himself too thin. If the songs feel unfinished, the orchestrations sketchy, the talent behind them is evident.</p>
        <p>Sweeney Todd -- John Doyle's production of Stephen Sondheim's semioperatic masterpiece, reduced to an intimate chamber piece in which the actors play all the instruments, is a theatrical coup, a madhouse musicale that loses much of its shock value when heard away from the stage. Neither Michael Cerveris's Sweeney nor Patti LuPone's Mrs. Lovett comes close to matching Len Cariou's or Angela Lansbury's original performances in musical command, and the sweeping Puccinesque aspects of the score are diminished. That said, Mr. Cerveris and Ms. LuPone bring to their roles a demented malevolence that surpasses the originals in their concentrated fury and lewdness; they make a truly demonic team.</p>
        <p>Brian Stokes Mitchell -- Breaking the traditionally stoic mold of male romantic leads, Mr. Mitchell brings an unprecedented fusion of theatrical heroism, pop-jazz sizzle and emotional vulnerability to mostly famous songs (five by Mr. Sondheim) that ride on expansive musical landscapes, many concocted by Mr. Mitchell himself. Emotional risks abound: his ''Lazy Afternoon'' stretches out on the grass like a 5 o'clock shadow, and that diva war horse, ''Losing My Mind,'' is reimagined as the woozy soliloquy of a possible stalker reeling on the edge of madness. But generally the performances sustain a mood of vaulting exhilaration.</p>
        <p>The pinnacle is a rendition of ''How Glory Goes,'' Adam Guettel's epic contemplation of the afterlife (from ''Floyd Collins''), that carries the song from hereto eternity and back. This auspicious debut album is comparable in its sweep to Audra McDonald's 1998 debut, ''Way Back to Paradise.''</p>
        <p>South Pacific -- Another coup for Mr. Mitchell. In this concert revival of the 1949 Rodgers and Hammerstein show, recorded at Carnegie Hall last June, he lays claim to ''This Nearly Was Mine,'' bringing to it a heartbroken virility, a mood left out of his solo album. Reba McEntire is perfectly cast as Nellie Forbush, the spunky Arkansas nurse whom his character, the French planter Émile de Becque, loves and nearly loses.</p>
        <p>Two decades ago ''South Pacific,'' with its cautious liberalism and smug, stiff-backed morality, seemed quaint. Nowadays it speaks more directly to the culture wars than anyone might have imagined. The concert, which had its premiere two months ago on PBS's ''Great Performances,'' has also been released on DVD.</p>
        <p>JERSEY BOYS -- As with all culture, musical-theater innovation is driven by technology. Today's audience is habituated to electric guitars, synthesizers, heavy drums and bass, and surround-sound acoustics. Among the cognoscenti there lingers a sense of disappointment that the 70's singer-songwriters, who they imagined might restore a great tradition to its former glory, failed at the task.</p>
        <p>Instead of Paul Simon and Randy Newman, who tried and struck out, kitschmeisters like Elton John and Frank Wildhorn have stepped in. And the much-despised ''karaoke'' musical has put down commercial roots.</p>
        <p>In defense of the karaoke musical, it provides a comfortable listening experience that is hard to come by at a pop concert. And when carried off with genuine affection and knowledge, as in ''Jersey Boys,'' this year's Tony winner for best musical, it almost transcends the dreaded label. ''Jersey Boys'' (like ''Mamma Mia!'' before it) offers an optimal concert experience in which the sound system is as much a star as the performers and the material.</p>
        <p>It's unlikely that the audiences flocking to ''Jersey Boys'' ever heard a live performance by the Four Seasons that was as sonically immaculate as this meticulous theatrical simulation, led by John Lloyd Young's phenomenal vocal embodiment of Frankie Valli. It's no coincidence that the show's director, Des McAnuff, is the man who started it all with the Who's ''Tommy'' in 1993.</p>
        <p>Pushing up from below is an emerging, more specialized brand of music theater, taught in a thriving network of schools and workshops, that keeps one eye planted on tradition and whose greatest talent is Mr. Guettel, whose score for ''The Light in the Piazza'' won the Tony last season. This tradition is likely to get a major boost if the Metropolitan Opera makes good on its determination to bring modern hybrids of pop, classical art song and music theater into its hallowed space.</p>
        <p>At the same time the boutique labels like Ghostlight and Sh-K-Boom, both founded by Kurt Deutsch, and PS Classics, founded by Tommy Krasker and Philip Chaffin, are flourishing. Begun as experiments, they have grown into modestly profitable enterprises of incalculable historical usefulness.</p>
        <p>A major breakthrough for Mr. Deutsch, and for the greater business of musical theater, has been the success of the cast album of Jason Robert Brown's 2002 Off Broadway show, ''The Last Five Years,'' which was instrumental in triggering 250 regional productions. Together Mr. Deutsch's sister labels (Ghostlight is more theater oriented, and Sh-K-Boom is devoted to individuals) have put out about 30 albums. They include Broadway cast albums (''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels,'' ''Little Women,'' ''The 25th Annual Putnam County Spelling Bee'') and the Michael John LaChiusa shows ''See What I Wanna See'' (his smart contemporary take on ''Rashomon'') and ''Bernarda Alba.'' Without Ghostlight, a small gem like ''Songs From an Unmade Bed,'' a theatrical song cycle in which 18 different composers set lyrics of Mark Campbell into a thematic suite, beautifully performed by Michael Winther, might have disappeared.</p>
        <p>PS Classics, which has just released the London cast album of ''Sunday in the Park With George'' and is committed to recording the Broadway-bound musical ''Grey Gardens,'' is having comparable success. PS Classics has already given us two volumes of ''Sondheim Sings,'' an invaluable archival resource. It just released a recording of an all-star 2004 concert of ''Dream True,'' a delicate 1999 Off Broadway show with music by Ricky Ian Gordon and lyrics by Tina Landau; its signature song, ''We Will Always Walk Together'' (with lyrics by Mr. Gordon) is an imposing modern ballad, comparable in sweep to Mr. Guettel's ''How Glory Goes.''</p>
        <p>Only a fool would imagine that this alternative musical-theater movement could begin commercially to challenge the mass-musical culture symbolized (even on Broadway) by the values of ''American Idol.'' For better or worse we live in a steroidal body culture in which quality is measured by the standards of Olympic competition. That's technology for you. But only a fool would imagine that the movement would not continue to grow and establish its own much smaller, but equally solid, tradition.</p>
        <p>The Sounds Of the Stage</p>
        <p>Albums referred to in Stephen Holden's Critic's Notebook:</p>
        <p>BERNARDA ALBA -- Ghostlight. $18.98.</p>
        <p>BRIAN STOKES MITCHELL -- Playbill Records. $18.98.</p>
        <p>THE COLOR PURPLE (2005 original Broadway cast), Angel Records. $18.98.</p>
        <p>DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS (2005 original Broadway cast), Ghostlight. $18.98.</p>
        <p>DREAM TRUE -- PS Classics. $18.99.</p>
        <p>THE DROWSY CHAPERONE (2006 original Broadway cast), Ghostlight. $18.98.</p>
        <p>JERSEY BOYS (2005 original Broadway cast), Rhino/Wea. $18.98.</p>
        <p>LITTLE WOMEN THE MUSICAL (2005 original Broadway cast), Ghostlight. $18.98.</p>
        <p>HARRY ON BROADWAY ACT 1, with Kelli O'Hara, ''The Pajama Game'' and ''Thou Shalt Not,'' Sony; two CDs. $21.98.</p>
        <p>THE LAST FIVE YEARS (2002 Off Broadway cast), Sh-K Boom. $18.98.</p>
        <p>SEE WHAT I WANNA SEE (2005 Off Broadway cast), Ghostlight. $18.98.</p>
        <p>SONGS FROM AN UNMADE BED with Michael Winther and Mark Campbell, Ghostlight. $18.98.</p>
        <p>SOUTH PACIFIC -- In concert from Carnegie Hall, with Brian Stokes Mitchell, Reba McEntire and Alec Baldwin. Decca. $18.98.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY IN THE PARK WITH GEORGE (2006 London revival cast), PS Classics. $21.98.</p>
        <p>SWEENEY TODD (2005 Broadway revival cast), Nonesuch; two CDs. $21.98.</p>
        <p>THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE (2005 original Broadway cast), Ghostlight. $18.98.</p>
        <p>THE WEDDING SINGER (2006 original Broadway cast), Sony. $18.98.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
