<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why I Should Run the U.N.; Go Global</title>
    <meta content="28zeid" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1793247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDE1630F93BA1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why I Should Run the U.N.; Go Global</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ZEID RAAD ZEID AL-HUSSEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations selects its next secretary general this fall through a series of straw polls. The third of these -- the most decisive to date -- will be held today. In the vote, the 15 members of the Security Council ''encourage,'' ''discourage'' or venture ''no opinion'' on each of the candidates. To win, a candidate must have at least nine encouraging votes and no discouragement from any of the five permanent members of the Security Council. The winner is then presented to the General Assembly for ratification.</p>
        <p>The Op-Ed page asked all seven candidates to respond to two questions. First, we asked them to discuss an avoidable mistake the United Nations had made within the last five years. Second, we asked them what major reform they would undertake as secretary general. Five candidates gave us their answers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Nations selects its next secretary general this fall through a series of straw polls. The third of these -- the most decisive to date -- will be held today. In the vote, the 15 members of the Security Council ''encourage,'' ''discourage'' or venture ''no opinion'' on each of the candidates. To win, a candidate must have at least nine encouraging votes and no discouragement from any of the five permanent members of the Security Council. The winner is then presented to the General Assembly for ratification.</p>
        <p>The Op-Ed page asked all seven candidates to respond to two questions. First, we asked them to discuss an avoidable mistake the United Nations had made within the last five years. Second, we asked them what major reform they would undertake as secretary general. Five candidates gave us their answers.</p>
        <p>THE United Nations faces a daunting range of challenges in the 21st century: promoting development without fostering dependency; combating climate change without reducing growth; defending human rights without insisting on one true path. But in the past five years, a specter has risen, casting a shadow across the world: the specter of extremism, instability and injustice gripping the Middle East.</p>
        <p>The United Nations needs new leadership that understands these issues and can address all sides with experience and credibility. The fight against extremism is necessarily one with winners and losers -- one where compromise may equal defeat and where genocide, mass murder and terrorism loom. The leadership of the United Nations must take a stand. To me, there is no starker lesson from the United Nations' failures in Bosnia and Rwanda.</p>
        <p>The recent outbreak of war (and fragile peace) in Lebanon, and the conflicts in Africa, have reminded the world of the United Nations' unique legitimacy in restoring peace and security. Global legitimacy on its own, however, is not enough. The United Nations must also be effective. It should draw on the remarkable success of those societies -- not least in Asia -- that have seized on the promise of globalization to renew themselves. Like them, the United Nations must have the courage to discard the old and embrace the new in the name of progress.</p>
        <p>The struggle against extremism and intolerance requires the efforts of every society, faith and agent of human dignity. The United Nations must recognize this struggle for what it is and be willing to play its vital part. Only if the United Nations has the will to change itself can it change the world.</p>
        <p>ZEID RAAD ZEID AL-HUSSEIN, Jordan's ambassador to the United Nations, a former peacekeeper in the Balkans and the first president of the governing body of the International Criminal Court.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
