<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turbines With a View</title>
    <meta content="12bishop" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/12/opinion/nyregionopinions/12bishop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributors"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island Power Authority</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DB1231F931A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turbines With a View</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Turbines With a View</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Bishop and William Lauder</byline>
      <dateline>Babylon</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST Long Islanders would welcome the reduction of our dependence on foreign and polluting fossil fuels by harnessing wind power. But the current plan to install 40 turbines that rise more than 40 stories above the ocean off Jones Beach is based more on the whims of its corporate sponsor than on any regional energy plan or careful consideration of community concerns -- an approach that will result in fewer windmills and slower solutions to our energy predicament.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Power Authority and its partner, FPL Energy and Light, are clearly seeking to take advantage of federal laws written for the benefit of energy companies. Under these laws, the Army Corps of Engineers, not state and local reviewing bodies, has final authority on the placement of windmills more than three miles off the coast. Moreover, the review criteria of the Corps are limited to a project's technical feasibility and immediate environmental impact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>We're not ready for a wind farm off Jones Beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST Long Islanders would welcome the reduction of our dependence on foreign and polluting fossil fuels by harnessing wind power. But the current plan to install 40 turbines that rise more than 40 stories above the ocean off Jones Beach is based more on the whims of its corporate sponsor than on any regional energy plan or careful consideration of community concerns -- an approach that will result in fewer windmills and slower solutions to our energy predicament.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Power Authority and its partner, FPL Energy and Light, are clearly seeking to take advantage of federal laws written for the benefit of energy companies. Under these laws, the Army Corps of Engineers, not state and local reviewing bodies, has final authority on the placement of windmills more than three miles off the coast. Moreover, the review criteria of the Corps are limited to a project's technical feasibility and immediate environmental impact.</p>
        <p>Such a limited review will do little to instill confidence and ensure the long-term viability of such projects. Proposed wind farms need to fit in with an overall energy generation plan for Long Island, with their benefits clearly weighed against their costs. The siting of such windmills, of course, is a critical consideration. State and local governments must assert an oversight role lest ill-placed turbines stand as monuments to arrogance rather than vanguards of clean energy. Indeed, European governments that raced to embrace wind power now find themselves criticized by environmentalists and naturalists who view turbines as blights on pristine landscapes. ''It's not that I'm against wind power -- we do have to find alternative, renewable sources of energy,'' said a renowned mountaineer, Sir Chris Bonington, in considering the prospect of an industrial wind farm in England's Lake District. ''But I think each site should be assessed like a balance sheet, on one side the aesthetic and environmental impact that a particular wind farm will have, set against the benefit of the amount of clean power that's going to be generated.''</p>
        <p>The thought of windmills off Jones Beach is wondrous to some. To many, however, 40 turbines more than 40 stories high may look more like a floating Lefrak City. But in evaluating whether to permit an industrial wind farm just off the crown jewel of New York State parks and the beaches of Oyster Bay and Babylon, the Army Corps of Engineers will not be taking vista into account, nor will it do a cost-benefit analysis of the project's socioeconomic costs.</p>
        <p>For a more progressive, less intrusive approach, LIPA must be persuaded to defer to a research, development and demonstration project proposed by Long Island's Winergy Power. Winergy, a small Shirley-based firm, proposes to install three 3.6 megawatt wind turbines on 200 acres just off Plum Island. Originally designated for fish farming, the site has been subjected to an environmental impact review and has sustained winds of 15.7 to 17.9 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>Two of the turbines will be on steel cylinder monopole foundations that are industry standards. A third will be on a newly developed jackup barge with three telescoping legs. Unlike monopole installations, the barge-based turbine will be mobile and can be towed back to shore for repair or maintenance. This is a considerable concern, given mishaps like the failure of 80 offshore turbines at Denmark's Horns Rev farm in 2004 and the fact that LIPA will bear the cost of decommissioning failed turbines. Winergy hopes ultimately to place these mobile structures 20 miles offshore, in depths up to 150 feet.</p>
        <p>The Winergy approach at Plum Island offers three lessons for LIPA to consider. First, by starting with a modest demonstration project, Winergy is emulating the approach taken by the Blyth Offshore Wind Turbines project in Britain, where a smaller wind farm was used to evaluate performance and environmental impacts like bird deaths before the rollout of any larger-scale projects. Second, by providing a laboratory for regulators, it also gives the public a chance to become more comfortable and familiar with the idea of a wind farm. Third, it establishes a source of energy generation at the eastern end of Long Island, which will continue to experience the steepest increase in demand for electricity.</p>
        <p>Back in September, LIPA's chairman, Richard Kessel, discussing the possible future uses of Plum Island once the federal Animal Disease Research Center there closes, said, ''LIPA should take a look at that as a second offshore wind project.'' He was on the right track. There is substantial wind at Plum Island, which is also a site that will have a minimal impact on that precious aspect of our Long Island environment -- our view.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributors David Bishop is a councilman and William Lauder is a former supervisor of the Town of Babylon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Bishop is a councilman and William Lauder is a former supervisor of the Town of Babylon.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
