<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Astronomers Planning Close-Ups of Mars From (of All Things) a Balloon</title>
    <meta content="13mars" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/13/science/space/13mars.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1768739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Helium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Balloons</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">German Mars Society (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Technical University (Munich)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Institute for Spaceflight Technology</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Federal Armed Forces (Munich)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Svoboda, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griebel, Hannes</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hausler, Bernd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Balloons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Balloons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDC1331F930A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Astronomers Planning Close-Ups of Mars From (of All Things) a Balloon</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Astronomers Planning Close-Ups of Mars From (of All Things) a Balloon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH SVOBODA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Svoboda, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>German Mars Society (Munich, Germany) is financing mission to Mars that plans to use helium-filled balloon craft to survey surface and atomosphere; design of craft is brainchild of Hannes Griebel, who worked on concept as advanced engineering student at Munich's Technical University; Griebel then proposed idea to Bernd Hausler, Institute for Spaceflight Technology director at University of the Federal Armed Forces (Munich); design of craft and its deployment described; photos; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two Mars rovers, Spirit and Opportunity, have accomplished more than their creators thought possible. Stoic, plodding and reliable, they have muscled across the planet's rugged terrain for more than two years, collecting data about the composition of its rocks and soils in the process.</p>
        <p>Even the most dogged workhorses, however, have limitations. In their entire time on the planet, the slow-moving rovers have traversed less than 10 square miles, and their sensors cannot collect data more than a few feet above the ground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The proposed Archimedes balloon craft, which could reach the Red Planet in 2009, would snap crisp, full-color images of the surface.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The two Mars rovers, Spirit and Opportunity, have accomplished more than their creators thought possible. Stoic, plodding and reliable, they have muscled across the planet's rugged terrain for more than two years, collecting data about the composition of its rocks and soils in the process.</p>
        <p>Even the most dogged workhorses, however, have limitations. In their entire time on the planet, the slow-moving rovers have traversed less than 10 square miles, and their sensors cannot collect data more than a few feet above the ground.</p>
        <p>To survey areas of the planet that remain unknown, researchers affiliated with the privately financed German Mars Society in Munich are proposing a different kind of explorer: a vehicle inspired more by dirigibles like the Hindenburg than by land-rover predecessors. Projected to reach Mars in 2009, the balloon craft, named Archimedes, would hover much closer to the planet's surface than a satellite, snapping crisp, full-color images similar to those that an Earth photographer might take from a helicopter.</p>
        <p>In an hourlong descent to the ground, the balloon craft would use an array of sensors to take temperature, wind and humidity readings. These data, collected at a variety of altitudes, would provide the raw material scientists need to understand Martian weather patterns.</p>
        <p>''A rover can't tell you the atmospheric density several miles above Mars's surface, and it can't give you an image of the planet's surface taken from a mile up,'' said Bernd Hausler, a project scientist. ''A balloon craft can do both of those things.'' A suite of magnetic sensors could also record gravity fluctuations that provide clues about weight distribution inside the planet, lending insight into its geological makeup.</p>
        <p>The balloon craft was the brainchild of Hannes Griebel. In 2002, as an advanced engineering student at the Technical University of Munich, Mr. Griebel was looking for a Mars project that would not retread ground that rover missions planned to cover. ''There's so much about Mars we don't know,'' he said. ''I started to think, 'What are the data we haven't been able to get?' ''</p>
        <p>A helium-filled balloon craft, he reasoned, could obtain a more comprehensive profile of the planet's surface and atmosphere than any other vehicle. Best of all, the project would be cheap enough -- under $2 million -- that he could pursue it with money from private donors instead of depending on government financing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hausler, head of the Institute for Spaceflight Technology at the University of the Federal Armed Forces in Munich, was initially skeptical when Mr. Griebel approached him with the plan. ''Hannes was proposing this crazy idea that we try to put a balloon into Mars's atmosphere,'' he said. Still, seeing the project's potential, he decided to offer Dr. Griebel a faculty position instead of turning him away. ''I told him, 'Let's attack this.' ''</p>
        <p>With money from the German Mars Society, whose members -- mostly scientists -- had expressed interest in a balloon project for years, the two were off and running. However, they quickly found themselves up against a host of technical challenges. ''The balloon itself is no problem; we already have weather balloons that ferry you through the stratosphere, which has conditions very similar to Mars's atmosphere,'' Dr. Griebel said. ''Getting it into the atmosphere is the difficult part.''</p>
        <p>At first, Mr. Griebel envisioned a balloon that would inflate once its launch vehicle had entered the atmosphere. But in Mars's thin carbon dioxide surroundings, ''there isn't much to slow the craft down as it falls, so you need to inflate something big in a very short time,'' he said. Achieving this feat would require a complicated and expensive ground-based control system, so he scrapped the idea in favor of inflating the balloon in deep space and then propelling the buoyant orb into the Martian atmosphere. That option presented its own problems. As a spacecraft reaches the threshold between the vacuum of space and a planet's outer atmosphere, large amounts of friction turn the energy its orbital motion has generated into heat.</p>
        <p>At a little over 170 pounds, the craft would generate less than a quarter of the friction that a space shuttle might, but its filmy surface would still heat up to about 620 degrees Fahrenheit during atmospheric entry. The project team plans to coat the 33-foot-wide balloon with a heat-tolerant polymer.</p>
        <p>Making sure the inflation mechanism would work in a zero-gravity environment also proved daunting. If pockets of gas became trapped in the folded balloon's plastic crevices, they would expand rapidly in the vacuum of space, possibly jamming the delicate mechanical components that position the balloon for inflation.</p>
        <p>The team scheduled a test flight last spring on the Zero-G Airbus A300 of the French company Novespace. The plane flies in an up-and-down pattern that makes objects in the cabin weightless for seconds at a time. Project scientists deployed the balloon more than 80 times during these weightless moments, and it inflated as expected about 90 percent of the time.</p>
        <p>Last month, the researchers sent the craft into true zero gravity, strapping the balloon and a camera-containing module to a sounding rocket that went more than 60 miles above Earth's surface. Although a few grainy images that cameras transmitted to Earth showed that the balloon inflated properly upon reaching deep space, the remainder of the test was a comedy of errors. The rocket collided with the recently detached camera module, preventing it from acquiring planned high-resolution footage of the craft. Another trial is planned for October.</p>
        <p>What chance of success does the craft have, given the difficulties of deploying a balloon in space and the lack of financing from conventional space programs? The mission participants have no illusions, describing the project as a high-stakes gamble. ''The deployment system could fail, or the balloon could burst once it's inflated,'' Dr. Griebel said. ''There are all kinds of things that could go wrong.'' In addition, to cut costs the craft will travel to Mars on a satellite owned by the private Radio Amateur Satellite Corporation (Amsat), which will be launched from Germany in 2009 aboard an Ariane-5 rocket. If the rocket experiences technical problems, they will be beyond the control of the project team.</p>
        <p>The craft also faces competition from better-bankrolled Mars balloon projects, though these programs' projected launch dates are much further in the future. With financing from the Institute for Advanced Concepts at NASA, the Global Aerospace Corporation in Altadena, Calif., is developing a balloon craft for an image-gathering mission that would last up to a year.</p>
        <p>Unlike the German craft, which has no steering mechanism -- prevailing winds and its own orbital velocity will speed it along -- Global Aerospace's craft will feature a rudderlike sail to allow for limited maneuverability, said Alexey Pankine, a project scientist at Global Aerospace.</p>
        <p>Pioneer Astronautics in Lakewood, Colo., is working on a balloon-based Mars craft, though no new tests have been reported since a prototype was launched into the stratosphere six years ago.</p>
        <p>Robert Zubrin, an aerospace engineer and the author of ''The Case for Mars,'' thinks the German craft has the best immediate promise of the Mars balloon projects in the works. Dr. Zubrin sees the craft as a trailblazer for more elaborate, longer-lived future balloons, much as NASA's 1997 Sojourner rover paved the way for Spirit and Opportunity.</p>
        <p>''The scientists involved are taking this extremely seriously; they're putting the craft through the kind of rigorous testing that's needed,'' he said. If the German team succeeds, he added, it will mark a cultural as well as a scientific milestone, illustrating the extent to which private citizens can chart the course of space exploration.</p>
        <p>In addition to providing unique image and climate data, Dr. Pankine thinks the German craft could aid the cause of astrobiology. ''The magnetic field readings they're taking will tell us more about Mars's geological history, and the more we know about what originally shaped the surface, the more we can figure out whether conditions existed to create life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zubrin said the greatest potential of the German craft lay not in turning up unexpected findings, but in adding detail and breadth to public conceptions of Mars. ''Right now, the image of Mars most people have is either a small dot in the sky or an expanse of terrain a few miles wide,'' he said. ''With this mission, we'll get the big picture. We'll finally start to see Mars as an entire world in itself.''</p>
        <p>Mars Society Germany</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
