<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="30bizdigest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1750697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D91530F933A05750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Automakers Give Drivers the Power They Prefer, and Fuel Efficiency Lags  For two decades, automakers have been developing technology that could make vehicles go farther on a gallon of gasoline. But instead, they have chosen pep and size, responding to consumers' preferences by putting that technology into making heavier vehicles accelerate faster. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>The Transportation Department announced new fuel economy standards Wednesday for sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans that will make some of them go farther on a gallon of gasoline than the average car does, and will apply to many of the biggest S.U.V.'s for the first time. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Delphi and the United Automobile Workers agreed on one point: that the company is likely to ask a bankruptcy court judge to let it set aside its labor contracts and impose sharply lower wages and benefits. [C1.]</p>
        <p>New Tone but Same Environmental Position at Exxon  Since Rex W. Tillerson took over as Exxon's chairman three months ago he has gone out of his way to soften the company's public stance on climate change, a stark difference from the abrasive tone of the man he succeeded. But the substance of the company's position has not changed. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Justices Appear Wary of Reducing Patent Holders' Rights  Supreme Court justices showed little inclination to scale back the rights of patent holders, sharply questioning arguments made by a lawyer representing the online auctioneer eBay. Several of the justices, including Antonin Scalia, left, expressed skepticism during oral arguments about eBay's assertion that a federal appeals court had made it too easy for patent owners to obtain injunctions barring the use of their technologies. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Beatles' Record Company Fights Apple in British Court  The High Court of Britain was treated to a funky playback of the disco anthem ''Le Freak'' as a lawyer for the Beatles' record company argued that Apple Computer's iTunes digital music store violated a trademark agreement between the companies. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Guidant Scraps Some Stents After a Defect is Found  The Guidant Corporation said it would scrap $15 million of its Xience heart stents that had been manufactured for sale in Europe and for clinical testing in Japan after discovering that some of them had defects. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart Seeks P.R. Generals to Counter Critics  Wal-Mart Stores has begun circulating two senior-level job postings and if the language used to describe the positions is any indication, the giant discount retailer is on the public relations equivalent of war footing. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Microsoft and Europe Are Squaring Off Again  Microsoft and the European commission once again may be on a collision course over the shape of the company's next-generation computer operating system, Windows Vista. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Bill That May Help Grupo Televisa Before Mexican Senate  The Mexican Senate is scheduled to vote Thursday on legislation that critics say would strengthen the dominant position of Grupo Televisa in the country's television industry. The bill is expected to pass. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Whirlpool's Purchase of Maytag Clears Antitrust Review  The Justice Department's antitrust division said it had approved Whirlpool's purchase of its smaller rival Maytag, a $1.7 billion deal that will create one of largest home appliance companies in the world. Despite the dominant market share the companies would have, government lawyers concluded that the deal was not likely to substantially reduce competition among home appliance manufacturers. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Fashion Designers Lobbying for Copyright Protection  Fashion designers are lobbying in Washington for copyright protections like those governing books, music and other creative arts. [E1.]</p>
        <p>Delta Air Cuts Management Jobs by 20%  Delta Air Lines, which is trying to persuade its pilots to accept a $305 million-a-year pay cut, said it is cutting administrative and management employment at the carrier by 1,000 positions, or about 20 percent. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Rebound and Nasdaq Rises to a Five-Year High  Stocks staged a broad rebound yesterday, with gains in Google and Apple Computer leading a rally in tech shares that drove the Nasdaq to a five-year high. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 61.16 points, to 11,215.70. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gained 9.66 points, to 1,302.89. The Nasdaq composite index was up 33.32 points, at 2,337.78. [C11.]</p>
        <p>JetBlue in New Ad Campaign Featuring Consumer Input  JetBlue Airways is introducing an advertising campaign that carries the theme ''Sincerely, JetBlue'' and will include consumer-generated content. A focus will be JetBlue's efforts to encourage consumers to help create the advertising. The airline plans to set up booths where people can record their experiences on JetBlue. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Group Challenges Move That Eased Broadband Rules  A group representing telephone and Internet companies challenged action by federal regulators that freed Verizon Communications from rules on its broadband data services for businesses. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Automakers Give Drivers the Power They Prefer, and Fuel Efficiency Lags  For two decades, automakers have been developing technology that could make vehicles go farther on a gallon of gasoline. But instead, they have chosen pep and size, responding to consumers' preferences by putting that technology into making heavier vehicles accelerate faster. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>The Transportation Department announced new fuel economy standards Wednesday for sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans that will make some of them go farther on a gallon of gasoline than the average car does, and will apply to many of the biggest S.U.V.'s for the first time. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Delphi and the United Automobile Workers agreed on one point: that the company is likely to ask a bankruptcy court judge to let it set aside its labor contracts and impose sharply lower wages and benefits. [C1.]</p>
        <p>New Tone but Same Environmental Position at Exxon  Since Rex W. Tillerson took over as Exxon's chairman three months ago he has gone out of his way to soften the company's public stance on climate change, a stark difference from the abrasive tone of the man he succeeded. But the substance of the company's position has not changed. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Justices Appear Wary of Reducing Patent Holders' Rights  Supreme Court justices showed little inclination to scale back the rights of patent holders, sharply questioning arguments made by a lawyer representing the online auctioneer eBay. Several of the justices, including Antonin Scalia, left, expressed skepticism during oral arguments about eBay's assertion that a federal appeals court had made it too easy for patent owners to obtain injunctions barring the use of their technologies. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Beatles' Record Company Fights Apple in British Court  The High Court of Britain was treated to a funky playback of the disco anthem ''Le Freak'' as a lawyer for the Beatles' record company argued that Apple Computer's iTunes digital music store violated a trademark agreement between the companies. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Guidant Scraps Some Stents After a Defect is Found  The Guidant Corporation said it would scrap $15 million of its Xience heart stents that had been manufactured for sale in Europe and for clinical testing in Japan after discovering that some of them had defects. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart Seeks P.R. Generals to Counter Critics  Wal-Mart Stores has begun circulating two senior-level job postings and if the language used to describe the positions is any indication, the giant discount retailer is on the public relations equivalent of war footing. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Microsoft and Europe Are Squaring Off Again  Microsoft and the European commission once again may be on a collision course over the shape of the company's next-generation computer operating system, Windows Vista. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Bill That May Help Grupo Televisa Before Mexican Senate  The Mexican Senate is scheduled to vote Thursday on legislation that critics say would strengthen the dominant position of Grupo Televisa in the country's television industry. The bill is expected to pass. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Whirlpool's Purchase of Maytag Clears Antitrust Review  The Justice Department's antitrust division said it had approved Whirlpool's purchase of its smaller rival Maytag, a $1.7 billion deal that will create one of largest home appliance companies in the world. Despite the dominant market share the companies would have, government lawyers concluded that the deal was not likely to substantially reduce competition among home appliance manufacturers. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Fashion Designers Lobbying for Copyright Protection  Fashion designers are lobbying in Washington for copyright protections like those governing books, music and other creative arts. [E1.]</p>
        <p>Delta Air Cuts Management Jobs by 20%  Delta Air Lines, which is trying to persuade its pilots to accept a $305 million-a-year pay cut, said it is cutting administrative and management employment at the carrier by 1,000 positions, or about 20 percent. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Rebound and Nasdaq Rises to a Five-Year High  Stocks staged a broad rebound yesterday, with gains in Google and Apple Computer leading a rally in tech shares that drove the Nasdaq to a five-year high. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 61.16 points, to 11,215.70. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gained 9.66 points, to 1,302.89. The Nasdaq composite index was up 33.32 points, at 2,337.78. [C11.]</p>
        <p>JetBlue in New Ad Campaign Featuring Consumer Input  JetBlue Airways is introducing an advertising campaign that carries the theme ''Sincerely, JetBlue'' and will include consumer-generated content. A focus will be JetBlue's efforts to encourage consumers to help create the advertising. The airline plans to set up booths where people can record their experiences on JetBlue. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Group Challenges Move That Eased Broadband Rules  A group representing telephone and Internet companies challenged action by federal regulators that freed Verizon Communications from rules on its broadband data services for businesses. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
