<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Baykeeper Who Stirs The Waters</title>
    <meta content="12licolLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1804089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFDA1E3FF931A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Baykeeper Who Stirs The Waters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robin Finn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>QUOGUE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOT to nitpick, not when we've just been informed by a reliable source -- a global study led by a marine biologist with an unforgettable name, Dr. Boris Worm, and published in the journal Science -- that all the fish in the ocean could be belly up by 2048 if pollutants, predators and global warming continue to conspire against them. And to think Henny Penny was worried about the sky falling; imagine savoring a platter of tofu scampi or swimming in water dotted with aquatic corpses.</p>
        <p>But before translating the big-picture biodiversity scare into Long Island's culpability in the degradation of marine ecosystems, and without saying ''I told you so,'' Kevin McAllister, a rumpled guy with a set of pearly whites any shark would covet, wants it known that Peconic Baykeeper is the title he embodies as well as the name of the environmental group he runs. Even environmentalists have egos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOT to nitpick, not when we've just been informed by a reliable source -- a global study led by a marine biologist with an unforgettable name, Dr. Boris Worm, and published in the journal Science -- that all the fish in the ocean could be belly up by 2048 if pollutants, predators and global warming continue to conspire against them. And to think Henny Penny was worried about the sky falling; imagine savoring a platter of tofu scampi or swimming in water dotted with aquatic corpses.</p>
        <p>But before translating the big-picture biodiversity scare into Long Island's culpability in the degradation of marine ecosystems, and without saying ''I told you so,'' Kevin McAllister, a rumpled guy with a set of pearly whites any shark would covet, wants it known that Peconic Baykeeper is the title he embodies as well as the name of the environmental group he runs. Even environmentalists have egos.</p>
        <p>Referring to him as the nonprofit organization's president just doesn't cut it. Too corporate. Preferable to think of him as the committed skipper of a 36-year-old boat named Kathy; the author of a two-year study called Baywatch that assigns grades to indicators of bay health (bay scallops and hard clams rate F's, winter flounder a D); an irate litigant in a battle over Suffolk County's mosquito-control program; and the paid protector of every clam, scallop and striper that shows up on your plate. And his.</p>
        <p>O.K., then, baykeeper it is. And not just of the Peconic Bay. Since Mr. McAllister signed on in 1998 to this offshoot of the national Waterkeeper Alliance, which originated with the systematic rejuvenation of the drastically contaminated Hudson River, his purview has expanded to include the entire South Shore estuary. Granted, the estuary used to be a far larger -- and far healthier -- ecosystem than it is now. Which is why Mr. McAllister's job was invented. And, indirectly, why Dr. Worm published his study.</p>
        <p>''One study is macro and the other is provincial,'' says Mr. McAllister, waving a copy of each, ''but his study validates our findings and vice versa. We're seeing similar trends and they're not good. The data speaks for itself. But if I don't think there's reason for hope, I shouldn't be doing this. I'm not going to just sit here and be a cheerleader for bay health, not when I know what's killing the fish.''</p>
        <p>Hint: We are, he says, every time we flush a toilet, fertilize a lawn or direct the runoff from a storm drain toward the nearest ditch.</p>
        <p>Since 1930, some 29,000 acres of South Shore tidal wetlands have disappeared: paved over, dredged, bulkheaded, dammed up and, as is increasingly the case, sculptured into Mr. McAllister's personal nemesis, the fertilizer-fed trophy lawn. Because wetlands are to bays as kidneys are to the human body, he says, filtering nutrients and flushing out contaminants, this bodes ill.</p>
        <p>Ever walk along a tide line through a ''sea hash'' of dead clams? Ever scoop up sediment from a riverbed and find not one iota of life, not even a worm? Ever watch juvenile eels struggle to the surface to gasp for air because there is not enough oxygen in the water? And speaking of water, ever see water that is brown, red, black, gray, every tint except clear? Mr. McAllister has. And it offends more than his aesthetics.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister, 47, is ruthlessly noncorporate. That is why 25 percent of his personal office space in Peconic Baykeeper's barebones headquarters in Quogue is dedicated to his dog's bed -- Beans, a yellow Lab, is one big dog -- and much of the rest to an assemblage of tattered documents he intermittently thumbs through in search of statistics to bolster his meandering verbiage.</p>
        <p>It's also why he said he dropped out of the environmental consultancy business in Jupiter, Fla., after nearly coming to blows with his own client, a developer who jumped the gun and bulldozed a site before its previous occupants, protected gopher tortoises, had been relocated.</p>
        <p>Florida, he says, has transformed itself into ''an endless strip mall and a sea of pavement.'' He says Long Island, where he grew up in Center Moriches, a block from the water, and now lives (and surfs) in Quogue, must do better; he left a job as an environmental analyst for Palm Beach County, Fla., to see that it does.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister takes it as a backhanded compliment that he is routinely accused of caring more about crabs than his own species by certain builders (he is fighting major residential developments on the already-sickened Forge and Peconic Rivers) and county officials (he accuses their mosquito program of overkill and calls the consultants who endorse it ''biostitutes; sorry to be crass'').</p>
        <p>But this does not make him, horrors, the beach-and-bay version of a tree-hugger, his take on bleeding-heart conservationists. Mr. McAllister catches his fish and eats them, too. He just thinks the water that nourishes them, and us, ought to be clean.</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
