<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada's Next Leader Clashes With U.S. Over Arctic Waterways</title>
    <meta content="27canada" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/27/international/americas/27canada.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Harper, Stephen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wilkins, David H</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5DE113FF934A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada's Next Leader Clashes With U.S. Over Arctic Waterways</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Canada's Next Leader Clashes With U.S. Over Arctic Waterways</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Jan. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephen Harper, Canada's prime minister-designate, reproached the American ambassador on Thursday over an old difference of opinion about the control of Arctic waters claimed by Canada.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harper, the leader of the Conservative Party, which won a narrow victory in Monday's elections, is widely expected to usher in warmer relations with the Bush administration after years of squabbles between Canada and the United States over trade and the war in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephen Harper is expected to usher in warmer relations with the U.S., but the honeymoon took at least a temporary break.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stephen Harper, Canada's prime minister-designate, reproached the American ambassador on Thursday over an old difference of opinion about the control of Arctic waters claimed by Canada.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harper, the leader of the Conservative Party, which won a narrow victory in Monday's elections, is widely expected to usher in warmer relations with the Bush administration after years of squabbles between Canada and the United States over trade and the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>But the honeymoon took at least a temporary break when Mr. Harper reacted to a news report about comments made by the United States ambassador, David H. Wilkins, taking issue with Canada's assertion of sovereignty in northern Arctic water passages.</p>
        <p>''It is the Canadian people we get our mandate from, not the ambassador of the United States,'' Mr. Harper said. ''The United States defends its sovereignty, and the Canadian government will defend our sovereignty.''</p>
        <p>The United States for decades has opposed Canada's claims to Arctic passageways near the North Pole, as have the European Union and other countries. Canadian military scholars say that the United States, Russia, Britain and France sent submarines under the Arctic ice in waters claimed by Canada during the cold war without Canada's permission, and may still be doing so.</p>
        <p>Canada does not currently have the naval ability to stop such intrusions into those areas, which it claims as internal waters, although it is now modernizing satellite surveillance and upgrading its Arctic land and water patrols.</p>
        <p>''There's no reason to create a problem that doesn't exist,'' Mr. Wilkins was quoted as saying at a forum on American-Canadian relations on Wednesday at the University of Western Ontario, according to the CBC News Web site. ''We don't recognize Canada's claims to those waters.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilkins seemed to be trying not to kindle a dispute, though. ''We have agreed to disagree,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But on Thursday, in his first news conference since the election, Mr. Harper took issue with Mr. Wilkins, perhaps in part to show Canadians that he would not veer far from Canada's traditional foreign policy of pointed independence from the United States.</p>
        <p>American diplomats said that Mr. Wilkins had stated nothing more than an old policy in answering a student's question. They said he did not criticize a plan Mr. Harper announced during the campaign to build and deploy three new armed heavy icebreaking ships and construct a deep-water port in the Arctic territorial capital, Iqaluit.</p>
        <p>Differences between Canada and the United States over the Arctic have rarely surfaced in a public dispute, and leaders of both countries have preferred to cooperate on Arctic research and defense.</p>
        <p>But recently, the Arctic has become increasingly important because of climate change. With Arctic ice rapidly thinning, commercial navigation and tourism boats are making northern passages with increasing frequency. That has obliged Canada to begin planning security measures to protect waterways from smugglers and to prepare for the possibility of accidents and oil spills.</p>
        <p>The United States and Canada also have conflicting claims in the Beaufort Sea, in an area that is thought to have oil and natural gas reserves. Denmark and Canada have conflicting claims over another site, Hans Island, off Greenland's coast, in an area with a rich fishery.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
