<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Democrats' Jolt to the Political Landscape</title>
    <meta content="l09elect" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1803411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rome, Emily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernays, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swensen, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Acquadro, Stephanie Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lloyd, Reese</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bramhall, Geoffrey W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lenter, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neff, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minthorn, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feher, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4D91E3FF93AA35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Democrats' Jolt to the Political Landscape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eleven letters on election of House of Representatives controlled by Democrats; Emily Rome, Anne Bernays, Ken Swensen, Stephanie Nicholas Acquadro and Reese Lloyd voice satisfaction or jubilation at this rebuff to Pres Bush; Geoffrey W Bramhall tries to see good side from Republican perspective; Richard Lenter attributes outcome to Republican incompetence; Alan H Neff doubts if Democrats can undo damage done by Bush administration; Bruce Feher suggests what Republicans will have to do to regain power; Gail Minthorn says Democrats must act like employees of American people; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Democrats Take House'' (front page, Nov. 8):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Democrats Take House'' (front page, Nov. 8):</p>
        <p>So President Bush is not ''the decider.'' We, the American people, are -- as it was meant to be.</p>
        <p>Emily Rome  New York, Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I watched, disheartened, as our country grew sicker and sicker. On Tuesday, it proved that its legendary self-healing abilities were still in good working order.</p>
        <p>Anne Bernays  Cambridge, Mass., Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Now that our electorate has finally woken from its stupor, we should ask ourselves why it took six years to recognize the incompetence and demagogy of this administration and the responsibility of the Republican leadership that blindly followed its lead.</p>
        <p>The damage done is enormous, in Iraq, in the United States and around the world. Years have been squandered while the critical issues of our time have gone unattended.</p>
        <p>How and why were we fooled?</p>
        <p>We have a fascination with personalities instead of policy, a desire to be entertained rather than enlightened, and a need to have an enemy to define us and give our lives meaning.</p>
        <p>Thankfully, our democracy is still functioning, though we will not see really meaningful progress until we can disconnect the electoral and legislative processes from the flow of corporate cash.</p>
        <p>Let's not forget that the Senate voted to give President Bush authority to start a war in Iraq. Our euphoria should be short-lived, and our vigilance should be redoubled.</p>
        <p>Ken Swensen  Pound Ridge, N.Y., Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''A Loud Message for Bush'' (news analysis, front page, Nov. 8):</p>
        <p>It's almost too good to believe  the American people have done the ''almost'' impossible using the greatest democratic process known to man, the vote!</p>
        <p>A president so convinced of his power and his mandate has been handed a message: ''You wasted your power and your mandate to act without consensus. The people have shouted, Enough! No more abuses of the Constitution and our freedoms; no more disregard for the values our forefathers fought hard to establish; no more 'I am, therefore I can!' ''</p>
        <p>Thank you, my fellow Americans, for taking back our great country and for putting us back on the path to leadership and greatness in America and the world!</p>
        <p>Doris Fenig  Floral Park, Queens, Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''A Loud Message for Bush'':</p>
        <p>To President Bush et al.:</p>
        <p>Here's why we Democrats won: For six years, even though the Republicans barely won their elections (if they won at all: see the 2000 election), they have disregarded us, scorned us and demonized us.</p>
        <p>The debacle in Iraq is not the problem; it's a symptom of profound arrogance. Here's the ''loud message'': We don't like being ignored.</p>
        <p>Stephanie Nicholas Acquadro  Westfield, N.J., Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The shift in power in Washington is the result of a desire by midterm voters to cut the engines of President Bush's wayward ship of state.</p>
        <p>That most of us regard the present course as being disastrous is shown by the fact that we made this change with no clear, unified ideas as to how to plot a better path.</p>
        <p>We can only hope that the White House will get the message, accept this verdict and unbend somewhat from its rigid ideology.</p>
        <p>While there is certainly a need for an accounting by the Bush administration on many matters, the investigative powers that the Democrats have gained are not means for revenge.</p>
        <p>Any true wrongdoing must be brought to justice, of course, but our most immediate goal should be to stanch the bleeding in Iraq.</p>
        <p>As is so often the case, the way out of this mess seems to lie somewhere in the middle ground. We must all be prepared for sacrifice, to seek compromise where we can find it and tolerance where we can't.</p>
        <p>Like it or not, we are all Americans, all with a common fate. And we're in trouble.</p>
        <p>Reese Lloyd  Atlanta, Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a Republican, I suppose I could go on and on with excuses for Tuesday's debacle, but nothing would change what has happened, so let's look at the bright side. It should be clear to all that much of the recent spike in violence in Iraq was an effort to affect our election.</p>
        <p>With this out of the way now, perhaps there will be less of this bloodshed and the Iraqi government can get a handle on the pacification of the country and give us a legitimate reason to leave.</p>
        <p>Also, with the election out of the way, the Democrats will have less need to carp at the administration; at the very least, they should start coming up with some solutions of their own.</p>
        <p>I am hopeful that as much as the Democrats enjoy railing against the wealthy, productive element of our society, they will not kill the tax cuts that have led our economy out of recession and given us the best economic numbers seen in a long time.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey W. Bramhall  Bronxville, N.Y., Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>While voters may have identified Iraq, the economy or scandals as the issues that were important to them, I am convinced that it is the incompetence of this administration that was the foundation for the Democratic victory.</p>
        <p>Its incompetence in every sphere belied its claim that there were pros now running the country.</p>
        <p>The list of failures is long. Here is my abbreviated list:</p>
        <p>Failing to heed clear warnings and evidence before 9/11; failure to believe the intelligence on Iraq's ''weapons of mass destruction''; failure to address health care costs; Katrina, of course; failure to address energy concerns; failure to address global warming; and failure to accept scientific principles.</p>
        <p>This was the foundation for the Republicans' defeat.</p>
        <p>The debacle in Iraq was the catalyst. Defeat was the result.</p>
        <p>Richard Lenter  Bloomfield Hills, Mich.  Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a liberal independent who generally but not always votes Democratic, I'd like to be jubilant about the results from Tuesday's election. But I can't be.</p>
        <p>Over the last six years, this administration has done perhaps irreparable damage to our international relations, our constitutional guarantees, our economy, our credibility on human rights, our middle class and working poor, and the environment.</p>
        <p>Above all, I mourn the ordinary people, Iraqi and American, killed needlessly in the administration's wrong-footed adventure in Iraq.</p>
        <p>I'm sure that the Democrats are sharpening their knives for their new day of leadership. Doubtless, the public will learn many disturbing things about the way our country has been run by this government.</p>
        <p>But this president and his enablers will continue to insist that their theory of a unitary presidency should trump every attempt to bring them to heel. They will, for example, resist every investigation, arguing that the only check on the president's power is the voters' power to displace him.</p>
        <p>That opportunity was lost forever in 2004.</p>
        <p>The adults stand again in the doorway of the nursery, surveying the wreckage. Perhaps we can repair this mess, but I am not optimistic.</p>
        <p>Alan H. Neff  Chicago, Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Now that the election is over, the Republicans might appreciate some advice: If you intend to regain power, consider getting back to basics. Lower taxes, more freedom and less government are what Republicans care about. Immigration and the Iraq mess are important, too.</p>
        <p>Instead of paying attention, the leadership allowed members to engage in self-dealing beyond comprehension, allowed out-of-control spending and looked the other way as the system was abused.</p>
        <p>More advice: Consider fielding candidates who care more about the people than lining their pockets with ill-gotten gains. It's amazing what a few honest people can accomplish.</p>
        <p>And finally, visit your G.O.P. Web site and read the section on what a Republican is, follow the basics and maybe, just maybe, you'll be back in power one day.</p>
        <p>Bruce Feher  Las Vegas, Nov. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''For Democrats, Time to Savor Victory at Last'' (front page, Nov. 8): If all of the newly elected and re-elected officials remember that they are employees of the citizens of the United States and act accordingly, the American public will also be able to ''savor victory at last.''</p>
        <p>Gail Minthorn  Wilton, Conn., Nov. 8, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
