<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tory Introduces Himself to a Skeptical Lot: His Party</title>
    <meta content="04britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/04/world/europe/04britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1794639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="MEMO FROM BRITAIN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cameron, David (Mp)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Scotland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Wales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blue Collar Workers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blue Collar Workers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Scotland</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Wales</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Conservative Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Labor Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cameron, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thatcher, Margaret H</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6D71430F937A35753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tory Introduces Himself to a Skeptical Lot: His Party</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tory Introduces Himself to a Skeptical Lot: His Party</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>BOURNEMOUTH, England, Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Memo From Britain on new Conservative leader David Cameron's task of rewriting party narrative into script for electoral success, as Tony Blair did for Labor decade ago; Cameron, 39, leads aging party whose support in north of England, Scotland and Wales withered before 1997 election; effort to win young voters is not easy in party associated with country fetes and retirees; photo of party conference in Bournemouth (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the opposition Conservatives hold their first annual conference with David Cameron as their leader this week, Britons have taken to wondering whether he can rewrite his party's narrative into a new script for electoral success, just as Tony Blair did for Labor a decade ago.</p>
        <p>They have plenty to wonder about.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britons wonder whether new Tory leader David Cameron can rewrite his party’s narrative into a new script for electoral success.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the opposition Conservatives hold their first annual conference with David Cameron as their leader this week, Britons have taken to wondering whether he can rewrite his party's narrative into a new script for electoral success, just as Tony Blair did for Labor a decade ago.</p>
        <p>They have plenty to wonder about.</p>
        <p>In the sprawling conference center in this old resort in the southern part of the country, the traditional assumptions of British politics sometimes seem to have been upended. In the post-ideological age, Cameron Conservatives now reach for compassion, as President Bush once did, back in the pre-9/11 days. The onetime champions of the right campaign against public-health spending cuts by the left.</p>
        <p>Youthful, at 39, and slick in front of audiences and cameras, Mr. Cameron has checked all the boxes.</p>
        <p>He traveled to the north of Norway to be photographed with a team of huskies, showing his worries about global warming and the disappearing glaciers. He was photographed cycling to work (though an official car followed him) to display his concern about air pollution. Last weekend, he unveiled a video Web log that shows him at home, washing the dishes with children heard off-camera, a regular guy.</p>
        <p>His eldest child, Ivan, is severely disabled with cerebral palsy, and Mr. Cameron has discussed the condition openly. Where it is not unusual for politicians to keep their children out of the public eye, he has allowed himself to be photographed with all three of his children, reaching for a gentler image -- neither the tough love of Margaret Thatcher nor the dark brooding of Michael Howard, his immediate predecessor.</p>
        <p>''What he's got to do is keep the Conservative voters on board and get a lot back who have left us,'' said Jane Harrison, a Conservative city councilor from Stratford-on-Avon, who was attending the gathering here. ''He's trying to round everybody up. He's trying to be inclusive.''</p>
        <p>Whatever else, he has capitalized on the Labor Party's troubles with Iraq and the end of Tony Blair's tenure and turned around Conservative fortunes, placing the party ahead, if only slightly, in opinion surveys, in contrast to its lagging status in the years of Labor's ascendancy.</p>
        <p>But, as he confronts the task of consolidating those gains, he also inspires questions about his sincerity and lack of experience. ''He has still got a lot to learn,'' said Glenys Hurle-Hobbs, another Conservative delegate from Chichester, in southern England.</p>
        <p>Not only that, he leads an aging party whose support in the north of England, Scotland and Wales withered before the 1997 election. ''It's very important that we don't portray ourselves as a southern party,'' said George Osborne, the Conservative finance spokesman and a close aide to Mr. Cameron. ''If we don't win in the north of England, we won't win in the general election.''</p>
        <p>Some Conservative bloggers, like Tim Montgomerie, the editor of ConservativeHome.com, argue that Mr. Cameron's green and caring policies risk forfeiting what he calls the ''Morrison'' voters, named for a cost-cutting supermarket chain whose blue-collar customers are most vulnerable to crime and poor public services, who resent tax increases and who feel most unsettled by low-wage immigrants.</p>
        <p>Then there's the effort to win young voters, not easy in a party associated with country fetes and retirees. Last week, Mr. Cameron took to the airwaves on a music station, XFM, with a youthful, urban audience. He has suggested that perhaps an embrace would achieve more than a jail term for youthful delinquents known as ''hoodies,'' for the hooded tops they wear.</p>
        <p>(That inspired one of his more hard-line allies, David Davis, a former special forces reservist who is the Conservative home affairs spokesman, to say that, if it were up to him, he would hug the hoodies a little harder and a little longer.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Cameron's critics say he is all style, no substance, heading an institution with a middle-class core, blue-blazered and blue-rinsed, drawn from a largely white, middle-class comfort zone that aspires to low taxes and high walls of privilege. All that, they say, could make many Tories wonder about his promise of a new party built on issues like the environment, the family and social responsibility.</p>
        <p>He has tried to refashion the party's public face in obvious ways. The logo has been changed from a Tory torch to a scribbled green tree that may be an oak. There is, for some, an unnerving sense that traditional political distinctions have blurred. One motto, playing on the party's traditional color and its new ecological credentials, runs: vote blue, go green.</p>
        <p>At the conference here, the backdrop is all cloudless sky and verdant trees surrounding the slogan, ''A New Direction.'' The puzzle is that Mr. Cameron has yet to spell out precisely where that direction lies.</p>
        <p>One issue is taxes, a traditional Conservative theme. While old-guard Conservatives demand a public commitment to reduced taxes, Mr. Cameron has resisted the siren call to embrace a traditional Tory platform, saying that he will not jeopardize economic stability with tax cuts. Indeed, some political analysts argue that it suits his purpose to have an argument with the old guard to show off his newness.</p>
        <p>''He's got to change how the rest of the electorate perceives the Conservative Party,'' said David Harrison, a Conservative supporter. But Mr. Cameron has refused to be drawn out on specific policies so far ahead of the next expected election, in 2009.</p>
        <p>''I'm being very deliberate and purposeful about not producing policies immediately,'' Mr. Cameron told the BBC. He has promised more details about the new direction in a conference-closing speech on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Some things do not change. As William Hague, Mr. Cameron's foreign affairs spokesman and a former party leader, made clear on Tuesday, Conservatives remain Euroskeptics, opposed to deeper integration and the European single currency.</p>
        <p>Much of the campaign for change centers on Mr. Cameron's own personality and style. He traces his lineage to upper-crust politicians in the 19th and early 20th centuries. He was schooled at Eton and Oxford, where he was a member of the secretive and exclusive Bullingdon Club of diners and drinkers. His voice and accent, tribal markers in Britain's class system, define him as a member of the elite.</p>
        <p>During the fight for the Conservative leadership last year, Mr. Cameron, a former public relations executive, was forced to devote much time to reporters' questions about whether he had abused narcotics. (His response was simply to say that whatever happened before he entered politics was no longer relevant.)</p>
        <p>The larger question, perhaps, is whether he can define himself to a dubious populace.</p>
        <p>''The public no longer hate you,'' Peter Riddell, a columnist for The Times of London, said of Mr. Cameron to a gathering of Conservative loyalists on the fringes of the conference here. ''But they are not yet quite sure about you.''</p>
        <p>MEMO FROM BRITAIN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
