<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South From Alaska: Tricky Years of Maneuver Ahead for Proposed Gas Pipeline</title>
    <meta content="23pipeline" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/23/business/worldbusiness/23pipeline.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1741792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Slope (Alaska)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bp Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conocophillips</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Exxon Mobil</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alaska</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <org class="online_producer">BP Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3DB1E3EF930A15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South From Alaska: Tricky Years of Maneuver Ahead for Proposed Gas Pipeline</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tricky Years of Maneuver Ahead for Proposed Gas Pipeline</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, Feb. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of conditional agreement between Alaska and BP, ConocoPhilliops and Exxon Mobil to guild $20 billion gas pipeline from North Slope to lower 48 states by way of Canada; says significant political, environmental and regulatory hurdles must be overcome before project can begin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A conditional agreement between Alaska and three big energy companies may be, as Gov. Frank H. Murkowski put it, a milestone toward building a natural gas pipeline.</p>
        <p>But significant political, environmental and regulatory hurdles must be overcome before a single section of pipe meets a welding torch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Significant political, environmental and regulatory hurdles must be overcome before a pipeline from Alaska through Canada to the lower 48 states can be built.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A conditional agreement between Alaska and three big energy companies may be, as Gov. Frank H. Murkowski put it, a milestone toward building a natural gas pipeline.</p>
        <p>But significant political, environmental and regulatory hurdles must be overcome before a single section of pipe meets a welding torch.</p>
        <p>After prolonged negotiations, Governor Murkowski announced late Monday that Alaska had reached an agreement in principle with BP, ConocoPhillips and Exxon Mobil to build a $20 billion pipeline from the North Slope to the lower 48 states by way of Canada.</p>
        <p>As envisioned, the pipeline would move 4.5 billion to 6 billion cubic feet of gas daily and begin operating sometime from 2012 to 2014. Alaska has an estimated 35 trillion cubic feet of gas reserves.</p>
        <p>The announcement came with news of a significant change to the oil royalty system that provides most of Alaska's state budget revenue. Under the plan, the system will be shifted to one based on net profit rather than the volume of production.</p>
        <p>''These are two historic events,'' Governor Murkowski said, ''ones that will define the state's economy for decades to come.''</p>
        <p>Almost no one denies that changes to the royalty system, which now provides about 83 percent of the state's revenue, will have a potentially significant effect. But some gas analysts cautioned that the pipeline's future would be shaped by forces well beyond the governor's control.</p>
        <p>''This agreement is only one step on the part of one potential applicant to build a project,'' said Arlon Tussing, a research economist at the University of Alaska, Anchorage, who specializes in gas projects. ''The final decision about this is going to be made by the respective regulatory authorities in the United States and Canada, as well as their governments. And there's going to be tremendous opposition.''</p>
        <p>The plan will meet its most immediate tests in Alaska's Legislature, where Democrats have criticized the governor's decision to reduce proposed pipeline taxes to 20 percent of profit from an earlier plan of 25 percent. The broader overhaul of the oil tax system is also expected to face criticism.</p>
        <p>And there is substantial popular support for another proposal in Alaska that would build a smaller pipeline to Anchorage and the port of Valdez, and then ship the gas south by tanker.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the political maneuvering at the state level may prove easier to resolve than other issues.</p>
        <p>The idea of increasing American gas supplies using American sources has obvious political and national security appeal, particularly given that the fuel is increasingly used as a substitute for coal in electricity-generating stations.</p>
        <p>André Plourde, an energy economist at the University of Alberta in Edmonton, said that the world's largest known gas reserves were concentrated in countries not known for political stability, notably Iran and Russia.</p>
        <p>''Given the Bush administration's focus on what it considers to be energy security,'' Mr. Plourde said, ''Alaska is going to get a favorable hearing.''</p>
        <p>But if natural gas prices drop from their current levels, as many expect, economic concerns may outweigh the emphasis on security. If the forecasts of Professor Tussing and others bear out, gas piped from Alaska will have a difficult time competing with gas shipped by tanker from low-cost producers overseas.</p>
        <p>Professor Tussing estimates that North American gas reserves are now about 9.5 times annual production. Reserves elsewhere, by contrast, are 88 times production.</p>
        <p>''That means it is a lot easier to increase production almost anywhere other than North America,'' he said. ''We have pretty much wrung out the continent.''</p>
        <p>A preview of some regulatory issues facing an Alaska pipeline might be found in more advanced efforts to build a gas pipeline from the Canadian Arctic. That project, with investors that also include Exxon Mobil, has been repeatedly delayed, in part because of issues surrounding land claims by native groups along the route. The Alaskan project will encounter similar issues over permission to dip into the Yukon Territory and parts of Alberta.</p>
        <p>Climate change may also complicate environmental reviews. Antoni Lewkowicz, a professor of geography at the University of Ottawa, worked on permafrost issues surrounding an Alaska pipeline plan more than 20 years ago. A pattern of warming weather in the Arctic today, he warned, will make engineering the current proposal difficult and costly.</p>
        <p>''One of the things that killed the pipeline back in 1982 was the expense of the permafrost accommodations,'' Professor Lewkowicz said. ''Today, it's going to be very difficult to come up with a design that can deal with current conditions and the climate changes that will occur over the next 30 to 50 years. It's a significant and very costly engineering challenge.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
