<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="25biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1799624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD7173FF936A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VIETNAM'S ECONOMIC GROWTH -- In the three decades since Vietnam has gone from communism to a form of capitalism, it has become Asia's second-fastest-growing economy, trailing only China's. And now, in the latest sign of its economic vitality, trade negotiators are preparing to put the finishing touches on an agreement for Vietnam to join the World Trade Organization. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>MORE THAN HOME IMPROVEMENT -- Home Depot is displaying a growing willingness to stray from its single-minded focus on home improvement. The company's experiment with everyday products like gas, cigarettes and seasonal decorations exemplifies the belief of the chief executive, Robert L. Nardelli, above, that Home Depot can not only survive a downturn in the housing market unscathed, but exploit the situation by plowing money into the chain. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SCOUTING FOR ONLINE TALENT -- One of Hollywood's top five talent agencies, the United Talent Agency, has created an online unit solely devoted to scouting out up-and-coming creators of Internet content -- particularly video -- and finding work for them in Web-based advertising and entertainment as well as in the older media. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CONCERNS ON RADIO PLAY -- In the last two weeks, songs from two record labels -- both distributed through Vivendi's Universal Music Group -- got a lift on the charts after a radio chain was paid to play the tunes in an advertising program that New York state officials say is used to trick radio programmers. The ad purchases come five months after Universal settled accusations that it bribed radio programmers with gifts like laptop computers and luxury hotel stays in exchange for airplay. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A NOD TO PREVENTIVE CARE -- With the number of uninsured Americans reaching a record 46.6 million last year, a handful of hospital systems around the country have done the math and decided that for many patients with chronic diseases, it would be cheaper to provide free preventive care than to absorb the high cost of repeated emergencies. [A1.]</p>
        <p>WAL-MART'S UPSCALE WOES -- The chief executive of Wal-Mart Stores, H. Lee Scott Jr., said the introduction of upscale products, like silk camisoles and 300-thread-count sheets, has proven ''choppier than it should be'' and the company has ''moved too far too fast'' with fashionable clothing. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PUBLISHERS THINK GREEN -- Media companies have published numerous articles on greenhouse emissions in recent years. Now, large publishers like Time Inc. and Hearst are starting to think about their own production of emissions that contribute to global warming. Advertising. [C3.]</p>
        <p>FINANCE CHIEF INDICTED -- Robert C. Trosten, the former finance chief of Refco, once one of the world's largest commodities brokerage firms, was indicted, accused of helping to hide hundreds of millions of losses. [C3.]</p>
        <p>EUROPE PRESSURES CHINA -- The European Union told China that it could face barriers to its booming exports like clothes, shoes and electronic goods if it did not work toward creating a two-way street for global commerce. [C4.]</p>
        <p>BELLSOUTH'S PARTING GIFT -- BellSouth, which is preparing to be gobbled up by the telecommunications giant AT&amp;T, left investors a parting gift with news that its third-quarter profit jumped by almost a third, to $1.1 billion. [C6.]</p>
        <p>UNLIKELY USES FOR RICO -- Some corporations are using the RICO statutes, often associated with mob bosses and corrupt union chiefs, to attack other companies, including many that have headquarters overseas. On Monday, Vivendi, the French media and telecommunications company, became the latest company willing to take that leap when it sued Deutsche Telekom for $7.5 billion in United States District Court in Seattle. [C6.]</p>
        <p>BP'S PROFIT SHRINKS -- Third-quarter profit at the energy company BP declined 3.6 percent, slumping on lost Alaskan production, higher taxes in Britain and a sharp drop in gasoline prices. [C10.]</p>
        <p>DISPUTE OVER A COMMA -- A dispute between Rogers Communications of Toronto, Canada's largest cable television provider, and a telephone company in Atlantic Canada, Bell Aliant, turns on a single comma in the 14-page contract, and the resolution is worth 1 million Canadian dollars ($888,000). [C10.]</p>
        <p>AMAZON PULLS BACK ON SPENDING -- Going into the critical holiday shopping season, Amazon.com, the giant online retailer, said it would slow its investment in new technology in a bid to start reaping the rewards of its continuing growth. It reported that its third-quarter earnings fell by more than a third, even as its sales rose 24 percent. [C1.]</p>
        <p>MANY FIRSTS FOR NEW CHIEF -- Cynthia Carroll, a longtime executive at the aluminum producer Alcan, is to become the first woman, outsider and non-South African chief executive at Anglo American, the mining giant based in London. [C10.]</p>
        <p>NEW RULES AT N.Y.S.E. -- The New York Stock Exchange moved to bar Wall Street firms from casting votes on behalf of customers who do not provide voting instructions on corporate proxy matters. [C12.]</p>
        <p>SLOW DAY ON WALL STREET -- Wall Street wobbled through a listless session and closed mixed as investors awaited the results of this week's Federal Reserve meeting. [C12.]</p>
        <p>DEATH OF A RECORD STORE -- The liquidation of the retail chain Tower Records will have a severe impact on niche markets like classical music. According to one industry insider's estimate, Tower Records alone accounted for up to 50 percent of sales in the specialty genres. [E1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VIETNAM'S ECONOMIC GROWTH -- In the three decades since Vietnam has gone from communism to a form of capitalism, it has become Asia's second-fastest-growing economy, trailing only China's. And now, in the latest sign of its economic vitality, trade negotiators are preparing to put the finishing touches on an agreement for Vietnam to join the World Trade Organization. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>MORE THAN HOME IMPROVEMENT -- Home Depot is displaying a growing willingness to stray from its single-minded focus on home improvement. The company's experiment with everyday products like gas, cigarettes and seasonal decorations exemplifies the belief of the chief executive, Robert L. Nardelli, above, that Home Depot can not only survive a downturn in the housing market unscathed, but exploit the situation by plowing money into the chain. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SCOUTING FOR ONLINE TALENT -- One of Hollywood's top five talent agencies, the United Talent Agency, has created an online unit solely devoted to scouting out up-and-coming creators of Internet content -- particularly video -- and finding work for them in Web-based advertising and entertainment as well as in the older media. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CONCERNS ON RADIO PLAY -- In the last two weeks, songs from two record labels -- both distributed through Vivendi's Universal Music Group -- got a lift on the charts after a radio chain was paid to play the tunes in an advertising program that New York state officials say is used to trick radio programmers. The ad purchases come five months after Universal settled accusations that it bribed radio programmers with gifts like laptop computers and luxury hotel stays in exchange for airplay. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A NOD TO PREVENTIVE CARE -- With the number of uninsured Americans reaching a record 46.6 million last year, a handful of hospital systems around the country have done the math and decided that for many patients with chronic diseases, it would be cheaper to provide free preventive care than to absorb the high cost of repeated emergencies. [A1.]</p>
        <p>WAL-MART'S UPSCALE WOES -- The chief executive of Wal-Mart Stores, H. Lee Scott Jr., said the introduction of upscale products, like silk camisoles and 300-thread-count sheets, has proven ''choppier than it should be'' and the company has ''moved too far too fast'' with fashionable clothing. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PUBLISHERS THINK GREEN -- Media companies have published numerous articles on greenhouse emissions in recent years. Now, large publishers like Time Inc. and Hearst are starting to think about their own production of emissions that contribute to global warming. Advertising. [C3.]</p>
        <p>FINANCE CHIEF INDICTED -- Robert C. Trosten, the former finance chief of Refco, once one of the world's largest commodities brokerage firms, was indicted, accused of helping to hide hundreds of millions of losses. [C3.]</p>
        <p>EUROPE PRESSURES CHINA -- The European Union told China that it could face barriers to its booming exports like clothes, shoes and electronic goods if it did not work toward creating a two-way street for global commerce. [C4.]</p>
        <p>BELLSOUTH'S PARTING GIFT -- BellSouth, which is preparing to be gobbled up by the telecommunications giant AT&amp;T, left investors a parting gift with news that its third-quarter profit jumped by almost a third, to $1.1 billion. [C6.]</p>
        <p>UNLIKELY USES FOR RICO -- Some corporations are using the RICO statutes, often associated with mob bosses and corrupt union chiefs, to attack other companies, including many that have headquarters overseas. On Monday, Vivendi, the French media and telecommunications company, became the latest company willing to take that leap when it sued Deutsche Telekom for $7.5 billion in United States District Court in Seattle. [C6.]</p>
        <p>BP'S PROFIT SHRINKS -- Third-quarter profit at the energy company BP declined 3.6 percent, slumping on lost Alaskan production, higher taxes in Britain and a sharp drop in gasoline prices. [C10.]</p>
        <p>DISPUTE OVER A COMMA -- A dispute between Rogers Communications of Toronto, Canada's largest cable television provider, and a telephone company in Atlantic Canada, Bell Aliant, turns on a single comma in the 14-page contract, and the resolution is worth 1 million Canadian dollars ($888,000). [C10.]</p>
        <p>AMAZON PULLS BACK ON SPENDING -- Going into the critical holiday shopping season, Amazon.com, the giant online retailer, said it would slow its investment in new technology in a bid to start reaping the rewards of its continuing growth. It reported that its third-quarter earnings fell by more than a third, even as its sales rose 24 percent. [C1.]</p>
        <p>MANY FIRSTS FOR NEW CHIEF -- Cynthia Carroll, a longtime executive at the aluminum producer Alcan, is to become the first woman, outsider and non-South African chief executive at Anglo American, the mining giant based in London. [C10.]</p>
        <p>NEW RULES AT N.Y.S.E. -- The New York Stock Exchange moved to bar Wall Street firms from casting votes on behalf of customers who do not provide voting instructions on corporate proxy matters. [C12.]</p>
        <p>SLOW DAY ON WALL STREET -- Wall Street wobbled through a listless session and closed mixed as investors awaited the results of this week's Federal Reserve meeting. [C12.]</p>
        <p>DEATH OF A RECORD STORE -- The liquidation of the retail chain Tower Records will have a severe impact on niche markets like classical music. According to one industry insider's estimate, Tower Records alone accounted for up to 50 percent of sales in the specialty genres. [E1.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
