<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Never Mind the MTV Awards. Just Bring On the Show.</title>
    <meta content="01video" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/01/nyregion/01video.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1786857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">MTV Video Music Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Radio City Music Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Shakira</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Timberlake, Justin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clarkson, Kelly</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0D71E3EF932A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Never Mind the MTV Awards. Just Bring On the Show.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Never Mind the MTV Awards. Just Bring on the Show.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four guys on eight treadmills -- the Chicago power-pop band OK Go -- drew cheers to rival Beyoncé and Shakira when they performed the dance routine made famous by their video clip for ''Here It Goes Again'' at this year's MTV Video Music Awards, which were telecast last night from Radio City Music Hall.</p>
        <p>OK Go's low-budget, one-take, funny, nerdy video is a favorite on the Web site YouTube. It's the opposite of what MTV touts most of the time: conspicuous consumption directly equated with sexiness. ''Here It Goes Again'' didn't get OK Go the Best Dance Video nomination or any others, but MTV is still canny enough to latch onto its rivals. A little anti-glamour makes the bling shine brighter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When MTV gets around to playing video clips nowadays, as opposed to reality shows or visits to celebrities, it’s a strange coalition of niches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four guys on eight treadmills -- the Chicago power-pop band OK Go -- drew cheers to rival Beyoncé and Shakira when they performed the dance routine made famous by their video clip for ''Here It Goes Again'' at this year's MTV Video Music Awards, which were telecast last night from Radio City Music Hall.</p>
        <p>OK Go's low-budget, one-take, funny, nerdy video is a favorite on the Web site YouTube. It's the opposite of what MTV touts most of the time: conspicuous consumption directly equated with sexiness. ''Here It Goes Again'' didn't get OK Go the Best Dance Video nomination or any others, but MTV is still canny enough to latch onto its rivals. A little anti-glamour makes the bling shine brighter.</p>
        <p>When MTV gets around to playing video clips nowadays, as opposed to reality shows or visits to celebrities, it's a strange coalition of niches. There are tough-talking rappers laden with gold and diamonds. There are former punk-rockers in eyeliner, whining about ex-girlfriends. There are sinuous, glamorous dance-pop divas flirting and shimmying in skimpy designer dresses. (The Best Dance Video went to the Pussycat Dolls, doing stripper moves in the clip for ''Buttons.'') And there are male pop crooners flirting and shimmying in designer suits, or with their shirts off. Justin Timberlake kept his suit on in the show's first number, as he urged, ''Get your sexy on.''</p>
        <p>Just about everyone in video clips seems to be a gold digger. When Kanye West paid tribute to the hip-hop video director Hype Williams, part of his praise was, ''Hype Williams taught me what shoes to buy, what cars to drive.'' In the pre-show telecast from the red carpet, MTV's hosts asked about the prices of shoes and earrings. The winning hip-hop song, ''My Humps'' by Black Eyed Peas, celebrated both female curves and the expensive presents they attract.</p>
        <p>But MTV played it both ways this year. Online, MTV's Web site broadcast live from 28 cameras backstage, promising unvarnished reality but mostly showing how TV-trained pop stars keep their cool anywhere a camera is running. Still, there were some nuggets of gossip, like Axl Rose promising that the long-delayed Guns N' Roses album, ''Chinese Democracy,'' would appear this year.</p>
        <p>The Raconteurs, led by Jack White of the White Stripes and Brendan Benson, filled interstices with the guitar crunch of their classic-rock revivalism.</p>
        <p>And the videos that actually won awards -- which are almost incidental to the Video Music Awards show -- went to some earnest songs, like Kelly Clarkson's traumatic memory of battling parents, ''Because of You,'' Pink's mockery of Hollywood superficiality, ''Stupid Girls,'' and James Blunt's aching (but bare-chested) ballad, ''You're Beautiful.''</p>
        <p>But glitz prevailed. The stage was filled with fancy production numbers. Christina Aguilera started out singing to a lone piano on a bare stage, but went on to belt in front of a string orchestra and a dozen video screens. Shakira remade her collaboration with Wyclef Jean, ''Hips Don't Lie,'' like a sequence from a Bollywood musical; Beyoncé led a phalanx of trench-coated dancers doing robot moves to ratchety noises, looking back to late-1980's Janet Jackson.</p>
        <p>The emo band Panic! at the Disco -- winners of the Video of the Year award for their ''I Write Sins Not Tragedies'' -- was dressed in 19th-century costumes alongside a bevy of can-can dancers. Even rappers who simply strutted and rhymed onstage, like Pharrell and Ludacris, had their T-shirts nearly covered in jewelry.</p>
        <p>MTV is made for spectacle, and rightly revels in it. In the channel's self-contained universe, some well-placed effects can fix everything from a weak voice to bad skin -- a big part of what makes music videos so much fun to watch.</p>
        <p>That's why it's amusing for the station to be touting a self-proclaimed reality, especially one that's so distant from most of its viewers' lives. But the channel is determined not to be entirely escapist; the awards show this year included an appearance by none other than Al Gore, warning of global warming. He also pointed out that MTV, which seeks to be eternally young, is actually 25 years old this year. But it won't outgrow sexiness, superficiality and glitz anytime soon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
