<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Utah, the Half-Life Of Arena Naming Rights</title>
    <meta content="29stadium" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1808151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Utah Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DB113EF93AA15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Utah, the Half-Life Of Arena Naming Rights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arenas and stadiums derive their names from many industries.</p>
        <p>Banks, airlines, insurers and car manufacturers. Telephone and computer companies. An overnight deliverer. And beer, soft drink and ketchup makers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Arenas and stadiums derive their names from many industries.</p>
        <p>Banks, airlines, insurers and car manufacturers. Telephone and computer companies. An overnight deliverer. And beer, soft drink and ketchup makers.</p>
        <p>And now, Energy Solutions, a benignly named company that disposes of nuclear waste, has replaced Delta Air Lines as the home of the Utah Jazz.</p>
        <p>Nuclear waste. Yes, it is low-level stuff -- not spent fuel or old bombs -- that is now associated with the team with the best record in the N.B.A., rather than, perhaps, last season's Knicks.</p>
        <p>Radioactivity is quite new to naming rights, unless you count the brief time before Minute Maid replaced Enron as the name of the Houston Astros' ballpark. But this is a niche that has reflected corporate America's changing fortunes -- whether by bankruptcy, merger or dot-com boom and bust -- and its need to market itself.</p>
        <p>There have been three names on the San Francisco Giants' home (PacBell, SBC and AT&amp;T) and a hat trick of titles on the arena used by the Philadelphia 76ers and the Flyers (First Union, CoreStates and Wachovia).</p>
        <p>Energy Solutions has a hazardous- waste facility in the Utah desert. That is a mite different from all those local Citibank branches that are 24-hour reminders of the new Mets' ballpark, to be called Citi Field because of the $20 million a year Citicorp will pay the Mets.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, Citi Field, which is scheduled to open in 2009, will spawn a nickname, as has been the case with Gillette Stadium (the Razor), Minute Maid Park (the Juice Box) and US Cellular Field (the Cell). When the Arizona Diamondbacks' stadium was called Bank One Ballpark, it was the Bob.</p>
        <p>But naming a stadium for a hazardous-waste disposer is a rare chance for smart alecks to make their bids for the most creative and silliest mockeries of Energy Solutions Arena. Since the announcement of the Delta-to-Energy Solutions name switcheroo last week, KSL-TV, in Salt Lake City, has invited people to send e-mail messages with their proposed monikers, which include:</p>
        <p>The Glow Bowl and the Isotope. The Dump and ChernoBowl. JazzMat (short for Jazzardous Materials), the Big Bang and the Tox Box. The Power House and the Hot Spot. The Fallout Shelter. And the Melta Center.</p>
        <p>A letter writer to The Salt Lake Tribune suggested the jaunty Radium Stadium.</p>
        <p>''It'll take on a life of its own,'' Dennis Haslam, the president of the Jazz, said. ''People will find a nickname, a shorthand name. But when we have 19,911 fans at a sellout, they aren't that concerned about the name of the building. They're here to be entertained.''</p>
        <p>Greg Hopkins, a senior vice president, said Energy Solutions analyzed the benefits of educating the public about the nuclear industry and assessed how much derision the arena deal might generate. He said the company also anticipated the dredging up of past stories about regulatory problems involving Envirocare, one of four companies that merged this year to create Energy Solutions.</p>
        <p>''We expected this,'' he said. ''It's an industry that people don't understand well, and it's radioactive, and you're going to get jokes about it. Some of the nicknames are funny. We expected all of this.''</p>
        <p>''But it's created a good opportunity to tell our story,'' he added -- how a safely run and efficient nuclear power industry can be a solution to global warming. But he said that he did not yet know whether the company would install educational kiosks inside the arena to promote the nuclear industry.</p>
        <p>Delta, which is in bankruptcy, did not renew its arena deal, which expired Sept. 30. The Jazz wanted a major Utah company, of which there are not many, and Haslam said that Energy Solutions would pay at least as much as Delta did, a figure that has been reported at $1.3 million annually. ''I think it will end up being a positive for both us,'' he said. ''I don't think people will call us the Dump.''</p>
        <p>Still, Steve Greenberg, the architect of the Mets-Citicorp deal, said that in general, the chance that a corporation's business will be derided is a major obstacle when a decision is being made on whether to proceed in the naming process.</p>
        <p>''You have to ask how your fans are going to react,'' as well as whether a business will engender negative associations, said Greenberg, a managing director at Allen &amp; Company, an investment firm.</p>
        <p>As he and Fred Wilpon, the Mets' principal owner, looked at candidates for the new ballpark's naming rights, Greenberg said they looked for long-term compatibility between the team's and company's business interests.</p>
        <p>As for the impact of binding a team and arena to a company whose line of business can be mocked, Greenberg added, ''It probably only gets worse.''</p>
        <p>SPORTS BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
