<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shoppers Seem Hesitant, but Ford Bets It All</title>
    <meta content="02five" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/02/business/02five.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1808712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="FIVE DAYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Durable Goods (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Commerce Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Paulson, Henry M Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4D71E3EF931A35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shoppers Seem Hesitant, but Ford Bets It All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shoppers Seem Hesitant, but Ford Bets It All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK A. STEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stein, Mark A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHRISTMAS shoppers crowded malls on the day after Thanksgiving, but they were not spending as freely as expected, and that made many economists and investors worry that holiday sales may disappoint and that consumers may not be able or willing to re-energize the slowing economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Holiday shoppers were not spending as freely as expected, causing worry for many economists and investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHRISTMAS shoppers crowded malls on the day after Thanksgiving, but they were not spending as freely as expected, and that made many economists and investors worry that holiday sales may disappoint and that consumers may not be able or willing to re-energize the slowing economy.</p>
        <p>Ford did not wait for the whole economy to rebound. It took several drastic steps to shore up its finances and scale back its production capacity to cope with an automobile market that is becoming smaller and more fragmented.</p>
        <p>MIXED MESSAGES -- The economy grew faster in the last quarter than initial estimates suggested, but other new data raised concern that growth may slow faster than forecast in the months ahead.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department said that gross domestic product expanded at a 2.2 percent annual rate in the third quarter, up from its initial estimate of 1.6 percent. Even the higher estimate, however, is down from the 5.6 percent rate in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Slower spending by businesses in October added to the gloom. Orders for durable goods -- things like jet engines and computers -- declined by 8.3 percent, the Commerce Department said. The drop was the largest in more than six years and led economists to conclude that businesses were responding to slower economic growth.</p>
        <p>Even as growth slowed, inflation remained above the Federal Reserve's target range, and the Ben S. Bernanke, the Fed chairman, said the central bank might raise interest rates again.</p>
        <p>READY, SET, SHOP -- Retail sales rose 2.2 percent in November, the slowest pace in seven months, according to the International Council of Shopping Centers, a trade group. That fed fears that the crucial holiday shopping season may disappoint.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart, by far the nation's biggest retailer, estimated that its sales actually fell in November -- and that includes the day after Thanksgiving, the traditional start of the holiday shopping season. That is the first time in 10 years that Wal-Mart's sales declined.</p>
        <p>Unexpectedly, sales at department stores rose 4.6 percent last month, suggesting shoppers are turning to chains like Macy's, Saks and Nordstrom at the expense of discounters like Wal-Mart and specialty stores like Gap, Ann Taylor and Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, the shopping centers group said.</p>
        <p>Federated, owner of Macy's and Bloomingdale's, raised its estimates for sales in December.</p>
        <p>GREENER PASTURES -- Stymied at home, Wal-Mart announced a joint venture to open stores in India, the first large-scale entry into that booming market by a major foreign retailer.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart will allow Bharti Enterprises, an Indian cellphone company, to open hundreds of franchised superstores throughout India in the next five years. A local partner is required by Indian law, but foreign companies like Wal-Mart can open their own wholesale outlets.</p>
        <p>India's retail industry is expected to more than double, to $600 billion, by 2015. Sales at big-box stores like Wal-Mart are expected to grow three times that fast.</p>
        <p>ROLLING BACK RULES -- An independent committee endorsed by Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr. called for a sweeping overhaul of securities market regulations, including some adopted in response to the wave of corporate scandals that began with the collapse of Enron.</p>
        <p>The committee, saying it is concerned about a loss of competitiveness, said it should be harder for the government to indict companies and easier for corporate directors and auditors to avoid shareholders' lawsuits. It also suggested limiting the Securities and Exchange Commission's ability to write rules that would be too costly for businesses to follow.</p>
        <p>The committee's report was released two days after the New York Stock Exchange and NASD said they planned to accede to Wall Street requests to merge their regulatory organizations.</p>
        <p>Sanjay Kumar, the former chief executive of Computer Associates, is to report to federal prison on Feb. 27 to begin his 12-year sentence for orchestrating a huge accounting fraud at the company, now known as CA.</p>
        <p>FORD GOES ALL IN -- For the first time in its 103-year history, the Ford Motor Company is mortgaging its assets, including factories, equipment, office buildings, patents and trademarks, and stakes in subsidiaries like Volvo, to raise $18 billion to overhaul itself.</p>
        <p>As a measure of the risk Ford is taking, the amount it is borrowing exceeds the total market value of its outstanding stock. Ford chose to offer collateral for the loans because its credit rating, well below investment grade, makes unsecured loans too expensive.</p>
        <p>The company, which lost about $7 billion in the first nine months of this year, says it does not expect to earn a profit in North America until 2009 at the soonest.</p>
        <p>AUTO WORKERS LEAVE -- More than 30,000 hourly workers at Ford -- nearly half of its unionized work force -- have agreed to quit in exchange for a buyout or a package of early retirement benefits, giving the company a lift in its revamping effort.</p>
        <p>Including 8,000 who accepted packages offered at specific plants earlier in the year, about 38,000 of Ford's 75,000 members of the United Automobile Workers union have agreed to take buyouts.</p>
        <p>Ford said ''just over half'' of the workers accepted buyouts that absolve the company from having to pay them retirement benefits. Others opted for cash payouts of up to $35,000 and the right to retiree health insurance and other pension benefits.</p>
        <p>Ford also intends to eliminate about 14,000 salaried positions through buyouts. Those workers still have time to decide whether to accept a package and leave.</p>
        <p>POWER UP -- Demonstrating that the current wave of mergers is a worldwide phenomenon, the Spanish utility Iberdrola agreed to pay $22.5 billion for Scottish Power, creating one of Europe's biggest power companies.</p>
        <p>In addition to British operations, Scottish Power generates power and sells natural gas in the United States and Canada.</p>
        <p>Iberdrola said the acquisition of Scottish Power would make it a leading producer of renewable energy, generating more than 6,000 megawatts from wind farms and hydroelectric dams.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the relatively low price Iberdrola offered might attract a competing bid for Scottish Power or encourage consolidation among other European utilities.</p>
        <p>MOST POPULAR -- Following are the most popular business news articles on nytimes.com from Nov. 25 through Dec. 1:</p>
        <p>1. Lure of Great Wealth Affects Career Choices</p>
        <p>2. For $150, Third-World Laptop Stirs Big Debate</p>
        <p>3. Free Services to Inspire Your Cellphone</p>
        <p>4. Wal-Mart Trips as It Changes a Bit Too Fast</p>
        <p>5. Free or Farmed, When Is a Fish Really Organic?</p>
        <p>Links are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>FIVE DAYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
