<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Next Steps on Energy</title>
    <meta content="06mon1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/06/opinion/06mon1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1737656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DC173EF935A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Next Steps on Energy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Next Steps on Energy</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The early reaction to President Bush's promise to wean the United States from foreign oil was, in some cases, oddly off-key. The Saudi ambassador, for instance, seemed to wonder whether Mr. Bush had some sort of personal grudge against Mideast oil. Senator John Cornyn, Republican of Texas, found it odd that someone would subsidize fuels other than oil. Yet there are some people in Congress who are prepared to take the president at his word, while giving his undernourished proposals the budgetary and regulatory heft they sorely need.</p>
        <p>The real question is not whether Mr. Bush's proposals are going to make life difficult for some people but whether they are tough and adventurous enough. The answer is plainly no. All the president has done is to give prominence to ideas about alternative fuels and new technologies that were mere afterthoughts in the 2001 Cheney energy report. This is progress of a sort; at least we are no longer talking about drilling our way out of dependency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The biggest shortcoming of President Bush's plan to wean the U.S. from foreign oil is the absence of a program that will deliver new technologies to the marketplace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The early reaction to President Bush's promise to wean the United States from foreign oil was, in some cases, oddly off-key. The Saudi ambassador, for instance, seemed to wonder whether Mr. Bush had some sort of personal grudge against Mideast oil. Senator John Cornyn, Republican of Texas, found it odd that someone would subsidize fuels other than oil. Yet there are some people in Congress who are prepared to take the president at his word, while giving his undernourished proposals the budgetary and regulatory heft they sorely need.</p>
        <p>The real question is not whether Mr. Bush's proposals are going to make life difficult for some people but whether they are tough and adventurous enough. The answer is plainly no. All the president has done is to give prominence to ideas about alternative fuels and new technologies that were mere afterthoughts in the 2001 Cheney energy report. This is progress of a sort; at least we are no longer talking about drilling our way out of dependency.</p>
        <p>Yet his actual budget proposals were pitiful. The $150 million the White House said it would commit to making biofuels more competitive, for instance, turns out to be $50 million less than the amount authorized by last year's energy bill. And while the president talks about a new generation of vehicles, he offers virtually nothing meaningful to help Detroit get there.</p>
        <p>These little gaps have been widely noted. But the biggest shortcoming is the total absence of a program that would deliver any of these dandy new technologies to the marketplace. By program we mean a uniform set of incentives -- what the economists call market signals -- that would drive American industry to build the more fuel-efficient vehicles and the cleaner power plants that we need.</p>
        <p>For vehicles, there are two ways to get there. One, favored by most research groups specializing in energy, is to greatly strengthen the fuel-economy standards for cars and trucks. The other, favored by many economists, is to enact a substantial gas tax. We like both. One way or another, through regulatory or market mechanisms, the country would soon be driving cars that were far more fuel-efficient.</p>
        <p>And how big a difference would this make? Mr. Bush described his dream of replacing 75 percent of Mideast oil as if it were some monster challenge, like the Marshall Plan or a mission to Mars. It's not. An increase in fuel-efficiency standards to 40 miles per gallon in 10 years -- a reasonable expectation, with no new technology -- would save about 2.5 millions barrels a day, which is just about what we import from the Middle East now.</p>
        <p>The same sort of broadly administered medicine is needed to clean up our power plants to combat global warming. Just saying ''technology will do it'' will not, in fact, do anything. The big utilities are simply not going to make the necessary investments unless a nationwide program of emissions targets compels them to do so.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush hates stuff like this, which means that it is now up to Congress to put something together. Right now there are several serious-minded proposals on Capitol Hill that would require, in one way or another, substantial reductions in oil consumption and generous production incentives for more-efficient cars and alternative fuels. This is the right direction, whether the administration wants to go there or not.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
