<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Is Business as Usual Despite Party Grumbles</title>
    <meta content="12bush" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/12/politics/12bush.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Political Memo"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dubai</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dubai Ports World</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/United Arab Emirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/United Arab Emirates/Dubai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EED61331F931A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Is Business as Usual Despite Party Grumbles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Is Business as Usual Despite Party Grumbles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER and DAVID E. SANGER; Carl Hulse, David D. Kirkpatrick and Adam Nagourney contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth; Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republicans say there is no escaping truth that Bush administration has moved from crisis to crisis in second term and that Bush has yet to develop coherent agenda, while his administration seems to be losing its once-vaunted discipline and control; failure of Dubai Ports World deal exposed limits of Republican loyalty to Bush; aides say Bush is in good spirits and calls for change in his administration make him even more stubborn to resist it; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Inside the White House, the staff is exhausted and the mood is defiant. Republicans are clamoring for a new chief of staff, the West Wing just cut its losses on a deal that would have given a Dubai company control of some terminal operations at six American ports, and President Bush's approval rating is at a record low.</p>
        <p>But senior staff members insist that Mr. Bush is in good spirits, that calls from his party to inject new blood into the White House make him ever more stubborn to keep the old, and that he has become so inured to outside criticism that he increasingly tunes it out. There is no sense of crisis, they say, even over rebellious Republicans in Congress, because the White House has been in almost constant crisis since Sept. 11, 2001, and Mr. Bush has never had much regard for Congress anyway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senior staff members insist that President Bush is in good spirits despite calls from his party to inject new blood to the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Inside the White House, the staff is exhausted and the mood is defiant. Republicans are clamoring for a new chief of staff, the West Wing just cut its losses on a deal that would have given a Dubai company control of some terminal operations at six American ports, and President Bush's approval rating is at a record low.</p>
        <p>But senior staff members insist that Mr. Bush is in good spirits, that calls from his party to inject new blood into the White House make him ever more stubborn to keep the old, and that he has become so inured to outside criticism that he increasingly tunes it out. There is no sense of crisis, they say, even over rebellious Republicans in Congress, because the White House has been in almost constant crisis since Sept. 11, 2001, and Mr. Bush has never had much regard for Congress anyway.</p>
        <p>''You know, people say to me, my buddies in Texas, 'How do you handle all this stuff?' '' Mr. Bush said at a gathering of newspaper editors Friday in Washington. ''You know, it's just after a while you get used to it.''</p>
        <p>Staff members, many of whom have been with Mr. Bush since he first began running for president in 1999, responded on Friday in a familiar way: To mark the three-year anniversary of the start of the Iraq war, they announced that Mr. Bush would give a new round of speeches, starting Monday at George Washington University.</p>
        <p>As ever, there will be no change in policy. Mr. Bush will talk, they said, about new progress in defeating ''improvised explosive devices'' and argue that the televised pictures of rising casualties and sectarian fighting obscure progress under way.</p>
        <p>But to answer criticism from both parties that Iraq cannot be fixed with another good-news speech, Mr. Bush will also try to confront the realities of the war. ''Amid the daily news of car bombs and kidnappings and brutal killings, I can understand why many of our fellow citizens are now wondering if the entire mission is worth it,'' Mr. Bush said Saturday in his weekly radio address, foreshadowing one of the themes of his Monday speech.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush struggles yet again to change public opinion on Iraq, Republicans say there is no escaping the truth that the White House has careered from crisis to crisis in the second term and that the president has yet to develop a coherent agenda.</p>
        <p>Every development, they say, including Vice President Dick Cheney's accidental shooting of a fellow hunter and the arrest on Thursday of Mr. Bush's former domestic policy adviser, Claude A. Allen, on theft charges, points to a White House that seems to be losing its once-vaunted discipline and control.</p>
        <p>The ports deal was a case in point, they said. Even White House officials acknowledged that by the time a delegation of Congressional Republicans told Mr. Bush in the Oval Office on Thursday morning that it was a lost cause, Mr. Bush put up no fight.</p>
        <p>By midafternoon, after the Dubai company had dropped out of the deal, the president just seemed relieved that the storm was over. In a gathering at the White House, Mr. Bush faked a playful punch at Representative Peter T. King, the New York Republican who led opposition to the deal, then pinched Mr. King's cheek.</p>
        <p>But if the president was determined to project cheer about cutting his losses, the uproar over the ports has set off bleak assessments from both parties in Washington that the White House has lost its focus, energy and political touch.</p>
        <p>''With the benefit of 20/20 hindsight they should have known it would create a storm,'' said Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, speaking of the ports deal, which he had supported.</p>
        <p>It was only the latest crisis to hit Mr. Bush in a second term that has been dominated by problems in Iraq, Hurricane Katrina, a C.I.A. leak investigation, a secret eavesdropping program and the failure of the president to push forward the centerpiece of his domestic agenda, an overhaul of Social Security.</p>
        <p>But the Dubai deal exposed as never before the limits of Republican loyalty to a weakened Mr. Bush, whose record low approval ratings, 34 percent in a CBS poll conducted in February, have pushed members of his own party to declare that the White House can no longer call all the shots. By the end of the week, the ports deal had brought to a boiling point years of anger on Capitol Hill about a White House seen as imperious and dismissive of real consultation with Congress.</p>
        <p>''They have a transmitter but not a listening device,'' said one well-known Republican with close ties to the administration who gets calls from White House staff members. ''They'll say, 'What are you hearing, what's going on?' You tell them things aren't good on the Hill, you've got problems here, you've got problems there, or 'I was in Detroit and boy did I get an earful.' And their answer is, 'Everybody's just reading the headlines, we've got to get our message out better.' There's denial going on, and it starts at the top.''</p>
        <p>The bottom line, Republicans say, is that the war continues to overshadow the domestic agenda that Mr. Bush put forth in January in a State of the Union address that was supposed to reinvigorate his presidency.</p>
        <p>''Roughly one out of three people say that the country is on the wrong track, and the reason they give is the Iraq war,'' said Bill McInturff, a leading Republican pollster. ''How will that situation be changed unless Iraq is resolved in the next few months? So the White House can do all the good things they're doing with renewable energy and health care and all their other initiatives, but that doesn't move that chunk of people with very hardened attitudes.''</p>
        <p>At the White House, senior aides say they are well aware of such polls and of widespread Republican complaints about the isolation of an administration now in its sixth difficult year. ''There's an acute situational awareness of the criticism being leveled at the staff,'' said Nicolle Wallace, the White House communications director.</p>
        <p>At this point, Republicans close to the White House say, Andrew H. Card Jr., the White House chief of staff, has no plans to step down and in fact is only seven months away from beating Sherman Adams's record under President Dwight D. Eisenhower as the longest-serving chief of staff in history.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the legal status of Karl Rove, the deputy chief of staff and Mr. Bush's senior political adviser, is in limbo. He is still under investigation in the C.I.A. leak case, although his lawyer expresses confidence that Mr. Rove will be cleared.</p>
        <p>But the uncertainty surrounding such a crucial member of Mr. Bush's inner circle has fed perceptions that a once politically agile White House is off its game. Republicans say that the port security case in particular has become a case study in how this White House has been slow to react to the unexpected, and how its early warning radar is off.</p>
        <p>''It's always the same story,'' said an administration official who no longer works in the White House but who would evaluate its problems only on the condition of anonymity. ''They have a plan -- an elaborate plan of the president's message, day by day. But there's something in the system that has a hard time coping with the unexpected,'' the official said, citing Hurricane Katrina, the dispute over Harriet E. Miers's nomination to the Supreme Court, and now the port issue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's first public comments on the matter -- a defiant veto threat issued to reporters in an unusual briefing on Air Force One, then repeated on the South Lawn of the White House -- antagonized Congress. The White House did not warn House or Senate Republican leaders that the veto threat was coming, aides in both chambers said, and the president's words immediately thrust the dispute into the context of a political battle, with the Republicans on the losing side.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Bush should have done, Mr. McCain said, was ''get Colin Powell and General Abizaid and Tommy Franks to come out and make public statements about why this is vital.''</p>
        <p>Although the president had committed himself to supporting the deal, the White House evidently did little to save it. Senator John W. Warner, the Virginia Republican who led the effort to keep the acquisition intact, said he had almost no contact with the White House about the matter until Thursday morning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Warner said he had sought to enlist the administration in creating an alternative structure for the deal that might mollify Congress. ''I was trying to determine if the company came forward with a proposal, would the White House be able to take a look at it and review it?'' Mr. Warner said.</p>
        <p>Asked if he was surprised that the White House had not worked with the company to defend or restructure the deal, Mr. Warner said, ''I don't get surprised by anything anymore.''</p>
        <p>Political Memo</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
