<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In War on Bird Flu, U.N. Looks to Recruit Killer Army</title>
    <meta content="29chickens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/29/international/29chickens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Veterinary Medicine</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Agricultural Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcneil, Donald G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Avian Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Avian Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterinary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFDE1E3FF93AA15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In War on Bird Flu, U.N. Looks to Recruit Killer Army</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In War on Bird Flu, U.N. Looks to Recruit Killer Army</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONALD G. McNEIL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcneil, Donald G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations is hindered by lack of international culling task force in fight against spread of avian influenza; many governments know little about killing millions of animals, especially when aim is spilling as little blood as possible and disposing of bodies safely; Food and Agricultural Organization would like to send 20 veterinarians to train brigades of cullers; poor countries cannot always afford humane methods and farmers must be persuaded to cooperate and be compensated for their losses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations is looking for some professional assassins. There is a world of chickens out there that need killing, and it must be done neatly -- and humanely.</p>
        <p>With migratory birds spreading avian flu, the disease is popping up from Asia to Turkey and from Siberia to the Equator, often in spots that are isolated, rural and unprepared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With migratory birds spreading avian flu, the United Nations is looking for people who can kill chickens neatly and humanely, and dispose of the bodies safely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Nations is looking for some professional assassins. There is a world of chickens out there that need killing, and it must be done neatly -- and humanely.</p>
        <p>With migratory birds spreading avian flu, the disease is popping up from Asia to Turkey and from Siberia to the Equator, often in spots that are isolated, rural and unprepared.</p>
        <p>Many governments, veterinary specialists say, know little about killing millions of animals -- especially when the aim is to spill as little blood as possible and to dispose of the bodies so they cannot spread the highly contagious virus to birds or humans.</p>
        <p>Problems are cropping up everywhere. In Vietnam, for example, home flocks range free across muddy rice paddies, where chasing them is next to impossible. High water tables mean they cannot be buried, and poor local farmers cannot spare the gasoline or wood to incinerate them.</p>
        <p>In villages from China to Turkey, cullers wearing biohazard suits recruit barefoot children to catch chickens for them. Older children kick dying turkeys around like footballs or play with severed heads. Farmers hide prize roosters or bribe cullers to spare their flocks. Chickens are buried alive or burned alive.</p>
        <p>''We need an international culling task force, a reliably robust, incorruptible public service to go around killing chickens,'' said Dr. David Nabarro, special representative for avian flu for the United Nations secretary general.</p>
        <p>Dr. Juan Lubroth, senior animal health officer for the United Nations Food and Agricultural Organization, said he would like to have at least 20 more veterinarians right now to send to Indonesia and Turkey simply to train ''brigades of cullers,'' and would need more for each country the disease reaches.</p>
        <p>The total cost, he said, would depend on whether he can borrow government veterinarians from wealthy countries or has to hire privately, and whether he sends a few to lead workshops in the capital or dozens into small villages to supervise culling. He is also negotiating with a Dutch company to bring its portable chicken-killing machines to southeast Asia, he said.</p>
        <p>Until recently, Dr. Lubroth said, he had no money for any of this. But since Jan. 18, when 33 nations and international institutions at a meeting in Beijing pledged $1.9 billion to fight avian flu, ''all of a sudden, I'm able to make some decisions.''</p>
        <p>His agency already has advisers in the field, but they are overwhelmed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter Roeder, a veterinarian for the United Nations agriculture agency who normally works out of Rome fighting rinderpest, a cattle virus, recently found himself fighting avian flu in Banda Aceh, Indonesia, which is still recovering from the 2004 tsunami.</p>
        <p>The disease took Indonesia, the world's fourth-most populous country, by surprise, he said. It had no response plan or clear chain of command for veterinarians, and it has endemic Newcastle disease, which mimics flu in chickens. Large producers protected their own flocks quickly, he said, but the flu became entrenched in ''kampong chickens,'' the millions of free-roaming household birds that roost in trees.</p>
        <p>''The virus got away before the first cases were detected,'' he said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>When even one bird with the A(H5N1) virus is found on a farm, its flock and those in a large circle around it must be exterminated.</p>
        <p>There are many ways to dispatch a chicken. Those approved by the Paris-based Organization for International Epizootics, which tracks diseases that cross between animals and humans, include firing bolts to the skull, shocking with bare electrodes, dipping in electrified baths, gassing with carbon dioxide or nitrogen, lethal injection or lacing feed with barbiturates. For small numbers, neck-breaking and decapitation are approved as long as the animals are already unconscious.</p>
        <p>But poor countries cannot always afford such niceties, though some are using variants.</p>
        <p>In Vietnam, said Dr. Tony Forman, a United Nations veterinarian consulting there, cullers have begun collecting chickens in large plastic bags and gassing them with carbon dioxide, which is available from any soda bottling plant.</p>
        <p>In Thailand, said Dr. Wantanee Kalpravidh, the regional head of flu surveillance for the United Nations agriculture agency, cullers pack chickens into the backs of trucks and run in a hose from the tailpipe.</p>
        <p>But in Indonesia, Dr. Roeder said, ''Cullers kill in the traditional fashion -- cutting their throats.''</p>
        <p>That is risky -- cut hands can be infected by chicken blood, although there have not yet been any confirmed cases of avian flu among cullers.</p>
        <p>Treating small farmers politely is also crucial, veterinary experts said.</p>
        <p>Ann M. Veneman, a former United States agriculture secretary who is the new head of Unicef, is another advocate of creating a chicken-culling task force. She oversaw a yearlong fight against a major outbreak of Newcastle disease as California's secretary of food and agriculture in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Three million chickens on 22 broiler and egg operations had to be killed, she said, but what was harder was killing the 150,000 birds in 18,000 quarantined households.</p>
        <p>''We didn't realize how many backyard birds there were, even in Los Angeles County,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Backyard birds'' all over the world can flee faster than big-breasted commercial birds, and their owners are often very attached to them.</p>
        <p>''People love their animals,'' said Dr. Richard Breitmeyer, the state veterinarian who oversaw the California culling. ''In many cases, they were pets.''</p>
        <p>Although he had the legal right to enter properties without owners' permissions and to kill every bird, ''We needed to treat the owners and birds with respect,'' he said. ''Otherwise, in a backyard setting, it's pretty hard to ensure you're seeing all the birds.''</p>
        <p>But farmers persuaded to cooperate can collect roosting flocks at night, or lure them in with corn.</p>
        <p>By contrast, said Dr. Roeder, Indonesian government teams often arrive in villages at midday, ''when birds are running all over the place.''</p>
        <p>Then, he said, ''They go in ordering people about with the attitude that the authorities know best.''</p>
        <p>Also, farmers will not cooperate without compensation, and most countries are paying relatively little.</p>
        <p>In Turkey, farmers get up to $3.50 a chicken, which Dr. Lubroth, said was about 60 percent of market value. ''But owners are getting only vouchers,'' he said in a telephone interview from Ankara. ''I haven't seen cash change hands.''</p>
        <p>Vietnam pays $1, about half the market value there. Indonesia, which is wealthier, pays about 80 cents, less than a third of market value.</p>
        <p>In China, the government officially pays 60 cents, and farmers complain that vouchers go unpaid.</p>
        <p>In Cambodia and Laos, which are poor, farmers are offered only 10 percent to 20 percent of market value, and only for flocks, said Dr. Kalpravidh, the flu watcher in Thailand, ''so we don't see much cooperation.''</p>
        <p>And in the case of fighting cocks -- entrenched in southeast Asian culture and worth up to $5,000, she said -- the breeders ''sneak their chickens away,'' unwilling to sacrifice the cash or the bloodlines.</p>
        <p>In the California Newcastle outbreak, Dr. Breitmeyer said, valuable fighting cocks were often found in Hispanic neighborhoods, and federal appraisers paid market value.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lubroth favored paying close to market value for birds from infected flocks, slightly more for those from healthy flocks nearby, and nothing for dead birds -- a plan that encourages farmers to cooperate promptly.</p>
        <p>Disposing of the carcasses so they cannot be dug up and eaten by people,wild animals or scavenging birds is also important. Shallow graves and composting are discouraged, though Dr. Forman said he had seen farmers ''piping methane out of compost piles and boiling tea with it.'' Furnace incineration is fine, but expensive. Open burning is not, and it is best not to truck birds from the killing site because the flu is so contagious that it can travel in dander and feathers blown off them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
