<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commencement Speeches; Graduates Get an Earful, From Left, Right and Center</title>
    <meta content="11commence" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060615T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1768398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foster, Jodie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rumsfeld, Donald H (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2D91231F932A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="3558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commencement Speeches; Graduates Get an Earful, From Left, Right and Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many commencement speakers this year are speaking out against what they consider growing belligerence of American foreign policy, while others condemn war, racism and poverty; White House officials defend Bush administration's initiatives; excerpts from speeches by Bill Bradley, Jodie Foster, Sec Donald H Rumsfeld and others; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's all been said before, at one university or another.</p>
        <p>And so, in trying to come up with something new, many commencement speakers do considerable research on what to say -- and what it is permissible to say -- before they address graduating students. This year, Judith Resnik, a legal scholar, could win the exhaustive-preparation prize. For her speech at Bryn Mawr, Dr. Resnik reviewed over 100 years of commencement addresses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's all been said before, at one university or another.</p>
        <p>And so, in trying to come up with something new, many commencement speakers do considerable research on what to say -- and what it is permissible to say -- before they address graduating students. This year, Judith Resnik, a legal scholar, could win the exhaustive-preparation prize. For her speech at Bryn Mawr, Dr. Resnik reviewed over 100 years of commencement addresses.</p>
        <p>''I found that these talks gave me utter license to talk about whatever I wanted, from chemistry to health care, from wars to Social Security and beyond, to ballooning,'' she told the graduates at the ceremony. Dr. Resnik used that license to speak out against torture (the text of her speech contained 54 footnotes).</p>
        <p>Dr. Resnik was one of many commencement speakers who spoke out against what they consider a growing belligerence in American foreign policy. Others condemned war, racism and poverty.</p>
        <p>At Marlboro College in Vermont, Nan Aron, the president of Alliance for Justice, a liberal group, denounced the Bush administration for its eavesdropping program and for holding prisoners at Guantánamo Bay without charging them with crimes.</p>
        <p>''It makes you think of what Jay Leno said when this administration's forces in the Iraq war were drafting a constitution,'' Ms. Aron said. ''He said, 'Give them ours. It was written by a lot of smart guys, worked well for 200 years -- and we're not using it any more.' ''</p>
        <p>White House officials defended the Bush administration's initiatives in various commencement speeches. To the graduates at the United States Naval Academy, Vice President Dick Cheney defended the administration's domestic surveillance program by saying, ''The terrorist surveillance program is fully consistent with the constitutional responsibilities and the legal authorities of the president,'' a line that brought sustained applause from the midshipmen.</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld, speaking at the Virginia Military Institute, defended his conduct of the Iraq war by reminding cadets that the D-Day invasion of World War II was fraught with blunders.</p>
        <p>Several commencement addresses, including Senator John McCain's at the New School University in New York and Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice's at Boston College, turned tumultuous, as some graduates heckled them. Two prominent Democrats lamented the degradation of civil discourse. One of them, Mayor Antonio R. Villaraigosa of Los Angeles, told University of Southern California graduates it was ''poisoning our politics.''</p>
        <p>And Mark Warner, the former Virginia governor, in an address at Wake Forest University, criticized the ''personal and partisan attacks'' and ''complex issues reduced to easy-to-digest sound bites.''</p>
        <p>''No one -- no one -- in politics has a monopoly on virtue, on patriotism, or most importantly, on the truth,'' Mr. Warner said. ''And that goes for everyone, from conservative to liberal.''</p>
        <p>Speakers this year included the usual politicians, including Attorney General Eliot Spitzer of New York, who spoke at several state commencements, and a string of governors speaking at less well-known state colleges; human rights advocates like Sister Helen Prejean, who opposes the death penalty; foreign dignitaries, including Juan Guzmán Tapia, the Chilean judge who indicted Gen. Augusto Pinochet, the Chilean dictator; actors like Viggo Mortensen; and athletes like Lance Armstrong.</p>
        <p>Several speakers, including the former CNN anchor Aaron Brown and the singer Billy Joel, acknowledged the incongruity of delivering college commencement addresses despite having never graduated themselves.</p>
        <p>And of course there was plenty of advice, some of it controversial, including that given by the former C.I.A. director Porter J. Goss the day after his dismissal last month.</p>
        <p>The Toledo Blade reported that Mr. Goss told graduates at Tiffin University in Ohio: ''If this were a graduating class of C.I.A. case officers, my advice would be short and to the point: Admit nothing, deny everything and make counteraccusations.''</p>
        <p>Bill Bradley  Former senator  Ithaca College</p>
        <p>President Williams, members of the faculty, members of the class of 2006, friends and family of the class of 2006. I want to continue my acknowledgments. I'm very sensitive, I want to make sure that I acknowledge every element of this community. And so let me borrow from Garry Trudeau and continue my acknowledgments: and so I recognize Chairman Bill Haines and members of the board of trustees, bored members of the trustees, those who watch ''The Sopranos,'' those who watch ''American Idol,'' those who still watch the reruns of ''Frasier,'' those who don't like TV. Denizens of Ithaca, denizens of the night, knights of Tompkins County, people of class, classy people, people of height, the vertically constrained, people of hair, the indifferently coiffed, the optically challenged, the temporarily sighted, the insightful, the out of sight, the out-of-towners, the Afrocentrics, the Eurocentrics, the Eurocentrics with Eurail passes, the eccentrically inclined. The sexually disinclined, people of sex, sexy people, earthy people, animal companions, friends of the earth, friends of the boss, the temporarily employed, the differently employed, the differently optioned, people with options, people with stock options, Knick fans, Celtic fans, those who don't have the wisdom to be either Knick or Celtic fans, the divestiturists, the deconstructionists, the home constructionists, the homeless, the temporarily housed at home, and, God save us parents, the permanently housed at home. Good morning!</p>
        <p>Antonio O. Garza Jr.  Ambassador to Mexico  University of Texas</p>
        <p>Life will test you in ways you cannot imagine. And one of the ways it will test you -- over and over -- is how you treat others who don't look like you, talk like you or earn like you. My grandparents came to America from Mexico looking for a better life. Their leap of faith made it possible for my dad to raise his family running a filling station in South Texas. His hard work and sacrifice allowed me to do what I am doing today.</p>
        <p>One generation removed from Mexico, and the grandson of four Mexican immigrants is now the face of America for millions of people in Mexico and around the world.</p>
        <p>We have come far as a society. We are no longer the Jim Crow nation that buried the hopes of so many long before we buried their bodies. But you and I know that our work is not done until the invisible are invisible no more.</p>
        <p>Jodie Foster  Actor, director and producer  University of Pennsylvania</p>
        <p>You pick up bits and pieces of treasure and trash, pain and pleasure, passions and disappointments, and you start throwing them in your bag, your big bag of experience. You do some dumb things that don't work out at all. You stumble excitedly on little gems that you never saw coming. And you stuff them all in your bag. You pursue the things you love and believe in. You cast off the images of yourself that don't fit. And suddenly you look behind you and a pattern emerges.</p>
        <p>You look in front of you and the path makes sense. There is nothing more beautiful than finding your course as you believe you bob aimlessly in the current. Wouldn't you know that your path was there all along, waiting for you to knock, waiting for you to become. This path does not belong to your parents, your teachers, your leaders, your lovers. Your path is your character defining itself more and more every day, like a photograph coming into focus.</p>
        <p>Melissa Etheridge  Rock Musician  Berklee College of Music</p>
        <p>I went to Los Angeles; I played in bars here and there. I discovered myself; I discovered my sexuality. I remember, it's not so easy being a musician, and I do remember dating a young gal -- you do know I'm gay? I was dating, and this girl was kind of coming out and she decided it was time to call her parents and tell them she was gay.</p>
        <p>And she called and said, ''Mom, Dad, I'm gay, and I'm dating a musician, and this is what I am.''</p>
        <p>And there was a long silence and kind of a grumble. And she said, ''Well, gee, I didn't think you would have such a hard time with me being gay.'' And they said: ''Oh no, it's not that. But really, honey, a musician?'' All the rest they can take but, oh, dating a musician!</p>
        <p>Anthony M. Kennedy  Associate justice of the Supreme Court  New York University</p>
        <p>Think of the people around the world, and particularly in Africa, who have no clean water. Women in Africa -- and the job falls to women -- must spend six, eight hours a day just in trying to bring clean water to their children.</p>
        <p>Eight billion hours a year of human effort are spent just in bringing water. And when I heard that statistic, sitting like you are in an audience, I thought, ''Well, he must have said eight million.'' Then I thought, ''Maybe it's 80 million.'' It's eight billion hours a year of wasted effort because the water is often contaminated when it gets there. This isn't rocket science. You can fix this.</p>
        <p>Judith Resnik  Law professor  Bryn Mawr College</p>
        <p>I do not think that either the world or my own country has been torture-free since the Renaissance. But I was hopeful enough, patriotic enough, to believe that my government would never justify harming a person just short of when his or her organs were failing.</p>
        <p>I believed that my American government would never claim that law itself (national and international) did not apply when it was acting ''offshore,'' or to the president whenever he is acting.</p>
        <p>It simply had never occurred to me that my government would claim that any zone was one in which the United States could act completely unbounded based on a theory that the Constitution gives the president a blank check -- not to be checked.</p>
        <p>Donald H. Rumsfeld  Secretary of defense  Virginia Military Institute</p>
        <p>The American people are seeing things they never saw before about the realities of conflict and of postwar violence. They will need the help of those of you who have studied military strategy to better understand what it is they're seeing every day, and to become more aware that war requires continuous adjustments and calibrations, just as the enemy, an enemy with a brain, is constantly adjusting its tactics.</p>
        <p>Today, for example, we remember the D-Day invasion in World War II as a great American victory. That's how it's taught. But many historians also remember it for a series of strategic and tactical errors and decisions based on imperfect intelligence, difficulties that cost lives and delayed the Allied advance. Actually, it was undoubtedly both of those things, which of course is often the nature of warfare.</p>
        <p>You might also want to remind folks that for every story of failure we know, there are hundreds more of courage and self-sacrifice.</p>
        <p>David McCullough  Historian  Bates College</p>
        <p>However little television you watch, watch less. Read. Read for pleasure. Read for happiness.</p>
        <p>Wynton Marsalis  Musician  The Juilliard School</p>
        <p>Realize that integrity is real, and so is starvation. Never let pay and the talk of pay occupy more time and space than the talk of your art. If you find that it is, go into banking or start a hedge fund or something.</p>
        <p>Also, about pay, understand where you are. When I was 19, I was on a tour with Herbie Hancock and I started complaining to him before we walked onstage about what I was being paid. I said, ''When am I being paid?''</p>
        <p>He said: ''Come here, man. Look out into the audience.'' He said, ''Now, do you see those people?''</p>
        <p>I said, ''Yes sir.''</p>
        <p>He said: ''They paid for these tickets. If you don't walk out of here, how many of them are going to leave? Now, if I don't walk out, how many will leave? That's why you're being paid what you're being paid.''</p>
        <p>Wendy Kopp  President and founder of Teach for America  University of North Carolina</p>
        <p>During my senior fall, I helped organize a conference about education reform, where one of the topics was the shortage of qualified teachers in urban and rural communities. It was at that conference that I thought of an idea: why doesn't our country have a national teacher corps that recruits us to teach in low-income communities the same way we're being recruited to work on Wall Street? From that moment, I was possessed by this idea. I thought it would make a huge difference in kids' lives  and that ultimately it could change the very consciousness of our country, by influencing the thinking and career paths of a generation of leaders. So I did the obvious thing. I wrote a very long and very passionate letter to the president of the United States suggesting he start this corps. That didn't get very far -- I received a job rejection letter in response. So in my undergraduate senior thesis, I declared that I would try to create such a corps myself, as a nonprofit organization. When my thesis adviser looked at my budget, which showed that to recruit 500 new teachers into this corps during the first year would cost $2.5 million, he asked me if I knew how hard it was to raise $2,500, let alone $2.5 million.</p>
        <p>Aided by my inexperience, I was unfazed by his question. When school district officials and potential funders laughed at the notion that the Me Generation would jump at the chance to teach in urban and rural communities, their concerns, too, went unheard. That year, 2,500 graduating seniors competed to enter Teach For America in response to a grass-roots recruitment campaign -- fliers under doors, since there was no e-mail back then.</p>
        <p>And one year after I graduated, with $2.5 million in hand from the corporate and foundation community, I was looking out on an auditorium full of 489 recent college graduates who had joined Teach for America's first corps. My very greatest asset in reaching this point was that I simply did not understand what was impossible.</p>
        <p>John Hope Franklin  Emeritus professor of history  Duke University</p>
        <p>Something has brought about the recrudescence of racism in this country. What triggered this bizarre demonstration of a trait that has too long been a part of American life? Perhaps it was the competition for the limited employment opportunities between recent immigrants and longtime citizens, such as African-Americans who have been mistakenly regarded as immigrants. Perhaps it was the view held by some that the civil rights movement had ended, thus no longer holding all of us accountable for this incipient racism.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it was the mistaken view that the best way to preserve American values is for each American to take the law into her or his own hands.</p>
        <p>Perhaps there were other forces at work: the sense of insecurity in the workplace on the part of some, the palpable resegregation of the public schools in many of our cities, the resistance to racial equality that has been ever present at all levels of American life and in every period of American history, and the mistaken belief by some that African-Americans should be made to understand that their rightful place in American society is one of subordination.</p>
        <p>What better way for you to take on your role as responsible, mature citizens than to insist that the American ideal of equality of race, sex, religion and ethnic groups be adhered to because that ideal was bought and paid for by all Americans, regardless of race.</p>
        <p>Cokie Roberts  Broadcast journalist  Wheaton College</p>
        <p>It would be especially useful for you to consider, now that you have this wonderful education, a life of public service, particularly public service in elective office. I know that that is not a popular thought or that these are not popular people. And some of it's their own fault. Right now they're misbehaving badly.</p>
        <p>Some of it is their fault because they tend to run against the institutions they serve in, rather than admire them and respect them. Some of it is your fault -- our fault as citizens -- because to be good leaders, you have to be good citizens and allow people to take leadership, not punish them the minute that they do something that you think is not in your immediate self-interest. Some of it is certainly our fault in the press for always jumping on public servants and politicians and denigrating them as ''professional politicians,'' as if that is some epithet of disgrace. But I would like to argue the other case because I think to denigrate the professional is to denigrate the profession.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey R. Immelt  Chairman and C.E.O. of General Electric  Northeastern University</p>
        <p>There's a lot of volatility out there, especially when you look 10 and 20 years down the road. Will China or India eclipse the United States as the dominant economic power in the world? Will global warming lead to more ecological turmoil? Will the cost of caring for aging populations around the world bankrupt national treasuries? These are only questions. We don't have the answers yet. The future hasn't been written yet. That's up to you.</p>
        <p>Elias A. Zerhouni  Director of the National Institutes of Health  Johns Hopkins University</p>
        <p>There is no question that our world is more connected through the wonders of information technology and the relative ease of global travel. We can get on a plane to California, London or Brazil, to Shanghai, Mumbai or Dubai, then walk out of the gate and find a Starbucks and a wireless connection in the airport. But I have come to believe that this world view is incomplete and misleading. I believe that there is not one but two divergent globalizations going on at the same time on our planet.</p>
        <p>One globalization is that of an increasingly connected world, as aptly described by Tom Friedman. But the other globalization is that of an increasingly disconnected world where knowledge may actually be decreasing and where poverty and disease are on a steady climb. This dawned on me as I traveled to Africa and Asia for N.I.H. Malaria, which was almost eliminated in the 1970's, has roared back, and tuberculosis and H.I.V./AIDS have exploded.</p>
        <p>Francine du Plessix Gray  Author  Barnard College</p>
        <p>You have to give hell to entrenched power when it violates our notions of human justice. So my final message to you is this: Whether it be on the issue of racial integration or gay rights or sexual equality or the pathetic state of health care in this country or one of the dumbest military excursions ever waged by an American government -- the Iraq War -- your motto should be ''Give 'em hell, give 'em hell, give 'em hell!'' There are never enough troublemakers fighting for justice, so go out there and give 'em hell to create a better world for you and your children to grow into.</p>
        <p>Margaret Spellings  Secretary of education  Texas Tech University</p>
        <p>When I first got to the White House, I felt completely out of my element, surrounded by Ivy Leaguers. But I got my guns up. I stood and delivered. I did my best. And before long I was meeting with senators, flying on Air Force One and helping the president perfect his pronunciations. We're still working on ''nucular.'' It just goes to show you: the only boundaries to what you can achieve are the ones you set for yourself.</p>
        <p>Lance Armstrong  Tour de France champion  Tufts University</p>
        <p>In 1998, when I decided to come back, there really were no guarantees. I was a year and a half off the bike. I got back into the sport, and as I mentioned, you have to have a team. Well, I barely found a team, and I started to train and I figured that since I was so sick before -- I had just done the Olympic Games in '96 -- I figured if I ridded my body of all the cancer, I would come back on the bike and I would win immediately. I had abdomen, lung and brain metastases, and I thought, let's get rid of all that stuff, I'll win everything.</p>
        <p>I trained that way and I raced that way, at least I started to race that way. The sad news is that I didn't win. I didn't win at all. I was completely disillusioned. I fell out of love with the sport. I fell out of love with the bike. I didn't like my job. I didn't like Europe. I quit and I came home in the spring of '98. That's a story that nobody tells. I was done with cycling forever.</p>
        <p>I proceeded to hang out with my friends, drink a few beers, play golf. I certainly was not living the life of a professional athlete, until, one day, a group of friends sat me down and said: ''You can't go out like this. You've got to get back on the bike, at least finish the year. You made a commitment to your team and to a whole population of cancer survivors that you'll try this. You have to at least finish the year.'' So I did that, and I went and found a remote training camp in Boone, N.C., with a coach and a friend. For eight days in the pouring rain, 40 degrees, I fell back in love with the bike. That was the start of the comeback.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 15, 2006, Thursday  An article on Sunday about commencement speeches around the country referred imprecisely to audience reaction to a speech by Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice at Boston College. While some people turned their backs on her and a protest banner was unfurled during her appearance, the scene inside Alumni Stadium where she spoke did not turn tumultuous, nor was she heckled while speaking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 15, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about commencement speeches around the country referred imprecisely to audience reaction to a speech by Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice at Boston College. While some people turned their backs on her and a protest banner was unfurled during her appearance, the scene inside Alumni Stadium where she spoke did not turn tumultuous, nor was she heckled while speaking.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
