<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="12obse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/12/science/12observ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1789489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DC1531F931A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Many More Dinosaurs Still to Be Found</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Henry Fountain</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mammal Mimicry</p>
        <p>Several years ago, scientists recorded the sounds of sea lions barking underwater in Nootka Sound off Vancouver Island in British Columbia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Discovering dinosaurs, killer whales that imitate, weathered asteroids and more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mammal Mimicry</p>
        <p>Several years ago, scientists recorded the sounds of sea lions barking underwater in Nootka Sound off Vancouver Island in British Columbia.</p>
        <p>At least they thought sea lions were making the sounds. But closer analysis revealed something strange. Some of the barks included harmonic frequencies over 10 kilohertz. Sea lions don't usually produce harmonics over 4 kilohertz. And during many of the recordings, no sea lions were observed in the area. But a lone killer whale was.</p>
        <p>Now, Andrew D. Foote of the University of Durham in Britain and colleagues say they are certain it was the whale that was doing the barking. The imitative behavior, they write in the journal Biology Letters, shows that the mammals (which are not whales but members of the dolphin family) are capable of vocal learning.</p>
        <p>The killer whale in question, named Luna, was separated from its family group, or pod, at an early age. Pod members tend to have a repertoire of normal calls that they use to varying degrees. The researchers studied recordings of Luna and another separated killer whale named Springer, and found evidence in both animals that they used their repertoire of calls differently than the pod they were born into.</p>
        <p>But it was the imitation barking by Luna (who was killed last March by a tugboat) that was most unusual. Many birds are capable of this kind of learning, but it is relatively rare in mammals. Most recently it was recognized in an elephant that imitated the sounds of trucks on a highway.</p>
        <p>Weathered Asteroids</p>
        <p>Most meteorites are thought to originate in the asteroid belt. They are bits and pieces of rock, the remnants of asteroidal collisions, that have been pulled by Jupiter's gravity into a collision course with Earth.</p>
        <p>But there's something about this theory that has always puzzled scientists: the most common meteorites don't look like the most common asteroids. Like well-aged beef, the asteroids are darker and redder.</p>
        <p>One explanation could be that the asteroids have weathered in the millions of years since the collisions that created the meteorites. The impact of dust, radiation and particles in the solar wind, the thinking goes, would vaporize materials on the surface, in particular iron. As clouds of tiny iron particles settled, they would make the surface appear redder.</p>
        <p>Some ground-based observations of asteroids, and a few spacecraft fly-bys, have appeared to show signs of such weathering. But the best evidence yet comes from a Japanese mission to the small asteroid Itokawa a year ago.</p>
        <p>Takahiro Hiroi of Brown University and colleagues analyzed data from a near-infrared spectrometer aboard the spacecraft, which spent three months orbiting the asteroid. Two locations on Itokawa were studied, and one was found to be significantly darker and redder than the other. Calculations suggest that the difference was because of a higher concentration of iron particles at the darker location, indicating that the products of weathering accumulate on the surface. The findings were published in the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Why weren't both locations the same? Most likely, the darker surface has been exposed to the ''weather'' longer than the lighter surface has. As some point in the not-too-distant past, a small rock may have hit the lighter area, blasting off the old exposed surface and exposing virgin material underneath.</p>
        <p>Genes for Plastic</p>
        <p>By most measures, Ralstonia eutropha is an unusual bacterium. It feeds on carbon dioxide and hydrogen and stores energy in the form of plastic-like molecules called PHA's. Strains of R. eutropha are used to make biodegradable plastics.</p>
        <p>A team of scientists in Germany has now sequenced the genome of one strain. The work, reported in the journal Nature Biotechnology, reveals about 50 genes that are probably involved in PHA accumulation and opens the way for bioengineering techniques to fine-tune the process.</p>
        <p>Many More Dinosaurs Still to Be Found</p>
        <p>The last few decades have been a golden era of dinosaur hunting. Thanks in part to discoveries of fossil beds in Asia and South America, paleontologists have nearly doubled the number of known dinosaur genera. (Scientists generally keep count by genus, rather than species, because 90 percent of dinosaur genera include just one species.)</p>
        <p>Still, as of last spring, only 527 genera had been described. So that raises the question: how many dinosaurs are yet to be found?</p>
        <p>Steven C. Wang of Swarthmore College and Peter Dodson of the University of Pennsylvania have come up with a new estimate. Using a statistical method that incorporates data on dinosaur discoveries, they say there are 1,850 genera. That means that 28 percent have been found.</p>
        <p>Paleontologists have made estimates in the past. Dr. Dodson, for one, once put the total at 1,200. But with all the recent discoveries, ''we thought it was a good time for a new estimate,'' Dr. Wang wrote in an e-mail message. Their findings were published in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>The statistical method relies on the rarity of finds. That is, if every time a fossil is uncovered it represents a new genus, then it is likely that many more genera will be found. If most new fossils are of genera that have already been described, then relatively few new genera will be found. Dinosaur hunting, it turns out, is more like the first situation than the second -- almost all genera are represented by just one or two specimens.</p>
        <p>Some scientists have suggested that dinosaurs were in decline long before they were wiped out 65 million years ago. The researchers looked at this question and found no evidence that the number of genera had dwindled in the 10 million years before extinction. But Dr. Wang cautioned that fossil dating was not precise enough to rule out a decline.</p>
        <p>With about 1,300 genera left to find, paleontologists clearly have a lot of work to do. But the researchers also predicted the rate of future discoveries and suggested that dinosaur hunters were up to the task. Within 100 to 140 years, the researchers say, 90 percent of dinosaurs will have been discovered.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
