<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Year of Political Films, This Time From America</title>
    <meta content="26cann" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/26/movies/26cann.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1764381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="CANNES JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Inconvenient Truth, an (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fast Food Nation (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Scanner Darkly, A (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Southland Tales (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, John Cameron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gore, Al</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Linklater, Richard</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schlosser, Eric</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Loach, Ken</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6D8113EF935A15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Year of Political Films, This Time From America</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cannes Again Offers a Year of Political Films, This Time From America</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <dateline>CANNES, France</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott Cannes Journal on prevalence of political films at Cannes International Film Festival; large portion are United States entries, including An Inconvenient Truth, Fast Food Nation, A Scanner Darkly and Southland Tales; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''IT'S like the 60's but with less hope.'' That line, from John Cameron Mitchell's ''Shortbus,'' refers to the hectic atmosphere of sexual experimentation in post-9/11 New York, where the film is set, but it also seems to resonate more generally at this festival (where ''Shortbus'' was shown out of competition last weekend).</p>
        <p>The 60's mean different things to different people, but to the tribe of cinephiles who gather here each spring, the decade represents, perhaps above all, a golden age of international filmmaking. The artistic ferment of the era intersected with its political tumult in memorably dramatic fashion at the 1968 Cannes Film Festival, which came to a halt when the ''events of May'' spilled into the Palais screening rooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As always, the work varies widely in quality and subject matter this year, but movies with political themes seem especially prevalent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''IT'S like the 60's but with less hope.'' That line, from John Cameron Mitchell's ''Shortbus,'' refers to the hectic atmosphere of sexual experimentation in post-9/11 New York, where the film is set, but it also seems to resonate more generally at this festival (where ''Shortbus'' was shown out of competition last weekend).</p>
        <p>The 60's mean different things to different people, but to the tribe of cinephiles who gather here each spring, the decade represents, perhaps above all, a golden age of international filmmaking. The artistic ferment of the era intersected with its political tumult in memorably dramatic fashion at the 1968 Cannes Film Festival, which came to a halt when the ''events of May'' spilled into the Palais screening rooms.</p>
        <p>It's hard to imagine anything so convulsive happening these days. But it would be a mistake to conclude that the glory days of world cinema are gone forever. Each year, even through its ups and downs, Cannes reveals just how much interesting, ambitious and surprising work is being done, both in established centers of film production and in countries whose film industries have lain fallow or barely existed.</p>
        <p>A palpable diminution of hope arises from the frustrating sense that too many of these movies are fated to remain on the cultural margins, unavailable to the audiences that might appreciate them. Movies may still be, for the moment, the engine that drives the global culture industry, but the central role of cinema in the transformation of tastes and sensibilities seems to have waned.</p>
        <p>Of course individual filmmakers are properly concerned less with the overall state of their art than with the grain and direction of their own work. As always, that work has varied widely in quality and subject matter this year -- does Cannes have a quota for mediocre French and Italian movies? -- but movies with political themes seem especially prevalent.</p>
        <p>In ''The Caiman,'' Nanni Moretti's shaggy-dog satire of Italian society (and Italian cinema) in the age of Silvio Berlusconi, a character remarks somewhat wistfully that Americans are more inclined toward political filmmaking than their peers in Europe. To an American critic the remark may be a bit startling since some of us spend a fair amount of time complaining about the lack of political engagement on the part of our writers and directors and casting our eyes jealously overseas.</p>
        <p>But then again, to look at the American movies represented in Cannes is to see politics everywhere. Here was Al Gore, in town for the out-of-competition screening of ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' his documentary about global warming. And here was ''Fast Food Nation,'' Richard Linklater and Eric Schlosser's adaptation of Mr. Schlosser's muckracking best seller about the American food industry, a film that deals not only with food safety and the treatment of animals but also with immigration, corporate influence on daily life and the quixotic nature of student activism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Linklater's other festival film, the Certain Regard Selection ''A Scanner Darkly,'' based on a novel by Philip K. Dick, sends tendrils of anxiety in all directions. Is the war on drugs worse than the drug epidemic? Can you tell the difference? Is the government spying on us, or does our own paranoia make such a program redundant?</p>
        <p>These movies direct their attention to the present and the future. ''A Scanner Darkly,'' Richard Kelly's apocalyptic ''Southland Tales'' and, for that matter, ''An Inconvenient Truth'' all offer dire speculations, based on interpretations of present circumstances, about what might lie ahead.</p>
        <p>Another way of examining the present, of course, is to investigate the past, which seems to be the strategy of quite a few filmmakers from Europe, Latin America and Asia with films in and out of competition. Ken Loach revisited the Irish rebellion and civil war of the 1920's in ''The Wind That Shakes the Barley,'' while ''Crónica de Una Fuga,'' from the Argentine director Adrián Caetano, takes place during the military dictatorship of the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Lou Ye's ''Summer Palace'' follows a group of Chinese students before and after Tiananmen Square, an event that the film treats both candidly and carefully. (Though not carefully enough for the Chinese government, which has rebuked Mr. Lou for submitting the film to Cannes without official permission and threatened to ban him from shooting for five years.)</p>
        <p>Last year critics were agog over Cristi Puiu's ''Death of Mr. Lazarescu,'' which won the Certain Regard prize and which turned out to be the harbinger of a boomlet in Romanian film. This year two features from Romania -- both of them first films from young directors -- address the legacy of the revolution of 1989, which toppled the communist regime of Nicolae Ceausescu. Catalin Mitulescu's ''How I Spent the End of the World'' takes place during the months before the revolution, and it is an affecting if somewhat conventional coming-of-age story against a backdrop of political upheaval.</p>
        <p>Corneliu Porumboiu's ''12:08, East of Bucharest'' poses, with mordant Balkan wit, the question of whether the revolution really took place at all, at least in the grim little town where the anniversary of Ceausescu's fall is being discussed on local television. The saturnine host welcomes two supposed participants in the revolution into his shabby studio. One of them is a debt-ridden, alcoholic teacher (who also may be a pathological liar), while the other is a distracted old codger who folds pages of the host's scripts into little hats and at one point seems to doze off on the air.</p>
        <p>On screen the 20th century marches on. And as far as the movies are concerned, World War II will never end, or at least it will remain an inexhaustible source of stories and the inspiration for feats of directorial bravura. The English title of ''Indigènes,'' the new film by the French director Rachid Bouchareb, is ''Days of Glory,'' which sounds like the name of a classic Hollywood combat picture from the 50's. Mr. Bouchareb has updated a sturdy genre, the infantry platoon picture, which follows a small band of men through harrowing combat. True to its type, ''Days of Glory'' is full of vivid, masculine performances (notably from Sami Bouajila, whose stoical sensitivity anchors one of the festival's few true movie-star performances), intense combat scenes and speeches that announce its themes in italics.</p>
        <p>Its story concerns a French Army unit composed of men recruited from Algeria, at the time a French colony and therefore, officially, a part of France. They are called to arms to liberate their ''motherland'' from the Nazis, only to find themselves treated like stepchildren.</p>
        <p>Fighting for the universal ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity, they find themselves discriminated against in large and small ways: denied the leaves and promotions that their French comrades receive as a matter of course; refused fresh tomatoes at the company mess; treated with condescension and hostility by most of their superiors.</p>
        <p>While ''Days of Glory'' is emphatic, it is far from heavy-handed, and the problem it addresses is hardly one that ended with the liberation of France (or, for that matter, of Algeria). You only have to think back to the riots of last autumn -- or walk the streets of Cannes outside the festival perimeter -- to see that the tensions between France's republican ideals and its social realities have, if anything, grown more acute in the generations since 1945.</p>
        <p>CANNES JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
