<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atlantic Tops Nominee List For Awards</title>
    <meta content="16mag" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/16/business/media/16mag.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1747143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Magazine Awards</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Society of Magazine Editors</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlantic Monthly</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Yorker (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Quarterly Review (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Magazine Awards</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlantic Monthly</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Yorker</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EEDB1131F935A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atlantic Tops Nominee List For Awards</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Atlantic Tops Nominee List for Awards</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlantic Monthly, outpacing New Yorker, receives eight nominations for National Magazine Awards; Virginia Quarterly Review garners six nominations; winners will be announced May 9 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite unusual turmoil last year, and no permanent editor since Michael Kelly stepped down in 2002, The Atlantic Monthly received eight nominations for National Magazine Awards yesterday, outpacing even The New Yorker, which has dominated the field for eight years.</p>
        <p>Right behind The Atlantic was The Virginia Quarterly Review, with six nominations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Atlantic Monthly received eight nominations for National Magazine Awards, outpacing even The New Yorker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite unusual turmoil last year, and no permanent editor since Michael Kelly stepped down in 2002, The Atlantic Monthly received eight nominations for National Magazine Awards yesterday, outpacing even The New Yorker, which has dominated the field for eight years.</p>
        <p>Right behind The Atlantic was The Virginia Quarterly Review, with six nominations.</p>
        <p>The awards, sponsored by the American Society of Magazine Editors in conjunction with the Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism, are the top journalistic honors in the magazine industry. Winners will be announced May 9.</p>
        <p>The magazine association said that the biggest themes among the nominees were health care, the war in Iraq, the American response to terrorism and global warming.</p>
        <p>The Atlantic's nominations include one for general excellence among magazines with a circulation of 250,000 to 500,000. Its competitors are Backpacker, New York Magazine, Texas Monthly and Technology Review.</p>
        <p>Nominated for general excellence for magazines with circulation over two million were Glamour, National Geographic, Prevention, Time and O, The Oprah Magazine. Glamour won last year, the first time a women's magazine had taken the top prize since Mirabella in 1992.</p>
        <p>General excellence nominees for magazines with a circulation of one to two million were ESPN The Magazine, Fortune, Martha Stewart Living, The New Yorker and Vogue.</p>
        <p>The New Yorker won the category last year, when it took home five awards. The New Yorker has won 44 of the awards, the most of any magazine in the competition's 40-year history, and is nominated for 5 this year, as is New York Magazine.</p>
        <p>For magazines with a circulation of 500,000 to a million, the nominees were Esquire, Everyday Food, House &amp; Garden, Marie Claire, Runner's World and Wired.</p>
        <p>Competing for the general excellence award online are Beliefnet, CNET.com, Men.style.com, National Geographic Online and Newsweek.com.</p>
        <p>The Atlantic has been unsettled since Mr. Kelly stepped down from the editorship; he was on assignment for the magazine in Iraq when he was killed in 2003. The managing editor, Cullen Murphy, was running The Atlantic but no one had the title of editor in chief until this month, when James Bennet, a New York Times reporter, was named to the position.</p>
        <p>The staff was in further turmoil last year as the owner, David G. Bradley, moved The Atlantic to Washington from its home in Boston, where it was founded in 1857. Many staff members stayed in Boston and have left the magazine as Mr. Bradley has built it anew along the Potomac.</p>
        <p>A complete list of the nominees by article and issue can be found at the magazine society's Web site (http://asme.magazine.org).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
