<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking the Rough-and-Tumble Approach to Science</title>
    <meta content="29sanfran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Museums" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/29/arts/artsspecial/29sanfran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1750381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Exploratorium (San Francisco)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gnatek, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppenheimer, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Exploratorium</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7DF1F31F93AA15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking the Rough-and-Tumble Approach to Science</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Taking the Rough-and-Tumble Approach to Science</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GNATEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gnatek, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>San Francisco</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exploratorium science museum in San Francisco has since 1996 provided online coverage of science events, including six eclipses, scientific expeditions to Antarctica and rain forests and multimedia events; photo; site and physical museum, which was founded in 1969 by physicist Frank Oppenheimer, have been pioneers in designing hands-on exhibitions (special section, Museums) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH today's solar eclipse will not be visible in North America, science fans will get a chance to see it online. The Exploratorium science museum will transmit a live Webcast of the event from Turkey to www.exploratorium.edu.</p>
        <p>Webcasting special events is an increasingly common practice for science museums that are trying to nurture online visitors, but it has been a longstanding activity at the Exploratorium. Since 1996, the museum has covered science events online, including six eclipses and scientific expeditions to Antarctica and the rain forests of Belize. Webcasts are so common for the Exploratorium, which regularly produces science-themed presentations and even game shows, that it has a broadcasting studio on its exhibition floor, complete with a podium, backdrops and stage lighting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The site of the San Francisco-based Exploratorium has become a popular source for science made simple, whether through multimedia events or interactive science exhibits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH today's solar eclipse will not be visible in North America, science fans will get a chance to see it online. The Exploratorium science museum will transmit a live Webcast of the event from Turkey to www.exploratorium.edu.</p>
        <p>Webcasting special events is an increasingly common practice for science museums that are trying to nurture online visitors, but it has been a longstanding activity at the Exploratorium. Since 1996, the museum has covered science events online, including six eclipses and scientific expeditions to Antarctica and the rain forests of Belize. Webcasts are so common for the Exploratorium, which regularly produces science-themed presentations and even game shows, that it has a broadcasting studio on its exhibition floor, complete with a podium, backdrops and stage lighting.</p>
        <p>But the museum plays an even larger role online than being a video producer for the Web. Over the last 12 years, the Exploratorium's site has become a popular source for science made simple, whether through multimedia events or interactive science exhibitions.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, the Exploratorium made its site more than a museum marquee for current shows. Like the physical museum -- founded in 1969 by the physicist Frank Oppenheimer (brother of the renowned physicist J. Robert Oppenheimer), it was a pioneer in designing hands-on science exhibitions -- the site strives to present science in new ways.</p>
        <p>As with many museums today, the Exploratorium's virtual visitors far outnumber real-world patrons: last year the Web site had more than 20 million visitors while the museum had about 600,000.</p>
        <p>The Exploratorium's online history dates back to the fall of 1993, when there were about 600 Web sites and only one for a museum -- the Museum of Paleontology at the University of California, Berkeley. Ron Hipschman, the Exploratorium's Webmaster, then registered the domain name www.exploratorium.edu after becoming fascinated with early online message boards among scientists and academics.</p>
        <p>The Internet was so unpopulated that Mr. Hipschman's domain registrar allowed him two liberties in naming the site: picking the extension ''edu'' even though the museum is not an academic institution, a rule impossible to sidestep today; and selecting a name with more than 12 characters, a number that has since increased to 63 to accommodate the millions of sites that followed.</p>
        <p>The museum's earliest online exhibitions presented how-to experiments and sensory illusions using graphics and text. Even today, the museum's low-bandwidth presentations remain appealing to Web visitors, Mr. Hipschman said. ''We like the rough-and-tumble approach, because it makes people feel that science is doable,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The most trafficked exhibition is a project from 1996 called Common Cents, where viewers pick out a real penny from 12 identical images. It receives about 5,500 hits a day.</p>
        <p>The most recent exhibitions include the ''Microscope Imaging Station,'' where visitors can watch videos of processes like fertilization and mitosis; ''Origins,'' which explores the origins of existence by giving a behind-the-scenes look at the work of scientific observatories; and ''The Accidental Scientist,'' a continuous series about the science of everyday activities, like cooking.</p>
        <p>The online projects take years to develop and are often done with science and art groups like the National Science Foundation, the Jet Propulsion Laboratory and the San Francisco Opera, which provide special content or expertise. The exhibitions are often underwritten from philanthropic groups like the David and Lucile Packard Foundation and the McBean Family Foundation.</p>
        <p>The Exploratorium site has received recognition from both the Internet and museum communities. Over the last few years, it has won five Webby Awards, which are given annually to honor Web creativity. It has also received praise from museum entities like Archives and Museum Informatics, a consulting group in Toronto that promotes information technology to museums.</p>
        <p>''In lots of ways, the museum community looks to the Exploratorium to see what kinds of exciting things are being done,'' said David Bearman, president of the group.</p>
        <p>Robert Semper, an associate director at the Exploratorium who oversees the Web programs, says there is as much value in online programs as in their real-world counterparts. ''There are some who would say that a museum's relationship to the Web should not be a primary focus,'' he said. ''But I believe that we can give sets of experiences that are well crafted, allowing people to make new discoveries and experiences. That's our artifact.''</p>
        <p>Besides creating virtual exhibitions, the site also provides educational resources, like instructions for home science projects, and a free digital library with about 12,000 multimedia materials.</p>
        <p>''There are things we can do on the Web that are hard to do in the museum,'' Mr. Semper said, citing a program on climate change that uses real-time data from the Internet to highlight environmental trends.</p>
        <p>New forms of communication may be the next advance for the site, and designers are already working on how to add devices like video blogs, podcasts and shared media portals.</p>
        <p>''We're looking at adding all of these Web 2.0 ideas,'' Mr. Semper said, referring to the term used to describe interactive technologies. ''E-mailing content to people's cellphones, sending pictures and giving downloads to hand-held devices are all possible now.''</p>
        <p>While there are more than 15,000 pages on the site, there are few ways to navigate them beyond plugging in keywords using a Google search box. In that way, the museum's online presence is similar to a real museum, where a vast collection is just waiting to be stumbled upon.</p>
        <p>''There's 12 years of material there, and we don't take things down,'' Mr. Hipschman said. ''Even I get lost in it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
