<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Four Minutes Of R&amp;B Angst; Two Lifetimes Of Originality</title>
    <meta content="07play" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/07/arts/07play.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1759847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC: PLAYLIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Playlist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Avant</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Owens, Buck</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McLean, Jackie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DB1E3FF934A35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Four Minutes Of R&amp;B Angst; Two Lifetimes Of Originality</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Four Minutes of R&amp;B Angst; Two Lifetimes of Originality</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ben Ratliff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews five new CD's; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Avant</p>
        <p>The new single by the R&amp;B singer Avant is called ''Four Minutes,'' and it's the kind of concept that comes to a songwriter complete as a single thought, with a bow wrapped around it. (Though one suspects it did not come simultaneously to the six songwriters credited.) It's about a guy who hears that his woman is leaving him, calls her frantically, and says he'll be there in 10 minutes -- no, 5 -- no, 4. There's a clock rhythm at the back of the drum programming, but the song is a ballad. So the tempo is nice and easy, yet you are subconsciously reminded, from a songwriter's or producer's perspective, how well each bar must be designed. This is the song's masterstroke. Of course, Avant's out of luck; you can't have a panic, a chase and a reconciliation in so short a song. In the video, she offers him her middle finger and a few farewell insults, then speeds away in cab as he is running the final block to her doorstep.) Equally obviously, the song ends at four minutes exactly.</p>
        <p>Buck Owens and Jackie McLean</p>
        <p>Beyond the fact that they both died within one depressing week at the end of March, the country singer Buck Owens and the jazz alto saxophonist Jackie McLean had something else in common: musical forthrightness. They broke through the crust of their contexts. Buck Owens and the Buckaroos developed their sound in the bars of Bakersfield, Calif., with loud, trebly blasts of Telecaster guitars and vocal harmonies in thirds, patterned after traditional Mexican music. Mr. McLean adapted Charlie Parker's lines, harmonies and rhythms, but blaringly and more than a touch sharply. They also made their best music at around the same time: Mr. Owens from 1961 to 1966 on Capitol, Mr. McLean from 1959 to 1967 on Blue Note. In Owens records like one I've recently had on constant repeat, ''On the Bandstand'' (Sundazed), Mr. Owens and his bandmate Don Rich recorded their vocals like driving nails into wood, while lead and steel guitar were allowed to rise high in the mix. And on Mr. McLean's ''Bluesnik'' (Blue Note), an old favorite that has become a favorite again, the saxophonist's cry is extruded almost brazenly from a standard post-bop ensemble sound. This is the kind of music that turns you on for life: I'm sure I'm not the only one who heard Buck or Jackie and decided I had to know more about the forces that produced them.</p>
        <p>Zach Hill and Mick Barr</p>
        <p>Both of these musicians have conditioned themselves to going all out all the time: Mick Barr as the guitarist in Orthrelm, and Zach Hill as the drummer in Hella, among other bands. In ''Shred Earthship'' (Kill Rock Stars), the shaggy, sweaty, delirious first results of their new duo project, Mr. Barr plays cascades of rapidly phrased lines, but gets momentum from maniacal repetition. Mr. Hill keeps his drum kit on permanent heavy rumble, with incredibly fast strokes of a single kick drum and a carpet of cymbal sounds. It's nasty, heavy-gauge noise-rock that could never exist if not for jazz: the heart of it is late Coltrane and early jazz-rock fusion at the same time, ''Interstellar Space'' and the Mahavishnu Orchestra. But they seem to have learned the lesson of the Kyoto Protocol: too many greenhouse gases, even musical ones, will be our ruin. Those older forms have inspired heaps of musicians to emit too many notes, too loudly and for too long, with too many improvising at once. Here, the fact that there are only two people playing, and in real time, gives you all the intensity you need without the possibility of overload.</p>
        <p>Jolie Holland</p>
        <p>Ms. Holland is a Texas singer-songwriter with a badly behaved voice. Her pronunciation is almost Southern cockney, and she can swallow and muffle words, as if shy or disinterested. But she has absorbed her Billie Holiday and, one assumes, Cat Power, as well as Appalachian singing styles. Her third album, ''Springtime Can Kill You'' (Anti), can be too precious even as it aims for knockabout junk-shop roughness. But some of these songs have a kind of lingering power, particularly the title track, with the drummer playing a clattery version of jazz triplets, an instrumental chorus shared by a baritone horn and Ms. Holland's whistling.</p>
        <p>Bennie Maupin</p>
        <p>''Penumbra'' (Cryptogramophone) marks the return of the musician who played the spidery, sepulchral bass clarinet lines all over Miles Davis's ''Bitches Brew.'' Mr. Maupin, who also plays saxophones and flute as well as some piano, has lived in California since 1972, enduring the career limitations of West Coast jazz. He has a patient, concentrated, self-possessed sound, as if he has a lot of time, knows what he can do and isn't interested in blowing you away all at once. The new record, with a California band, is immensely satisfying: a sustained mood of laid-back wariness, at times close to chamber music, with lots of space in the music and grooves played subtly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reviews of new releases by Avant, Buck Owens and Jackie McLean, Zach Hill and Mick Barr, Jolie Holland and Bennie Maupin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Avant</p>
        <p>The new single by the R&amp;B singer Avant is called ''Four Minutes,'' and it's the kind of concept that comes to a songwriter complete as a single thought, with a bow wrapped around it. (Though one suspects it did not come simultaneously to the six songwriters credited.) It's about a guy who hears that his woman is leaving him, calls her frantically, and says he'll be there in 10 minutes -- no, 5 -- no, 4. There's a clock rhythm at the back of the drum programming, but the song is a ballad. So the tempo is nice and easy, yet you are subconsciously reminded, from a songwriter's or producer's perspective, how well each bar must be designed. This is the song's masterstroke. Of course, Avant's out of luck; you can't have a panic, a chase and a reconciliation in so short a song. In the video, she offers him her middle finger and a few farewell insults, then speeds away in cab as he is running the final block to her doorstep.) Equally obviously, the song ends at four minutes exactly.</p>
        <p>Buck Owens and Jackie McLean</p>
        <p>Beyond the fact that they both died within one depressing week at the end of March, the country singer Buck Owens and the jazz alto saxophonist Jackie McLean had something else in common: musical forthrightness. They broke through the crust of their contexts. Buck Owens and the Buckaroos developed their sound in the bars of Bakersfield, Calif., with loud, trebly blasts of Telecaster guitars and vocal harmonies in thirds, patterned after traditional Mexican music. Mr. McLean adapted Charlie Parker's lines, harmonies and rhythms, but blaringly and more than a touch sharply. They also made their best music at around the same time: Mr. Owens from 1961 to 1966 on Capitol, Mr. McLean from 1959 to 1967 on Blue Note. In Owens records like one I've recently had on constant repeat, ''On the Bandstand'' (Sundazed), Mr. Owens and his bandmate Don Rich recorded their vocals like driving nails into wood, while lead and steel guitar were allowed to rise high in the mix. And on Mr. McLean's ''Bluesnik'' (Blue Note), an old favorite that has become a favorite again, the saxophonist's cry is extruded almost brazenly from a standard post-bop ensemble sound. This is the kind of music that turns you on for life: I'm sure I'm not the only one who heard Buck or Jackie and decided I had to know more about the forces that produced them.</p>
        <p>Zach Hill and Mick Barr</p>
        <p>Both of these musicians have conditioned themselves to going all out all the time: Mick Barr as the guitarist in Orthrelm, and Zach Hill as the drummer in Hella, among other bands. In ''Shred Earthship'' (Kill Rock Stars), the shaggy, sweaty, delirious first results of their new duo project, Mr. Barr plays cascades of rapidly phrased lines, but gets momentum from maniacal repetition. Mr. Hill keeps his drum kit on permanent heavy rumble, with incredibly fast strokes of a single kick drum and a carpet of cymbal sounds. It's nasty, heavy-gauge noise-rock that could never exist if not for jazz: the heart of it is late Coltrane and early jazz-rock fusion at the same time, ''Interstellar Space'' and the Mahavishnu Orchestra. But they seem to have learned the lesson of the Kyoto Protocol: too many greenhouse gases, even musical ones, will be our ruin. Those older forms have inspired heaps of musicians to emit too many notes, too loudly and for too long, with too many improvising at once. Here, the fact that there are only two people playing, and in real time, gives you all the intensity you need without the possibility of overload.</p>
        <p>Jolie Holland</p>
        <p>Ms. Holland is a Texas singer-songwriter with a badly behaved voice. Her pronunciation is almost Southern cockney, and she can swallow and muffle words, as if shy or disinterested. But she has absorbed her Billie Holiday and, one assumes, Cat Power, as well as Appalachian singing styles. Her third album, ''Springtime Can Kill You'' (Anti), can be too precious even as it aims for knockabout junk-shop roughness. But some of these songs have a kind of lingering power, particularly the title track, with the drummer playing a clattery version of jazz triplets, an instrumental chorus shared by a baritone horn and Ms. Holland's whistling.</p>
        <p>Bennie Maupin</p>
        <p>''Penumbra'' (Cryptogramophone) marks the return of the musician who played the spidery, sepulchral bass clarinet lines all over Miles Davis's ''Bitches Brew.'' Mr. Maupin, who also plays saxophones and flute as well as some piano, has lived in California since 1972, enduring the career limitations of West Coast jazz. He has a patient, concentrated, self-possessed sound, as if he has a lot of time, knows what he can do and isn't interested in blowing you away all at once. The new record, with a California band, is immensely satisfying: a sustained mood of laid-back wariness, at times close to chamber music, with lots of space in the music and grooves played subtly.  MUSIC: PLAYLIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
