<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>P What? PZEV's Are Unsung Heroes in the Push to Clean Up the Air</title>
    <meta content="30PZEV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/30/automobiles/30PZEV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1779491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="GREEN TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric and Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Motavalli, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFDD123FF933A05754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>P What? PZEV's Are Unsung Heroes in the Push to Clean Up the Air</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">P What? PZEV’s Are Unsung Heroes in the Push to Clean Up the Air</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM MOTAVALLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Motavalli, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Partial emissions vehicle standards refers to cars certified to standard set by California regulators; cars that meet criteria are specially equipped versions of familiar models that use improved pollution-control system to meet California's toughest tailpipe standard for cars with combustion engines; exhaust can be as clean as that of many hybrids, yet cars do not incur hybrid's price premium of several thousand dollars; few buyers know about these cars, as they have not been promoted heavily; chart; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you think you can help the environment by parking your car and walking, you may be dismayed to learn this: that parked car -- even if it is a recent model officially designated as a low-emission vehicle, according to the California Air Resources Board -- gives off more pollutants even when shut off than some new models do while driving down the road.</p>
        <p>The clean-running cars in question are those certified to a standard set by California regulators that is known as PZEV -- bureaucratic shorthand for a partial zero emission vehicle. They are also available, or soon will be, in a handful of states on the West Coast and in the Northeast that have adopted California's emissions rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Partial zero emission technology is available, or soon will be, in some popular vehicles in a handful of states that have adopted California’s emissions rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you think you can help the environment by parking your car and walking, you may be dismayed to learn this: that parked car -- even if it is a recent model officially designated as a low-emission vehicle, according to the California Air Resources Board -- gives off more pollutants even when shut off than some new models do while driving down the road.</p>
        <p>The clean-running cars in question are those certified to a standard set by California regulators that is known as PZEV -- bureaucratic shorthand for a partial zero emission vehicle. They are also available, or soon will be, in a handful of states on the West Coast and in the Northeast that have adopted California's emissions rules.</p>
        <p>According to the air quality agency, some 500,000 PZEV's are already on California roads, though their drivers may not even be aware of the contribution they are making to air quality. These are not the sort of vehicles that young enthusiasts spot from blocks away and point at excitedly.</p>
        <p>PZEV's hide in plain sight as specially equipped versions of cars as familiar as the Chevrolet Cobalt, the Ford Fusion, the Honda Accord and the Volvo V70, usually with four- or six-cylinder engines. They use an improved pollution-control system to meet California's toughest tailpipe standard for cars with combustion engines. The system carries a factory emissions warranty stretched to 15 years or 150,000 miles, from 10 years and 120,000 miles.</p>
        <p>Because a PZEV complies with tailpipe standards for a SULEV, or super ultra low emission vehicle, the exhaust can be as clean as that of many hybrids -- yet the cars do not incur the hybrid's price premium of several thousand dollars. PZEV's generally cost consumers no more than identical models that do not have the squeaky-clean certification, which are built for states that have not adopted California's rules, though they are estimated to cost automakers between $200 and $500 extra to produce. That money buys special parts like a steel gas tank, a catalytic converter with more precious metals inside, a larger trap for evaporative fumes and in some cases, an air injection system.</p>
        <p>One might think that green-leaning drivers would be lining up for this relative bargain, especially in light of some hybrid models' commanding a price well above the window sticker. But hybrids still enjoy a perception of phenomenal fuel economy in the public's eye while a PZEV's fuel economy rating is the same as its non-PZEV counterpart. And there is a powerful draw to the hybrid's earth-friendly reputation.</p>
        <p>To be sure, a hybrid still comes out ahead in overall environmental impact, because while it is driving on its electric motor alone it produces no pollutants and uses no gasoline (so it produces no carbon dioxide).</p>
        <p>An important part of the PZEV's advantage is its elimination of evaporative emissions, the gasoline fumes that escape during refueling or, especially on hot days, from the fuel tank and supply lines. Even a car that is not running can emit a significant amount of evaporative pollution -- perhaps 25 percent of the vehicle's total emissions, the air resources board says -- so the special fuel system makes a real difference in air quality.</p>
        <p>Few buyers know about these below-the-radar green machines. Automakers have not promoted them heavily, as they have done with hybrids, and an informal survey of salespeople at dealerships turned up more confusion than useful information.</p>
        <p>Jim Kliesch, a research associate at the American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy, an environmental nonprofit group, and the author of the council's annual Green Book guide to cars and trucks, admits that California's alphabet soup of emission levels is ''pretty confusing stuff. They haven't made the nomenclature very easy.''</p>
        <p>PZEV's might be better known if the process that created them had not been so convoluted. The effort began in 1990 when California established its Zero Emission Vehicle program to reduce smog. The original goal called for 2 percent of new cars and trucks sold in California in 1998 to produce no emissions at all, with the percentage increasing in steps to 10 percent in 2003.</p>
        <p>The plan, which essentially mandated battery-powered vehicles, came under attack by automakers and oil companies as unachievable, and has been considerably modified over the years. But the 2 percent rule for zero-emission cars is still in place, said Jerry Martin, a spokesman. The difference is that a compromise was struck to allow automakers to earn credits against the obligation to ''produce, deliver for sale and put in service'' zero-emission vehicles by selling hybrids or PZEV's.</p>
        <p>The phase-in began in 2005 and the percentages are scheduled to increase in coming years. Credits may be sold, traded or banked for the future, and some carmakers are meeting the mandate with credits earned in past years. The rules stipulate penalties for failure to meet the goals.</p>
        <p>Although manufacturers get just a fraction of the credit for a PZEV car that they would get from a fuel-cell or a battery-electric vehicle, the PZEV's are produced in such large numbers that the credits accumulate and keep the manufacturers within the bounds of the state mandate. In the worst case, noncompliance could result in a manufacturer losing the right to sell cars and trucks in California.</p>
        <p>All new cars sold in the United States must meet at least federal emissions standards. With the worst air quality in the nation, California won the right to set tougher limits, and some states have adopted California's laws in place of the federal rules set by the Environmental Protection Agency. The states that have passed or are phasing in California rules are New York, Massachusetts, Connecticut, Maine, New Jersey, Oregon, Rhode Island, Vermont and Washington (and Pennsylvania has begun the process as well); together, the California-compliant states account for about a third of all cars sold in this country.</p>
        <p>Theoretically, then, the PZEV's that are made by manufacturers in 2006 are, or soon will be, available at dealers in those states. But with nearly no advertising for PZEV's, the vehicles have a low profile.</p>
        <p>Automakers say they are not trying to hide their PZEV's. One challenge, according to Chris Naughton, a Honda spokesman, is that companies do not want to promise what they cannot deliver in a market that is a patchwork of California and non-California states. ''If we run ads, we run the risk of having them bleed over into states where PZEV's are not available,'' he said.</p>
        <p>How much cleaner are PZEV tailpipes? In terms of one common pollutant, oxides of nitrogen, today's federal standard for an average car, known as Tier 2 Bin 5, is 0.07 grams per mile. But PZEV's have to meet the California SULEV II standard, which allows only .02 grams per mile.</p>
        <p>''They're 70 percent cleaner than cars that are pretty darn clean to begin with,'' said David Hermance, executive engineer for advanced technology vehicles at Toyota.</p>
        <p>Ethanol additives to gasoline in some states pose a challenge to PZEV evaporative emission performance. Steve Mazure, a DaimlerChrysler spokesman, said that solving the problem may require new engine parts to deal with ethanol. DaimlerChrysler, which sold 20,000 Dodge Stratus and Chrysler Sebring PZEV's in the 2004 and 2005 model years but is not currently offering any, publicized its PZEV's through corporate environmental reports, dealer training and vehicle press kits.</p>
        <p>Ford has sold 185,000 Focus PZEV's since 2003, and according to Alan Hall, a spokesman, it hopes to raise the awareness of its clean cars with an exterior badge that incorporates the company's environmental logo -- a green-leaf and highway symbol -- and lettering that spells out its status as a partial zero emission vehicle.</p>
        <p>In California, where an estimated 90 percent of all PZEV's have been sold so far, the visibility of these cars is increasing. The air resources group and its cheering section in the environmental community hope that the number of participating states will soon reach the point that it become cost-effective for carmakers to simply build one version -- the PZEV -- for the whole country.</p>
        <p>By 2012 California could have as many as three million PZEV's on the road, the agency says. ''We expect this to be the dominant technology,'' Mr. Martin said. ''And it won't matter if people can say what the acronym stands for, because everyone they know will be driving one.''</p>
        <p>GREEN TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
