<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid the Ivy, A Battle About The Climate</title>
    <meta content="21leonhardt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/21/business/21leonhardt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1827802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nordhaus, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Yale University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stern, Nicholas</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E7D7123EF932A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid the Ivy, A Battle About The Climate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Battle Over the Costs of Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Leonhardt column on controversy surrounding report led by Sir Nicholas Stern, top adviser to British government, that calls for 'urgent action' against global warming to prevent economic damage that could rival world wars and Great Depression; holds many American economists think that Sir Nicholas may have exaggerated likely speed of warming, among other things, and overstated case for big, quick action; says epicenter of opposition has been at Yale, where Sir Nicholas engaged in debate; says most influential critics has been Yale Prof William Nordhaus; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is an unofficial code of conduct that dictates how intellectuals should behave when they're jousting with each other, a sort of Geneva Convention for the ivory tower.</p>
        <p>Before they attack somebody else's work, they first need to praise their opponent. A typical way to do so is to describe another professor as a distinguished scholar who has made an important contribution to the research literature. When you hear that, you can be pretty sure things are about to get nasty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A British economist calls for urgent, sweeping action. Some Americans call him alarmist. Who is right?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is an unofficial code of conduct that dictates how intellectuals should behave when they're jousting with each other, a sort of Geneva Convention for the ivory tower.</p>
        <p>Before they attack somebody else's work, they first need to praise their opponent. A typical way to do so is to describe another professor as a distinguished scholar who has made an important contribution to the research literature. When you hear that, you can be pretty sure things are about to get nasty.</p>
        <p>The rest of us can usually ignore these spats, but once in a while there is an academic fight that really matters. The economics profession is engaged in one of those right now and, as luck would have it, it's even more entertaining than most.</p>
        <p>Last week, Sir Nicholas Stern, a top adviser to the British government, came to the United States to talk about climate change. In October, a commission he led released a 700-page report  calling for ''urgent action'' against global warming to prevent economic damage that could rival that of the world wars and the Great Depression. Given its source and its tone, the Stern Review has nudged people to talk more seriously about climate change.</p>
        <p>In the minds of a lot of American economists, however, the review is a badly flawed piece of work. These economists don't doubt that earth is getting hotter, that human activity is the cause and that the results could be bad. But they think that Sir Nicholas may have exaggerated the likely speed of warming, among other things, and overstated the case for big, quick action.</p>
        <p>The epicenter of the opposition has been here at Yale, and so last week, after stopping in Washington to testify before Congress, Sir Nicholas came to New Haven for a public debate with his critics. With a couple of hundred students and professors in the audience -- and a sculpture of an angry Zeus-like figure looming above the stage -- the two sides went at it in the dignified, vicious way that academics do.</p>
        <p>Sir Nicholas spoke during the morning, and his case  is really quite simple. The carbon dioxide that has already been pumped into the atmosphere guarantees that the planet will keep getting warmer. But the decisions that people make over the next couple of decades will determine how much warmer -- and, in all likelihood, how many floods, droughts, hurricanes, crop failures and species extinctions occur. The surest way to reduce emissions is a big economic deterrent, like a carbon tax.</p>
        <p>''The later we leave it, the more difficult it will be,'' he said, ''and the more risks you run.''</p>
        <p>The Stern Review's most influential critic has probably been William Nordhaus,  a 65-year-old Yale professor who is as mainstream as economists come. Jeffrey D. Sachs, the anti-poverty advocate, calls Mr. Nordhaus ''about the most reasonable man I know.''</p>
        <p>He was the first speaker after lunch, and, of course, he had some very nice things to say about Sir Nicholas. The report ''was presented here very eloquently by a distinguished scholar,'' Mr. Nordhaus said. But then came the juicy stuff: the Stern Review ''commits cruel and unusual punishment on the English language,'' Mr. Nordhaus said, and the British government's opinion on climate change is no more infallible than was its prewar view about weapons of mass destruction in Iraq.</p>
        <p>This was fairly tame compared with the comments of another Yale economist, Robert O. Mendelsohn.  ''I was awestruck,'' he said, comparing Sir Nicholas to ''The Wizard of Oz.'' But ''my job is to be Toto,'' he added, in the same good-humored tone Mr. Nordhaus used. ''Is it in fact The Wizard of Oz, or is it nothing at all?''</p>
        <p>The two professors raised some questions about the science in the Stern Review. Mr. Nordhaus wondered if carbon emissions and temperatures would rise as quickly as the report suggests, and Mr. Mendelsohn predicted that people would learn to adapt to climate change, reducing its ultimate cost.</p>
        <p>But their main objection  revolved around something called the discount rate. The Stern Review assumed that a dollar of economic damage prevented a century from now (adjusted for inflation) is roughly as valuable as a dollar spent reducing emissions today. In effect, the report argues for spending the money to cut emissions because future generations have as much claim on resources as current generations. ''I've still not heard a decent ethical argument'' for believing otherwise, Sir Nicholas said at the debate.</p>
        <p>I'm guessing that your instinct is to agree with him. Mine certainly was. The problem is that none of us actually behave this way. If we really thought that our great-grandchild deserved our money as much as we do, we would never go out to dinner again. Instead, we would invest the $50 we would have spent on dinner, confident that it would grow over time and become perhaps $1,000 for our great-grandchild to put toward health care, education or a supercomputer. Any of that is preferable to our measly dinner.</p>
        <p>But a dollar today truly is more valuable than a dollar a century from now. For one thing, your great-grandchild will almost certainly be richer than you are and won't need your money as much as you do. So spending a dollar on carbon reduction today to avoid a dollar's worth of economic damage in 2107 doesn't make sense. We would be better off putting the money toward something likely to have a higher return than alternative energy, like education.</p>
        <p>Technically, then, Sir Nicholas's opponents win the debate. But in practical terms, their argument has a weak link. They are assuming that the economic gains from, say, education will make future generations rich enough to make up for any damage caused by climate change. Sea walls will be able to protect cities; technology can allow crops to grow in new ways; better medicines can stop the spread of disease.</p>
        <p>No one knows whether this is true, let alone desirable, because no one knows what life will be like on a planet that is five degrees hotter. ''If ever there was an example where there was uncertainty, this is it,'' said Martin L. Weitzman,  a Harvard economist who attended the debate.</p>
        <p>While sitting there, I was reminded of the speeches that Alan Greenspan gave a few years ago about the risks of deflation. It wasn't the most likely outcome, he said, but the consequences of it could be so bad that policy makers had to take steps to prevent it. Focusing attention on this point -- the catastrophic risks of climate change -- is Sir Nicholas's biggest accomplishment, whatever you think of his math.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Weitzman puts it, the Stern Review is ''right for the wrong reasons.''</p>
        <p>Even its critics seem open to this idea. When Mr. Nordhaus and Sir Nicholas were exchanging e-mail messages before the debate -- to their credit, some academics keep their arguments from becoming personal -- Mr. Nordhaus sent a note that summed up his view. ''I think it's a great study, but it's 50 years ahead of its time,'' he recalled writing. ''Since everybody else is 50 years behind the times, if you average the two, you might come out just right.''</p>
        <p>In other words, it's time for a tax on carbon emissions.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIX</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
