<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Corporate Hippies' Seek Their Bliss In a New Environmental Economy</title>
    <meta content="07jobs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Business of Green" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/07/business/businessspecial2/07jobs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1831215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rainforest Alliance</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DA1531F934A35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Corporate Hippies' Seek Their Bliss In a New Environmental Economy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Corporate Hippies’ Seek Their Bliss in a New Environmental Economy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHANGE once came slowly to the job market for people seeking careers focused on the environment. No more.</p>
        <p>There were signs as early as the 1980s, when the Rainforest Alliance began working with businesses to create a program for identifying environmentally sound wood products: more graduates were taking jobs outside traditional environmental arenas like engineering, waste management, policy development, law and resource protection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those interested in environmental work are looking to financial firms, small businesses and even corporations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHANGE once came slowly to the job market for people seeking careers focused on the environment. No more.</p>
        <p>There were signs as early as the 1980s, when the Rainforest Alliance began working with businesses to create a program for identifying environmentally sound wood products: more graduates were taking jobs outside traditional environmental arenas like engineering, waste management, policy development, law and resource protection.</p>
        <p>The shift gathered steam in the 1990s, when companies like Starbucks and Nike started to integrate such concerns into everyday business practices.</p>
        <p>Early this decade, Daniel C. Esty, a professor of environmental law and policy at Yale University, noticed changes in the goals of younger students and the kinds of jobs students took when they left the Yale School of Forestry and the Environment.</p>
        <p>Law and science, which were traditional environmental specialties, still attracted many students; but a newer one, corporate environmental management, was growing. The latest ones -- finance, venture investment, entrepreneurialism -- barely registered.</p>
        <p>''I am overwhelmed by how this has evolved,'' Dr. Esty said recently.</p>
        <p>Students still gravitate toward nongovernmental organizations, advocacy groups and government, but a large plurality of the current generation interested in environmental work are looking elsewhere, particularly to financial firms, small businesses and even corporations. They seek employment there because, among other things, they think that is where they can have the greatest impact.</p>
        <p>''It's extraordinary how many students see themselves as going into business as a place to have leverage on the issues,'' Dr. Esty said.</p>
        <p>Take Samantha Unger, 27, a graduate of Barnard College and the school of engineering at Columbia University. She started with a summer job in a California program, trading state-issued pollution-emission credits. Now she trades credits for greenhouse gas emissions at Evolution Markets, a company in White Plains.</p>
        <p>''I would call myself a corporate hippie,'' she said. ''I'm in the business of definitely caring for and supporting environmental growth and change for the better, but I also believe in the growth of business. And from the beginning I have believed there should be a cost associated with pollution.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Unger and her colleague Jason Patrick, 34, are examples of what Charles F. Mason, a professor of economics at the University of Wyoming, describes as a new driving force. ''The person who knows how to play the financial markets, the middleman looking for someone who has something to sell and can anticipate who will buy it,'' he said -- they will make a real difference.</p>
        <p>None of the academics, employers or young professionals would call these boom times for environmental employment; plenty of graduates with degrees in environmental science must work at finding a job. But all say they are witnessing both an upward trend in the number of jobs and a change in the definition of environmental work.</p>
        <p>''The issues themselves have changed -- climate change is far and away an example of that,'' said Kevin Doyle, the national director of program development for the Environmental Careers Organization, a nonprofit group that places recent graduates in environmental internships at federal agencies, businesses, nonprofit groups and state and local governments.</p>
        <p>''Businesses as businesses are becoming actors of environmental sustainability, either because they want to, or they feel they can do good public relations, or because they have to,'' Mr. Doyle said. ''The axis of influence is starting to shift from a more exclusive focus on activists and government. You can work in business because you're an environmentalist.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doyle and others named several paths to environmental work: law, government, nonprofit groups and, increasingly, management and finance, often in alternative energy.</p>
        <p>Private employers providing environmental jobs include Goldman Sachs, General Electric, Nike, Timberland, engineering consultants and philanthropic foundations. Some workers bounce among the various subgroups, adding skills as they go.</p>
        <p>Jesse Johnson, 36, graduated from Princeton in 1993 and worked in finance in Hong Kong. He said that he loved the intensity of finance and the intellectual caliber of his co-workers, but missed ''the things that motivated me in college -- the environment, the outdoors.''</p>
        <p>He returned to Yale and graduated in 2002 with joint master's degrees in environmental management and business. When he finished, he and a friend started a furniture business, the Q Collection, in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''It took a while to get it up and running,'' Mr. Johnson said of the company, which is not yet profitable. ''It's home furnishings, furniture, textiles, baby furniture. But we add a whole new layer. We are thinking about sustainability.''</p>
        <p>Right now, the horizontal expansion of environmental careers is most evident among the 20- and 30-something age groups. They have been trained in what Mr. Doyle called the ''sustainable ecosystems'' mind-set of this generation's environmental policy makers, blending scientific understanding with concerns like economics or social justice.</p>
        <p>Many switch among environmental jobs -- starting out, say, at a nonprofit, then getting a master's degree and ending up at a business.</p>
        <p>While Jill Gravender was an undergraduate in economics and taking an ecology class at Arizona State University, she said, ''It became apparent to me that when you're thinking about economics, environmental issues are all considered to be market externalities.'' The two disciplines, she said, ''were talking past one another; I realized I wanted to be that facilitator.''</p>
        <p>After college, she got policy jobs with the New America Foundation and the nonprofit California Climate Action Registry, which collects data on various companies' greenhouse gas emissions. She went back to get a master's degree in environmental science and management at the University of California at Santa Barbara and now, at 33, is director of water programs for a small foundation called Environment Now.</p>
        <p>It is not just industrial concerns that are adding environmental jobs. In 1992, Shelley Billik started as a recycling coordinator at Warner Brothers. Now she is vice president for environmental projects. ''When I started in 1992, it was just me,'' she said. ''Now we have a staff of four in the office and a recycling crew of seven.''</p>
        <p>''The place where the department fits'' has changed as well, she added, becoming part of corporate strategy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
