<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lively or Sedate, a Spot Carves Out Its Own Niche</title>
    <meta content="06dineliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/06dineli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/BRIGHTWATERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sea Levels (Brightwaters, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seafood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DB103EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lively or Sedate, a Spot Carves Out Its Own Niche</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lively or Sedate, a Spot Carves Out Its Own Niche</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Sea Levels restaurant in Brightwaters, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOUT 30 years ago a charming little restaurant called As Time Goes By put Brightwaters on Long Island's culinary map. That place closed a while ago, but an equally attractive spot, Sea Levels, has been drawing crowds to the same location since it opened last November.</p>
        <p>The scene is especially lively in the bar on Thursdays through Saturdays, when there is music (two singer-guitarists on a recent Saturday). Besides the long wooden bar itself, the furnishings include one big round table for large groups and a number of small high tables. The bar also has a separate tavern menu.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sea Levels in Brightwaters has been drawing crowds since it opened last November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOUT 30 years ago a charming little restaurant called As Time Goes By put Brightwaters on Long Island's culinary map. That place closed a while ago, but an equally attractive spot, Sea Levels, has been drawing crowds to the same location since it opened last November.</p>
        <p>The scene is especially lively in the bar on Thursdays through Saturdays, when there is music (two singer-guitarists on a recent Saturday). Besides the long wooden bar itself, the furnishings include one big round table for large groups and a number of small high tables. The bar also has a separate tavern menu.</p>
        <p>In comparison, the dining room is sedate, separated from the bar by a sliding French door that does a good job of keeping out the din. The seating is eclectic and fun: big squishy couches, imposing armchairs, banquettes and small wooden chairs. The room is aglow with votive candles on the tables and along a ledge on the wainscoted wall.</p>
        <p>John Montgomery, the chef and owner of Sea Levels, was formerly executive chef at the Bridge in West Islip and earlier at the Garden City Hotel.</p>
        <p>Though popular wisdom suggests that a restaurant would be better on a slow weeknight than on a busy Saturday, that was not the case here. On the weekend we had a near-perfect meal with snappy service and well-turned-out food. On a Tuesday, though, everything was a bit off. There were long waits between courses, and the meal dragged.</p>
        <p>Even the breadbasket had its ups and downs. It was a delight on the weekend, when it held warm crusty rolls, slices of country bread and addictive seed-covered flatbreads. On Tuesday the basket was skimpy and was never refilled.</p>
        <p>The food that night was also not what it had been on Saturday. (I wondered if Mr. Montgomery was in the kitchen.) The mixed grill contained an unimpressive filet mignon and a dry lamb chop along with its two jumbo shrimp; the chicken Milanese was dry, the swordfish with Parmesan crust mushy.</p>
        <p>The star entree on Saturday was a special of thyme-infused broiled halibut, accompanied by crunchy asparagus and roasted fingerling potatoes. The fish was snowy white and flaky. Other hits from the seafood side of the menu were pan-seared rare tuna with a three-spice rub and baked king salmon topped with crab meat. Carnivores gave high marks to the juicy rib-eye steak covered with wispy onion rings.</p>
        <p>Diners debating which soup to order should go for the creamy, flavorful lobster bisque; the chicken corn chowder was bland.</p>
        <p>Salads were winners. We liked the classic Caesar, as well as a version under a blizzard of crispy rock shrimp, and the green salad topped with tender, crunchy calamari. Fluffy arugula with slices of apple, candied walnuts and a medallion of goat cheese also drew praise. The Long Island duck cakes, similar to crab cakes, were tasty and enhanced by corn salsa and drizzles of chipotle sour cream on the plate.</p>
        <p>On both our visits, dessert was the high point of the meal. Every one of the house-made treats was memorable. The most impressive-looking was the big brownie sundae, which featured a moist square covered with malted-milk-ball ice cream and a mound of whipped cream. Another chocolate success was the dark chocolate bread pudding, which resembled a very moist and delicious individual chocolate cake.</p>
        <p>The cheesecake portion was small but good and creamy. The warm apple crisp crowned with vanilla ice cream kept the winning streak going.</p>
        <p>Sea Levels</p>
        <p>391 North Windsor Avenue  Brightwaters  (631) 665-8300  www.sealevelsrestaurant.com</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Charming; divided between a sedate dining room and a lively bar. Wheelchair accessible.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Casual and young, mainly couples; some children on weeknights.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Bustling, especially on Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays when there is live entertainment. The list of 38 wines ($27 to $93) is a bit pricey; only one bottle is below $30. Nine wines by the glass, $6 to $12.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Entrees $8 to $16 at lunch and on the tavern menu, $19 to $29 at dinner. A $21.95 three-course meal is served from 4:30 to 7 p.m. Tuesday to Thursday. American Express, MasterCard, Visa and Discover are accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Lobster bisque, Caesar salad (with or without shrimp), calamari salad, duck cakes, arugula salad; rib-eye steak, salmon, tuna, halibut; all desserts.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Open 4 to 10 p.m. Tuesday, noon to 10 p.m. Wednesday, noon to midnight Thursday and Friday and 4 p.m. to midnight Saturday. Closed Sunday and Monday. Reservations are recommended.</p>
        <p>Reviewed May 6, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/BRIGHTWATERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
