<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The President And Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="l05warming" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DB163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The President And Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush Splits on Greenhouse Gases With Congress and State Officials'' (front page, April 4):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush Splits on Greenhouse Gases With Congress and State Officials'' (front page, April 4):</p>
        <p>I suggest that President Bush, the automakers and the coal industry wake up and smell the greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Instead of stubbornly standing in the way of progress, they have the opportunity to demonstrate true leadership by using this country's vaunted technological know-how to pivot into action. The tired excuse that ''China has to do it, too'' rings false, since we create far more heat-trapping gases per capita than any other country on the planet.</p>
        <p>If we can put a man on the moon, we can surely put hybrid cars, fuel efficiency and clean coal technology on the front burner without damaging our economy.</p>
        <p>Voluntary steps are clearly insufficient, and Americans are hungry for government support of these vital undertakings.</p>
        <p>Alexandra Forbes  Wingdale, N.Y., April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You report, ''A day after the Supreme Court ruled that the federal government had the authority to regulate heat-trapping gases, President Bush said he thought that the measures he had taken so far were sufficient.''</p>
        <p>Am I the only one who wants a president who strives for more than just enough?</p>
        <p>On the other hand, it does do wonders in explaining why New Orleans and Iraq are still such disasters.</p>
        <p>Barbara Davilman  Studio City, Calif., April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>President Bush, when asked about the Supreme Court decision on greenhouse gas emissions, said, ''Whatever we do must be in concert with what happens internationally.'' He added, ''Unless there is an accord with China, China will produce greenhouse gases that will offset anything we do in a brief period of time.''</p>
        <p>Assuming this is true, this does not have to be a recipe for inaction. Our government could heavily tax goods and services from countries that are big polluters (including our own country, one of the biggest) and reward the relatively nonpolluting countries.</p>
        <p>Our government can do a lot in the international arena regarding the pollution of other countries by simply making the goods and services of big polluters less attractive. We don't have to wait for them to get their act together.</p>
        <p>Ronald Gans  New York, April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Justices Say E.P.A. Has Power to Act on Harmful Gases'' (front page, April 3):</p>
        <p>Let us not forget that the four justices who almost blocked the Supreme Court's demand that the administration enforce environmental standards were appointed by President Ronald Reagan and the first and second Bush administrations for their perceived conservative beliefs.</p>
        <p>Those who call for more conservative justices to rule on matters like abortion should recognize that this comes with environmental costs as well.</p>
        <p>Peter K. Frost  Oxford, Miss., April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 12, 2007, Thursday  A letter from Wingdale, N.Y., last Thursday about global warming referred incorrectly to the United States' production of heat-trapping gases. It is the leader in emissions over all, but not per capita.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A letter from Wingdale, N.Y., last Thursday about global warming referred incorrectly to the United States' production of heat-trapping gases. It is the leader in emissions over all, but not per capita.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
