<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Mayors' Summit, Bloomberg Campaigns for Clean Air</title>
    <meta content="16climate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/16/nyregion/16climate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Conference of Mayors</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardwell, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Palmer, Douglas (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DA1331F935A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Mayors' Summit, Bloomberg Campaigns for Clean Air</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Mayors’ Summit, Bloomberg Campaigns for Clean Air</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL; Ray Rivera contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Michael R Bloomberg says cities are responsible for 80 percent of world's greenhouse emissions and must take lead in addressing issue of global wawrming where national governments have not; highlights 'greenprint' for guiding New York City's development over next 23 years in environmentally sustainable way; Mayor Douglas H Palmer of Trenton announces that 500 cities have signed onto US Conference of Mayor's agreement requiring them to reduce emissions below 1990 levels; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg thrust himself onto an international stage yesterday as a champion of the environment, telling a roomful of leaders from this country and overseas that the solution to global warming lay with the world's mayors.</p>
        <p>Addressing roughly 250 mayors and other leaders over lunch at the Jumeirah Essex House on Central Park South, Mr. Bloomberg argued that cities, which are responsible for 80 percent of the world's greenhouse gas emissions, must take the lead in addressing issues where national governments have not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg told a roomful of leaders from this country and overseas that the solution to global warming lay with the world’s mayors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg thrust himself onto an international stage yesterday as a champion of the environment, telling a roomful of leaders from this country and overseas that the solution to global warming lay with the world's mayors.</p>
        <p>Addressing roughly 250 mayors and other leaders over lunch at the Jumeirah Essex House on Central Park South, Mr. Bloomberg argued that cities, which are responsible for 80 percent of the world's greenhouse gas emissions, must take the lead in addressing issues where national governments have not.</p>
        <p>''The world really is looking to these cities for leadership,'' he said, straying from his prepared remarks at the C40 Large Cities Climate Summit. ''You're not going to get this from other government bodies. You're going to get it from the mayors of the world and the cities of the world, where they have to make decisions, and the consequences of their decisions are visible within hours or days. We are the ones that can take this world ahead.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg highlighted what he called ''our greenprint'' for guiding New York City's development over the next 23 years in an environmentally sustainable way. Expecting 900,000 more residents by 2030, he said, the city would focus on encouraging the use of cleaner and more efficient heating and cooling systems and appliances, upgrading heavily polluting power plants, promoting greater use of renewable power and reducing transportation-related carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>He also promoted his most contentious proposal, known as congestion pricing, under which -- with several exceptions -- the city would impose fees on drivers below 86th Street from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m. on weekdays.</p>
        <p>The plan, similar to a program in London, calls for the revenue to be used to finance environmental and mass transportation projects.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bloomberg's main message was the importance of local leaders working together, an approach he has pursued in creating a national coalition of mayors to fight illegal gun sales. After the lunchtime address, Mr. Bloomberg crossed the street to Central Park for a news conference with a phalanx of mayors behind him, like a bureaucrat's version of ''The Warriors.''</p>
        <p>And there are signs that the message is being heard.</p>
        <p>Among those assembled in the park, Mayor Douglas H. Palmer of Trenton, president of the U.S. Conference of Mayors, announced that 500 cities had signed onto the organization's agreement requiring them to reduce emissions below 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>Across the country, said Eric A. Goldstein, a co-director of the urban program at the Natural Resources Defense Council, an advocacy group, ''cities and states have increasingly taken the lead in climate and sustainability issues as frustration has grown with the federal government's environmental policies.'' Among cities that have been in the forefront of the movement are San Francisco, Seattle, Portland, Chicago and New York, Mr. Goldstein said.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Bloomberg struggles to sell congestion pricing to state lawmakers, other local leaders are running into roadblocks. Senate Republicans in Texas, for instance, recently voted to block a plan by Mayor Bill White of Houston that would allow him to fine industrial plants outside city limits that pollute city air.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Bloomberg's visibility at the conference was only part of an elaborate effort to overcome the political challenges of enacting his program. Flanked in the park by mayors from the United States, Europe and South America, Mr. Bloomberg announced that New York had joined the nonprofit Climate Group, which is dedicated to accelerating emissions reduction. In turn, officials with the group said they would work to support Mr. Bloomberg's plan.</p>
        <p>There is the advertisement on television released by Environmental Defense, an advocacy group, and the Partnership for New York City, a business group that has pushed for congestion pricing and helped organize the climate summit. In addition, the Campaign for New York's Future, a coalition of 80 environmental, civic, business, labor, neighborhood and public health groups, put up a Web site to provide information about the city's proposals. Members are also creating a brochure and are to lobby legislators in Albany today.</p>
        <p>In addition, the city's marketing department is devising a public education campaign, officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
