<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Complicated Balance Of Policy and Personal</title>
    <meta content="01edwards" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/us/01edwards.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CAMPAIGN '08: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Health Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3D61130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Complicated Balance Of Policy and Personal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Complicated Balance of Policy and Personal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic presidential candidate John Edwards has battled perceptions that he lacks experience and political heft; being defined by his wife Elizabeth's cancer and his response to it could help candidate whose signature issue is health care; her condition could pose major logistical problems for campaign, while strengthening his candidacy by giving voters intimate look at Edwards and his marriage in difficult time; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All political campaigns start with a script, brace for it to be rewritten by unforeseen events and then adapt, for better or worse. But few, if any, presidential candidates have faced a situation quite like John Edwards's as he responds to audiences consumed with curiosity and compassion about his wife's recurrent cancer while still trying to push his agenda.</p>
        <p>A case in point was a speech last week in Washington before the Communication Workers of America. Mr. Edwards deviated from the script at the beginning and end of his appearance, first telling a story, to wild applause, about his wife's reaction to her current celebrity and later accepting a get-well card for her from the delegates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Edwards is trying to respond to audiences consumed with curiosity and compassion about his wife’s recurrent cancer while still trying to push his agenda.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All political campaigns start with a script, brace for it to be rewritten by unforeseen events and then adapt, for better or worse. But few, if any, presidential candidates have faced a situation quite like John Edwards's as he responds to audiences consumed with curiosity and compassion about his wife's recurrent cancer while still trying to push his agenda.</p>
        <p>A case in point was a speech last week in Washington before the Communication Workers of America. Mr. Edwards deviated from the script at the beginning and end of his appearance, first telling a story, to wild applause, about his wife's reaction to her current celebrity and later accepting a get-well card for her from the delegates.</p>
        <p>But in between, with the audience politely attentive but far less engaged, Mr. Edwards returned to his normal stump speech. A living wage for all Americans. Universal health care. Reductions in greenhouse emissions. A timetable for withdrawal from Iraq. It was a deft balancing act as he tried to highlight his positions on the issues while capturing the attention of an audience fixated by Elizabeth Edwards's recurrent and incurable breast cancer.</p>
        <p>As campaign events of the last week showed, Mrs. Edwards's situation has the potential to overshadow his candidacy in a period when the voters are forming first impressions that can be hard to shake as the campaign unfolds.</p>
        <p>For a one-term senator who has battled perceptions among some voters that he lacks experience and policy heft, especially on national security, being defined by his wife's cancer and his response to it is not guaranteed to be a good thing in political terms. But neither is it guaranteed to hurt a candidate whose signature issue is health care and who until now has been campaigning in the shadow of two flashier rivals, Senators Hillary Rodham Clinton and Barack Obama.</p>
        <p>What grabbed crowds as the couple moved about the country this week were not Mr. Edwards's proposals, like banning new coal-fired power plants that do not incorporate emerging technology for ''carbon capture.'' Rather, voters, union members and the news media were far more interested in Mr. Edwards's yellow Livestrong wristband that signifies Lance Armstrong's determined return from cancer as grave as Mrs. Edwards's or her inspiring pep talk from Mr. Armstrong, the seven-time Tour de France champion.</p>
        <p>''This is how it's going to be for at least a little while longer,'' one of Mr. Edwards's senior advisers said. ''Right now, people rightly want to know about this other thing, and the Edwardses want to explain the decision they made. There's nothing wrong with that at the moment. But then we will get back to why he's running and his vision for change. Even now, what we want to do is show that he is continuing to focus on policy.''</p>
        <p>Democratic consultants outside the Edwards campaign see the effort as futile and even counterproductive. Mrs. Edwards's illness is more than a mere issue to be dealt with on the campaign trail, like Rudolph W. Giuliani's three marriages, these political experts say. Her condition could pose major logistical problems for a national campaign, while strengthening his candidacy by giving voters an intimate look at a man and a marriage at a trying time.</p>
        <p>Bill Carrick, a Democratic strategist in California, said Mr. Edwards seemed to appreciate that demonstrating ''how he handles a real crisis'' is at least as important as ''any formal position paper on foreign policy or who makes the best speech to the C.W.A.'' But, Mr. Carrick said, the professionals who run campaigns crave control, and this situation is ''uncontrollable and outside their ability to influence, which will drive them crazy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carrick and other consultants unaffiliated with the Edwards campaign doubted that things would ever return to normal unless it was a ''new normal.''</p>
        <p>''At no point will this not be a very big part of their campaign,'' he said. ''This is not one of those stories of the day where you deal with it and it goes away,'' especially because Mrs. Edwards's condition could worsen or her treatment could be debilitating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards's aides are insistent that they have not altered course, expect for the first few hectic days after Mrs. Edwards learned her cancer had returned when the campaign schedule was modified accordingly. The couple held an emotional news conference in North Carolina. They made Mrs. Edwards's oncologist available for interviews. They did a turn on ''60 Minutes.''</p>
        <p>The campaign Web site reflects a desire to wall off the personal and the political. The home page features a photograph of the couple at the news conference and offers links to send good wishes to Mrs. Edwards. But video from some of Mr. Edwards's campaign events has been edited to include only his policy proposals, with none of the questions or comments about his wife.</p>
        <p>And voters appear to be compelled by Mrs. Edwards's battle. At a luncheon in Cleveland last week, many questions from the audience were more like prayers or paeans. One woman, bald from six months of chemotherapy and 30 days of radiation, told Mrs. Edwards, ''I came to feel the inspiration you exude.'' Another, who lost a year of teaching to cancer treatment, called her, ''My angel, my idol, my everything.'' A third, the healthy mother of triplets, said, ''This is all anyone is talking about at kitchen tables and around water coolers: life, health, balance.''</p>
        <p>A candidate with a personal narrative tends to have more appeal than one with a vast, though bloodless, collection of position papers, said Paul E. Begala, part of the team of advisers who turned Bill Clinton from a policy wonk into ''the man from Hope.'' Mr. Begala, now a professor at the Georgetown Public Policy Institute, added that ''one of the enduring problems of the Democrats'' in the last two elections was ''leading from the head and not the heart.''</p>
        <p>Mr. and Mrs. Edwards's situation, Mr. Begala said, will animate the health care proposal that was already central to Mr. Edwards's candidacy and widely praised for its specificity. That proposal, Mr. Begala added, was driven in part by Mrs. Edwards's original diagnosis and treatment, and says to 2008 voters that his focus on health care is as personal as it gets.</p>
        <p>All of these political consultants cited the current yearning among American voters for authenticity and character in a candidate and agreed that Mr. Edwards, without exploiting his family situation, has a singular opportunity in a crowded field.</p>
        <p>Mr. and Mrs. Edwards understand the power of narrative from his days as a plaintiffs' lawyer who could move a jury to award an enormous judgment with the tale of a child maimed because of a defective $1 widget. That human connection was missing from the Kerry/Edwards campaign in 2004, Mrs. Edwards said at the Cleveland luncheon when one voter asked how the Democratic ticket managed to lose Ohio and thus the election.</p>
        <p>She said every lost job in the state and every unsecured chemical plant should have been translated into a story about a real person unable to feed a family, pay for health insurance or feel safe in a world besieged by terrorists. ''Our storytelling,'' she said, ''needs to improve.''</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN '08: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
