<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="01biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D8133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAJOR PATENT RULING -- The Supreme Court, in its most significant patent ruling in years, made it more difficult to get a patent on new products that combine elements of existing inventions. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>SAFEGUARDING FOOD -- As Food and Drug Administration inspectors head to China to investigate contaminated pet food, critics in Washington are warning that the agency is wholly understaffed and underfunded to safeguard America's food supply. [C1.]</p>
        <p>DELTA EXITS BANKRUPTCY -- Delta Air Lines has emerged from bankruptcy protection after cutting billions in costs during a 19-month reorganization. Its board must now find a new chief executive to replace Gerald Grinstein, above, and decide whether to sell or spin off Comair, its regional feeder carrier. [C6.]</p>
        <p>LURE OF LASALLE -- For Bank of America and the Royal Bank of Scotland, acquiring LaSalle Bank of Chicago would offer each an efficient way to gain a strong foothold there and throughout the Midwest, where LaSalle has 140 branches. [C1.]</p>
        <p>QUESTIONABLE TECHNIQUE -- An accounting technique called gain on sale is haunting New Century Financial, a subprime mortgage lender now facing bankruptcy and investigations by federal prosecutors and securities regulators. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PROMISE OF PLANKTON -- Some Silicon Valley technocrats are betting plankton can save the planet. Several groups are working on ventures to grow vast floating fields of plankton that could absorb carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and carry it to the depths of the ocean. [C1.]</p>
        <p>WOLFOWITZ DEFENDS HIMSELF -- Paul D. Wolfowitz, the president of the World Bank, told bank directors it would be unfair and hypocritical to dismiss him, but he hinted he might be willing to resign if he was cleared of any misconduct. [A3.]</p>
        <p>HALLIBURTON DENIES BREAKING LAW -- A Halliburton executive insisted during a Senate hearing concerning the company's business dealings in Iran that it had done nothing wrong. [A6.]</p>
        <p>DEBATE OVER CHANGES FOR F.D.A. -- he Senate debated legislation that could fundamentally change the way the F.D.A. operates by providing it with more power and more money to insure that drugs are as safe as advertised. [A18.]</p>
        <p>AN ENERGY CHALLENGE -- With the increasing use of coal inevitable, clearing a hurdle to burn it on a big scale -- separating the carbon dioxide and sequestering it -- could turn out to be one of the major engineering challenges of the century. [Science, F3.]</p>
        <p>CHINESE WEB COMPANY TO GO PUBLIC -- China's leading e-commerce company, Alibaba.com, is planning to go public later this year in what could be the biggest initial public offering there for an Internet company. [C10.]</p>
        <p>GROUP CRITICIZES WAL-MART -- Human Rights Watch contends that Wal-Mart's efforts to keep out labor unions have often violated federal law and infringed on workers' rights. Wal-Mart, with more than 1.3 million workers at nearly 4,000 stores in the United States, strongly defended its practices. [C3.]</p>
        <p>UPDATING 'OL' LONELY' -- The Maytag repairman, who started appearing in national commercials in 1967, is becoming more active and gregarious in a change meant to update the concept of ''Ol' Lonely'' for a new generation of shoppers. [C3.]</p>
        <p>GOOGLE RESPONDS TO VIACOM SUIT -- In an initial response to the lawsuit filed in United States District Court in Manhattan, Google says Viacom's $1 billion copyright infringement suit over video clips on YouTube is unfounded and ought to be dismissed. [C2.]</p>
        <p>PROFIT DECLINES AT VERIZON -- Verizon's profit declined in the first quarter, but the company continued to have strong growth in wireless and broadband subscriptions as it begins to offer Internet and television services. [C2.]</p>
        <p>GOOD NEWS FOR TWO TABLOIDS -- With the exception of two New York tabloids that showed solid gains -- The New York Post and The Daily News -- newspaper circulation continued a sharp decline nationally, new figures show. [C10.]</p>
        <p>KELLOGG'S EARNINGS RISE -- Kellogg's first-quarter earnings climbed 17 percent, helped by stronger snack sales and a tax benefit. The company, which makes food like cereal, cookies and waffles, also raised its full-year outlook. Kellogg's North American sales rose 7 percent as revenue rose 9 percent. Excluding the tax benefit, earnings were 70 cents a share. [C11.]</p>
        <p>DEUTSCHE BÖRSE BUYS EXCHANGE -- The German stock exchange operator Deutsche Börse has agreed to buy International Securities Exchange Holdings, an options exchange in New York that is the largest after the Chicago Board Options Exchange, for $2.8 billion. [C10.]</p>
        <p>WHEN THE BACKUP FAILS -- When the editorial computer system crashed at Business 2.0, a Time Inc. magazine that has written about the importance of backing up computer files, its back-up server failed to do its job. Luckily, the monthly magazine has been able to recover. [C11.]</p>
        <p>LESSONS FOR HEDGE FUNDS -- Hedge and equity funds are discovering the they may need to develop a credible public persona to capitalize on the keen interest in their high-returning funds and to go public. [C10.]</p>
        <p>WHEN TRAVELING, TAKE FOOD -- Dieticians and nutritionists recommend taking along a stash of food, which can help relieve stress if you should get stuck on the tarmac. [C5.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAJOR PATENT RULING -- The Supreme Court, in its most significant patent ruling in years, made it more difficult to get a patent on new products that combine elements of existing inventions. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>SAFEGUARDING FOOD -- As Food and Drug Administration inspectors head to China to investigate contaminated pet food, critics in Washington are warning that the agency is wholly understaffed and underfunded to safeguard America's food supply. [C1.]</p>
        <p>DELTA EXITS BANKRUPTCY -- Delta Air Lines has emerged from bankruptcy protection after cutting billions in costs during a 19-month reorganization. Its board must now find a new chief executive to replace Gerald Grinstein, above, and decide whether to sell or spin off Comair, its regional feeder carrier. [C6.]</p>
        <p>LURE OF LASALLE -- For Bank of America and the Royal Bank of Scotland, acquiring LaSalle Bank of Chicago would offer each an efficient way to gain a strong foothold there and throughout the Midwest, where LaSalle has 140 branches. [C1.]</p>
        <p>QUESTIONABLE TECHNIQUE -- An accounting technique called gain on sale is haunting New Century Financial, a subprime mortgage lender now facing bankruptcy and investigations by federal prosecutors and securities regulators. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PROMISE OF PLANKTON -- Some Silicon Valley technocrats are betting plankton can save the planet. Several groups are working on ventures to grow vast floating fields of plankton that could absorb carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and carry it to the depths of the ocean. [C1.]</p>
        <p>WOLFOWITZ DEFENDS HIMSELF -- Paul D. Wolfowitz, the president of the World Bank, told bank directors it would be unfair and hypocritical to dismiss him, but he hinted he might be willing to resign if he was cleared of any misconduct. [A3.]</p>
        <p>HALLIBURTON DENIES BREAKING LAW -- A Halliburton executive insisted during a Senate hearing concerning the company's business dealings in Iran that it had done nothing wrong. [A6.]</p>
        <p>DEBATE OVER CHANGES FOR F.D.A. -- he Senate debated legislation that could fundamentally change the way the F.D.A. operates by providing it with more power and more money to insure that drugs are as safe as advertised. [A18.]</p>
        <p>AN ENERGY CHALLENGE -- With the increasing use of coal inevitable, clearing a hurdle to burn it on a big scale -- separating the carbon dioxide and sequestering it -- could turn out to be one of the major engineering challenges of the century. [Science, F3.]</p>
        <p>CHINESE WEB COMPANY TO GO PUBLIC -- China's leading e-commerce company, Alibaba.com, is planning to go public later this year in what could be the biggest initial public offering there for an Internet company. [C10.]</p>
        <p>GROUP CRITICIZES WAL-MART -- Human Rights Watch contends that Wal-Mart's efforts to keep out labor unions have often violated federal law and infringed on workers' rights. Wal-Mart, with more than 1.3 million workers at nearly 4,000 stores in the United States, strongly defended its practices. [C3.]</p>
        <p>UPDATING 'OL' LONELY' -- The Maytag repairman, who started appearing in national commercials in 1967, is becoming more active and gregarious in a change meant to update the concept of ''Ol' Lonely'' for a new generation of shoppers. [C3.]</p>
        <p>GOOGLE RESPONDS TO VIACOM SUIT -- In an initial response to the lawsuit filed in United States District Court in Manhattan, Google says Viacom's $1 billion copyright infringement suit over video clips on YouTube is unfounded and ought to be dismissed. [C2.]</p>
        <p>PROFIT DECLINES AT VERIZON -- Verizon's profit declined in the first quarter, but the company continued to have strong growth in wireless and broadband subscriptions as it begins to offer Internet and television services. [C2.]</p>
        <p>GOOD NEWS FOR TWO TABLOIDS -- With the exception of two New York tabloids that showed solid gains -- The New York Post and The Daily News -- newspaper circulation continued a sharp decline nationally, new figures show. [C10.]</p>
        <p>KELLOGG'S EARNINGS RISE -- Kellogg's first-quarter earnings climbed 17 percent, helped by stronger snack sales and a tax benefit. The company, which makes food like cereal, cookies and waffles, also raised its full-year outlook. Kellogg's North American sales rose 7 percent as revenue rose 9 percent. Excluding the tax benefit, earnings were 70 cents a share. [C11.]</p>
        <p>DEUTSCHE BÖRSE BUYS EXCHANGE -- The German stock exchange operator Deutsche Börse has agreed to buy International Securities Exchange Holdings, an options exchange in New York that is the largest after the Chicago Board Options Exchange, for $2.8 billion. [C10.]</p>
        <p>WHEN THE BACKUP FAILS -- When the editorial computer system crashed at Business 2.0, a Time Inc. magazine that has written about the importance of backing up computer files, its back-up server failed to do its job. Luckily, the monthly magazine has been able to recover. [C11.]</p>
        <p>LESSONS FOR HEDGE FUNDS -- Hedge and equity funds are discovering the they may need to develop a credible public persona to capitalize on the keen interest in their high-returning funds and to go public. [C10.]</p>
        <p>WHEN TRAVELING, TAKE FOOD -- Dieticians and nutritionists recommend taking along a stash of food, which can help relieve stress if you should get stuck on the tarmac. [C5.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
