<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Clean Is Your Carbon Credit?</title>
    <meta content="05online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/05/business/05online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070509T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S ONLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cleansers, Detergents and Soaps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lost and Found Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">News Corporation Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dow Jones &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD9113EF936A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Clean Is Your Carbon Credit?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How Clean Is Your Carbon Credit?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Dan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CARBON credits are advertised as a way for polluters to offset the greenhouse gases they produce. Just write a check, and someone else will reduce his emissions, so you can keep driving your Hummer or operating your coal-burning power plant without guilt.</p>
        <p>Of course, it is not that easy. Even some environmentalists oppose carbon credits because, they say, offsets tend to give the impression that global warming is being solved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reports of carbon credit fraud and abuse are piling up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CARBON credits are advertised as a way for polluters to offset the greenhouse gases they produce. Just write a check, and someone else will reduce his emissions, so you can keep driving your Hummer or operating your coal-burning power plant without guilt.</p>
        <p>Of course, it is not that easy. Even some environmentalists oppose carbon credits because, they say, offsets tend to give the impression that global warming is being solved.</p>
        <p>Worse, reports of fraud and abuse are piling up. Most recently, an investigation by The Financial Times found that companies and individuals ''rushing to go green have been spending millions on 'carbon credit' projects that yield few if any environmental benefits'' (ft.com).</p>
        <p>The newspaper's environment correspondent, Fiona Harvey, wrote of ''widespread failings in the new markets for greenhouse gases, suggesting some organizations are paying for emissions reductions that do not take place.'' In other cases, organizations profit by selling credits for environmental projects they would have undertaken anyway.</p>
        <p>Francis Sullivan, the environment adviser for the banking giant HSBC, said: ''The police, the fraud squad and trading standards need to be looking into this. Otherwise people will lose faith in it.''</p>
        <p>Besides 16 articles examining just about every aspect of carbon trading and its problems, the package also includes an interactive graphic detailing carbon-reduction projects around the world, an online chat with Ms. Harvey, a video interview with her and a guide to navigating the world of carbon credits.</p>
        <p>Some bloggers who oppose initiatives to reduce carbon emissions piled on, most of them making sure to mention Al Gore, whom The Financial Times does not even mention. Upon reading the newspaper series,  Noel Sheppard of NewsBusters wondered, ''Will Media Report Global Warming 'Carbon Credit' Fraud?'' (newsbusters.org).</p>
        <p>Bryan Preston of the Hot Air blog, run by Michelle Malkin, characterized the investigation as proving that carbon credits are ''nothing but a scam'' (hotair.com).</p>
        <p>The series says no such thing, but Ms. Harvey does caution that if you are going to buy carbon credits, ''you have to do lots of homework first.''</p>
        <p>GRAPHIC DEPICTIONS -- Some things are easier to understand in pictures than words. Take, for instance, the tangle of relationships among current and former directors of the News Corporation and Dow Jones. The former company made a surprise $5 billion bid for the latter this week.</p>
        <p>A narrative explanation of the relationships might read: Vernon Jordan sits on the Dow Jones board, as well as the American Express board, where he joins Peter Chernin, the News Corporation's president. And so on.</p>
        <p>NewsVisuals simplifies matters by presenting a graphic that makes the connections easy to grasp. It connects six principals of Dow Jones with four of the News Corporation's, with five companies in between (newsvisual.com).</p>
        <p>And that's nothing. This week, the site featured a graphic of the relationships of just two men -- the media mogul Barry Diller and the financier Nelson Peltz -- that looks like the wiring schematic for the space shuttle.</p>
        <p>$67 MILLION PANTS -- Roy Pearson has sued his dry cleaner for losing his pants in 2005, seeking damages of $67 million.</p>
        <p>He asserts ''mental suffering, inconvenience, and discomfort'' in part because he had planned to wear the pants on his first day of work -- as an administrative law judge in Washington (abcnews.go.com).</p>
        <p>The store's owners, Jin and Soo Chung, say they have spent thousands of dollars defending themselves, and their credit rating has been damaged. Breaking down in tears, Soo Chung told ABC News: ''I don't want to live here anymore. It's been so difficult. I just want to go home, go back to Korea.'' Mr. Pearson did not comment.</p>
        <p>''People in America are now scared of each other,'' a legal specialist, Philip Howard, told ABC News. ''That's why teachers won't put an arm around a crying child, and doctors order unnecessary tests and ministers won't meet with parishioners. It's a distrust of justice, and it's changing our culture.''</p>
        <p>DAN MITCHELL</p>
        <p>WHAT'S ONLINE E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 9, 2007, Wednesday  A report in the What's Online column in Business Day on Saturday, about the relationship between the current and former directors of the News Corporation and Dow Jones &amp; Company, referred incorrectly to Vernon Jordan's business relationship with Dow Jones. He left the company's board last year; he is no longer a director.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 9, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A report in the What's Online column in Business Day on Saturday, about the relationship between the current and former directors of the News Corporation and Dow Jones &amp; Company, referred incorrectly to Vernon Jordan's business relationship with Dow Jones. He left the company's board last year; he is no longer a director.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
