<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Avoiding All That Heat About the Environment</title>
    <meta content="24genz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/arts/television/24genz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4D6173EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Avoiding All That Heat About the Environment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Avoiding All That Heat About the Environment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Earth Day has come and gone, and with it the usual gestures: some trees planted, some litter picked up, some green oratory delivered by public figures. All well intended, probably, but all well short of matching the scope of the environmental problems that loom.</p>
        <p>And that, roughly, is how the double dose of environmental programming offered on PBS tonight feels: too timid for the task at hand. ''Saved by the Sun,'' on ''Nova,'' and ''Hot Politics,'' on ''Frontline,'' are very different programs, but both are for the most part content to stick to the easy and the familiar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The double dose of environmental programming offered on PBS’s “Nova” and “Frontline” on Tuesday feels too timid for the task at hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Earth Day has come and gone, and with it the usual gestures: some trees planted, some litter picked up, some green oratory delivered by public figures. All well intended, probably, but all well short of matching the scope of the environmental problems that loom.</p>
        <p>And that, roughly, is how the double dose of environmental programming offered on PBS tonight feels: too timid for the task at hand. ''Saved by the Sun,'' on ''Nova,'' and ''Hot Politics,'' on ''Frontline,'' are very different programs, but both are for the most part content to stick to the easy and the familiar.</p>
        <p>The ''Nova'' program looks at the current state of solar power. Ostensibly, it is inquiring into whether that technology can provide the vast quantities of clean power that the world demands, but the tone is so chirpy that the program feels not like an inquiry, but like one of those gee-whiz newsreels promoting the ''amazing new wonders'' of perma-pressed trousers. (An activity that's fun for viewers: Start a betting pool on which sun-related pop song -- ''Here Comes the Sun''? ''You Are the Sunshine of My Life''? -- will turn up next in the soundtrack.)</p>
        <p>The program does take an interesting detour to Germany, where solar panels have sprouted like weeds because of an incentive program that includes paying more for solar power sold to the communal grid than is charged for power purchased off that grid.</p>
        <p>''It didn't take long for the Germans to figure out that this is worth it: they could make money,'' says Lawrence Kazmerski of the National Renewable Energy Laboratory in Golden, Colo. As the show's narration notes, ''Any open space has become fair game for solar panels.''</p>
        <p>It's a policy jolt that makes the solar-energy incentives in the United States look timid. But the program only hints at its drawbacks, like higher costs.</p>
        <p>On ''Frontline,'' ''Hot Politics'' looks at the United States' reluctance to do anything substantive about global warming over the last three presidential administrations. The program, commendably, doesn't give the reborn darling of the green movement, Al Gore, a pass: the Clinton administration didn't seize its opportunity for bold action any more than the two Bush administrations did.</p>
        <p>But there's not much new here. The current administration is portrayed as worse than head-in-the-sand, as actively promoting bad science, but others have already made that claim.</p>
        <p>Both programs engage in a little wishful thinking, suggesting that business and science are finally getting together to act where politicians have failed. There are solar panels on a Whole Foods in New Jersey! But the hard questions about what it will take to force significant changes in the energy-guzzling ways of Americans and emerging powers go largely unasked.</p>
        <p>Phil Reavis Jr. of Somerville, Mass., the obligatory everyman in the ''Nova'' program, who has put solar panels on his roof and may be the most common-sense voice in either documentary, seems to know that people like him will remain a very small minority so long as oil and coal are the easier option.</p>
        <p>''Thinking back to the '70s,'' he says, ''man, if everybody had started installing solar panels back then, we'd be in much better shape, really, for the future of the planet.''</p>
        <p>But, of course, almost nobody did.</p>
        <p>Nova  Saved by the Sun  On most PBS stations tonight (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Directed by Steven Latham; Paula S. Apsell, senior executive producer and series director; Mr. Latham, Larry Klein and Evan I. Schwartz, producers; Mr. Klein and Mr. Schwartz, writers; WGBH Science Unit, series producer. Produced by Steven Latham Productions for WGBH/Nova.</p>
        <p>Frontline  Hot Politics  On most PBS stations tonight (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Produced and written by Peter Bull; Michael Sullivan, Frontline executive producer for special projects. David Fanning, Frontline executive producer; Deborah Amos, correspondent. Produced by Frontline with the Center for Investigative Reporting Inc.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
