<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Green Face-Lift for the Governor's Mansion</title>
    <meta content="02mansion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/02/nyregion/02mansion.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Albany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wall Spitzer, Silda</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DD103EF931A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Green Face-Lift for the Governor's Mansion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Green Face-Lift for the Governor’s Mansion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS CONFESSORE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Confessore, Nicholas</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The house at 138 Eagle Street here does not immediately seem like a fixer-upper. A stately 20,000-square-foot mansion, home to New York's governors and their families since 1875, it has a pool, a tennis court and views of the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>But during the next year, the executive residence will undergo its most extensive renovation in decades, as Gov. Eliot Spitzer and his wife, Silda Wall Spitzer, turn the home into a model of environmentally friendly living.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Governor Eliot Spitzer and his wife are planning to turn their new home into a model of environmentally friendly living.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The house at 138 Eagle Street here does not immediately seem like a fixer-upper. A stately 20,000-square-foot mansion, home to New York's governors and their families since 1875, it has a pool, a tennis court and views of the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>But during the next year, the executive residence will undergo its most extensive renovation in decades, as Gov. Eliot Spitzer and his wife, Silda Wall Spitzer, turn the home into a model of environmentally friendly living.</p>
        <p>In a speech delivered on Tuesday from the home's north porch, Ms. Wall Spitzer said the planned renovations would ''transition the mansion into the 21st century as a sustainable home going into the future, while preserving its historic character.''</p>
        <p>The renovation will take place in three phases, Ms. Wall Spitzer said. In Phase 1, the mansion's appliances will be replaced by energy-efficient models. A washing machine was to be installed on Tuesday, while low-flow shower heads and fluorescent light bulbs will soon follow. The gasoline-powered lawn mowers that currently manicure the rolling grounds will be replaced by electric models, and the mansion's staff members will begin using hybrid vehicles.</p>
        <p>In Phase 2, contractors will install three sets of solar panels around the mansion and its grounds. And in the final phase, the staff members will begin converting to ecologically sound maintenance, using nontoxic cleaning supplies and organic pest control on the property. Workers will also begin composting food waste and recycle more, and the chefs will buy as much organic produce as they can.</p>
        <p>By the time the changes are completed in June 2008, planners estimate, the mansion will use 50 percent less power and give off half as much greenhouse emission as it does now. The mansion's annual utility costs are expected to drop to below $60,000 a year from $86,000.</p>
        <p>The renovation will cost about $650,000, but Ms. Wall Spitzer emphasized that no state capital funds will be used. The mansion qualifies for a Power Authority program that provides grants to help state buildings convert to solar power, and state officials will also apply for other grants through the state's Energy Research and Development Authority.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wall Spitzer said Governor Spitzer stays at the mansion an average of two nights a week. (The Spitzers have an apartment in New York City, where their children attend school, and a farm in the town of Gallatin in Columbia County near Poughkeepsie.) But in her speech, she described the renovations as a symbolic expression of Governor Spitzer's environmental policy priorities, like sharply reducing the state's electricity consumption by 2015 and spurring growth in the state's renewable energy industry.</p>
        <p>''We also hope greening the mansion will serve as a model for the myriad ways, large and small, that New Yorkers can help decrease demand for electricity in their homes,'' Ms. Wall Spitzer said. ''This will, in turn, help lower energy bills, contribute to a safer and cleaner environment for our children, help reduce our imprint on global warming and decrease out dependence on fossil fuels.''</p>
        <p>The planned changes will not be the first time change has come to the mansion. In fact, the joys of home renovation have proved irresistible to governors throughout the last hundred-odd years.</p>
        <p>During the late 1800s, Gov. David B. Hill added enough rooms to nearly double the mansion's size, though he was a bachelor. Gov. Franklin D. Roosevelt, who had polio, added a heated indoor swimming pool. And a large portion of the first floor of the mansion had to be remodeled after a fire destroyed it in 1961, while Nelson A. Rockefeller was governor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
