<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Yawning</title>
    <meta content="06age" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/fashion/06age.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE AGE OF DISSONANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DA113EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Yawning</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Global Yawning</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bob</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was running errands the other day when a pleasant young woman with a clipboard tried to stop me. ''Do you have a moment for the environment, sir?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>''No,'' I barked as I evaded her, ''I don't!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is it possible that all the marketing for the environment is cheapening the cause?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was running errands the other day when a pleasant young woman with a clipboard tried to stop me. ''Do you have a moment for the environment, sir?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>''No,'' I barked as I evaded her, ''I don't!''</p>
        <p>I felt guilty, but also vindicated. I mean, of course I have a moment for the environment. Saying you're not for the environment right now is like saying you're not for education, children, world peace, Africa or a cure for cancer. These days you would have to be a fool or a lobbyist to dismiss global warming and natural resource issues.</p>
        <p>But is it possible that all this marketing is cheapening the cause?</p>
        <p>Must every hotel, restaurant, shampoo, detergent and beverage that is environmentally responsible talk so much about it? Yuban ''sustainable development'' coffee. Paul Mitchell ''protecting our planet for generations to come.'' Levi's Eco jeans.</p>
        <p>How much green-standing can we stand? It's enough hot air to melt Antarctica.</p>
        <p>In no time, an inconvenient truth has become an obnoxious one.</p>
        <p>But from what I can see, there's as much selling as thinking going on.</p>
        <p>The other night I attended a magazine party in a photography studio that had been turned into an elaborate garden with 10-foot-high privet hedges fashioned from shrubbery trucked up from the South. After the party, the walls of greens went into a chipper for recycling.</p>
        <p>''It's giving back to the environment in a good way,'' the decorator told me.</p>
        <p>Sure. Unless you consider the fuel to truck all that greenery up from the South in the first place. I guess it could be worse. John Travolta, for instance, recently flew his own Boeing 707 to England to promote a new movie and urged everyone to ''do their bit'' to combat global warming. Closer to home, meanwhile, the Sheryl Crow ''Stop Global Warming College Tour'' stipulated parking for three tractor-trailers, four buses and six cars. Ms. Crow is a spokeswoman for Revlon, a tour sponsor. Maybe I'm missing something. But is there anything green about that except money?</p>
        <p>And cynical as this sounds, how does Vanity Fair, with its May ''Green Issue,'' reconcile its high-minded battle cry with all those pages selling cars, bottled water, watches, perfumes and clothes? Ads in the magazine for Diesel and Svedka vodka even mock global warming by suggesting you dress for the heat and add more ice to drinks.</p>
        <p>I guess it's all par for the golf course in a country where people are more interested in broadcasting their ideals than curtailing their consumption. How else would you explain buying ''carbon credits'' to offset your ''carbon footprint?''</p>
        <p>Not that it isn't nice to do be able to do some penance by paying to support environmentally helpful projects. But are these projects all so well thought-out?</p>
        <p>Even when the issues are green, things are rarely black or white.</p>
        <p>Ethanol, for instance, is now under question for causing more smog than gasoline, according to a new Stanford University study. Oilseed rape, the new crop used for European biofuel that is especially popular in Germany, requires dangerously high levels of fertilizers and pesticides. Even those energy-efficient compact fluorescent light bulbs are problematic. They contain mercury. Companies and governments have not come up with convenient ways to recycle them, so people just throw them in the trash.</p>
        <p>''In a bid to solve one problem,'' said Chris Davies, a member of the European Parliament, ''we risk creating another and making things worse.'' He was referrring to a study warning that the rush to biofuels in Europe could decimate Asian rain forests.</p>
        <p>I wonder what Mother Nature would say about all this. Perhaps she'd be pleased that so many mavericks are addressing the problems that have given her emphysema, making it necessary for Laurie David and Al Gore to step in to replace her.</p>
        <p>Or perhaps she'd echo Ingrid Johnson, a professor at the Fashion Institute of Technology. ''If you really want to be environmentally friendly, buy fewer things,'' Ms. Johnson said. ''It's that simple. I mean how many pairs of jeans do you need? And how many shopping bags at Saks?''</p>
        <p>Me? I'm no eco-saint. I do have a personal plea. But it's for the social environment rather than the natural one: Please, tone it done. The world is in terrible shape right now. Global warming isn't another happy opportunity for marketing clothes, candles and sustainable weddings or for green-washing your bad corporate karma.</p>
        <p>It's not about having a moment for the environment, either.</p>
        <p>It's about a lifetime.</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF DISSONANCE E-mail: Bobmorris@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Bobmorris@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
