<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth's Climate Needs the Help Of Incentives</title>
    <meta content="28leonhardt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/28/business/28leonhardt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1836289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EFDA1330F93BA15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth's Climate Needs the Help Of Incentives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Earth’s Climate Needs the Help of Incentives</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Leonhardt column on renewed interest in global warming; says attention qualifies as progress, but some of ideas before Congress would do very little to change situation; holds feckless new law would be worse than nothing at all (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The politicians who deny that global warming is a problem used to be the biggest obstacle to a solution. They're not anymore. They have lost the argument.</p>
        <p>When former Vice President Al Gore came back to Capitol Hill to testify last week, a few of the global-warming holdouts in Congress confronted him with their usual tactics. They took the actual uncertainties over climate change -- how fast seas and temperatures will rise, how serious the effects will be -- and tried to make them sound like uncertainty over whether human beings were making the planet hotter. But the skeptics didn't get very far. In the last few months, this debate has shifted incredibly quickly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congress seems poised to pass a bill to deal with climate change, but some ideas would do very little to change the situation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The politicians who deny that global warming is a problem used to be the biggest obstacle to a solution. They're not anymore. They have lost the argument.</p>
        <p>When former Vice President Al Gore came back to Capitol Hill to testify last week, a few of the global-warming holdouts in Congress confronted him with their usual tactics. They took the actual uncertainties over climate change -- how fast seas and temperatures will rise, how serious the effects will be -- and tried to make them sound like uncertainty over whether human beings were making the planet hotter. But the skeptics didn't get very far. In the last few months, this debate has shifted incredibly quickly.</p>
        <p>As Representative Ed Whitfield, a Kentucky Republican (lifetime rating from the American Conservative Union: 90 out of 100 ), told Mr. Gore, ''I think everyone recognizes -- as you have said and the scientific community agrees -- that there is global warming caused by human activity.'' On Monday, Gallup released a new poll conducted before the hearings. In it, 86 percent of respondents said they favored new action to deal with environmental problems.</p>
        <p>No wonder, then, that the political debate now revolves around what that action should be. In the current Congress, there are six bills to deal with climate change, and more are on the way. Senator John McCain, a Republican presidential candidate, helped write one bill, and Senators Hillary Rodham Clinton and Barack Obama, the leading Democratic hopefuls, are co-sponsors of it.</p>
        <p>This attention certainly qualifies as progress. But it is also creating the newest big obstacle to a climate solution, an obstacle that's far less obvious than the efforts to deny scientific reality. The would-be reformers may be saying all the right things; every last one of them may even be pursuing the solution she or he honestly believes to be the best one.</p>
        <p>But the truth is that some of the ideas now on the table would do very little to change the situation. And a feckless new law would be worse than nothing at all right now.</p>
        <p>The discussion about climate change can be mind-numbingly complex, filled as it often is with economic and scientific jargon. But I think there are three broad principles that help sort out the substantive attempts at change from the others.</p>
        <p>The place to start -- the first thing that distinguishes the most serious reformers -- is an acknowledgment that a cooler planet will cost money. It's extremely tempting to focus instead on the dazzling economic opportunities that come with alternative energies. President Bush did so during this year's State of the Union address  when he said, ''The way forward is through technology.''</p>
        <p>Likewise, Mrs. Clinton, when laying out her solution  to climate and energy problems last year, asked: ''How will we get there? Two words: innovation and efficiency.'' She then recited a list of nifty technologies -- wind power, solar cells, cellulosic ethanol, hybrid plug-ins, clean coal, clean diesel -- that Mr. Bush also likes.</p>
        <p>Some of these probably will become major energy sources in the decades ahead. But in most places they're not yet nearly as cheap as oil, coal or the other fossil fuels that make the planet hotter by emitting carbon. Government subsidies cannot make up the gap, and, more to the point, nobody can accurately predict which alternative energies are the most promising and most deserving of subsidy. So a hodgepodge of new research-and-development tax credits just isn't the answer.</p>
        <p>The only reliable way to reduce carbon emissions is to make them more expensive. When you hear somebody talk first about doing this and only then about the wonderful innovations that will follow -- and they will follow -- you know that person is serious.</p>
        <p>This is essence of the second principle: the market created this problem, and the market is going to have to solve it. The issue, says David H. Festa, director for the oceans program at the advocacy group Environmental Defense is 'how do we make sure people are given the right economic signals to do what we need them to do.' ''</p>
        <p>Later today, Mr. Festa is going to release a fascinating study about the fishing business that on its face has nothing to do with global warming, and yet has everything to do with a solution. At dozens of the nation's fisheries, the fish population is in danger because fishermen have no incentive not to take everything out of the water that they can. But 10 fisheries, stretching from the halibut fishery off Alaska to the surf clam industry in New England, have tried a different route.</p>
        <p>They have capped their annual catch and then granted fishermen the right to a certain share of that catch. The fishermen can buy and sell these rights among themselves, creating a market that rewards the most efficient companies. The fishermen also have a stake in the long-term health of the fishery, as it will dictate the value of their fishing rights when they retire.</p>
        <p>The new study is important because it shows that the benefits aren't just hypothetical. At the 10 fisheries, there are fewer fatal accidents than elsewhere and the fish populations are healthier. The fact that halibut has returned to restaurant menus in the last decade is a direct result of these cap-and-trade programs.</p>
        <p>All of the climate bills in Congress revolve around a similar idea. The government would cap greenhouse-gas emissions and issue tradable permits, each giving power plants the right to pump out a set amount. The plants that did the best job of reducing their emissions could then profit by selling unused permits to inefficient plants. A similar system put in place during George H. W. Bush's presidency reduced acid rain much more quickly than economists had predicted.</p>
        <p>The successes of the acid rain and fishing programs point to the third principle: the solution should be clear and straightforward. It should cover the entire economy, and it shouldn't have escape hatches that undermine the market mechanisms. Mrs. Clinton, whatever her rhetorical weaknesses, has signed onto a bill that passes this test.</p>
        <p>But at least two of the current Senate bills fail it. The one proposed by Dianne Feinstein, a California Democrat, covers only the electricity business, among other problems. The one being prepared by Jeff Bingaman, a New Mexico Democrat, sets a maximum price on the carbon permits, which undermines their whole point. It's like asking people to invest in the stock market and then forbidding them from making more than a 5 percent return.</p>
        <p>These three principles -- acknowledge the costs; let the market work; and keep the solution simple -- won't cover everything. But they will go a long way toward reducing carbon emissions here, in the country that produces more of them than any other, and then letting us turn to another big problem: persuading China and India to follow suit.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIX E-mail: Leonhardt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Leonhardt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
