<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SCIENTIST AT WORK --  Linda J. Gormezano; A Team of 2, Following the Scent of Polar Bears</title>
    <meta content="05prof" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/science/05prof.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Scientist at Work | Linda J. Gormezano"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Scientist at Work</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Polar Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Museum of Natural History</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4DB1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1256" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SCIENTIST AT WORK --  Linda J. Gormezano; A Team of 2, Following the Scent of Polar Bears</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Team of 2, Following the Scent of Polar Bears</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hunt begins with a loud shout in Spanish by Linda J. Gormezano.</p>
        <p>''¡Búscalo!'' Seek.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Linda J. Gormezano is using scat to track the wanderings, genetics and condition of polar bears, which have shown signs of stress recently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The hunt begins with a loud shout in Spanish by Linda J. Gormezano.</p>
        <p>''¡Búscalo!'' Seek.</p>
        <p>Waiting with ears pricked and tail wagging, Quinoa, her black male Dutch shepherd, leaps to work, straining at the leash, nose down, weaving left and right.</p>
        <p>He is doing something that comes naturally to dogs, which spend many waking hours sniffing out traces left by other animals -- the smellier the better.</p>
        <p>That skill has been transferred over the centuries to help humans find prison escapees, game, bombs, drugs, avalanche victims and more. The quarry sought by Quinoa, named for the Andean grain, is something utterly conventional and doglike: feces, poop or, as field biologists prefer to call it -- scat.</p>
        <p>What makes this dog special is his behavior when he finds his goal. No peeing or rolling. He simply sits. He stares attentively back at Ms. Gormezano, 35, awaiting an inevitable torrent of praise and then the toss of a plastic ball, his sole reward, before returning to the hunt.</p>
        <p>The other thing special on this particular training day is the nature of the scat he seeks.</p>
        <p>It comes from polar bears.</p>
        <p>Although this exercise is taking place in the Mianus River Gorge Preserve, a wooded nook tucked in Bedford, N.Y., 40 miles northeast of Manhattan, the small hidden heaps contain things as foreign to New York as can be -- the bones and feathers of snow geese, kelp and lyme grass, a trace of seal.</p>
        <p>The samples, hidden ahead of time (on Petri dishes), came from the collection Ms. Gormezano has been amassing since 2005 in fieldwork on the grassy coastal plains ringing the western shore of Hudson Bay in central Canada, one of the southernmost bastions of the great ice-roaming predators.</p>
        <p>With biologists at the American Museum of Natural History and the City University of New York, where she is pursuing a doctorate, Ms. Gormezano is using scat to track the wanderings, genetics and condition of the bears, which in that northern region, particularly, have shown signs of stress that could be related to the warming Arctic climate and retreating sea ice.</p>
        <p>The United States Fish and Wildlife Service, which in December proposed designating polar bears around the Arctic as a threatened species because of climate change and the ice retreat, is halfway through a yearlong assessment  of that question.</p>
        <p>''There's a need to do this right now, and it's never been done on polar bears before,'' Ms. Gormezano said of the research on scat.</p>
        <p>Other methods for tracking shifts in populations involve chasing the bears in helicopters, sedating them with darts and tagging or collaring them. But such methods can pose risks or alter the bears' behavior, she said. Some Canadian national parks require a shift from darting. In contrast, bear scat, and also tufts of fur left in dens or sleeping spots, can be collected without affecting the bears. Tests of DNA in the feces can distinguish individual animals. So the dispersion of scat provides a map of a particular bear's wanderings.</p>
        <p>''All the issues with global warming are going to affect southernmost populations, especially around southern Hudson Bay and western Hudson Bay, where they're already starting to see changes, reduced reproductive output, thinner subadults,'' Ms. Gormezano said. ''So this is a great opportunity to try out a new method.''</p>
        <p>The Mianus gorge was chosen for a final spring tune-up for Quinoa because Ms. Gormezano has another research project under way there on a very different predator -- coyotes.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the polar bear, which is under study because some populations appear to be in retreat, coyotes have become a conservation concern because they have been expanding, growing physically and in pack size, in the deer-rich woods and lawns surrounding New York City.</p>
        <p>Quinoa is an equal-opportunity seeker of polar bear and coyote poop. With coyotes, it is particularly important that the dog not touch the scat, Ms. Gormezano said, given that their DNA is nearly identical. Those samples are placed in paper bags, allowing air to circulate and desiccate the material, with the location noted using a global positioning system device.</p>
        <p>Up north, she said, bear scat is handled differently.</p>
        <p>''Each sample, regardless of how I initially store it, is subsampled and dried in a food dehydrator for a few hours at about 100 degrees Fahrenheit, then vacuum sealed in plastic,'' Ms. Gormezano said. ''Basically, I turn it into scat jerky. Getting rid of moisture is the key to preserving the DNA most effectively until it can be extracted.''</p>
        <p>As she followed Quinoa in his sniff, sit, play and hunt routine through woods and fields, Ms. Gormezano reflected on the odd trajectory that brought her to this place. She grew up in Queens in New York City and studied classical percussion at Queens College. Then she started pursuing internships in field biology, mainly on predators. Later came work for the National Park Service with overabundant deer on Fire Island and in Front Royal, Va.</p>
        <p>The polar bear study grew out of fieldwork that her thesis adviser, Robert F. Rockwell  of the City University, had been conducting for decades in the far north on lesser snow geese. Like deer, the lesser snow goose is mainly a focus because it, too, is overabundant.</p>
        <p>While working along Hudson Bay, Dr. Rockwell and Ms. Gormezano began collecting polar bear scat. For her doctoral thesis, she began parallel studies, using scat and hair samples, of the potentially threatened polar bear populations around western Hudson Bay and also the expanding coyote ranks of suburbs north of New York.</p>
        <p>To find more scat, Ms. Gormezano began canvassing biologists around the country using dogs to seek other species , or their scat, like the black-footed ferret, cougar and killer whales, on Puget Sound.</p>
        <p>She toured the Bureau of Alcohol Tobacco and Firearms center for training detection dogs., learning how to select the right animal and motivate it. Some dogs used in field research are dropouts from that program. Ms. Gormezano found her research partner through a breeder in Rhode Island two years ago.</p>
        <p>''He was 6 months old,'' she recalled as she followed him across a field in the gorge preserve. ''He has to be play obsessed, and he is. So I reinforced that from the very beginning. Now he just loves to work, too.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rockwell and Ms. Gormezano said they reserved judgment on whether the Hudson Bay bears stand to fade or adjust in a warming climate. For now, they clearly derive most of their sustenance from seals that they hunt in winter out on the sea ice, instead of ashore where they travel to forage, breed and seek dens in summer.</p>
        <p>Their scat reveals an extraordinarily varied diet, including snow geese and their eggs. The bear populations also show signs of shifting north a bit along the coast in response to shifting climate patterns. Among the other merits of the scat studies, Ms. Gormezano said, is that they lay down a baseline of data on the animals that will be useful for years to come.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rockwell said t the bears' earlier arrival onshore in spring could potentially lead to more overlap with the hundreds of thousands of nesting geese, potentially providing a vast store of bear food in the form of birds and their eggs.</p>
        <p>The threesome of researchers headed north late last month, and in e-mail messages over the last few days, Ms. Gormezano and Dr. Rockwell provided updates. On Sunday, Dr. Rockwell wrote: ''Quinoa is on fire with poop finding -- we got 71 samples one day.''</p>
        <p>Scientist at Work | Linda J. Gormezano</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
