<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: May 25 - May 31</title>
    <meta content="25theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1849688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1DB1630F936A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="15780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: May 25 - May 31</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. ? denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'BEYOND GLORY' Previews start today. Opens on June 21. War stories from Stephen Lang in this solo play based on the tales of eight veterans from World War II, Korea and Vietnam (1:20). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'THE BUTCHER OF BARABOO' In previews; opens on June 11. Did the butcher of Baraboo, Wis., kill her husband? Find out in this black comedy (2:00). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'CRAZY MARY' In previews; opens on June 3. In A. R. Gurney's new play, Sigourney Weaver stars as a woman who discovers that her cousin, the title character and a patient in a psychiatric hospital, holds the keys to the family fortune (2:00). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'EURYDICE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on June 18. The hot young playwright Sarah Ruhl (''The Clean House'') gives her spin on the classic myth of Orpheus and Eurydice (1:30). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'IN A DARK DARK HOUSE' In previews; opens on June 7. Neil LaBute's latest drama features Frederick Weller and Ron Livingston as hostile siblings sorting out a history of abuse (1:30). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'INTIMATE EXCHANGES' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on June 14. Alan Ayckbourn's eight different (but related) plays all begin with the same very modern question: should I smoke? Part of the Brits Off Broadway festival (1:30 to 2:15). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'SESSIONS' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on June 10. Albert Tapper's comic new musical takes place in a therapist's office. Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'TEA' In previews; opens on Wednesday. Set in Kansas in 1968, this play is about four Japanese war brides who gather to mourn a friend (1:30). West End Theater, 263 West 86th Street, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'10 MILLION MILES' In previews; opens on June 14. A new musical by the singer Patty Griffin and the playwright Keith Bunin (''The Busy World Is Hushed'') is about a road trip from Florida to New York. Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'XANADU' In previews; opens on June 26. The 1980 cult roller disco film about a Greek muse sent to earth goes Broadway -- and it's about time. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' Back on Broadway for the first time in 25 years, Angela Lansbury is so vitally and indelibly present that she even gives flesh to this flimsy comedy. Terrence McNally's play, about the reunion of two former doubles partners (Ms. Lansbury and Marian Seldes), is a jerry-built shrine to enduring star power. Directed by Michael Blakemore (1:45). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'FROST/NIXON' Frank Langella turns in a truly titanic performance as Richard M. Nixon in Peter Morgan's briskly entertaining, if all-too-tidy, play about the former president's annihilating television interviews with the British talk show host David Frost (the excellent Michael Sheen). Michael Grandage directs with the momentum of a ticking-bomb thriller and the zing of a boulevard comedy (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' Doug Hughes's wooden revival of this worthy war horse, based on the Scopes ''monkey'' trial of 1925, never musters much more velocity than a drugstore fan. Be grateful that the cast includes Christopher Plummer, in savory form as a Will Rogers of jurisprudence. An oddly subdued Brian Dennehy plays his pompous adversary (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40).Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' This nonstop sugar rush of a musical about a powder puff who finds her inner power-broker, based on the 2001 film, approximates the experience of eating a jumbo bag of Gummi Bears in one sitting. Flossing between songs is recommended (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' As Lotte Lenya and Kurt Weill, Donna Murphy and Michael Cerveris turn in stunningly shaded performances in what is, alas, a sluggish, mixed-up bio-musical. Scored with an eclectic sampler of Weill's songs, ''LoveMusik'' strives to achieve chilly distance and cozy intimacy in the same breath. Harold Prince directs; Alfred Uhry wrote the conventionally sentimental book (2:40). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' Is it possible for a performance to be too good? Audra McDonald brings such breadth of skill and depth of feeling to Lonny Price's lukewarm revival of this musical about a love-starved spinster that she threatens to burst the seams of this small, homey musical. She's an overwhelming presence in an underwhelming show (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PIRATE QUEEN' How to river-dance your way to the bottom of the ocean, courtesy of the songwriters of ''Les Misérables'' (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RADIO GOLF' The final -- and in dramatic terms, the weakest -- of August Wilson's magnificent 10-play cycle about the African-American experience, ''Radio Golf'' has the crackle of a bustling comedy. But this tale of getting and spending in the 1990s, directed by Kenny Leon, throbs with a lament for a lost time, a lost culture, a lost language (2:30). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' John Fugelsang's amiable solo show mixes memoir and stand-up comedy in a tale of family, faith and Roman Catholic guilt. Slight but engaging (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'BE' A high-energy, low-content Israeli show that blends music, dance and sex appeal in the latest attempt to tap into the ''Stomp'' market (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 307-4100. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE BRIG' Serious students of the stage will want to check out the Living Theater's first revival since 1963 of Kenneth H. Brown's docudrama about the soul-shredding grind of daily life in a Marine Corps prison, once again directed by the company co-founder Judith Malina. One of the most celebrated productions in the company's history, ''The Brig'' harks back to an era when theater was at the forefront of both political and artistic radicalism (2:00). Living Theater, 21 Clinton Street, Lower East Side. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAUGHTER OF A CUBAN REVOLUTIONARY' A standard-issue solo play about a fascinating Cuban family (1:10). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GASLIGHT' The Irish Repertory Theater's revival of Patrick Hamilton's 1938 thriller about a husband intent on driving his wife mad strips away the claustrophobia and ably resists clichéd feminist interpretation. As the impish detective who saves the day, Brian Murray is the play's great leavening agent. He prompts the heroine to whiskey drinking, and you want to raise a glass to him (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'GOD'S EAR' Jenny Schwartz's formally inventive and brilliantly performed drama about how the death of a child affects a family is more interested in language than in narrative (1:20). East 13th Street Theater, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'I LOVE YOU , YOU'RE PERFECT, NOW CHANGE!' This revue has proved as indestructible as the truisms about men and women on which it is based: it has run for 11 years Off Broadway and spread around the world. Now one of its avatars is coming for a visit: the Mandarin production with Lin Yilun, a major Chinese star, has arrived in New York for a limited run, playing concurrently with the English version. This is supposedly the first time a foreign production of an American musical has played in the United States (and the first Chinese-language production of a major American musical). It will be interesting to see how the piece's hoary stereotypes change in translation; Joel Bishoff, the original director, modified the piece to reflect Chinese culture for its Shanghai run (2:00). The Westside Theater, 407 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212 239-6200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE J.A.P. SHOW: JEWISH AMERICAN PRINCESSES of comedy' Laughs along with longueurs (1:30). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'MOTHER LOAD' In her one-woman show on the perils of affluent motherhood, Amy Wilson derides the culture of obsessive child-rearing as she chronicles her submission to it. An affable presence onstage, Ms. Wilson nevertheless mines overly clichéd territory: the nut allergies, the horrors of preschool admission, the importance of knowing two languages by the time you are 3. Posters on Urbanbaby.com will find themselves amusedly looking in the mirror. All other New Yorkers will find themselves wanting to move to Patagonia (1:15). Sage Theater, 711 Seventh Avenue, at 47th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30).Westside Theater Downstairs, 407 West 43rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'PASSING STRANGE' Composer-performer Stew narrates this semi-autobiographical show about a songwriter on a journey of self-discovery. Part rock concert, part book musical, it flows smoothly on a strong current of feeling and humor as the L.A.-born central character searches for his musical voice in the hash bars of Amsterdam and the cabarets of Berlin (2:30). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SILVERLAND' Global warming and the melting of the ice caps have destroyed London in this environmentally (if not dramatically) aware debut. Part of the Brits Off Broadway festival (2:00). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  A pasteboard pastiche of 1920's musicals, as remembered by a witty show queen(1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  A writhing green blob with music (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY ON THE VINE' Zak Berkman presents muddled politics and distorted anxieties in his quasi science-fiction play about the influence of plastic surgery on young women who start modeling themselves after a right-wing radio host. Adding to the atmosphere of hysteria is the inability of the actors onstage to render a single subtle or nuanced moment (2:10). Harold Clurman Theater, 412 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'BETROTHED' Rachel Dickstein weds dance and spoken drama in a distinctive theatrical language. The marriages in this lovely and uneven work are less convincing: aiming to depict women's views about matrimony, this piece, based on three dissimilar short stories, actually depicts marriage as an imprisoning convention from which all three heroines escape. It's no accident that the first part of this triptych, based on Jhumpa Lahiri's story ''The Treatment of Bibi Haldar,'' provides the defining image of the work as a whole: wreathed in a haze of (implied) incense and saffron, this lovely sequence is the strongest of the evening (1:20). Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' Set in 18th-century England, this melodrama about imperiled orphans is big and broad but not particularly deep. With a cast of 40, an orchestra in the pit and bursts of choral music (Handel, mostly) decorating the proceedings, it is tastefully splashy and certainly impressive, but less emotionally engaging than you might hope (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'HAMLET' Gorilla Rep specializes in outdoor performances of Shakespeare; this workshop is a free indoor performance of an outdoor performance, which removes the gimmick and leaves, simply, good theater. The strong cast revolves around note-perfect portrayals of Claudius and Gertrude (Elizabeth McGuire is particularly fine); of the Polonius family (Al Twanmo plays the patriarch as a kind of insurance salesman battling forgetfulness); and, finally, of Hamlet, which Jacob H. Knoll pulls off as an angry young Dane. Christopher Carter Sanderson, the director, shows that the play's the thing, indoors or out (3:00). Roy Arias Theater Center at Times Square Arts Center, 300 West 43rd Street, Clinton; closes on Tuesday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'MEMORY'  Jonathan Lichtenstein's play is an engrossing but overcomplicated backstage story that gradually bleeds into a tale of a Holocaust survivor facing up to painful memories. And there's a side plot about a Palestinian losing his home. In any case, superb acting holds the attention in this mainstage entry in the Brits Off Broadway festival (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MOON ON A RAINBOW SHAWL' This is a lyrical example of kitchen-sink realism, a slice of life about neighbors who live around a crowded, cacophonous yard in Port of Spain, Trinidad. Written by Errol John and first produced in 1958, it deserves to be better known. This small, committed production, directed by Shirley Parkinson Wright, with outstanding performances by Lola Loui and Erwin E. A. Thomas, is infused with a love and understanding of the material (2:00 ). Henry Street Settlement's Abrons Arts Center/Recital Hall, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 353-1176; closes on Sunday. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'OF MICE AND MEN' The 70th-anniversary production of John Steinbeck's classic of two Depression-era ranch hands feels as stylized as an after-school special and just oversimplified. The actors work hard but their efforts fall short. (2:15) Urban Stages, 259 West 30th Street, (212) 868-4444; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'THE RECeiPT' A lost bar receipt provides a one-way ticket to bedlam in a clever and diverting show that mirrors the idiosyncrasies of modern life as two young archaeologists study a ''lost'' city and postulate on a day in the life of one of its inhabitants (1:15). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AWAY FROM HER' (PG-13, 110 minutes) Sarah Polley's well-observed adaptation of a story by Alice Munro is a quiet tour de force about love and loss, anchored by fine performances by Gordon Pinsent and Julie Christie as a couple dealing with the loss of memory and memories of past hurt. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BRAND UPON THE BRAIN' (No rating, 96 minutes) A baroque entertainment with one foot in silent cinema and the other gingerly toeing the sound waves, Guy Maddin's latest centers on a man who, in visiting a now-emptied foundling home, journeys deep into his childhood. It's wild! It's weird! It's strangely touching and a total must-see! (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BROOKLYN RULES' (R, 99 minutes) However authentic and heartfelt the film's depiction of life on the meaner streets of the Northeast corridor may be, this story of three friends growing up in a mob-infested Brooklyn neighborhood doesn't begin to match ''The Sopranos'' in its epic vision of violence, class struggle and upward mobility in a barbarous culture. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'DAY NIGHT DAY NIGHT' (No rating, 94 minutes) For most of its 94 minutes, this gripping but evasive portrait of an unidentified 19-year-old terrorist undertaking a suicide bombing mission in Times Square focuses on the face of its star, Luisa Williams. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'DISTURBIA' (PG-13, 104 minutes) A pleasant, scary, well-directed variation on the killer-next-door theme, with the engaging Shia LeBeouf as Kale, a young man who turns house arrest into an occasion for voyeurism and crime-fighting. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'EVEN MONEY' (R, 108 minutes) This grim, lurid scare movie about gambling addiction consists of several interlocking horror stories that converge in a format similar to that of ''Crash.'' More than its forerunner, this film sacrifices realism to forced plot mechanics. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE EX' (PG-13, 89 minutes) The best jokes in this scattershot screwball satire -- about the cutthroat workplace, job insecurity, upward mobility, political correctness, yuppie marital tensions and the disabled -- have claws that leave scratches. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FAY GRIM' (R, 118 minutes) Too light-headed to qualify as satire, too poker-faced to register as comedy, this elaborate spy spoof, a sequel to ''Henry Fool,'' belongs in its own stylistic niche: the Hal Hartley film. Movies emanating from Planet Hartley are an acquired taste shared by hipper-than-thou insiders. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FLANDERS' (No rating, 91 minutes, in French) Whether you like or loathe the movies of the French director Bruno Dumont, his unsettling vision of humanity stripped of cultural finery feels profoundly truthful. Beneath the facade of civilization, life is a barnyard. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FRACTURE' (R, 111 minutes) A glib entertainment that offers up the spectacle of that crafty scene-stealer Anthony Hopkins mixing it up with that equally cunning screen-nibbler Ryan Gosling. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GEORGIA RULE' (R, 111 minutes) Jane Fonda, Felicity Huffman and Lindsay Lohan play three generations of strong-willed, dysfunctional women in this comedy-melodrama from Garry Marshall. It's a mess, but it does have some vitality, thanks mainly to Ms. Fonda and Ms. Lohan. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than an entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'HOT FUZZ' (R, 121 minutes) A British parody of Hollywood-style action flicks from the wits behind ''Shaun of the Dead.'' Think of it as ''The Full Monty'' blown to smithereens. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'I DON'T WANT TO SLEEP ALONE' (No rating, 115 minutes, in Taiwanese, Malay, Mandarin and Bengali) A dreamy, melancholy tale of three-way desire, shot in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, and imagined by the director Tsai Ming-Liang with his usual blend of sensuality and formal rigor. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE INVISIBLE' (PG-13, 102 minutes) This supremely silly retread of the 2002 Swedish film ''Den Osynlige'' proves it's tough to be in love and in limbo at one and the same time. When a rich-yet-troubled teenager (Justin Chatwin) crosses paths with a violently disturbed classmate (Margarita Levieva), we learn that there's nothing quite like a near-death experience to repair those stubborn emotional wounds. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'NEXT' (PG-13, 96 minutes) Nicolas Cage plays a guy who can see into the future in this crummy adaptation of a nifty Philip K. Dick story. Too bad Mr. Cage couldn't tap into those same powers to save himself from another bad role. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'ONCE' (R, 88 minutes) A modest, scruffy movie about two musicians who meet on a Dublin street and sort of fall in love. Charming, touching and true. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'PARIS JE T'AIME' (R, 120 minutes, in French and English) ''Paris Je T'Aime,'' a mosaic of 18 miniatures, each set in a different location in the City of Light, is a cinematic tasting menu consisting entirely of amuse-bouches. After two hours of such tidbits, the palate is sated. But if there is no need for a main course, you still leave feeling vaguely disappointed at not being served one. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PIRATES OF THE CARIBBEAN: AT WORLD'S END' (PG-13, 167 minutes) This third and perhaps final episode in Gore Verbinski's swishy, swashbuckling saga wisely returns to the high-seas high jinx that made the first film so enjoyable. In service to a typically convoluted plot -- involving British perfidy, pieces of eight and a Godzilla-size sorceress -- all the usual suspects return to lie, swindle and marvel at Keith Richards's longevity, if not his line delivery. Jack Sparrow hallucinates, Barbossa agitates, and Elizabeth Swann is elected Pirate King. Really. Mr. Verbinski knows who wears the trousers in his trilogy. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'PERFECT STRANGER' (R, 109 minutes) There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish, paranoid thriller set in the New York media world that even after it lurches from the farfetched into the preposterous, the movie leaves a clammy residue of unease. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PROVOKED' (No rating, 113 minutes) Holding fast to the movie-of-the-week formula perfected by Lifetime Television, Jag Mundhra's overly restrained drama is based on the true story of Kiranjit Ahluwalia, a London-based Punjabi housewife who torched her sleeping husband in 1989 after suffering a decade of abuse. Unfortunately, by keeping its inflammatory subject matter at arm's length, ''Provoked'' does exactly the same to its audience. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SEVERANCE' (R, 90 minutes) A weapons company retreat in a Hungarian forest turns into a bloody game of whack-a-mole in this sophomore horror film from the British director Christopher Smith. The political argument may be broad -- there is some satisfaction in seeing the gung-ho team leader hoisted by his own explosive petard -- but the visual technique is sharp, creating a lively romp through terrain less traveled than you might think. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SHREK THE THIRD' (PG, 93 minutes) The ogre faces impending fatherhood and a career crisis. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SHOWBUSINESS' (PG, 102 minutes) This documentary by Dori Bernstein follows four Broadway musicals from rehearsal through the 2004 Tony Awards: ''Caroline, or Change''; ''Taboo''; ''Avenue Q''; and ''Wicked.'' On top of the usual challenges (fund-raising, rewrites, tryouts, marketing), they all had to endure scrutiny by theater critics and gossip columnists. Lively, sometimes cutting but mostly humane, ''ShowBusiness'' is packed with telling details. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'SPIDER-MAN 3' (PG-13, 139 minutes) Please, God, make this be the last one. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TA RA RUM PUM' (No rating, 156 minutes, in English and Hindi) This movie about a race car driver (the versatile Saif Ali Khan) takes place in New York, but that doesn't stop it from being a classic example of Bollywood family values. Here, all the city's a stage set, perfect for ''Fame''-meets-''West Side Story'' production numbers. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'300' (R, 116 minutes) Greeks versus Persians in the big rumble at Thermopylae, via Frank Miller's graphic novel. As dumb as they get. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 28 WEEKS LATER' (R, 91 minutes) The virus that killed off most of England -- after turning its population into rabid, flesh-hungry zombies -- seems to be under control at the start of this terrifying sequel to ''28 Days Later.'' But if anything, the horror is deeper, and the social criticism more acute. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VACANCY' (R, 80 minutes) This banal horror retread involves a couple of critters (Luke Wilson, Kate Beckinsale) flailing inside a sticky trap for what is, in effect, the big-screen equivalent of a roach motel. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VALET' (PG-13, 85 minutes, in French) If you love to hate the superrich, this delectable comedy, in which the great French actor Daniel Auteuil portrays a piggy billionaire industrialist facing his comeuppance, is a sinfully delicious bonbon, a classic French farce with modern touches. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WAITRESS' (PG-13, 104 minutes) Keri Russell is a small-town waitress in a bad marriage who finds solace in pie-baking and adultery in Adrienne Shelly's wry and winning final feature. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE WENDELL BAKER STORY' (PG-13, 99 minutes) This goofy slacker comedy is a Wilson family affair. Written by Luke Wilson, who co-directed with his older brother, Andrew, it also stars Owen Wilson as the title character's nemesis. Its appeal depends on how charming you find the Wilson brothers with their hip, smart-aleck attitude. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'YEAR OF THE DOG' (PG-13, 97 minutes) Mike White's touching comedy about a woman who loses a dog and finds herself is funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means that it's also funny in a kind of existential way. Molly Shannon stars alongside a menagerie of howling scene-stealers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ZOO' (No rating, 76 minutes) Robinson Devor's heavily reconstructed documentary is, to a large extent, about the rhetorical uses of beauty. It is, rather more coyly, also about a man who died after having sex with a stallion. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>SAM FULLER (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Museum of the Moving Image's continuing retrospective devoted to the blunt, visceral work of the tabloid reporter turned filmmaker Sam Fuller turns this weekend to his increasingly stylized work of the late 1950s. Included are rare archival prints of ''China Gate'' (1957), Fuller's anticipation of American involvement in Vietnam, starring Gene Barry and, in her first leading role, Angie Dickinson as a Eurasian lady of the evening; ''Run of the Arrow,'' a political western about a Confederate soldier (Rod Steiger) who learns about racism when he joins a Sioux tribe rather than surrender to the Union Army; and the eternally astonishing ''Forty Guns,'' a mad western in black-and-white CinemaScope, with Barbara Stanwyck as a ruthless land baroness. The sight of Stanwyck leading her private army -- the 40 guns of the title -- as they charge across an open plain is an unforgettable image. Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>BARRY LYNDON (Sunday through Tuesday) The Walter Reade Theater at Lincoln Center has landed a new 35-millimeter copy of Stanley Kubrick's 1975 historical drama, printed under the supervision of Kubrick's former assistant Leon Vitali. Ryan O'Neal stars as a devious but strangely dimwitted Irishman who climbs into the bed of a wealthy widow (Marisa Berenson) and up the ladder of 18th-century English society. The distant, painterly film -- you remember the candlelight more than the characters -- will be introduced by Mr. Vitali at three of the six scheduled screenings. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, (212) 875-5600, filmlinc.org; $11. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>THIRTY YEARS OF DANCE AFRICA (Today through Wednesday) As part of the Brooklyn Academy of Music's multimedia celebration of the DanceAfrica festival, the BAMcinématek is screening a well-chosen group of recent films with African themes. Running all week except Tuesday is ''Kirikou and the Wild Beasts'' (2006), Michel Ocelot's sequel to ''Kirikou and the Sorceress'' (1998), his popular animated film based on a West African folktale. The weekend highlights include Dumisani Phakathi's documentary about his search for his family in South Africa (tonight); ''The Night of Truth'' (2004), a drama by Fanta Régina Nacro about the social collapse of an imaginary West African country (tomorrow); and Mehdi Charef's ''Daughter of Keltoum'' (2001) a trip into the Berber region of Algeria (Sunday). BAMcinématek, BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DAN BERN (Tonight) With a nasal sing-speak that recalls the young Bob Dylan, Mr. Bern offers smooth folk-rock and a world-weary cynicism. (''There's nothing innocent about a newborn babe,'' he sings, ''that a few years here can't cure.'') At 7:30, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $16. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLACK REBEL MOTORCYCLE CLUB (Thursday) Not a Motorhead copycat, as its name would imply, but rather a dutiful and listless revivalist of the haystack hairdos and slithery gloom-rock of 1980s and early-'90s British bands like the Jesus and Mary Chain and Love and Rockets. Motorhead would be more exciting. With the Cobbs. At 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRAND NEW (Sunday and Tuesday) Not all emo goes the way of smirky punk-pop or sentimental singalongs. This excellent Long Island band plies dense, angry tangles of guitar and opaque lyrics of spiritual crisis, a cross between the grandeur of Pink Floyd and the agonized outbursts of Nirvana. With Anathallo and Colour Revolt. Sunday at 6 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Blender Theater at Gramercy, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; both sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRIGHT EYES, GILLIAN WELCH (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Monday through Thursday) In the indie-rock equivalent of Bruce Springsteen filling up Giants Stadium for weeks on end, Bright Eyes -- consisting of the painfully, excessively confessional man-child Conor Oberst and whomever he's playing with -- has sold out seven shows at Town Hall, beginning tonight. His guest is Gillian Welch, who plays a mellow bluegrass-folk hybrid with grace. At 7:30, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, the-townhall-nyc.org. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE BRAVERY (Tuesday and Wednesday) Disco first met punk in Britain in the late '70s, but they have had quite a romance in turn-of-the-21st-century New York. The Bravery arrived a few years ago with catchy, radio-ready songs and buckets of hair gel; the band has been compared, accurately, to the Strokes, New Order, U2 and Franz Ferdinand. With the Photo Atlas and the Cinematics. At 9 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday and Monday) Elegant, witty and touching, this classically trained jazz pianist and singer, now 82, is in her prime: the female counterpart of Bobby Short. Sunday at 2 p.m., Monday at 8 p.m., Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $58 on Sunday, with brunch at noon; $40 on Monday, with a $20 minimum. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>COMAS (Tomorrow and Thursday) This Brooklyn band pushes garage-rock into a soulful psychedelia. Fans used to comb Andy Herod's lyrics for not-so-veiled references to his breakup with the actress Michelle Williams. He's still smarting about heartbreak on the band's new album, ''Spells'' (Vagrant), but the objects of his longing are a little more obscure -- what does ''telepathic aftertaste'' mean, for example, and is it good or bad if your girlfriend has it? With the Broken West and Nethers. Tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $12. Thursday at 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DICK DALE (Sunday) Dick Dale, king of the surf guitar, provides no polite nostalgia trip to the mid-1960s. He's out to summon elemental forces with the stomping beat of his band and his heavily reverbed, brusquely attacked guitar lines, along with the dive-bombing, tremolo glissandos that literally melt his guitar picks from the heat of their friction on the strings. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $20 in advance, $25.50 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DEAD INFECTION, MORTICIAN (Today) Dead Infection, a veteran Polish grindcore band on its first United States tour, dispensed long ago with the problem of finding the appropriate lyrics for its high-speed, guttural churn of guitars; the vocals are simply deep, wordless growls -- a sort of universal language of metal. Mortician, from Yonkers, has only two members, but with its indistinct rumble and relentless drum blasts, it sounds like an invading alien army. With Regurgitate and Malignancy. At 5 p.m., Europa, 98 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-2322, europaclub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOS DEF (Tomorrow) Though Hollywood jobs take up most of his time these days, Mos Def, once the great, socially conscious hope of New York hip-hop, has never walked away from his calling as a rapper. When he's not feeling sluggish or preoccupied -- or simply bored, as he says on his latest album, ''True Magic'' (Geffen) -- he is a passionately literate and polemical performer. At 9 p.m., Highline Ballroom, 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIRTY DOZEN BRASS BAND (Wednesday) The magnificent ensemble that revitalized New Orleans brass-band music. It swaggers through the city's whole musical heritage: parades, rumba, swing, bebop and modern jazz, for starters. Solos can head for the far side of tonality, but the band never loses touch with gutbucket, danceable funk. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $16 in advance, $19 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>EARTH, WIND AND FIRE (Tuesday) In its 1970s heyday, Earth, Wind and Fire was the glossy, horn-powered hit machine that covered all bases, from idealism (''Keep Your Head to the Sky,'' ''Shining Star'') to dance tunes (''Boogie Wonderland'') to lovers' pleas (''Reasons''). At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; sold out. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>KEANE (Wednesday) This British band consists of just a drummer, a singer and an awfully hard-working keyboardist, but manages to flesh out beautifully melodramatic songs of yearning and self-pity with rich sonorities and sharp hooks that make you swear that there's a guitar in there somewhere. With Rocco Deluca and the Burden. At 5:30 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, Central Park, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KIKI AND HERB (Sunday) A few years ago this brilliantly perverse cabaret duo played their farewell show at Carnegie Hall. Then came a run on Broadway. And some late-night gigs at Joe's Pub. And the inimitable Christmas show. (Highlight: a medley of ''Smells Like Teen Spirit'' and ''Frosty the Snowman.'') Kiki and Herb can't stay away from the stage, and New York is the better for it. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LIFESAVAS (Tonight) There are plenty of criminals and scofflaws on ''Gutterfly'' (Quannum Projects), the excellent new concept album -- a funk-drenched soundtrack to an imaginary blackxploitation movie from the 1970s -- by this underground hip-hop trio from Portland, Ore. (The group really went the distance with it: George Clinton makes an appearance.) But the twist here is that the gangsters and dealers are the bad guys, and the Lifesavas play the law enforcers, fighting crime with style on the streets of ''Razorblade City.'' With Strange Fruit Project. At 8, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LIGHTNING BOLT, DMBQ, BIG A LITTLE A, APES (Tomorrow) At first it's hard to believe that all the glorious chaos of Lightning Bolt, from Providence, R.I., is being made by only two people. But as the sound comes into focus, a playful give-and-take becomes clear, as the bassist Brian Gibson and the drummer and vocalist Brian Chippendale toss back and forth gigantic metal riffs and giggly high notes, creating rainbows of dissonance. In the latest of several recent New York gigs, Lightning Bolt plays with the Japanese '70s-metal revivalists DMBQ; the passionately clamorous local experimenters Big A Little A; and the Apes, from Washington, whose spooky, keyboard-driven grooves quickly turn violent. At 8 p.m., 600 Bushwick Avenue, at Jefferson Street, Bushwick, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MEMPHIS (Wednesday and Thursday) Fans of Stars, the superbly urbane indie-cabaret band from Toronto, have been waiting three long years for a new album. (Its new remix disc is cold comfort.) Torquil Campbell, one of its singers and the band's resident wit, helps tide followers over with Memphis, his side project with Chris Dumont. The delicate melodies and cool dissection of heartbreak on Memphis's latest album, ''A Little Place in the Wilderness'' (Good Fences), are vaguely Stars-y, but it only makes the wait that much harder. Wednesday at 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $15. Thursday at 8 p.m., with Mascott and Jade McNelis, at Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* THE NATIONAL (Monday through Thursday) This Brooklyn group has become an under-the-radar local hit with flawless, wilting ballads featuring subtly inventive guitar playing by Bryce Dessner and the weary, cynical baritone of Matt Berninger, who seems pained by his ability to conjure cruelties like ''You could have been a legend/But you became a father.'' These first four shows of a five-night sold-out run also feature the Broken West (Monday), Doveman (Tuesday), My Brightest Diamond (Wednesday) and Elysian Fields (Thursday). At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JENNIFER O'CONNOR (Wednesday) Ms. O'Connor's portraits of the lovelorn and depressed, sung with the guileless vulnerability of a 2 a.m. phone confession, are dry but not unsympathetic: ''Maybe she's on her lunch break thinking of you.'' She has a Wednesday residency this month at the Living Room. At 11 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JOHN PIZZARELLI AND JESSICA MOLASKEY (Tonight and tomorrow night) These married musicians have been called ''the Nick and Nora of cabaret,'' a sobriquet that only begins to describe their upbeat sophistication. They fuse two distantly related musical worlds into a larger whole in which Stephen Sondheim, Dave Frishberg, Paul Simon, and Lambert, Hendricks and Ross join hands. At 8:45 and 10:45, Café Carlyle, at the Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; $85. (Holden)</p>
        <p>T-PAIN (Thursday) The former Faheem Najm of Tallahassee, Fla., offered a concise résumé in the title of his 2005 debut album: ''Rappa Ternt Sanga.'' He broke big with the equally self-descriptive ''I'm N Luv (Wit a Stripper),'' but on his new album he confesses that he doesn't mind being domesticated by the right woman. ''She got me doin' the dishes,'' he sings. ''Anything she want for some kisses.'' Aww. At 8 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROGER WATERS (Wednesday) Calling himself with characteristic modesty ''the creative genius of Pink Floyd,'' Mr. Waters continues his extensive tour performing ''The Dark Side of the Moon,'' his former band's epochal 1973 concept album about insanity. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $39 to $174.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>!!! (Wednesday) Punk-funk usually leans on the punk side, with short blasts of indignation or defiance filtered through dance beats. This local eight-piece (whose name is pronounced ''chik-chik-chik,'' or, they say, however you want) goes for immersion, transcendence and kicks through long and steady workouts of aggressive disco-rock, making each groove last until it burns up or falls apart. With Maserati and Telepathe. At 8 p.m., Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $16. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>THEO BLECKMAN AND BEN MONDER (Tuesday) Mr. Bleckman, a vocalist, and Mr. Monder, a guitarist, share a fondness for diaphanous atmosphere, as they demonstrate on ''At Night'' (Songlines), their mysterious new album. At 10 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, near Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 614-0505, bowerypoetry.com; cover, $8. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>REGINA CARTER (Wednesday and Thursday) Ms. Carter, a recent MacArthur fellow, is one of jazz's top violinists, equally at home with burnished romanticism and hard-driving swing. (Through June 2.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL CHARLAP TRIO (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The new Blue Note album by this standard-bearing trio is called ''Live at the Village Vanguard,'' but here they hold court elsewhere. As always, the pianist Bill Charlap enjoys crisp support from Peter Washington on bass and Kenny Washington on drums. (Through June 3.) At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CARLA COOK (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Cook is a confident and vivacious jazz singer with a growing book of original tunes. At 9 and 11, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AL FOSTER QUARTET WITH WALLACE RONEY (Tonight and tomorrow night) This two-night stand, which bears the subtitle ''A Tribute to Miles,'' commemorates the fact that Al Foster was once the drummer with Miles Davis, and Wallace Roney was once Davis's anointed heir. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $28. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIZZY GILLESPIE ALL-STAR BIG BAND (Tonight through Sunday night) Dizzy Gillespie, Bebop's goateed ambassador, did some of his best work with big bands, a fact that this one, led by his former trombonist Slide Hampton, happily exploits. The band includes other veterans of Gillespie's employ, like the saxophonists James Moody and Jimmy Heath. The trumpeter Roy Hargrove is a fine choice to fill Gillespie's shoes. At 8 and 10:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BILLY HART QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Revisiting the assertive post-bop of his recent album ''Quartet'' (High Note), the drummer Billy Hart fronts a dream team of younger players: the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the bassist Ben Street. (Through June 3.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20 to $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARI HOENIG (Tonight and Monday night) Mr. Hoenig, an irrepressibly kinetic drummer, recently issued ''Inversations'' (Dreyfus), an album that proves his adroitness as a composer while confirming his rapport with the pianist Jean-Michel Pilc. On Monday he plays in a trio with Mr. Pilc; tonight he communes with Joel Frahm on tenor saxophone, Orlando Le Fleming on bass and Gilad Hekselman on guitar. At 9 and 10:30, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, smallsjazzclub.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BOBBY HUTCHERSON QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Bobby Hutcherson has been the chief proponent of a harmonically restless post-bop vibraphone style for some 40 years. Celebrating the release of a quiet new album, ''For Sentimental Reasons'' (Kind of Blue), he leads a blue-chip rhythm section composed of Russell Malone on guitar, Renee Rosnes on piano, Dwayne Burno on bass and Al Foster on drums. (Through June 3.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAZZ MANDOLIN PROJECT (Wednesday) This groove-oriented band, led by the mandolin virtuoso Jamie Masefield, presents an original multimedia work inspired by one of Leo Tolstoy's short stories, and driven by an ideal of environmental conservation. At 8 p.m., Highline Ballroom, 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; $15 in advance, $17 at the door. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRISTINE JENSEN (Monday) Ms. Jensen, a saxophonist based in Montreal, makes a New York appearance with her more established sister, the trumpeter Ingrid Jensen. The pianist Dave Restivo, the bassist Fraser Hollins and the drummer Jon Wikan round out the band. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $15, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEF LEE JOHNSON BAND/ROB REDDY TRIO (Tonight) Groove is the common denominator of these two progressive trios, the first led by the guitarist and vocalist Jef Lee Johnson, and the second organized by Rob Reddy, a saxophonist. At 9, Jalopy Theater, 315 Columbia Street, Brooklyn, (718) 395-3214, jalopy.biz; $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEE KONITZ AND DAN TEPFER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Konitz, who will turn 80 this year, applies his dry-martini alto saxophone tone to a round of duets with Mr. Tepfer, a pianist now in his mid-20s. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE KUHN (Tonight) The estimable Mr. Kuhn, who has lately been working with great success in a trio, ventures unaccompanied into the Fazioli Salon, a weekly solo piano series at the Klavierhaus workshop near Carnegie Hall. At 8 p.m., Klavierhaus, 211 West 58th Street, Manhattan, (212) 245-4535, pianoculture.com; $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RUSS LOSSING GROUP/KRIS DAVIS QUARTET (Wednesday) For this week's installment of the smartly programmed Night of Ravished Limbs series, the keyboardist Russ Lossing opens with a quartet that includes Mat Maneri on viola, Ben Monder on guitar and Michaël Attias on saxophones. Then Kris Davis, another keyboardist, corrals the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, the bassist Eivind Opvsik and the drummer Jeff Davis. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10 a set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE MAINIERI AND STEPS AHEAD (Thursday) It has been roughly 30 years since the vibraphonist Mike Mainieri established Steps Ahead, a polished yet often intrepid fusion outfit. He now presides over an edition of the group featuring the saxophonist Bill Evans, the guitarist Mike Stern, the bassist Anthony Jackson and the drummer Steve Smith. (Through June 2.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY'S NOVELA (Tomorrow) Yet another adventurous new project from the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, with Nate Wooley on trumpet, Ben Gerstein on trombone, Angelica Sanchez on piano, Jason Ajemian on bass and Chad Taylor on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* WYNTON MARSALIS SEPTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Fifteen years ago Wynton Marsalis closed the Jazz at Lincoln Center concert season with ''In This House, on This Morning,'' an original commission thematically linked to the customs of the gospel church. Now Mr. Marsalis ends the current season by calling upon some of the same musicians, including the trombonist Wycliffe Gordon and the drummer Herlin Riley, to reinterpret that evocative work. At 8, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOE MARTIN QUARTET (Thursday) Joe Martin, a versatile bassist and a thoughtful composer, leads a post-bop band with John Ellis on saxophones, Aaron Parks on piano and Obed Calvaire on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONNY MCCASLIN TRIO (Tuesday) Latin rhythms have become an increasingly prominent concern for the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin, who seems likely to take a strenuous approach in this pared-down setting, with Thomas Morgan on bass and Richie Barshay on drums. At 9 p.m. and midnight, Louis 649, 649 East Ninth Street, at Avenue C, East Village, (212) 673-1190, louis649.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER (Thursday) In the hands of Mr. Monder the electric guitar is a coloristic instrument. He features his coolly convoluted pieces for a trio with Chris Lightcap on bass and Ted Poor drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NEW LANGUAGES FESTIVAL (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Advancing an ideal of cross-fertilization, this Williamsburg, Brooklyn, festival is organized partly by the alto saxophonist Jackson Moore, who leads a trio tomorrow night at 10. The schedule also includes Attack/Adorn/Decay, a project of the trumpeter Nate Wooley (tonight at 10); Heavy Merge, a trio led by the pianist Russ Lossing (tomorrow night at 8:30); and the Indo-Pak Coalition, assembled by the alto saxophonist Rudresh Mahanthappa (Thursday night at 8:30). At 8:30, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Rose Live Music, 345 Grand Street, near Marcy Avenue, Williamsburg, (646) 644-2766, newlanguages.org; $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PLAYDATE (Wednesday) The guitarist Amanda Monaco and the pianist Noah Baerman are the core of this whimsically named ensemble, which also includes the bassist Henry Lugo and the drummer Vinnie Sperrazza, along with Steve Wilson, a special guest, on alto saxophone. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $15, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TODD SICKAFOOSE'S BLOOD ORANGE (Tonight) A bassist and composer equally fond of rough edges and rounded forms, Todd Sickafoose performs here with two guitarists (Adam Levy and Mike Gamble), two drummers (Allison Miller and Simon Lott) and a frontline of Shane Endsley on trumpet, Ben Wendel on saxophones and Alan Ferber on trombone. At 9 and 10, Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DR. LONNIE SMITH TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Under the command of Dr. Lonnie Smith, the Hammond B-3 organ can be subtly atmospheric or growlingly ecstatic; together with the guitarist Peter Bernstein and the drummer Anthony Pinciotti, he makes a searching brand of soul jazz. (Through June 3.) At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20 to $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE STERN BAND (Monday and Wednesday) The guitarist Mike Stern has a goofily titled but musically rewarding recent album, ''Who Let the Cats Out?'' (Heads Up), that only begins to capture the energy of this longstanding regular engagement. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETER VAN HUFFEL QUINTET (Sunday and Thursday) On his new release, ''Silvester Battlefield'' (Fresh Sound New Talent), the saxophonist Peter Van Huffel showcases his exploratory compositions for this working band with the pianist Jesse Stacken, the guitarist Scott DuBois, the bassist Michael Bates and the drummer Jeff Davis. Sunday at 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. Thursday at 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JEFF (TAIN) WATTS QUARTET (Tomorrow and Sunday) Jeff (Tain) Watts, an ingeniously propulsive drummer, has a new album, ''Folk Songs'' (Dark Key Music), that consists almost entirely of his own sturdy tunes. The tenor saxophonist Marcus Strickland and the pianist David Kikowski are both featured on the album; the bassist James Genus fills in here for Christian McBride. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KENNY WERNER (Tonight) Mr. Werner is a well-seasoned pianist who tempers his technique with a kind of questing spiritualism, an appropriate quality for this solo recital in a museum of Himalayan art. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'FALSTAFF' (Tomorrow and Sunday) In its heyday on Bleecker Street, Amato Opera was where young New Yorkers saw their first operas; in its current home on the Bowery, it has taken on a certain quality of camp. But its loyal fans still love it, and it still loves opera. It offers Verdi with all of that love, if too few of the musical skills required to perform it, so that some of it, by gosh, still gets across. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Amato Opera, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200, amato.org; $35; $28 for students and 65+. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday) Bargemusic, the floating chamber music hall on the Brooklyn side of the East River, is offering varied programs this week. Tonight Mira Jevitch offers a piano recital that runs from Romantic works by Brahms and Liszt to movements from ''Eight Voyages'' by the contemporary Australian composer Grant Foster. Tomorrow and Sunday the Manhattan String Quartet performs Beethoven's three Opus 59 quartets. And on Wednesday the Sonar Players offer an overview of George Crumb's music, including two of his 1970s classics, ''Vox Balaenae'' (1971) and ''Black Angels'' (1970) for electric string quartet. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Wednesday at 8 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35; $30 for 65+ tonight; $20 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>EMERSON STRING QUARTET (Thursday) Playing string quartets in a 2,800-seat hall may contradict the term ''chamber music,'' but this is a chance for a larger audience to hear a distinguished American ensemble playing Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $32 to $79. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>* KONSTANTIN LIFSCHITZ (Sunday) Last year the Free for All at Town Hall series presented this Russian-born pianist in a marathon event, playing the 24 Preludes and Fugues of Shostakovich in two programs on a single Sunday. Mr. Lifschitz, who won high praise for that performance, returns to the Free for All series with an even more daunting marathon, the 48 Preludes and Fugues of Bach, again to be played in two programs on Sunday. At 2 and 7 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 707-8787, freeforallattownhall.org; free, but tickets are required. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Tonight and tomorrow night) Julian Rachlin, a Lithuanian-born violinist who lives in Austria, has been playing with Lorin Maazel since a tender age. He returns with the Philharmonic this weekend to offer Saint-Saëns's Third Concerto. Of more musical weight, perhaps, is Bartok's Concerto for Orchestra, which Mr. Maazel should use to put the orchestra through its paces. Also on the program is Rimsky-Korsakov's ''Russian Easter'' Overture. At 8, Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $28 to $96. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK YOUTH SYMPHONY (Sunday) There is nothing like hearing a major repertory work performed by exuberant and gifted musicians who are palpably excited to be playing the piece. The New York Youth Symphony has been delivering such performances for the last five years under its dynamic young music director, Paul Haas. Mr. Haas ends his tenure on Sunday with a particularly ambitious program: arrangements of Bach chorales, the premiere of Dan Visconti's ''Some Day the Sun Won't Shine,'' and Mahler's daunting Ninth Symphony. At 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $7 to $55. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>JOHN SCOTT (Tomorrow) Mr. Scott, the organist and music director at St. Thomas Church, plays the last concert in his 10-part series exploring the organ works of Buxtehude, in honor of the 300th anniversary of that composer's death. Built in a style similar to that seen in northern Germany and the Netherlands in the 17th and 18th centuries, St. Thomas's Taylor &amp; Boody organ is ideal for this venture. At 4 p.m., Fifth Avenue at 53rd Street, (212) 757-7013, saintthomaschurch.org; free. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN BALLET THEATER (Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday) The programming this week pairs two master ballet choreographers, George Balanchine and Frederick Ashton, whose styles may be polar opposites but whose love for the art form shines through in the works that will represent them. A number of role debuts promise to add spice to Balanchine's ''Symphonie Concertante,'' an elegant re-envisioning of Mozart in movement, and Ashton's ''Dream,'' Shakespeare's ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' in a magical new realm. Among those making debuts in their roles are Gillian Murphy and David Hallberg (tomorrow afternoon), who would seem to have been born to dance Titania and Oberon in ''Dream.'' Diana Vishneva, Angel Corella and Craig Salstein as Puck (Tuesday) are not far behind. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Monday and Tuesday at 8 p.m.; Wednesday at 2 and 8 p.m.; Thursday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, abt.org; $24 to $110. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* WALLY CARDONA QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) ''Site'' examines the artist's will to construct something out of nothing. (Through June 2.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $25; $15 for students and 65+. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>'CROSSING BOUNDARIES' (Tuesday) Artists featured in this showcase, chosen by Marcia Monroe, include Joyce S. Lim, Elke Rindfleisch, Adrienne Fadjo, Rachel Bernsen and Taylor Ho Bynum. At 8 p.m., Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, dixonplace.org; $10 to $12, and Theater Development Fund vouchers accepted. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DANCEAFRICA (Tonight through Sunday) This annual festival at the Brooklyn Academy of Music celebrates three decades of African and African-American dance with performances by the Bambara Drum and Dance Ensemble, Forces of Nature Dance Theater Company, Kulu Mele African American Dance Ensemble, Ndere Troupe, Sabar Ak Ru Afriq Dance Theater and BAM/Restoration DanceAfrica Ensemble. Tonight at 7:30; Saturday and Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m.; BAM Howard Gilman Opera House, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $15 to $45; $10 for under 16. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT THE CHOCOLATE FACTORY (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Michael Helland's ''Dress Up Show'' will be performed tonight and tomorrow night. Starting on Thursday night, Renee Archibald's ''Oh Dear Natascha'' explores darkness and confinement in an environment filled with small piles of samples and clippings quietly waiting, as Ms. Archibald puts it, ''for an imaginary domestic life in various imaginary cities.'' Well, why not? (''Oh Dear Natascha,'' through June 2.) At 8, the Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101, chocolatefactorytheater.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EAR TO THE GROUND (Thursday) A program of premieres by Anita Cheng and Noopur Singha honors Asian Heritage Month. (Through June 2.) At 7:30 p.m., Mulberry Street Theater, 70 Mulberry Street, Chinatown, (212) 349-0126; $14; $12 for students and 65+. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>HILARY EASTON AND COMPANY (Thursday) ''It's All True'' concerns a man grappling with his recollections and trying to distinguish fact from fiction. (Through June 3.) At 8 p.m., the Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200; $25. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>KOOSIL-JA'S MECH[A] OUTPUT (Thursday) Koosil-Ja Hwang blends elements of dance and music from the classic Japanese Noh play ''Dojoji'' with what Ms. Hwang describes as multimedia technology, including live 3-D video. (Through June 2.) At 7:30 p.m., Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>TIFFANY MILLS COMPANY (Thursday) In ''LandFall'' three interlocking duets evoke the physical and emotional power of a storm. (Through June 3.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $30 for opening night. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* MOMIX (Tuesday through Thursday) A company that revels in theatrical illusion reviews a quarter-century in ''Momix reMIX.'' (Through June 10.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $44. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>BEN MUNISTERI DANCE PROJECTS (Thursday) In Mr. Munisteri's new ''Terra Nova,'' dancers leave a design of moving colors and patterns in their wake, courtesy of motion-capture technology. (Through June 3.) At 8 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The week's programs are ''Four Voices,'' consisting of Christopher Wheeldon's ''Carousel (a Dance),'' Alexei Ratmansky's ''Middle Duet,'' Jerome Robbins's ''Moves'' and Balanchine's ''Sonnambula''; ''Essential Robbins,'' with ''In G Major,'' ''Dances at a Gathering'' and ''I'm Old- Fashioned''; ''Essential Balanchine,'' with ''Walpurgisnacht Ballet,'' ''Liebeslieder Walzer'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements''; and ''Three Masters: Tchaikovsky, Balanchine, Robbins,'' which features Balanchine's ''Mozartiana'' and ''Tchaikovsky Piano Concerto No. 2,'' and Robbins's ''Piano Pieces'' and ''International Balanchine'' (''Serenade,'' ''Bugaku'' and ''Union Jack''). Kyra Nichols, who retires at the end of the season, will dance ''Mozartiana,'' in a role that brings out all her innate musicality, with Ashley Bouder and Jonathan Stafford new in ''Tchaikovsky.'' Maria Kowroski is an intriguing choice for the sensuous geisha in ''Bugaku,'' which she will dance for the first time. And Robbins's ''Dances at a Gathering'' will feature debuts by Jenifer Ringer, Megan Fairchild, Sarah Mearns and Adam Hendrickson on Thursday. ''Four Voices,'' tonight at 8; ''Essential Robbins,'' tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Tuesday at 7:30 p.m.; ''Symphony in Three Movements,'' tomorrow night at 8; ''Three Masters,'' Sunday at 3 p.m.; ''International Balanchine,'' Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $15 to $86. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>STREB S.L.A.M. (Tonight through Sunday) High-flying, wall-crashing thrills and chills, and popcorn besides. (Through June 17.) Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 3 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Streb Laboratory for Action Mechanics, 51 North First Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, strebusa.org; $20; $10 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* 2007 TAP EXTRAVAGANZA (Sunday) This annual event, presented by the New York Committee to Celebrate National Tap Dance Day, is just the ticket for tap enthusiasts and dance fans who have to have a little unruly fun with their art form. The lineup includes Jimmy Slyde, Mable Lee, Dormesha Sumbry Edwards and Savion Glover. And Mr. Glover's mother, Yvette, a powerful singer, will be honored along with Bob Audy and Deborah Mitchell, tap teachers and choreographers. At 7 p.m., Fashion Institute of Technology, Haft Auditorium, 227 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $25 to $65. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'GLOBAL FEMINISMS,' through July 1. Too much of the work in this sprawling, international assembly of recent pieces by nearly 90 women from nearly 50 countries is body-oriented and doesn't venture far beyond the essentialism of Judy Chicago's indomitable 1975-79 installation opus, ''The Dinner Party,'' whose enshrinement in the new Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art this exhibition celebrates. Nearly devoid of significant painting and sculpture and Thoroughly dominated by photography and video, with a documentary slant to many of its better moments, the show is more about information, politics and the struggle for equality than it is about art in any very concentrated or satisfying sense. That doesn't keep parts of it from being energetic and illuminating, especially as a record of the way that feminism has gripped and jump-started the imaginations of women around the world. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by Durand has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet and journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape. He explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage and rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. Like its two predecessors, this ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field of design, but fails to call it to order. The inclusions range from genius to schlock, delightful to dispiriting. They cover medical innovation, military hardware, completely frivolous reiterations of received ideas (far too many of which trace to Surrealism), sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and recycling -- more varieties of recycling than you can easily count. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Grey Art Gallery: 'Beyond the White Cube: A Retrospective of Brian O'Doherty/Patrick Ireland,' through July 14. Starting in the mid-1960s and in concert with the most influential thinkers of the period (Roland Barthes, Marcel Duchamp and Susan Sontag), Brian O'Doherty made Conceptual art in a Minimalist vein. This show displays his sculptures, drawings, performance videos, paintings and rope drawings, which could easily be called installations. It's a must-see show for anyone who wants to understand the conceptual frameworks that underpin so much of today's most significant installation and performance art. 100 Washington Square East, Greenwich Village, (212) 998-6780, nyu.edu/greyart/. (Bridget L. Goodbody)</p>
        <p>GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'DIVISIONISM/NEO-IMPRESSIONISM: ARCADIA AND ANARCHY,' through Aug. 6. Ultimately this rare, compressed, mercurial exhibition of work by the Italian Divisionists of the 1890s is long on history and short on truly convincing paintings. The inclusion of works by Seurat and his French, Dutch and Belgian followers clarifies how the Italians pushed Pointillism, Seurat's invention, in all directions: toward realism, academic classicism, Symbolism, class consciousness and even Impressionism. The show opens a new, albeit small, window on the genesis of Modernism beyond the French canon. If many of the works are period pieces, they are also immensely appealing, big-hearted and physically robust period pieces. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'BIOGRAPHICAL LANDSCAPE: THE PHOTOGRAPHY OF STEPHEN SHORE, 1969-1979,' through Sept. 9. In 1971 the Metropolitan Museum of Art gave Stephen Shore its second-ever exhibition by a living photographer. (Alfred Stieglitz had the first.) He was 23 when it opened. What he did makes up most of this wonderful show. Mr. Shore has reprinted the photographs digitally, with rejuvenated colors as fresh and subtle as the day the pictures were shot. The work's laconic eloquence speaks of an era and a nation. Its wit and affection add buoyancy to scenes of threadbare America from a moment when the country was depressed by war and years of civil unrest. Its formal rigor makes an uncanny order out of images that, at first glance, look like no place or nothing. Look again. His show reminds us of a period when cutting-edge American art and the tradition of straight, documentary photography got together. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at West 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'Let Your Motto Be Resistance: African American Portraits,' through Sept. 9. This show of photographic portraits is a praise-song in pictures, a shout-out to history. It's also a fancy-dress inaugural party for the yet-to-be-built National Museum of African American History and Culture in Washington. It tends to be a little too fancy, too heavy on glitz, too short on grit. Still, what a party it is, with a Who's Who of charismatic black statesmen, from Frederick Douglass to Malcolm X, and with Leontyne Price, Mahalia Jackson and the Supremes sharing a stage. (See above.) (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. It covers a broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls, not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>The Jewish Museum: Dateline: Israel: 'New Photography and Video Art,' through Aug. 5. Roughly every decade, the Jewish Museum offers a survey of contemporary art from and about Israel. This year non-Israeli artists from Europe and the United States -- and a single artist from Palestine -- have been added to the mix. There's some very good work here, though, on the whole, the show grapples with crucial political issues in an indirect way. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, jewishmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* THE METropolitan museum of art: 'Poiret: KING OF FASHION,' through Aug. 5. A revolutionary in revolutionary times, the fashion designer Paul Poiret introduced unstructured garments that freed women from corsets in 1906, the year before Picasso committed his decidedly uninhibited (and unstaid) ''Demoiselles d'Avignon'' to canvas. But the modern painter whom Poiret most resembles, in his love of the exotic, his brilliant use of color and pattern and his penchant for simplified, almost rudimentary form, is Matisse. This rare exhibition -- from the Met's Costume Institute -- does his sartorial genius justice with a spare installation rendered radiant by hand-painted silk backdrops of the leafy parks and luxurious drawing rooms of Paris. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>The Met: 'FRANK STELLA: PAINTING INTO ARCHITECTURE,' through July 29. Crammed into a gallery that feels like an obstacle course, this exhibition spans 43 years with 25 paintings, reliefs, drawings and architectural models, all with the goal of tracing an evolution that has not yet occurred. Taking up most of the space are enlarged versions of models that are considered sculptures -- and that look as if they date from the early 1960s. The main draws are the examples of the paintings and reliefs that are the basis of Mr. Stella's importance as an artist. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>The Met: 'FRANK STELLA ON THE ROOF,' through Oct. 28. Two large Pop Art sculptures, two architectural models and a model enlarged into a sculpture-installation piece confirm that one of the greatest American artists of the postwar era doesn't do himself or anyone else any favors when he strays from the wall to work fully in the round. The results have a certain Stella-like verve but are otherwise generic. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'Apocalypse Then: Medieval Illuminations From the Morgan,' through June 17. The symbolism of the Book of Revelation, with its demons and lakes of fire, has a subversive appeal. This new exhibition at the Morgan Library celebrates a facsimile of ''Las Huelgas Apocalypse'' (1220), the largest surviving Spanish illuminated commentary on the Apocalypse. The show, which includes 50 leaves from the original text, unbound and installed around the gallery's perimeter, offers a walking tour of the medieval imagination. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Andrea K. Scott)</p>
        <p>* El Museo del Barrio: 'The Disappeared (Los Desaparecidos),' through June 17. The most potent show of contemporary political art of the season, and one of the most moving shows of any kind in the city right now. The title refers to a peculiarly chilling form of violence associated with political upheavals in Latin America over the past 40 years, and now becoming more common in Iraq. 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212) 831-7272, elmuseo .org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of modern art: 'COMIC ABSTRACTION: IMAGE-BREAKING, IMAGE-MAKING,' through June 11. This unimaginative and uniformed treatment of a big idea -- the healthy and essential contamination of Modernist abstraction by popular culture -- should be seen if only because it is such a dispiriting symptom of the Modern's paralysis where contemporary art is concerned. Including 30 works by 13 artists from the last 16 years, it alternates between the literal and the arbitrary and favors sincere political intent over genuine artistic quality. Although it promises work that addresses ''perplexing questions,'' nearly everything here is perfectly pleasant and innocuous. The exceptions are provided by Gary Simmons, Ellen Gallagher and Sue Williams. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Neuberger Museum of Art: FUGITIVE ARTIST: THE EARLY WORK OF RICHARD PRINCE, 1974-77, through June 24. Mr. Prince is one of the most elusive, perverse and sardonic of all of the important appropriation artists to emerge in the early 1980s, so perhaps it is not surprising that he has boycotted this exhibition of little-known early work, all from public and private collections. But that doesn't stop the 50 pieces on view from revealing his roots in 1970s Conceptual Art; his progress from generic to original and radical; or the depth and duration of his fascination with language, photography, printmaking, the more banal forms of urban postwar Americana and a disconnected, decidedly male blankness. If anything, it increases his stature. Purchase College, State University of New York, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6100, neuberger.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Neue Galerie: 'Van Gogh and Expressionism,' through July 2. The Neue has, as usual, gathered a stellar roundup of Expressionist art. In one of the show's most exciting rooms, a third-floor gallery devoted mostly to self-portraits, two extraordinary van Goghs hang at opposite ends: ''Self-Portrait With Straw Hat'' (1887-88), from the Metropolitan Museum's collection, filled with energetic, radiating brushstrokes, and the National Gallery's vibrant self-portrait of the artist holding a palette and brushes, painted about a year later. The most compelling pairing in this room, though, is van Gogh's ''Bedroom'' from 1889, the second of three versions he painted of his room in Arles, with Egon Schiele's obvious homage, ''The Artist's Bedroom in Neulengbach,'' painted in 1911, in a darker palette and with a perspective tipped precariously toward the viewer. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, neuegalerie.org. (Martha Schwendener)</p>
        <p>STOREFRONT FOR ART AND ARCHITECTURE: 'CCCP: Cosmic Communist Constructions Photographed,' through June 16. Covering a period ignored by academics and mainstream architects, this show is packed with obscure architectural gems. It relies almost exclusively on the photographs of Frédéric Chaubin, who spent five years traveling across the former Soviet Union, uncovering forgotten architectural works in cities like Tbilisi, Yalta and Yerevan. The results are a revelation. Among the outright gems is Georgy Chakhava's 1975 Roads Ministry building, a monumental grid of interlocking concrete forms rising on a steep wooded site in Tbilisi, Georgia. Rising on an incline between two highways, the building's heavy, cantilevered forms reflect the Soviet-era penchant for heroic scale. Yet they also relate sensitively to their context, celebrating the natural landscape that flows directly underneath the building. What's refreshing about this exhibition is its lack of an ideological agenda: it is open to all sorts of possibilities. The Gaudiesque romanticism of a sanitarium in Druskininkai, Lithuania, for example, spins the aesthetic off in yet another direction. Compelling and easy to digest, this show piques our interest in ways that some larger institutions, ever more averse to risk, often fail to do. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>The Studio Museum in Harlem: 'Philosophy of Time Travel,' through July 1. This flawed show, which was created by a group of artists who studied together at the California Institute of the Arts, is nonetheless an interesting example of one of the art world's latest trends: the art collective. It takes Brancusi's ''Endless Column'' as its point of departure and reimagines this Modernist icon from the point of view of art school grads, who are versed in the language of artspeak and wed to the righteous cause of freedom of expression. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, studiomuseum.org. (Goodbody)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM AT ALTRIA: Matthew Brannon, 'Where Were We,' through Aug. 26. Matthew Brannon brings together art, poetry and advertising in a series of letterpress prints that hark back to 1950s and 1960s textile designs by Astrid Sampe and Marimekko. Texts written by the artist and accompanying the images read like song lyrics crossed with Conceptual Art and Language Poetry (which emphasized experimentalism and reader interaction). Consumption and excess are frequent references, as well as how art, design and fashion feed these modern yet primordial urges and desires. 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917) 663-2453, whitney.org. (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'LINCOLN KIRSTEIN,' through Aug. 27. In the middle of the last century Lincoln Kirstein particularly relished attacking the Museum of Modern Art. Pure abstraction was ridiculous, he thought. It had no standards. Against Mondrian and Pollock, he endorsed, among others, the artists in this show. They are the sculptors Elie Nadelman and Gaston Lachaise and the painters Paul Cadmus, who was Kirstein's brother-in-law, Walker Evans and Pavel Tchelitchew. With the exception of Evans, Kirstein's taste clearly hasn't won the day, but it's never bad to re-examine received opinions or to be reminded of a generous advocate. (See above.) (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Gordon MaTTA-cLARK rETROSPECTIVE,' through June 3. I have no doubt that Matta-Clark is now being turned into a hot commercial commodity, but at least at the Whitney you can see what he aspired to be. He came up with various wonderfully harebrained ideas. Literally, in one case: after letting his hair grow for a year, he cut it off as a kind of performance and phrenological gag. The preserved hair, dutifully tagged piece by piece, opens the show like a holy relic. At the center of the exhibition is ''Splitting.'' To a plain single-family suburban frame house in Englewood, N.J., he made a cut straight down the middle, bisecting the building, then severing the four corners of the roof. The retrospective consists of films, drawings, photographs and some of the architectural pieces he cut out of buildings. The drawings are casual and not too interesting, but the luxurious black-and-white photographs from Paris speak more to Matta-Clark's formal elegance. The big message was: Life as art, and art as life, a philosophy dependent on our being properly attuned and keen to the moment. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Taryn Simon,' through June 24. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics, yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly. Though she has also worked in war-torn areas, Ms. Simon is best known for ''The Innocents,'' a series of portraits of men and women who were wrongly convicted but later cleared by DNA test results. Ms. Simon can work as long as a year to gain permission to photograph high-security zones like the government-regulated quarantine sites, nuclear waste storage facilities, prison death rows and C.I.A. offices on view in the show. There are also pictures with lighter themes: the sandpit where the Grucci family tests fireworks, ski slopes being dynamited for avalanche control and the second Death Star, from ''Return of the Jedi,'' at George Lucas's Skywalker Ranch. Ms. Simon is at her artistic best when her delight in the strangeness of American culture shines. (See above.) (Goodbody)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>CLAUDE MONET (1840-1926): A TRIBUTE TO DANIEL WILDENSTEIN AND KATIA GRANOFF This exhibition of nearly 60 paintings by one of the most beloved painters in the world feels a little like having dinner with a celebrity. The gallery setting eliminates the usual distance; the startling intimacy allows you to experience afresh the momentum and innovations of Monet's astounding trajectory in the span of three small galleries. Basically, it is a chance to encounter, up close and in detail, the evolving ways of seeing and painting that established the originality, historical importance and continuing irresistibility of Monet's art. It should not be missed. Wildenstein &amp; Company, 19 East 64th Street, (212) 879-0500, through June 15. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>* 'Gego, Between Transparency and the Invisible' The artist named Gego was born Gertrud Goldschmidt in Germany in 1912, but lived most of her life in Venezuela, where she produced netlike drawings in ink and watercolor and what she called ''drawings without paper'': semi-geometric, see-through, two- and three-dimensional pieces of twisted and knotted wires, suspended in space. Whether you think of them as grids gone haywire or as rational forms charged with emotion, they're out of this world, and this small survey gives a good sense of what is distinctive and radical about Gego's art. The Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 219-2166, drawingcenter.org, through July 21. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>* MARTIN KIPPENBERGER: PREIS PAINTINGS Seven canvases from two series of paintings rarely exhibited in this country play on the double German meaning of preis (price and prize), some variation of which appears on each surface. They show this famous bad-boy sculptor conveying his usual sarcasm into surprisingly beautiful terms that couldn't get much flatter. Hard-edged and brushy techniques contrast the main tactics of formalist painting while converting the modernist grid into designs redolent of drapery and checked tablecloths. A preponderance of hot pink inveigles for the pleasure principle. 1018 Art, 1018 Madison Avenue, near 78th Street, (212) 537-0453, www.1018art.net, through July 27. (Smith)</p>
        <p>SOL LEWITT: DRAWING SERIES  If the greatness of Sol LeWitt, the Minimal-Conceptual artist who died in April at 78, has so far escaped you, this exhilarating show of 14 of his mind-teasing, eye-filling wall drawings from the late 1960s and early '70s may do the trick. Selected and arranged by the artist, they proceed in carefully sequenced contrasts and echoes that are both insightful and idiosyncratic. Since their generating instructions are part of their titles, they reduce the creative process to a short, highly visible straight line. But their crisp geometries, accumulating marks and radiating patterns force us to mind the gap between artistic thought and artistic action, to experience the inability of language to account fully for visual outcome. Dia:Beacon, 3 Beekman Street, Beacon, N.Y., (845) 440-0100, through Sept. 10. (Smith)</p>
        <p>JOAQUÍN TORRES-GARCÍA This choice exhibition concentrates on small, lively ink drawings from the early 1930s, when Torres-García ironed out Cubism into a compartmentalized grid that could either be abstract -- like Mondrian's work -- or a container for assorted symbols and hieroglyphs. Two earlier paintings underscore that, either way, his inspiration came from combined order and disorder of bustling city views. CDS Gallery, 76 East 79th Street, (212) 772-9555, through June 9. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Public Art</p>
        <p>Madison Square Park: Roxy Paine This installation is made up of two stainless-steel tree sculptures -- ''Conjoined'' and ''Defunct'' -- and a glacierlike boulder, ''Erratic,'' by Mr. Paine. The tree sculptures are made from thousands of pieces of metal pipe and rod elements that have been cut, welded and polished. They are real enough to resemble actual trees but not so real that they form a continuum with the surrounding foliage. What captures your immediate attention is ''Conjoined,'' a 40-foot-tall-by-45-foot-wide sculpture of two trees whose gleaming steel branches cantilever and then improbably connect in midair. It is impossible to tell where the branches of one tree begin and the other end. But the piece is also beautifully eccentric, a futuristic fantasy of streamlined vegetation manufactured in imitation of the real thing, only much more appealing and exciting. Madison Square Park, 23rd Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 538-4689, www.madisonsquarepark.org, through Dec. 31. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,'. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases, elegiac celebrations of farm workers raking and reaping grain, have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org.; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* 'Rebel, Rebel: Remembering Karlheinz Weinberger (1921-2006)' The self-taught Swiss photographer Karlheinz Weinberger, who died last year at 81, began his career taking pictures for a gay club in Zurich, but found his true subject in rebellious, working-class teenagers who dressed to shock in the 1960s and '70s. The Weinberger pictures in this show are fairly tame, as if chosen to complement the cooled-out work of the three younger artists -- Ryan McGinley, Walter Pfeiffer and Collier Schorr -- who surround him. But at his best, he's in a class by himself. Anna Kustera, 520 West 21st Street, (212) 989-0082, kusteratiltongallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. ? denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'BEYOND GLORY' Previews start today. Opens on June 21. War stories from Stephen Lang in this solo play based on the tales of eight veterans from World War II, Korea and Vietnam (1:20). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'THE BUTCHER OF BARABOO' In previews; opens on June 11. Did the butcher of Baraboo, Wis., kill her husband? Find out in this black comedy (2:00). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'CRAZY MARY' In previews; opens on June 3. In A. R. Gurney's new play, Sigourney Weaver stars as a woman who discovers that her cousin, the title character and a patient in a psychiatric hospital, holds the keys to the family fortune (2:00). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'EURYDICE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on June 18. The hot young playwright Sarah Ruhl (''The Clean House'') gives her spin on the classic myth of Orpheus and Eurydice (1:30). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'IN A DARK DARK HOUSE' In previews; opens on June 7. Neil LaBute's latest drama features Frederick Weller and Ron Livingston as hostile siblings sorting out a history of abuse (1:30). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'INTIMATE EXCHANGES' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on June 14. Alan Ayckbourn's eight different (but related) plays all begin with the same very modern question: should I smoke? Part of the Brits Off Broadway festival (1:30 to 2:15). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'SESSIONS' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on June 10. Albert Tapper's comic new musical takes place in a therapist's office. Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'TEA' In previews; opens on Wednesday. Set in Kansas in 1968, this play is about four Japanese war brides who gather to mourn a friend (1:30). West End Theater, 263 West 86th Street, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'10 MILLION MILES' In previews; opens on June 14. A new musical by the singer Patty Griffin and the playwright Keith Bunin (''The Busy World Is Hushed'') is about a road trip from Florida to New York. Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'XANADU' In previews; opens on June 26. The 1980 cult roller disco film about a Greek muse sent to earth goes Broadway -- and it's about time. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' Back on Broadway for the first time in 25 years, Angela Lansbury is so vitally and indelibly present that she even gives flesh to this flimsy comedy. Terrence McNally's play, about the reunion of two former doubles partners (Ms. Lansbury and Marian Seldes), is a jerry-built shrine to enduring star power. Directed by Michael Blakemore (1:45). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'FROST/NIXON' Frank Langella turns in a truly titanic performance as Richard M. Nixon in Peter Morgan's briskly entertaining, if all-too-tidy, play about the former president's annihilating television interviews with the British talk show host David Frost (the excellent Michael Sheen). Michael Grandage directs with the momentum of a ticking-bomb thriller and the zing of a boulevard comedy (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' Doug Hughes's wooden revival of this worthy war horse, based on the Scopes ''monkey'' trial of 1925, never musters much more velocity than a drugstore fan. Be grateful that the cast includes Christopher Plummer, in savory form as a Will Rogers of jurisprudence. An oddly subdued Brian Dennehy plays his pompous adversary (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40).Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' This nonstop sugar rush of a musical about a powder puff who finds her inner power-broker, based on the 2001 film, approximates the experience of eating a jumbo bag of Gummi Bears in one sitting. Flossing between songs is recommended (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' As Lotte Lenya and Kurt Weill, Donna Murphy and Michael Cerveris turn in stunningly shaded performances in what is, alas, a sluggish, mixed-up bio-musical. Scored with an eclectic sampler of Weill's songs, ''LoveMusik'' strives to achieve chilly distance and cozy intimacy in the same breath. Harold Prince directs; Alfred Uhry wrote the conventionally sentimental book (2:40). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' Is it possible for a performance to be too good? Audra McDonald brings such breadth of skill and depth of feeling to Lonny Price's lukewarm revival of this musical about a love-starved spinster that she threatens to burst the seams of this small, homey musical. She's an overwhelming presence in an underwhelming show (2:30). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PIRATE QUEEN' How to river-dance your way to the bottom of the ocean, courtesy of the songwriters of ''Les Misérables'' (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RADIO GOLF' The final -- and in dramatic terms, the weakest -- of August Wilson's magnificent 10-play cycle about the African-American experience, ''Radio Golf'' has the crackle of a bustling comedy. But this tale of getting and spending in the 1990s, directed by Kenny Leon, throbs with a lament for a lost time, a lost culture, a lost language (2:30). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' John Fugelsang's amiable solo show mixes memoir and stand-up comedy in a tale of family, faith and Roman Catholic guilt. Slight but engaging (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'BE' A high-energy, low-content Israeli show that blends music, dance and sex appeal in the latest attempt to tap into the ''Stomp'' market (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 307-4100. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE BRIG' Serious students of the stage will want to check out the Living Theater's first revival since 1963 of Kenneth H. Brown's docudrama about the soul-shredding grind of daily life in a Marine Corps prison, once again directed by the company co-founder Judith Malina. One of the most celebrated productions in the company's history, ''The Brig'' harks back to an era when theater was at the forefront of both political and artistic radicalism (2:00). Living Theater, 21 Clinton Street, Lower East Side. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DAUGHTER OF A CUBAN REVOLUTIONARY' A standard-issue solo play about a fascinating Cuban family (1:10). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GASLIGHT' The Irish Repertory Theater's revival of Patrick Hamilton's 1938 thriller about a husband intent on driving his wife mad strips away the claustrophobia and ably resists clichéd feminist interpretation. As the impish detective who saves the day, Brian Murray is the play's great leavening agent. He prompts the heroine to whiskey drinking, and you want to raise a glass to him (2:00). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'GOD'S EAR' Jenny Schwartz's formally inventive and brilliantly performed drama about how the death of a child affects a family is more interested in language than in narrative (1:20). East 13th Street Theater, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'I LOVE YOU , YOU'RE PERFECT, NOW CHANGE!' This revue has proved as indestructible as the truisms about men and women on which it is based: it has run for 11 years Off Broadway and spread around the world. Now one of its avatars is coming for a visit: the Mandarin production with Lin Yilun, a major Chinese star, has arrived in New York for a limited run, playing concurrently with the English version. This is supposedly the first time a foreign production of an American musical has played in the United States (and the first Chinese-language production of a major American musical). It will be interesting to see how the piece's hoary stereotypes change in translation; Joel Bishoff, the original director, modified the piece to reflect Chinese culture for its Shanghai run (2:00). The Westside Theater, 407 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212 239-6200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE J.A.P. SHOW: JEWISH AMERICAN PRINCESSES of comedy' Laughs along with longueurs (1:30). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'MOTHER LOAD' In her one-woman show on the perils of affluent motherhood, Amy Wilson derides the culture of obsessive child-rearing as she chronicles her submission to it. An affable presence onstage, Ms. Wilson nevertheless mines overly clichéd territory: the nut allergies, the horrors of preschool admission, the importance of knowing two languages by the time you are 3. Posters on Urbanbaby.com will find themselves amusedly looking in the mirror. All other New Yorkers will find themselves wanting to move to Patagonia (1:15). Sage Theater, 711 Seventh Avenue, at 47th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30).Westside Theater Downstairs, 407 West 43rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'PASSING STRANGE' Composer-performer Stew narrates this semi-autobiographical show about a songwriter on a journey of self-discovery. Part rock concert, part book musical, it flows smoothly on a strong current of feeling and humor as the L.A.-born central character searches for his musical voice in the hash bars of Amsterdam and the cabarets of Berlin (2:30). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SILVERLAND' Global warming and the melting of the ice caps have destroyed London in this environmentally (if not dramatically) aware debut. Part of the Brits Off Broadway festival (2:00). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  A pasteboard pastiche of 1920's musicals, as remembered by a witty show queen(1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  A writhing green blob with music (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY ON THE VINE' Zak Berkman presents muddled politics and distorted anxieties in his quasi science-fiction play about the influence of plastic surgery on young women who start modeling themselves after a right-wing radio host. Adding to the atmosphere of hysteria is the inability of the actors onstage to render a single subtle or nuanced moment (2:10). Harold Clurman Theater, 412 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'BETROTHED' Rachel Dickstein weds dance and spoken drama in a distinctive theatrical language. The marriages in this lovely and uneven work are less convincing: aiming to depict women's views about matrimony, this piece, based on three dissimilar short stories, actually depicts marriage as an imprisoning convention from which all three heroines escape. It's no accident that the first part of this triptych, based on Jhumpa Lahiri's story ''The Treatment of Bibi Haldar,'' provides the defining image of the work as a whole: wreathed in a haze of (implied) incense and saffron, this lovely sequence is the strongest of the evening (1:20). Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' Set in 18th-century England, this melodrama about imperiled orphans is big and broad but not particularly deep. With a cast of 40, an orchestra in the pit and bursts of choral music (Handel, mostly) decorating the proceedings, it is tastefully splashy and certainly impressive, but less emotionally engaging than you might hope (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'HAMLET' Gorilla Rep specializes in outdoor performances of Shakespeare; this workshop is a free indoor performance of an outdoor performance, which removes the gimmick and leaves, simply, good theater. The strong cast revolves around note-perfect portrayals of Claudius and Gertrude (Elizabeth McGuire is particularly fine); of the Polonius family (Al Twanmo plays the patriarch as a kind of insurance salesman battling forgetfulness); and, finally, of Hamlet, which Jacob H. Knoll pulls off as an angry young Dane. Christopher Carter Sanderson, the director, shows that the play's the thing, indoors or out (3:00). Roy Arias Theater Center at Times Square Arts Center, 300 West 43rd Street, Clinton; closes on Tuesday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'MEMORY'  Jonathan Lichtenstein's play is an engrossing but overcomplicated backstage story that gradually bleeds into a tale of a Holocaust survivor facing up to painful memories. And there's a side plot about a Palestinian losing his home. In any case, superb acting holds the attention in this mainstage entry in the Brits Off Broadway festival (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MOON ON A RAINBOW SHAWL' This is a lyrical example of kitchen-sink realism, a slice of life about neighbors who live around a crowded, cacophonous yard in Port of Spain, Trinidad. Written by Errol John and first produced in 1958, it deserves to be better known. This small, committed production, directed by Shirley Parkinson Wright, with outstanding performances by Lola Loui and Erwin E. A. Thomas, is infused with a love and understanding of the material (2:00 ). Henry Street Settlement's Abrons Arts Center/Recital Hall, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 353-1176; closes on Sunday. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'OF MICE AND MEN' The 70th-anniversary production of John Steinbeck's classic of two Depression-era ranch hands feels as stylized as an after-school special and just oversimplified. The actors work hard but their efforts fall short. (2:15) Urban Stages, 259 West 30th Street, (212) 868-4444; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'THE RECeiPT' A lost bar receipt provides a one-way ticket to bedlam in a clever and diverting show that mirrors the idiosyncrasies of modern life as two young archaeologists study a ''lost'' city and postulate on a day in the life of one of its inhabitants (1:15). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AWAY FROM HER' (PG-13, 110 minutes) Sarah Polley's well-observed adaptation of a story by Alice Munro is a quiet tour de force about love and loss, anchored by fine performances by Gordon Pinsent and Julie Christie as a couple dealing with the loss of memory and memories of past hurt. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BRAND UPON THE BRAIN' (No rating, 96 minutes) A baroque entertainment with one foot in silent cinema and the other gingerly toeing the sound waves, Guy Maddin's latest centers on a man who, in visiting a now-emptied foundling home, journeys deep into his childhood. It's wild! It's weird! It's strangely touching and a total must-see! (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BROOKLYN RULES' (R, 99 minutes) However authentic and heartfelt the film's depiction of life on the meaner streets of the Northeast corridor may be, this story of three friends growing up in a mob-infested Brooklyn neighborhood doesn't begin to match ''The Sopranos'' in its epic vision of violence, class struggle and upward mobility in a barbarous culture. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'DAY NIGHT DAY NIGHT' (No rating, 94 minutes) For most of its 94 minutes, this gripping but evasive portrait of an unidentified 19-year-old terrorist undertaking a suicide bombing mission in Times Square focuses on the face of its star, Luisa Williams. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'DISTURBIA' (PG-13, 104 minutes) A pleasant, scary, well-directed variation on the killer-next-door theme, with the engaging Shia LeBeouf as Kale, a young man who turns house arrest into an occasion for voyeurism and crime-fighting. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'EVEN MONEY' (R, 108 minutes) This grim, lurid scare movie about gambling addiction consists of several interlocking horror stories that converge in a format similar to that of ''Crash.'' More than its forerunner, this film sacrifices realism to forced plot mechanics. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE EX' (PG-13, 89 minutes) The best jokes in this scattershot screwball satire -- about the cutthroat workplace, job insecurity, upward mobility, political correctness, yuppie marital tensions and the disabled -- have claws that leave scratches. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FAY GRIM' (R, 118 minutes) Too light-headed to qualify as satire, too poker-faced to register as comedy, this elaborate spy spoof, a sequel to ''Henry Fool,'' belongs in its own stylistic niche: the Hal Hartley film. Movies emanating from Planet Hartley are an acquired taste shared by hipper-than-thou insiders. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FLANDERS' (No rating, 91 minutes, in French) Whether you like or loathe the movies of the French director Bruno Dumont, his unsettling vision of humanity stripped of cultural finery feels profoundly truthful. Beneath the facade of civilization, life is a barnyard. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'FRACTURE' (R, 111 minutes) A glib entertainment that offers up the spectacle of that crafty scene-stealer Anthony Hopkins mixing it up with that equally cunning screen-nibbler Ryan Gosling. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GEORGIA RULE' (R, 111 minutes) Jane Fonda, Felicity Huffman and Lindsay Lohan play three generations of strong-willed, dysfunctional women in this comedy-melodrama from Garry Marshall. It's a mess, but it does have some vitality, thanks mainly to Ms. Fonda and Ms. Lohan. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than an entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'HOT FUZZ' (R, 121 minutes) A British parody of Hollywood-style action flicks from the wits behind ''Shaun of the Dead.'' Think of it as ''The Full Monty'' blown to smithereens. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'I DON'T WANT TO SLEEP ALONE' (No rating, 115 minutes, in Taiwanese, Malay, Mandarin and Bengali) A dreamy, melancholy tale of three-way desire, shot in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, and imagined by the director Tsai Ming-Liang with his usual blend of sensuality and formal rigor. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE INVISIBLE' (PG-13, 102 minutes) This supremely silly retread of the 2002 Swedish film ''Den Osynlige'' proves it's tough to be in love and in limbo at one and the same time. When a rich-yet-troubled teenager (Justin Chatwin) crosses paths with a violently disturbed classmate (Margarita Levieva), we learn that there's nothing quite like a near-death experience to repair those stubborn emotional wounds. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'NEXT' (PG-13, 96 minutes) Nicolas Cage plays a guy who can see into the future in this crummy adaptation of a nifty Philip K. Dick story. Too bad Mr. Cage couldn't tap into those same powers to save himself from another bad role. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'ONCE' (R, 88 minutes) A modest, scruffy movie about two musicians who meet on a Dublin street and sort of fall in love. Charming, touching and true. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'PARIS JE T'AIME' (R, 120 minutes, in French and English) ''Paris Je T'Aime,'' a mosaic of 18 miniatures, each set in a different location in the City of Light, is a cinematic tasting menu consisting entirely of amuse-bouches. After two hours of such tidbits, the palate is sated. But if there is no need for a main course, you still leave feeling vaguely disappointed at not being served one. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PIRATES OF THE CARIBBEAN: AT WORLD'S END' (PG-13, 167 minutes) This third and perhaps final episode in Gore Verbinski's swishy, swashbuckling saga wisely returns to the high-seas high jinx that made the first film so enjoyable. In service to a typically convoluted plot -- involving British perfidy, pieces of eight and a Godzilla-size sorceress -- all the usual suspects return to lie, swindle and marvel at Keith Richards's longevity, if not his line delivery. Jack Sparrow hallucinates, Barbossa agitates, and Elizabeth Swann is elected Pirate King. Really. Mr. Verbinski knows who wears the trousers in his trilogy. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'PERFECT STRANGER' (R, 109 minutes) There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish, paranoid thriller set in the New York media world that even after it lurches from the farfetched into the preposterous, the movie leaves a clammy residue of unease. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PROVOKED' (No rating, 113 minutes) Holding fast to the movie-of-the-week formula perfected by Lifetime Television, Jag Mundhra's overly restrained drama is based on the true story of Kiranjit Ahluwalia, a London-based Punjabi housewife who torched her sleeping husband in 1989 after suffering a decade of abuse. Unfortunately, by keeping its inflammatory subject matter at arm's length, ''Provoked'' does exactly the same to its audience. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SEVERANCE' (R, 90 minutes) A weapons company retreat in a Hungarian forest turns into a bloody game of whack-a-mole in this sophomore horror film from the British director Christopher Smith. The political argument may be broad -- there is some satisfaction in seeing the gung-ho team leader hoisted by his own explosive petard -- but the visual technique is sharp, creating a lively romp through terrain less traveled than you might think. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SHREK THE THIRD' (PG, 93 minutes) The ogre faces impending fatherhood and a career crisis. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SHOWBUSINESS' (PG, 102 minutes) This documentary by Dori Bernstein follows four Broadway musicals from rehearsal through the 2004 Tony Awards: ''Caroline, or Change''; ''Taboo''; ''Avenue Q''; and ''Wicked.'' On top of the usual challenges (fund-raising, rewrites, tryouts, marketing), they all had to endure scrutiny by theater critics and gossip columnists. Lively, sometimes cutting but mostly humane, ''ShowBusiness'' is packed with telling details. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'SPIDER-MAN 3' (PG-13, 139 minutes) Please, God, make this be the last one. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TA RA RUM PUM' (No rating, 156 minutes, in English and Hindi) This movie about a race car driver (the versatile Saif Ali Khan) takes place in New York, but that doesn't stop it from being a classic example of Bollywood family values. Here, all the city's a stage set, perfect for ''Fame''-meets-''West Side Story'' production numbers. (Rachel Saltz)</p>
        <p>'300' (R, 116 minutes) Greeks versus Persians in the big rumble at Thermopylae, via Frank Miller's graphic novel. As dumb as they get. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 28 WEEKS LATER' (R, 91 minutes) The virus that killed off most of England -- after turning its population into rabid, flesh-hungry zombies -- seems to be under control at the start of this terrifying sequel to ''28 Days Later.'' But if anything, the horror is deeper, and the social criticism more acute. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VACANCY' (R, 80 minutes) This banal horror retread involves a couple of critters (Luke Wilson, Kate Beckinsale) flailing inside a sticky trap for what is, in effect, the big-screen equivalent of a roach motel. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VALET' (PG-13, 85 minutes, in French) If you love to hate the superrich, this delectable comedy, in which the great French actor Daniel Auteuil portrays a piggy billionaire industrialist facing his comeuppance, is a sinfully delicious bonbon, a classic French farce with modern touches. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WAITRESS' (PG-13, 104 minutes) Keri Russell is a small-town waitress in a bad marriage who finds solace in pie-baking and adultery in Adrienne Shelly's wry and winning final feature. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE WENDELL BAKER STORY' (PG-13, 99 minutes) This goofy slacker comedy is a Wilson family affair. Written by Luke Wilson, who co-directed with his older brother, Andrew, it also stars Owen Wilson as the title character's nemesis. Its appeal depends on how charming you find the Wilson brothers with their hip, smart-aleck attitude. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'YEAR OF THE DOG' (PG-13, 97 minutes) Mike White's touching comedy about a woman who loses a dog and finds herself is funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means that it's also funny in a kind of existential way. Molly Shannon stars alongside a menagerie of howling scene-stealers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ZOO' (No rating, 76 minutes) Robinson Devor's heavily reconstructed documentary is, to a large extent, about the rhetorical uses of beauty. It is, rather more coyly, also about a man who died after having sex with a stallion. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>SAM FULLER (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Museum of the Moving Image's continuing retrospective devoted to the blunt, visceral work of the tabloid reporter turned filmmaker Sam Fuller turns this weekend to his increasingly stylized work of the late 1950s. Included are rare archival prints of ''China Gate'' (1957), Fuller's anticipation of American involvement in Vietnam, starring Gene Barry and, in her first leading role, Angie Dickinson as a Eurasian lady of the evening; ''Run of the Arrow,'' a political western about a Confederate soldier (Rod Steiger) who learns about racism when he joins a Sioux tribe rather than surrender to the Union Army; and the eternally astonishing ''Forty Guns,'' a mad western in black-and-white CinemaScope, with Barbara Stanwyck as a ruthless land baroness. The sight of Stanwyck leading her private army -- the 40 guns of the title -- as they charge across an open plain is an unforgettable image. Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>BARRY LYNDON (Sunday through Tuesday) The Walter Reade Theater at Lincoln Center has landed a new 35-millimeter copy of Stanley Kubrick's 1975 historical drama, printed under the supervision of Kubrick's former assistant Leon Vitali. Ryan O'Neal stars as a devious but strangely dimwitted Irishman who climbs into the bed of a wealthy widow (Marisa Berenson) and up the ladder of 18th-century English society. The distant, painterly film -- you remember the candlelight more than the characters -- will be introduced by Mr. Vitali at three of the six scheduled screenings. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, (212) 875-5600, filmlinc.org; $11. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>THIRTY YEARS OF DANCE AFRICA (Today through Wednesday) As part of the Brooklyn Academy of Music's multimedia celebration of the DanceAfrica festival, the BAMcinématek is screening a well-chosen group of recent films with African themes. Running all week except Tuesday is ''Kirikou and the Wild Beasts'' (2006), Michel Ocelot's sequel to ''Kirikou and the Sorceress'' (1998), his popular animated film based on a West African folktale. The weekend highlights include Dumisani Phakathi's documentary about his search for his family in South Africa (tonight); ''The Night of Truth'' (2004), a drama by Fanta Régina Nacro about the social collapse of an imaginary West African country (tomorrow); and Mehdi Charef's ''Daughter of Keltoum'' (2001) a trip into the Berber region of Algeria (Sunday). BAMcinématek, BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DAN BERN (Tonight) With a nasal sing-speak that recalls the young Bob Dylan, Mr. Bern offers smooth folk-rock and a world-weary cynicism. (''There's nothing innocent about a newborn babe,'' he sings, ''that a few years here can't cure.'') At 7:30, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $16. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLACK REBEL MOTORCYCLE CLUB (Thursday) Not a Motorhead copycat, as its name would imply, but rather a dutiful and listless revivalist of the haystack hairdos and slithery gloom-rock of 1980s and early-'90s British bands like the Jesus and Mary Chain and Love and Rockets. Motorhead would be more exciting. With the Cobbs. At 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRAND NEW (Sunday and Tuesday) Not all emo goes the way of smirky punk-pop or sentimental singalongs. This excellent Long Island band plies dense, angry tangles of guitar and opaque lyrics of spiritual crisis, a cross between the grandeur of Pink Floyd and the agonized outbursts of Nirvana. With Anathallo and Colour Revolt. Sunday at 6 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Blender Theater at Gramercy, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; both sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BRIGHT EYES, GILLIAN WELCH (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Monday through Thursday) In the indie-rock equivalent of Bruce Springsteen filling up Giants Stadium for weeks on end, Bright Eyes -- consisting of the painfully, excessively confessional man-child Conor Oberst and whomever he's playing with -- has sold out seven shows at Town Hall, beginning tonight. His guest is Gillian Welch, who plays a mellow bluegrass-folk hybrid with grace. At 7:30, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, the-townhall-nyc.org. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE BRAVERY (Tuesday and Wednesday) Disco first met punk in Britain in the late '70s, but they have had quite a romance in turn-of-the-21st-century New York. The Bravery arrived a few years ago with catchy, radio-ready songs and buckets of hair gel; the band has been compared, accurately, to the Strokes, New Order, U2 and Franz Ferdinand. With the Photo Atlas and the Cinematics. At 9 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday and Monday) Elegant, witty and touching, this classically trained jazz pianist and singer, now 82, is in her prime: the female counterpart of Bobby Short. Sunday at 2 p.m., Monday at 8 p.m., Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $58 on Sunday, with brunch at noon; $40 on Monday, with a $20 minimum. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>COMAS (Tomorrow and Thursday) This Brooklyn band pushes garage-rock into a soulful psychedelia. Fans used to comb Andy Herod's lyrics for not-so-veiled references to his breakup with the actress Michelle Williams. He's still smarting about heartbreak on the band's new album, ''Spells'' (Vagrant), but the objects of his longing are a little more obscure -- what does ''telepathic aftertaste'' mean, for example, and is it good or bad if your girlfriend has it? With the Broken West and Nethers. Tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $12. Thursday at 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DICK DALE (Sunday) Dick Dale, king of the surf guitar, provides no polite nostalgia trip to the mid-1960s. He's out to summon elemental forces with the stomping beat of his band and his heavily reverbed, brusquely attacked guitar lines, along with the dive-bombing, tremolo glissandos that literally melt his guitar picks from the heat of their friction on the strings. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $20 in advance, $25.50 at the door. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DEAD INFECTION, MORTICIAN (Today) Dead Infection, a veteran Polish grindcore band on its first United States tour, dispensed long ago with the problem of finding the appropriate lyrics for its high-speed, guttural churn of guitars; the vocals are simply deep, wordless growls -- a sort of universal language of metal. Mortician, from Yonkers, has only two members, but with its indistinct rumble and relentless drum blasts, it sounds like an invading alien army. With Regurgitate and Malignancy. At 5 p.m., Europa, 98 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-2322, europaclub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOS DEF (Tomorrow) Though Hollywood jobs take up most of his time these days, Mos Def, once the great, socially conscious hope of New York hip-hop, has never walked away from his calling as a rapper. When he's not feeling sluggish or preoccupied -- or simply bored, as he says on his latest album, ''True Magic'' (Geffen) -- he is a passionately literate and polemical performer. At 9 p.m., Highline Ballroom, 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIRTY DOZEN BRASS BAND (Wednesday) The magnificent ensemble that revitalized New Orleans brass-band music. It swaggers through the city's whole musical heritage: parades, rumba, swing, bebop and modern jazz, for starters. Solos can head for the far side of tonality, but the band never loses touch with gutbucket, danceable funk. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $16 in advance, $19 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>EARTH, WIND AND FIRE (Tuesday) In its 1970s heyday, Earth, Wind and Fire was the glossy, horn-powered hit machine that covered all bases, from idealism (''Keep Your Head to the Sky,'' ''Shining Star'') to dance tunes (''Boogie Wonderland'') to lovers' pleas (''Reasons''). At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; sold out. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>KEANE (Wednesday) This British band consists of just a drummer, a singer and an awfully hard-working keyboardist, but manages to flesh out beautifully melodramatic songs of yearning and self-pity with rich sonorities and sharp hooks that make you swear that there's a guitar in there somewhere. With Rocco Deluca and the Burden. At 5:30 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, Central Park, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 307-7171; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KIKI AND HERB (Sunday) A few years ago this brilliantly perverse cabaret duo played their farewell show at Carnegie Hall. Then came a run on Broadway. And some late-night gigs at Joe's Pub. And the inimitable Christmas show. (Highlight: a medley of ''Smells Like Teen Spirit'' and ''Frosty the Snowman.'') Kiki and Herb can't stay away from the stage, and New York is the better for it. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LIFESAVAS (Tonight) There are plenty of criminals and scofflaws on ''Gutterfly'' (Quannum Projects), the excellent new concept album -- a funk-drenched soundtrack to an imaginary blackxploitation movie from the 1970s -- by this underground hip-hop trio from Portland, Ore. (The group really went the distance with it: George Clinton makes an appearance.) But the twist here is that the gangsters and dealers are the bad guys, and the Lifesavas play the law enforcers, fighting crime with style on the streets of ''Razorblade City.'' With Strange Fruit Project. At 8, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LIGHTNING BOLT, DMBQ, BIG A LITTLE A, APES (Tomorrow) At first it's hard to believe that all the glorious chaos of Lightning Bolt, from Providence, R.I., is being made by only two people. But as the sound comes into focus, a playful give-and-take becomes clear, as the bassist Brian Gibson and the drummer and vocalist Brian Chippendale toss back and forth gigantic metal riffs and giggly high notes, creating rainbows of dissonance. In the latest of several recent New York gigs, Lightning Bolt plays with the Japanese '70s-metal revivalists DMBQ; the passionately clamorous local experimenters Big A Little A; and the Apes, from Washington, whose spooky, keyboard-driven grooves quickly turn violent. At 8 p.m., 600 Bushwick Avenue, at Jefferson Street, Bushwick, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MEMPHIS (Wednesday and Thursday) Fans of Stars, the superbly urbane indie-cabaret band from Toronto, have been waiting three long years for a new album. (Its new remix disc is cold comfort.) Torquil Campbell, one of its singers and the band's resident wit, helps tide followers over with Memphis, his side project with Chris Dumont. The delicate melodies and cool dissection of heartbreak on Memphis's latest album, ''A Little Place in the Wilderness'' (Good Fences), are vaguely Stars-y, but it only makes the wait that much harder. Wednesday at 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $15. Thursday at 8 p.m., with Mascott and Jade McNelis, at Union Hall, 702 Union Street, at Fifth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 638-4400, unionhallny.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* THE NATIONAL (Monday through Thursday) This Brooklyn group has become an under-the-radar local hit with flawless, wilting ballads featuring subtly inventive guitar playing by Bryce Dessner and the weary, cynical baritone of Matt Berninger, who seems pained by his ability to conjure cruelties like ''You could have been a legend/But you became a father.'' These first four shows of a five-night sold-out run also feature the Broken West (Monday), Doveman (Tuesday), My Brightest Diamond (Wednesday) and Elysian Fields (Thursday). At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JENNIFER O'CONNOR (Wednesday) Ms. O'Connor's portraits of the lovelorn and depressed, sung with the guileless vulnerability of a 2 a.m. phone confession, are dry but not unsympathetic: ''Maybe she's on her lunch break thinking of you.'' She has a Wednesday residency this month at the Living Room. At 11 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JOHN PIZZARELLI AND JESSICA MOLASKEY (Tonight and tomorrow night) These married musicians have been called ''the Nick and Nora of cabaret,'' a sobriquet that only begins to describe their upbeat sophistication. They fuse two distantly related musical worlds into a larger whole in which Stephen Sondheim, Dave Frishberg, Paul Simon, and Lambert, Hendricks and Ross join hands. At 8:45 and 10:45, Café Carlyle, at the Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; $85. (Holden)</p>
        <p>T-PAIN (Thursday) The former Faheem Najm of Tallahassee, Fla., offered a concise résumé in the title of his 2005 debut album: ''Rappa Ternt Sanga.'' He broke big with the equally self-descriptive ''I'm N Luv (Wit a Stripper),'' but on his new album he confesses that he doesn't mind being domesticated by the right woman. ''She got me doin' the dishes,'' he sings. ''Anything she want for some kisses.'' Aww. At 8 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROGER WATERS (Wednesday) Calling himself with characteristic modesty ''the creative genius of Pink Floyd,'' Mr. Waters continues his extensive tour performing ''The Dark Side of the Moon,'' his former band's epochal 1973 concept album about insanity. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $39 to $174.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>!!! (Wednesday) Punk-funk usually leans on the punk side, with short blasts of indignation or defiance filtered through dance beats. This local eight-piece (whose name is pronounced ''chik-chik-chik,'' or, they say, however you want) goes for immersion, transcendence and kicks through long and steady workouts of aggressive disco-rock, making each groove last until it burns up or falls apart. With Maserati and Telepathe. At 8 p.m., Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $16. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>THEO BLECKMAN AND BEN MONDER (Tuesday) Mr. Bleckman, a vocalist, and Mr. Monder, a guitarist, share a fondness for diaphanous atmosphere, as they demonstrate on ''At Night'' (Songlines), their mysterious new album. At 10 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, near Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 614-0505, bowerypoetry.com; cover, $8. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>REGINA CARTER (Wednesday and Thursday) Ms. Carter, a recent MacArthur fellow, is one of jazz's top violinists, equally at home with burnished romanticism and hard-driving swing. (Through June 2.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL CHARLAP TRIO (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The new Blue Note album by this standard-bearing trio is called ''Live at the Village Vanguard,'' but here they hold court elsewhere. As always, the pianist Bill Charlap enjoys crisp support from Peter Washington on bass and Kenny Washington on drums. (Through June 3.) At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CARLA COOK (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Cook is a confident and vivacious jazz singer with a growing book of original tunes. At 9 and 11, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AL FOSTER QUARTET WITH WALLACE RONEY (Tonight and tomorrow night) This two-night stand, which bears the subtitle ''A Tribute to Miles,'' commemorates the fact that Al Foster was once the drummer with Miles Davis, and Wallace Roney was once Davis's anointed heir. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $28. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIZZY GILLESPIE ALL-STAR BIG BAND (Tonight through Sunday night) Dizzy Gillespie, Bebop's goateed ambassador, did some of his best work with big bands, a fact that this one, led by his former trombonist Slide Hampton, happily exploits. The band includes other veterans of Gillespie's employ, like the saxophonists James Moody and Jimmy Heath. The trumpeter Roy Hargrove is a fine choice to fill Gillespie's shoes. At 8 and 10:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BILLY HART QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Revisiting the assertive post-bop of his recent album ''Quartet'' (High Note), the drummer Billy Hart fronts a dream team of younger players: the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the bassist Ben Street. (Through June 3.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20 to $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARI HOENIG (Tonight and Monday night) Mr. Hoenig, an irrepressibly kinetic drummer, recently issued ''Inversations'' (Dreyfus), an album that proves his adroitness as a composer while confirming his rapport with the pianist Jean-Michel Pilc. On Monday he plays in a trio with Mr. Pilc; tonight he communes with Joel Frahm on tenor saxophone, Orlando Le Fleming on bass and Gilad Hekselman on guitar. At 9 and 10:30, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, smallsjazzclub.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BOBBY HUTCHERSON QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Bobby Hutcherson has been the chief proponent of a harmonically restless post-bop vibraphone style for some 40 years. Celebrating the release of a quiet new album, ''For Sentimental Reasons'' (Kind of Blue), he leads a blue-chip rhythm section composed of Russell Malone on guitar, Renee Rosnes on piano, Dwayne Burno on bass and Al Foster on drums. (Through June 3.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JAZZ MANDOLIN PROJECT (Wednesday) This groove-oriented band, led by the mandolin virtuoso Jamie Masefield, presents an original multimedia work inspired by one of Leo Tolstoy's short stories, and driven by an ideal of environmental conservation. At 8 p.m., Highline Ballroom, 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; $15 in advance, $17 at the door. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRISTINE JENSEN (Monday) Ms. Jensen, a saxophonist based in Montreal, makes a New York appearance with her more established sister, the trumpeter Ingrid Jensen. The pianist Dave Restivo, the bassist Fraser Hollins and the drummer Jon Wikan round out the band. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $15, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEF LEE JOHNSON BAND/ROB REDDY TRIO (Tonight) Groove is the common denominator of these two progressive trios, the first led by the guitarist and vocalist Jef Lee Johnson, and the second organized by Rob Reddy, a saxophonist. At 9, Jalopy Theater, 315 Columbia Street, Brooklyn, (718) 395-3214, jalopy.biz; $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LEE KONITZ AND DAN TEPFER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Konitz, who will turn 80 this year, applies his dry-martini alto saxophone tone to a round of duets with Mr. Tepfer, a pianist now in his mid-20s. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE KUHN (Tonight) The estimable Mr. Kuhn, who has lately been working with great success in a trio, ventures unaccompanied into the Fazioli Salon, a weekly solo piano series at the Klavierhaus workshop near Carnegie Hall. At 8 p.m., Klavierhaus, 211 West 58th Street, Manhattan, (212) 245-4535, pianoculture.com; $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RUSS LOSSING GROUP/KRIS DAVIS QUARTET (Wednesday) For this week's installment of the smartly programmed Night of Ravished Limbs series, the keyboardist Russ Lossing opens with a quartet that includes Mat Maneri on viola, Ben Monder on guitar and Michaël Attias on saxophones. Then Kris Davis, another keyboardist, corrals the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, the bassist Eivind Opvsik and the drummer Jeff Davis. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10 a set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE MAINIERI AND STEPS AHEAD (Thursday) It has been roughly 30 years since the vibraphonist Mike Mainieri established Steps Ahead, a polished yet often intrepid fusion outfit. He now presides over an edition of the group featuring the saxophonist Bill Evans, the guitarist Mike Stern, the bassist Anthony Jackson and the drummer Steve Smith. (Through June 2.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY'S NOVELA (Tomorrow) Yet another adventurous new project from the tenor saxophonist Tony Malaby, with Nate Wooley on trumpet, Ben Gerstein on trombone, Angelica Sanchez on piano, Jason Ajemian on bass and Chad Taylor on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* WYNTON MARSALIS SEPTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Fifteen years ago Wynton Marsalis closed the Jazz at Lincoln Center concert season with ''In This House, on This Morning,'' an original commission thematically linked to the customs of the gospel church. Now Mr. Marsalis ends the current season by calling upon some of the same musicians, including the trombonist Wycliffe Gordon and the drummer Herlin Riley, to reinterpret that evocative work. At 8, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOE MARTIN QUARTET (Thursday) Joe Martin, a versatile bassist and a thoughtful composer, leads a post-bop band with John Ellis on saxophones, Aaron Parks on piano and Obed Calvaire on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DONNY MCCASLIN TRIO (Tuesday) Latin rhythms have become an increasingly prominent concern for the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin, who seems likely to take a strenuous approach in this pared-down setting, with Thomas Morgan on bass and Richie Barshay on drums. At 9 p.m. and midnight, Louis 649, 649 East Ninth Street, at Avenue C, East Village, (212) 673-1190, louis649.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER (Thursday) In the hands of Mr. Monder the electric guitar is a coloristic instrument. He features his coolly convoluted pieces for a trio with Chris Lightcap on bass and Ted Poor drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NEW LANGUAGES FESTIVAL (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Advancing an ideal of cross-fertilization, this Williamsburg, Brooklyn, festival is organized partly by the alto saxophonist Jackson Moore, who leads a trio tomorrow night at 10. The schedule also includes Attack/Adorn/Decay, a project of the trumpeter Nate Wooley (tonight at 10); Heavy Merge, a trio led by the pianist Russ Lossing (tomorrow night at 8:30); and the Indo-Pak Coalition, assembled by the alto saxophonist Rudresh Mahanthappa (Thursday night at 8:30). At 8:30, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Rose Live Music, 345 Grand Street, near Marcy Avenue, Williamsburg, (646) 644-2766, newlanguages.org; $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PLAYDATE (Wednesday) The guitarist Amanda Monaco and the pianist Noah Baerman are the core of this whimsically named ensemble, which also includes the bassist Henry Lugo and the drummer Vinnie Sperrazza, along with Steve Wilson, a special guest, on alto saxophone. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $15, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TODD SICKAFOOSE'S BLOOD ORANGE (Tonight) A bassist and composer equally fond of rough edges and rounded forms, Todd Sickafoose performs here with two guitarists (Adam Levy and Mike Gamble), two drummers (Allison Miller and Simon Lott) and a frontline of Shane Endsley on trumpet, Ben Wendel on saxophones and Alan Ferber on trombone. At 9 and 10, Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DR. LONNIE SMITH TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Under the command of Dr. Lonnie Smith, the Hammond B-3 organ can be subtly atmospheric or growlingly ecstatic; together with the guitarist Peter Bernstein and the drummer Anthony Pinciotti, he makes a searching brand of soul jazz. (Through June 3.) At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20 to $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE STERN BAND (Monday and Wednesday) The guitarist Mike Stern has a goofily titled but musically rewarding recent album, ''Who Let the Cats Out?'' (Heads Up), that only begins to capture the energy of this longstanding regular engagement. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETER VAN HUFFEL QUINTET (Sunday and Thursday) On his new release, ''Silvester Battlefield'' (Fresh Sound New Talent), the saxophonist Peter Van Huffel showcases his exploratory compositions for this working band with the pianist Jesse Stacken, the guitarist Scott DuBois, the bassist Michael Bates and the drummer Jeff Davis. Sunday at 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. Thursday at 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JEFF (TAIN) WATTS QUARTET (Tomorrow and Sunday) Jeff (Tain) Watts, an ingeniously propulsive drummer, has a new album, ''Folk Songs'' (Dark Key Music), that consists almost entirely of his own sturdy tunes. The tenor saxophonist Marcus Strickland and the pianist David Kikowski are both featured on the album; the bassist James Genus fills in here for Christian McBride. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KENNY WERNER (Tonight) Mr. Werner is a well-seasoned pianist who tempers his technique with a kind of questing spiritualism, an appropriate quality for this solo recital in a museum of Himalayan art. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'FALSTAFF' (Tomorrow and Sunday) In its heyday on Bleecker Street, Amato Opera was where young New Yorkers saw their first operas; in its current home on the Bowery, it has taken on a certain quality of camp. But its loyal fans still love it, and it still loves opera. It offers Verdi with all of that love, if too few of the musical skills required to perform it, so that some of it, by gosh, still gets across. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Amato Opera, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200, amato.org; $35; $28 for students and 65+. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday) Bargemusic, the floating chamber music hall on the Brooklyn side of the East River, is offering varied programs this week. Tonight Mira Jevitch offers a piano recital that runs from Romantic works by Brahms and Liszt to movements from ''Eight Voyages'' by the contemporary Australian composer Grant Foster. Tomorrow and Sunday the Manhattan String Quartet performs Beethoven's three Opus 59 quartets. And on Wednesday the Sonar Players offer an overview of George Crumb's music, including two of his 1970s classics, ''Vox Balaenae'' (1971) and ''Black Angels'' (1970) for electric string quartet. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Wednesday at 8 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35; $30 for 65+ tonight; $20 for students. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>EMERSON STRING QUARTET (Thursday) Playing string quartets in a 2,800-seat hall may contradict the term ''chamber music,'' but this is a chance for a larger audience to hear a distinguished American ensemble playing Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $32 to $79. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>* KONSTANTIN LIFSCHITZ (Sunday) Last year the Free for All at Town Hall series presented this Russian-born pianist in a marathon event, playing the 24 Preludes and Fugues of Shostakovich in two programs on a single Sunday. Mr. Lifschitz, who won high praise for that performance, returns to the Free for All series with an even more daunting marathon, the 48 Preludes and Fugues of Bach, again to be played in two programs on Sunday. At 2 and 7 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 707-8787, freeforallattownhall.org; free, but tickets are required. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Tonight and tomorrow night) Julian Rachlin, a Lithuanian-born violinist who lives in Austria, has been playing with Lorin Maazel since a tender age. He returns with the Philharmonic this weekend to offer Saint-Saëns's Third Concerto. Of more musical weight, perhaps, is Bartok's Concerto for Orchestra, which Mr. Maazel should use to put the orchestra through its paces. Also on the program is Rimsky-Korsakov's ''Russian Easter'' Overture. At 8, Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $28 to $96. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK YOUTH SYMPHONY (Sunday) There is nothing like hearing a major repertory work performed by exuberant and gifted musicians who are palpably excited to be playing the piece. The New York Youth Symphony has been delivering such performances for the last five years under its dynamic young music director, Paul Haas. Mr. Haas ends his tenure on Sunday with a particularly ambitious program: arrangements of Bach chorales, the premiere of Dan Visconti's ''Some Day the Sun Won't Shine,'' and Mahler's daunting Ninth Symphony. At 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $7 to $55. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>JOHN SCOTT (Tomorrow) Mr. Scott, the organist and music director at St. Thomas Church, plays the last concert in his 10-part series exploring the organ works of Buxtehude, in honor of the 300th anniversary of that composer's death. Built in a style similar to that seen in northern Germany and the Netherlands in the 17th and 18th centuries, St. Thomas's Taylor &amp; Boody organ is ideal for this venture. At 4 p.m., Fifth Avenue at 53rd Street, (212) 757-7013, saintthomaschurch.org; free. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN BALLET THEATER (Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday) The programming this week pairs two master ballet choreographers, George Balanchine and Frederick Ashton, whose styles may be polar opposites but whose love for the art form shines through in the works that will represent them. A number of role debuts promise to add spice to Balanchine's ''Symphonie Concertante,'' an elegant re-envisioning of Mozart in movement, and Ashton's ''Dream,'' Shakespeare's ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' in a magical new realm. Among those making debuts in their roles are Gillian Murphy and David Hallberg (tomorrow afternoon), who would seem to have been born to dance Titania and Oberon in ''Dream.'' Diana Vishneva, Angel Corella and Craig Salstein as Puck (Tuesday) are not far behind. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Monday and Tuesday at 8 p.m.; Wednesday at 2 and 8 p.m.; Thursday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, abt.org; $24 to $110. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* WALLY CARDONA QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) ''Site'' examines the artist's will to construct something out of nothing. (Through June 2.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $25; $15 for students and 65+. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>'CROSSING BOUNDARIES' (Tuesday) Artists featured in this showcase, chosen by Marcia Monroe, include Joyce S. Lim, Elke Rindfleisch, Adrienne Fadjo, Rachel Bernsen and Taylor Ho Bynum. At 8 p.m., Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, dixonplace.org; $10 to $12, and Theater Development Fund vouchers accepted. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DANCEAFRICA (Tonight through Sunday) This annual festival at the Brooklyn Academy of Music celebrates three decades of African and African-American dance with performances by the Bambara Drum and Dance Ensemble, Forces of Nature Dance Theater Company, Kulu Mele African American Dance Ensemble, Ndere Troupe, Sabar Ak Ru Afriq Dance Theater and BAM/Restoration DanceAfrica Ensemble. Tonight at 7:30; Saturday and Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m.; BAM Howard Gilman Opera House, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $15 to $45; $10 for under 16. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT THE CHOCOLATE FACTORY (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Michael Helland's ''Dress Up Show'' will be performed tonight and tomorrow night. Starting on Thursday night, Renee Archibald's ''Oh Dear Natascha'' explores darkness and confinement in an environment filled with small piles of samples and clippings quietly waiting, as Ms. Archibald puts it, ''for an imaginary domestic life in various imaginary cities.'' Well, why not? (''Oh Dear Natascha,'' through June 2.) At 8, the Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101, chocolatefactorytheater.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EAR TO THE GROUND (Thursday) A program of premieres by Anita Cheng and Noopur Singha honors Asian Heritage Month. (Through June 2.) At 7:30 p.m., Mulberry Street Theater, 70 Mulberry Street, Chinatown, (212) 349-0126; $14; $12 for students and 65+. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>HILARY EASTON AND COMPANY (Thursday) ''It's All True'' concerns a man grappling with his recollections and trying to distinguish fact from fiction. (Through June 3.) At 8 p.m., the Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200; $25. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>KOOSIL-JA'S MECH[A] OUTPUT (Thursday) Koosil-Ja Hwang blends elements of dance and music from the classic Japanese Noh play ''Dojoji'' with what Ms. Hwang describes as multimedia technology, including live 3-D video. (Through June 2.) At 7:30 p.m., Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>TIFFANY MILLS COMPANY (Thursday) In ''LandFall'' three interlocking duets evoke the physical and emotional power of a storm. (Through June 3.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $30 for opening night. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* MOMIX (Tuesday through Thursday) A company that revels in theatrical illusion reviews a quarter-century in ''Momix reMIX.'' (Through June 10.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $44. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>BEN MUNISTERI DANCE PROJECTS (Thursday) In Mr. Munisteri's new ''Terra Nova,'' dancers leave a design of moving colors and patterns in their wake, courtesy of motion-capture technology. (Through June 3.) At 8 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The week's programs are ''Four Voices,'' consisting of Christopher Wheeldon's ''Carousel (a Dance),'' Alexei Ratmansky's ''Middle Duet,'' Jerome Robbins's ''Moves'' and Balanchine's ''Sonnambula''; ''Essential Robbins,'' with ''In G Major,'' ''Dances at a Gathering'' and ''I'm Old- Fashioned''; ''Essential Balanchine,'' with ''Walpurgisnacht Ballet,'' ''Liebeslieder Walzer'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements''; and ''Three Masters: Tchaikovsky, Balanchine, Robbins,'' which features Balanchine's ''Mozartiana'' and ''Tchaikovsky Piano Concerto No. 2,'' and Robbins's ''Piano Pieces'' and ''International Balanchine'' (''Serenade,'' ''Bugaku'' and ''Union Jack''). Kyra Nichols, who retires at the end of the season, will dance ''Mozartiana,'' in a role that brings out all her innate musicality, with Ashley Bouder and Jonathan Stafford new in ''Tchaikovsky.'' Maria Kowroski is an intriguing choice for the sensuous geisha in ''Bugaku,'' which she will dance for the first time. And Robbins's ''Dances at a Gathering'' will feature debuts by Jenifer Ringer, Megan Fairchild, Sarah Mearns and Adam Hendrickson on Thursday. ''Four Voices,'' tonight at 8; ''Essential Robbins,'' tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Tuesday at 7:30 p.m.; ''Symphony in Three Movements,'' tomorrow night at 8; ''Three Masters,'' Sunday at 3 p.m.; ''International Balanchine,'' Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570, nycballet.com; $15 to $86. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>STREB S.L.A.M. (Tonight through Sunday) High-flying, wall-crashing thrills and chills, and popcorn besides. (Through June 17.) Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 3 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Streb Laboratory for Action Mechanics, 51 North First Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, strebusa.org; $20; $10 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* 2007 TAP EXTRAVAGANZA (Sunday) This annual event, presented by the New York Committee to Celebrate National Tap Dance Day, is just the ticket for tap enthusiasts and dance fans who have to have a little unruly fun with their art form. The lineup includes Jimmy Slyde, Mable Lee, Dormesha Sumbry Edwards and Savion Glover. And Mr. Glover's mother, Yvette, a powerful singer, will be honored along with Bob Audy and Deborah Mitchell, tap teachers and choreographers. At 7 p.m., Fashion Institute of Technology, Haft Auditorium, 227 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $25 to $65. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'GLOBAL FEMINISMS,' through July 1. Too much of the work in this sprawling, international assembly of recent pieces by nearly 90 women from nearly 50 countries is body-oriented and doesn't venture far beyond the essentialism of Judy Chicago's indomitable 1975-79 installation opus, ''The Dinner Party,'' whose enshrinement in the new Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art this exhibition celebrates. Nearly devoid of significant painting and sculpture and Thoroughly dominated by photography and video, with a documentary slant to many of its better moments, the show is more about information, politics and the struggle for equality than it is about art in any very concentrated or satisfying sense. That doesn't keep parts of it from being energetic and illuminating, especially as a record of the way that feminism has gripped and jump-started the imaginations of women around the world. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by Durand has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet and journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape. He explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage and rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. Like its two predecessors, this ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field of design, but fails to call it to order. The inclusions range from genius to schlock, delightful to dispiriting. They cover medical innovation, military hardware, completely frivolous reiterations of received ideas (far too many of which trace to Surrealism), sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and recycling -- more varieties of recycling than you can easily count. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Grey Art Gallery: 'Beyond the White Cube: A Retrospective of Brian O'Doherty/Patrick Ireland,' through July 14. Starting in the mid-1960s and in concert with the most influential thinkers of the period (Roland Barthes, Marcel Duchamp and Susan Sontag), Brian O'Doherty made Conceptual art in a Minimalist vein. This show displays his sculptures, drawings, performance videos, paintings and rope drawings, which could easily be called installations. It's a must-see show for anyone who wants to understand the conceptual frameworks that underpin so much of today's most significant installation and performance art. 100 Washington Square East, Greenwich Village, (212) 998-6780, nyu.edu/greyart/. (Bridget L. Goodbody)</p>
        <p>GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'DIVISIONISM/NEO-IMPRESSIONISM: ARCADIA AND ANARCHY,' through Aug. 6. Ultimately this rare, compressed, mercurial exhibition of work by the Italian Divisionists of the 1890s is long on history and short on truly convincing paintings. The inclusion of works by Seurat and his French, Dutch and Belgian followers clarifies how the Italians pushed Pointillism, Seurat's invention, in all directions: toward realism, academic classicism, Symbolism, class consciousness and even Impressionism. The show opens a new, albeit small, window on the genesis of Modernism beyond the French canon. If many of the works are period pieces, they are also immensely appealing, big-hearted and physically robust period pieces. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'BIOGRAPHICAL LANDSCAPE: THE PHOTOGRAPHY OF STEPHEN SHORE, 1969-1979,' through Sept. 9. In 1971 the Metropolitan Museum of Art gave Stephen Shore its second-ever exhibition by a living photographer. (Alfred Stieglitz had the first.) He was 23 when it opened. What he did makes up most of this wonderful show. Mr. Shore has reprinted the photographs digitally, with rejuvenated colors as fresh and subtle as the day the pictures were shot. The work's laconic eloquence speaks of an era and a nation. Its wit and affection add buoyancy to scenes of threadbare America from a moment when the country was depressed by war and years of civil unrest. Its formal rigor makes an uncanny order out of images that, at first glance, look like no place or nothing. Look again. His show reminds us of a period when cutting-edge American art and the tradition of straight, documentary photography got together. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at West 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'Let Your Motto Be Resistance: African American Portraits,' through Sept. 9. This show of photographic portraits is a praise-song in pictures, a shout-out to history. It's also a fancy-dress inaugural party for the yet-to-be-built National Museum of African American History and Culture in Washington. It tends to be a little too fancy, too heavy on glitz, too short on grit. Still, what a party it is, with a Who's Who of charismatic black statesmen, from Frederick Douglass to Malcolm X, and with Leontyne Price, Mahalia Jackson and the Supremes sharing a stage. (See above.) (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. It covers a broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls, not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>The Jewish Museum: Dateline: Israel: 'New Photography and Video Art,' through Aug. 5. Roughly every decade, the Jewish Museum offers a survey of contemporary art from and about Israel. This year non-Israeli artists from Europe and the United States -- and a single artist from Palestine -- have been added to the mix. There's some very good work here, though, on the whole, the show grapples with crucial political issues in an indirect way. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, jewishmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* THE METropolitan museum of art: 'Poiret: KING OF FASHION,' through Aug. 5. A revolutionary in revolutionary times, the fashion designer Paul Poiret introduced unstructured garments that freed women from corsets in 1906, the year before Picasso committed his decidedly uninhibited (and unstaid) ''Demoiselles d'Avignon'' to canvas. But the modern painter whom Poiret most resembles, in his love of the exotic, his brilliant use of color and pattern and his penchant for simplified, almost rudimentary form, is Matisse. This rare exhibition -- from the Met's Costume Institute -- does his sartorial genius justice with a spare installation rendered radiant by hand-painted silk backdrops of the leafy parks and luxurious drawing rooms of Paris. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>The Met: 'FRANK STELLA: PAINTING INTO ARCHITECTURE,' through July 29. Crammed into a gallery that feels like an obstacle course, this exhibition spans 43 years with 25 paintings, reliefs, drawings and architectural models, all with the goal of tracing an evolution that has not yet occurred. Taking up most of the space are enlarged versions of models that are considered sculptures -- and that look as if they date from the early 1960s. The main draws are the examples of the paintings and reliefs that are the basis of Mr. Stella's importance as an artist. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>The Met: 'FRANK STELLA ON THE ROOF,' through Oct. 28. Two large Pop Art sculptures, two architectural models and a model enlarged into a sculpture-installation piece confirm that one of the greatest American artists of the postwar era doesn't do himself or anyone else any favors when he strays from the wall to work fully in the round. The results have a certain Stella-like verve but are otherwise generic. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'Apocalypse Then: Medieval Illuminations From the Morgan,' through June 17. The symbolism of the Book of Revelation, with its demons and lakes of fire, has a subversive appeal. This new exhibition at the Morgan Library celebrates a facsimile of ''Las Huelgas Apocalypse'' (1220), the largest surviving Spanish illuminated commentary on the Apocalypse. The show, which includes 50 leaves from the original text, unbound and installed around the gallery's perimeter, offers a walking tour of the medieval imagination. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Andrea K. Scott)</p>
        <p>* El Museo del Barrio: 'The Disappeared (Los Desaparecidos),' through June 17. The most potent show of contemporary political art of the season, and one of the most moving shows of any kind in the city right now. The title refers to a peculiarly chilling form of violence associated with political upheavals in Latin America over the past 40 years, and now becoming more common in Iraq. 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212) 831-7272, elmuseo .org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of modern art: 'COMIC ABSTRACTION: IMAGE-BREAKING, IMAGE-MAKING,' through June 11. This unimaginative and uniformed treatment of a big idea -- the healthy and essential contamination of Modernist abstraction by popular culture -- should be seen if only because it is such a dispiriting symptom of the Modern's paralysis where contemporary art is concerned. Including 30 works by 13 artists from the last 16 years, it alternates between the literal and the arbitrary and favors sincere political intent over genuine artistic quality. Although it promises work that addresses ''perplexing questions,'' nearly everything here is perfectly pleasant and innocuous. The exceptions are provided by Gary Simmons, Ellen Gallagher and Sue Williams. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Neuberger Museum of Art: FUGITIVE ARTIST: THE EARLY WORK OF RICHARD PRINCE, 1974-77, through June 24. Mr. Prince is one of the most elusive, perverse and sardonic of all of the important appropriation artists to emerge in the early 1980s, so perhaps it is not surprising that he has boycotted this exhibition of little-known early work, all from public and private collections. But that doesn't stop the 50 pieces on view from revealing his roots in 1970s Conceptual Art; his progress from generic to original and radical; or the depth and duration of his fascination with language, photography, printmaking, the more banal forms of urban postwar Americana and a disconnected, decidedly male blankness. If anything, it increases his stature. Purchase College, State University of New York, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6100, neuberger.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Neue Galerie: 'Van Gogh and Expressionism,' through July 2. The Neue has, as usual, gathered a stellar roundup of Expressionist art. In one of the show's most exciting rooms, a third-floor gallery devoted mostly to self-portraits, two extraordinary van Goghs hang at opposite ends: ''Self-Portrait With Straw Hat'' (1887-88), from the Metropolitan Museum's collection, filled with energetic, radiating brushstrokes, and the National Gallery's vibrant self-portrait of the artist holding a palette and brushes, painted about a year later. The most compelling pairing in this room, though, is van Gogh's ''Bedroom'' from 1889, the second of three versions he painted of his room in Arles, with Egon Schiele's obvious homage, ''The Artist's Bedroom in Neulengbach,'' painted in 1911, in a darker palette and with a perspective tipped precariously toward the viewer. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, neuegalerie.org. (Martha Schwendener)</p>
        <p>STOREFRONT FOR ART AND ARCHITECTURE: 'CCCP: Cosmic Communist Constructions Photographed,' through June 16. Covering a period ignored by academics and mainstream architects, this show is packed with obscure architectural gems. It relies almost exclusively on the photographs of Frédéric Chaubin, who spent five years traveling across the former Soviet Union, uncovering forgotten architectural works in cities like Tbilisi, Yalta and Yerevan. The results are a revelation. Among the outright gems is Georgy Chakhava's 1975 Roads Ministry building, a monumental grid of interlocking concrete forms rising on a steep wooded site in Tbilisi, Georgia. Rising on an incline between two highways, the building's heavy, cantilevered forms reflect the Soviet-era penchant for heroic scale. Yet they also relate sensitively to their context, celebrating the natural landscape that flows directly underneath the building. What's refreshing about this exhibition is its lack of an ideological agenda: it is open to all sorts of possibilities. The Gaudiesque romanticism of a sanitarium in Druskininkai, Lithuania, for example, spins the aesthetic off in yet another direction. Compelling and easy to digest, this show piques our interest in ways that some larger institutions, ever more averse to risk, often fail to do. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>The Studio Museum in Harlem: 'Philosophy of Time Travel,' through July 1. This flawed show, which was created by a group of artists who studied together at the California Institute of the Arts, is nonetheless an interesting example of one of the art world's latest trends: the art collective. It takes Brancusi's ''Endless Column'' as its point of departure and reimagines this Modernist icon from the point of view of art school grads, who are versed in the language of artspeak and wed to the righteous cause of freedom of expression. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, studiomuseum.org. (Goodbody)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM AT ALTRIA: Matthew Brannon, 'Where Were We,' through Aug. 26. Matthew Brannon brings together art, poetry and advertising in a series of letterpress prints that hark back to 1950s and 1960s textile designs by Astrid Sampe and Marimekko. Texts written by the artist and accompanying the images read like song lyrics crossed with Conceptual Art and Language Poetry (which emphasized experimentalism and reader interaction). Consumption and excess are frequent references, as well as how art, design and fashion feed these modern yet primordial urges and desires. 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917) 663-2453, whitney.org. (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'LINCOLN KIRSTEIN,' through Aug. 27. In the middle of the last century Lincoln Kirstein particularly relished attacking the Museum of Modern Art. Pure abstraction was ridiculous, he thought. It had no standards. Against Mondrian and Pollock, he endorsed, among others, the artists in this show. They are the sculptors Elie Nadelman and Gaston Lachaise and the painters Paul Cadmus, who was Kirstein's brother-in-law, Walker Evans and Pavel Tchelitchew. With the exception of Evans, Kirstein's taste clearly hasn't won the day, but it's never bad to re-examine received opinions or to be reminded of a generous advocate. (See above.) (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Gordon MaTTA-cLARK rETROSPECTIVE,' through June 3. I have no doubt that Matta-Clark is now being turned into a hot commercial commodity, but at least at the Whitney you can see what he aspired to be. He came up with various wonderfully harebrained ideas. Literally, in one case: after letting his hair grow for a year, he cut it off as a kind of performance and phrenological gag. The preserved hair, dutifully tagged piece by piece, opens the show like a holy relic. At the center of the exhibition is ''Splitting.'' To a plain single-family suburban frame house in Englewood, N.J., he made a cut straight down the middle, bisecting the building, then severing the four corners of the roof. The retrospective consists of films, drawings, photographs and some of the architectural pieces he cut out of buildings. The drawings are casual and not too interesting, but the luxurious black-and-white photographs from Paris speak more to Matta-Clark's formal elegance. The big message was: Life as art, and art as life, a philosophy dependent on our being properly attuned and keen to the moment. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Taryn Simon,' through June 24. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics, yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly. Though she has also worked in war-torn areas, Ms. Simon is best known for ''The Innocents,'' a series of portraits of men and women who were wrongly convicted but later cleared by DNA test results. Ms. Simon can work as long as a year to gain permission to photograph high-security zones like the government-regulated quarantine sites, nuclear waste storage facilities, prison death rows and C.I.A. offices on view in the show. There are also pictures with lighter themes: the sandpit where the Grucci family tests fireworks, ski slopes being dynamited for avalanche control and the second Death Star, from ''Return of the Jedi,'' at George Lucas's Skywalker Ranch. Ms. Simon is at her artistic best when her delight in the strangeness of American culture shines. (See above.) (Goodbody)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>CLAUDE MONET (1840-1926): A TRIBUTE TO DANIEL WILDENSTEIN AND KATIA GRANOFF This exhibition of nearly 60 paintings by one of the most beloved painters in the world feels a little like having dinner with a celebrity. The gallery setting eliminates the usual distance; the startling intimacy allows you to experience afresh the momentum and innovations of Monet's astounding trajectory in the span of three small galleries. Basically, it is a chance to encounter, up close and in detail, the evolving ways of seeing and painting that established the originality, historical importance and continuing irresistibility of Monet's art. It should not be missed. Wildenstein &amp; Company, 19 East 64th Street, (212) 879-0500, through June 15. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>* 'Gego, Between Transparency and the Invisible' The artist named Gego was born Gertrud Goldschmidt in Germany in 1912, but lived most of her life in Venezuela, where she produced netlike drawings in ink and watercolor and what she called ''drawings without paper'': semi-geometric, see-through, two- and three-dimensional pieces of twisted and knotted wires, suspended in space. Whether you think of them as grids gone haywire or as rational forms charged with emotion, they're out of this world, and this small survey gives a good sense of what is distinctive and radical about Gego's art. The Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 219-2166, drawingcenter.org, through July 21. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>* MARTIN KIPPENBERGER: PREIS PAINTINGS Seven canvases from two series of paintings rarely exhibited in this country play on the double German meaning of preis (price and prize), some variation of which appears on each surface. They show this famous bad-boy sculptor conveying his usual sarcasm into surprisingly beautiful terms that couldn't get much flatter. Hard-edged and brushy techniques contrast the main tactics of formalist painting while converting the modernist grid into designs redolent of drapery and checked tablecloths. A preponderance of hot pink inveigles for the pleasure principle. 1018 Art, 1018 Madison Avenue, near 78th Street, (212) 537-0453, www.1018art.net, through July 27. (Smith)</p>
        <p>SOL LEWITT: DRAWING SERIES  If the greatness of Sol LeWitt, the Minimal-Conceptual artist who died in April at 78, has so far escaped you, this exhilarating show of 14 of his mind-teasing, eye-filling wall drawings from the late 1960s and early '70s may do the trick. Selected and arranged by the artist, they proceed in carefully sequenced contrasts and echoes that are both insightful and idiosyncratic. Since their generating instructions are part of their titles, they reduce the creative process to a short, highly visible straight line. But their crisp geometries, accumulating marks and radiating patterns force us to mind the gap between artistic thought and artistic action, to experience the inability of language to account fully for visual outcome. Dia:Beacon, 3 Beekman Street, Beacon, N.Y., (845) 440-0100, through Sept. 10. (Smith)</p>
        <p>JOAQUÍN TORRES-GARCÍA This choice exhibition concentrates on small, lively ink drawings from the early 1930s, when Torres-García ironed out Cubism into a compartmentalized grid that could either be abstract -- like Mondrian's work -- or a container for assorted symbols and hieroglyphs. Two earlier paintings underscore that, either way, his inspiration came from combined order and disorder of bustling city views. CDS Gallery, 76 East 79th Street, (212) 772-9555, through June 9. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Public Art</p>
        <p>Madison Square Park: Roxy Paine This installation is made up of two stainless-steel tree sculptures -- ''Conjoined'' and ''Defunct'' -- and a glacierlike boulder, ''Erratic,'' by Mr. Paine. The tree sculptures are made from thousands of pieces of metal pipe and rod elements that have been cut, welded and polished. They are real enough to resemble actual trees but not so real that they form a continuum with the surrounding foliage. What captures your immediate attention is ''Conjoined,'' a 40-foot-tall-by-45-foot-wide sculpture of two trees whose gleaming steel branches cantilever and then improbably connect in midair. It is impossible to tell where the branches of one tree begin and the other end. But the piece is also beautifully eccentric, a futuristic fantasy of streamlined vegetation manufactured in imitation of the real thing, only much more appealing and exciting. Madison Square Park, 23rd Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 538-4689, www.madisonsquarepark.org, through Dec. 31. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,'. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases, elegiac celebrations of farm workers raking and reaping grain, have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org.; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* 'Rebel, Rebel: Remembering Karlheinz Weinberger (1921-2006)' The self-taught Swiss photographer Karlheinz Weinberger, who died last year at 81, began his career taking pictures for a gay club in Zurich, but found his true subject in rebellious, working-class teenagers who dressed to shock in the 1960s and '70s. The Weinberger pictures in this show are fairly tame, as if chosen to complement the cooled-out work of the three younger artists -- Ryan McGinley, Walter Pfeiffer and Collier Schorr -- who surround him. But at his best, he's in a class by himself. Anna Kustera, 520 West 21st Street, (212) 989-0082, kusteratiltongallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
