<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unlikely Comrades Share Parting Moment</title>
    <meta content="18memo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/18/washington/18memo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070524T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHITE HOUSE MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DD1131F93BA25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unlikely Comrades Share Parting Moment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Unlikely Comrades Share Parting Moment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British Prime Min Tony Blair appears with Pres Bush for final time at joint news conference in Rose Garden of White House, where shouts of antiwar protesters outside gates threat to drown out their words; Blair, whose support of Bush and war in Iraq has brought him derision at home, is stepping down as prime minister in June; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a moment, as Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain and President Bush stood together in the bright sunshine on Thursday for their last joint appearance in the Rose Garden, when the shouts of antiwar protesters gathered outside the gates of the White House threatened to drown out their words.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush ignored the uproar. But Mr. Blair, whose support of the American president and the war in Iraq has brought him derision at home, addressed the dissent head on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain and President Bush stood together in the bright sunshine for their last joint appearance in the White House Rose Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was a moment, as Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain and President Bush stood together in the bright sunshine on Thursday for their last joint appearance in the Rose Garden, when the shouts of antiwar protesters gathered outside the gates of the White House threatened to drown out their words.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush ignored the uproar. But Mr. Blair, whose support of the American president and the war in Iraq has brought him derision at home, addressed the dissent head on.</p>
        <p>''I can't make out the words that they're shouting over there, but I bet they're not totally complimentary to us,'' Mr. Blair said, easing the tension before he began an impassioned defense arguing that ''history will make a judgment'' about Iraq.</p>
        <p>Moments earlier, Mr. Bush had offered his own parting embrace of the British prime minister, who steps down next month after 10 years in power.</p>
        <p>''Trying to do a tap dance on his political grave, aren't you?'' the president said, upbraiding a British reporter who suggested that Mr. Blair should move on. ''You don't understand how effective Blair is, I guess, because when we're in a room with world leaders and he speaks, people listen.''</p>
        <p>It was a revealing and at times emotional scene for the two world leaders, unlikely partners -- the British social liberal and the Texas conservative -- who began clinging to one another even before Sept. 11, 2001. Mr. Bush insisted that their meeting was a working policy visit, not ''a farewell deal,'' but it certainly had that air.</p>
        <p>Reginald Dale, an expert in British-American relations at the Center for Strategic and International Studies, assessed the verbal repartee this way: ''They were giving each other gifts the whole time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair, for instance, issued a veiled message to Congress not to mess with war financing, warning, as has Mr. Bush, that ''our enemy takes heart'' from any perception that political will is weakening. Mr. Bush said he and Mr. Blair shared ''common ground'' on global warming, an issue of utmost importance to Mr. Blair.</p>
        <p>There were gifts in private as well. The president and the prime minister shared an intimate dinner in the White House residence on Wednesday -- just the two of them, dining on she-crab soup and Wagyu beef. And Mr. Blair received the ultimate Bush perk, even bigger than an invitation to the president's Texas ranch: an offer to spend the night at 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue, ordinarily reserved only for family or friends. Mr. Blair accepted, sleeping in the Queen's Bedroom, of course -- the very same room where Winston Churchill stayed after Japan bombed Pearl Harbor.</p>
        <p>From the start, theirs was an unexpected bond. Mr. Blair had been especially close with Bill Clinton -- the two shared a vision of a ''third way'' in domestic politics and would spend hours bandying about ideas -- but few expected the same from Mr. Bush and Mr. Blair. At their first meeting at Camp David, in February 2001, they were asked what they had in common.</p>
        <p>''Well, we both use Colgate toothpaste,'' Mr. Bush said wryly, prompting Mr. Blair to interject, ''They're going to wonder how you know that, George.''</p>
        <p>Irwin M. Stelzer, an economist and a columnist for The Sunday Times of London who is a close friend of Mr. Blair's, said the two found themselves to be foreign policy soul mates, even before the Sept. 11 attacks. At that first Camp David meeting, they talked about how to contain Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>''When they first met,'' Mr. Stelzer said, ''Tony came away with almost an exalted impression of the president, and he's told me this.'' He said Mr. Blair liked Mr. Bush's directness, and felt confident that with Mr. Bush, ''he would never get zapped'' by a president who went back on his word. Mr. Blair, he said, felt strongly that the role of Britain in the world would be enhanced by a close relationship with the United States.</p>
        <p>''He saw himself as a bridge between the United States and Europe,'' Mr. Stelzer said, ''and I always used to joke with him that a bridge is something people walk on, so you'd better be careful.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, by the time Mr. Blair announced that he would leave office in June, he had been assailed for years in the British press as ''Bush's poodle.'' The prime minister was so sensitive to the criticism that he never collected the Congressional Medal of Honor he was awarded in 2003.</p>
        <p>''It would have been politically dangerous for him to be seen getting a medal draped around his neck by President Bush,'' Mr. Stelzer said.</p>
        <p>Thursday's news that Gordon Brown, the chancellor of the Exchequer, would succeed Mr. Blair brought more tough questions. One British reporter asked the prime minister whether he should step down earlier than next month, while another asked Mr. Bush if Mr. Blair was ''really still the right man to be talking to.''</p>
        <p>The president, clearly irritated, shot back, ''That's a lovely question.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush praised Mr. Brown as '''a good fellow,'' but the consensus on both sides of the Atlantic is that the bond will not be nearly as tight. ''The chemistry is unlikely to be the same,'' Mr. Dale said, ''because Brown is a much more introverted, less affable type. And he's calculating; he doesn't have a very good reputation for people skills.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's people skills were in rare form on Thursday, as he held forth with a poignant soliloquy -- an echo of the '''hand on heart, I did what I thought was right'' speech the prime minister delivered in London last week to a roomful of tearful Labor Party supporters.</p>
        <p>As the protesters shouted in the distance, Mr. Blair spoke with characteristic eloquence, winding up to a big finish: ''One thing I know is that what we represent coming here today, speaking in the Rose Garden to you people and getting your questions and being under your pressure, that is a finer and better way of life than either a brutal, secular dictatorship or religious extremism. It's a better way of life and it's the way of life, actually, people anytime they are given the choice, choose to have.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush opened his mouth, he chose not to step on Mr. Blair's moment. Instead, the president uttered two sentences praising the prime minister as ''a courageous man,'' following up with a quick, ''Thanks for coming.''</p>
        <p>At that, the two leaders turned their back and, for the last time together, exited the Washington stage.</p>
        <p>WHITE HOUSE MEMO</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 24, 2007, Thursday  A White House Memo article on Friday, about the last joint appearance by President Bush and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain at the White House, misstated the name of the medal Mr. Blair was awarded in 2003. It was the Congressional Gold Medal, not the Congressional Medal of Honor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 24, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A White House Memo article on Friday, about the last joint appearance by President Bush and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain at the White House, misstated the name of the medal Mr. Blair was awarded in 2003. It was the Congressional Gold Medal, not the Congressional Medal of Honor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
