<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Con Ed Seeks to Raise Electricity Rates by Up to 17 Percent</title>
    <meta content="05coned" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/05/nyregion/05coned.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Consolidated Edison Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Silver, Sheldon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D7113EF936A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Con Ed Seeks to Raise Electricity Rates by Up to 17 Percent</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Con Ed Seeks to Increase Electric Rates by Up to 17%</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN; Nicholas Confessore and Ray Rivera contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Consolidated Edison asked state regulators for permission yesterday to substantially raise electricity rates next April -- by 17 percent for a typical residential customer and by 10.7 percent for a typical business.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, which met with immediate criticism, the total monthly electric bills for the utility's 3.2 million electricity customers in New York City and most of Westchester County would rise by 11.6 percent in 2008.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The company’s request for the first rise in rates since 2004 was met with wide criticism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Consolidated Edison asked state regulators for permission yesterday to substantially raise electricity rates next April -- by 17 percent for a typical residential customer and by 10.7 percent for a typical business.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, which met with immediate criticism, the total monthly electric bills for the utility's 3.2 million electricity customers in New York City and most of Westchester County would rise by 11.6 percent in 2008.</p>
        <p>Bills would increase by another 3.2 percent in 2009 and by 3.7 percent in 2010.</p>
        <p>The rate increase request, the first since 2004, raised hackles among politicians and community advocates who were infuriated by the utility's sluggish response to a nine-day blackout in western Queens last July that affected some 170,000 people.</p>
        <p>''Con Edison's bold attempt to once again extract a blank check from ratepayers flies in the face of common logic,'' the State Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, a Manhattan Democrat, said in a statement. ''The mere act of asking for such an outrageous rate increase is particularly astonishing for a utility that has consistently demonstrated a lack of concern for its customers.''</p>
        <p>Christine Anderson, a spokeswoman for Gov. Eliot Spitzer, said, ''We are very concerned about the burden this rate hike will place on already strapped residents and business owners.''</p>
        <p>''We have long acknowledged that there is a serious need for infrastructure and transmission improvements in order to increase statewide efficiency objectives,'' Ms. Anderson said, ''and, as we carefully review Con Ed's proposal, we must think about how we make these improvements without unfairly burdening consumers.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg urged Con Ed's critics to judge the rate request ''on the merits, not on politics.''</p>
        <p>''Con Ed submitted more than 1,800 pages of data and testimony to the State's Public Service Commission today -- a commission that was created to analyze this kind of data and make decisions based on the facts, not political influence,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Gerald A. Norlander, executive director of the Public Utility Law Project, an advocacy group for energy users based in Albany, said that residents could end up paying even more if the cost of generating electricity goes up. In New York, Con Edison has mostly given up operating power plants, focusing on transmission and distribution, and must buy most of its power on wholesale markets. ''Supply is tightening, and wholesale prices may rise quite a lot, in addition to Con Edison's delivery charges,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The body that will vote on the rate increase, the New York State Public Service Commission, issued a blistering final staff report in February that attributed the Queens blackout to a failure by Con Edison to adequately maintain and operate its equipment.</p>
        <p>Last month, the commission voted to begin a formal proceeding to determine the ''prudence'' of Con Edison's actions before, during and after the blackout. Such a proceeding could result in hefty fines and penalties against the utility. Mr. Silver said yesterday that it was ''inappropriate to move forward'' on a rate increase until that process has been completed.</p>
        <p>Kevin M. Burke, the chairman and chief executive of Con Edison, defended the rate increase yesterday in a statement that made no mention of the blackout, although it did cite improvements planned for the underground network in Long Island City, Queens, where the blackout began.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burke said that along with the rate increase, Con Edison has proposed measures to increase energy conservation and reduce carbon dioxide emissions. He added that electricity use had risen by more than 20 percent over the past decade.</p>
        <p>''The energy efficiency measures we propose will help slow the rising demand for power,'' he said. ''At the same time, we need to increase our investments if we are to maintain a reliable, resilient and robust infrastructure necessary to meet the needs of a growing population and an increasing demand for electricity.''</p>
        <p>Lawmakers said they were preparing to scrutinize the proposed increase. ''I think it's unacceptable,'' said Assemblyman Paul D. Tonko, a Democrat from the Albany area who is chairman of the Assembly's Standing Committee on Energy.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Michael N. Gianaris, a Democrat whose Queens district was heavily affected by the July blackout, said he did not believe that Con Edison could justify the increase. ''It's a very profitable company that has proved to have serious failures in its reliability,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Under the Con Edison proposal, the average monthly bill would increase to $82 from $70 for a typical residential customer and to $2,435 from $2,200 for a typical business.</p>
        <p>Con Edison said it planned to spend billions of dollars on improvements over its next three-year rate plan, including $942 million on substations, $899 million on transformers and related equipment and $467 million on new underground primary cables.</p>
        <p>Con Edison's chief financial officer, Robert N. Hoglund, said the company would need an average of nearly $2 billion in new investor capital each year to pay for such improvements. The company needs the increase to obtain such capital, he said. Con Edison has $12 billion in annual revenues.</p>
        <p>Over the next 11 months, the Public Service Commission will hold a review process in which consumer and environmental groups, local officials and customers will have a chance to weigh in on the rate proposal, said James A. Denn, a commission spokesman. A decision is to be reached before Con Edison's current three-year rate plan expires on March 31, 2008. The commission's four current members were appointed by Mr. Spitzer's predecessor, Gov. George E. Pataki.</p>
        <p>The proposed rate increase comes as the New York City Water Board is poised to raise water and sewer rates by 11.5 percent, the largest annual increase in 15 years.</p>
        <p>Mayor Bloomberg, in his weekly radio call-in appearance on WABC-AM, defended the water rate increase yesterday.</p>
        <p>''The Department of Environmental Protection is a pretty good agency, efficient, needs to keep making investments, and fixing and building,'' Mr. Bloomberg said, ''and we need those things, and somebody's got to pay.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
