<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: April 29, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Besthard.nonfiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1247" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: April 29, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended April 14, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Editor's Choice  Other recent books of particular interest</p>
        <p>THE GRAND SURPRISE: The Journals of Leo Lerman. Edited by Stephen Pascal. (Knopf, $37.50.) Lerman, a contemporary of Truman Capote, was a larger-than-life figure in the magazine world who also gave great parties.</p>
        <p>DEEP ECONOMY: The Wealth of Communities and the Durable Future, by Bill McKibben. (Times Books/Holt, $25.) The noted environmentalist aims to change attitudes about economics and consumption in an age of global warming.</p>
        <p>... AND I HAVEN'T HAD A BAD DAY SINCE: From the Streets of Harlem to the Halls of Congress, by Charles B. Rangel with Leon Wynter. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $24.95.) This memoir from the chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee brims with brio.</p>
        <p>THE WILD TREES: A Story of Passion and Daring, by Richard Preston. (Random House, $25.95.) The strange biological world at the tops of giant redwoods obsesses a group of climbers.</p>
        <p>BLACK &amp; WHITE, by Dani Shapiro. (Knopf, $24.) The protagonist of Shapiro's novel is driven into exile by the notoriety of the raw art photos her famous mother made of her as a child.</p>
        <p>EASTER EVERYWHERE: A Memoir, by Darcey Steinke. (Bloomsbury, $24.95.) A minister's daughter confronts her own spiritual rootlessness.</p>
        <p>WAY MORE WEST: New and Selected Poems, by Edward Dorn. Edited by Michael Rothenberg. (Penguin Poets; paper, $20.) Dorn, who died in 1999, was the quintessential Black Mountain poet.</p>
        <p>BURIED IN THE BITTER WATERS: The Hidden History of Racial Cleansing in America, by Elliot Jaspin. (Basic Books, $26.95.) A troubling investigation of a dozen locales that engineered mass expulsions of blacks from 1890 to 1930.</p>
        <p>HUNK CITY, by James Wilcox. (Viking, $25.95.) The globalized marketplace has pressed its thumb on Tula Springs, La., the town Wilcox introduced in his 1983 novel, ''Modern Baptists.''</p>
        <p>ANT FARM: And Other Desperate Situations, by Simon Rich. (Random House, $12.95.) Very short, very sweet Monty Python-esque humor vignettes from a former Harvard Lampoon president.The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended April 14, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Editor's Choice  Other recent books of particular interest</p>
        <p>THE GRAND SURPRISE: The Journals of Leo Lerman. Edited by Stephen Pascal. (Knopf, $37.50.) Lerman, a contemporary of Truman Capote, was a larger-than-life figure in the magazine world who also gave great parties.</p>
        <p>DEEP ECONOMY: The Wealth of Communities and the Durable Future, by Bill McKibben. (Times Books/Holt, $25.) The noted environmentalist aims to change attitudes about economics and consumption in an age of global warming.</p>
        <p>... AND I HAVEN'T HAD A BAD DAY SINCE: From the Streets of Harlem to the Halls of Congress, by Charles B. Rangel with Leon Wynter. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $24.95.) This memoir from the chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee brims with brio.</p>
        <p>THE WILD TREES: A Story of Passion and Daring, by Richard Preston. (Random House, $25.95.) The strange biological world at the tops of giant redwoods obsesses a group of climbers.</p>
        <p>BLACK &amp; WHITE, by Dani Shapiro. (Knopf, $24.) The protagonist of Shapiro's novel is driven into exile by the notoriety of the raw art photos her famous mother made of her as a child.</p>
        <p>EASTER EVERYWHERE: A Memoir, by Darcey Steinke. (Bloomsbury, $24.95.) A minister's daughter confronts her own spiritual rootlessness.</p>
        <p>WAY MORE WEST: New and Selected Poems, by Edward Dorn. Edited by Michael Rothenberg. (Penguin Poets; paper, $20.) Dorn, who died in 1999, was the quintessential Black Mountain poet.</p>
        <p>BURIED IN THE BITTER WATERS: The Hidden History of Racial Cleansing in America, by Elliot Jaspin. (Basic Books, $26.95.) A troubling investigation of a dozen locales that engineered mass expulsions of blacks from 1890 to 1930.</p>
        <p>HUNK CITY, by James Wilcox. (Viking, $25.95.) The globalized marketplace has pressed its thumb on Tula Springs, La., the town Wilcox introduced in his 1983 novel, ''Modern Baptists.''</p>
        <p>ANT FARM: And Other Desperate Situations, by Simon Rich. (Random House, $12.95.) Very short, very sweet Monty Python-esque humor vignettes from a former Harvard Lampoon president.The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>05,05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  FICTION</p>
        <p>1  1  2  I HEARD THAT SONG BEFORE, by Mary Higgins Clark. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.95.) A woman marries a childhood acquaintance suspected of several murders.</p>
        <p>2  2  6  NINETEEN MINUTES, by Jodi Picoult. (Atria, $26.95.) The aftermath of a high school shooting reveals the fault lines in a small New Hampshire town.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>1  FRESH DISASTERS, by Stuart Woods. (Putnam, $25.95.) Stone Barrington, the New York cop turned lawyer, tangles with a mob boss and pursues a complicated romance.</p>
        <p>4*  6  2  THE RELUCTANT FUNDAMENTALIST, by Mohsin Hamid. (Harcourt, $22.) The life of a Pakistani immigrant, successful in the corporate world, is changed by 9/11.</p>
        <p>5  4  3  OBSESSION, by Jonathan Kellerman. (Ballantine, $26.95.)The psychologist-detective Alex Delaware investigates an apparent deathbed confession of murder.</p>
        <p>6  3  2  KINGDOM COME, by Tim LaHaye and Jerry B. Jenkins. (Tyndale, $25.99.) The final title in the ''Left Behind'' series.</p>
        <p>7  5  2  WHITE KNIGHT, by Jim Butcher. (Roc, $23.95.) Someone is killing Chicago's minor wizards, and the half-brother of Harry Dresden, a wizard detective, is a suspect.</p>
        <p>8  7  3  THE ALIBI MAN, by Tami Hoag. (Bantam, $26.) A disgraced former policewoman investigates a murder linked to a group of wealthy Palm Beach men.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>1  SLEEPING WITH STRANGERS, by Eric Jerome Dickey. (Dutton, $24.95.) A hit man who hopes to leave the business travels to London to escape pursuers and becomes involved in its underworld.</p>
        <p>10  8  6  WHITETHORN WOODS, by Maeve Binchy. (Knopf, $25.95.) A proposed highway threatens the existence of a religious shrine in a rural Irish village.</p>
        <p>11  9  3  ABSOLUTE FEAR, by Lisa Jackson. (Kensington, $19.95.) A New Orleans detective tracks a serial killer somehow linked to an abandoned asylum.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>27  FOR ONE MORE DAY, by Mitch Albom. (Hyperion, $21.95.) A troubled man gets a last chance to reconnect and restore his relationship with his dead mother.</p>
        <p>13*  10  10  STEP ON A CRACK, by James Patterson and Michael Ledwidge. (Little, Brown, $27.99.) A detective raising 10 children alone must rescue 34 high-level hostages.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>1  THE LAND OF MANGO SUNSETS, by Dorothea Benton Frank. (Morrow, $24.95.) A Manhattan socialite whose husband has left her learns to move on with her life.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>1  OBSESSION, by Karen Robards. (Putnam, $24.95.) The special assistant to the head of the C.I.A. flees for her life with a handsome doctor after she is savagely beaten by intruders.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1  EINSTEIN, by Walter Isaacson. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $32.) A biography based on newly released personal letters.</p>
        <p>2  1  9  A LONG WAY GONE, by Ishmael Beah. (Sarah Crichton/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A former child soldier from Sierra Leone describes his drug-crazed killing spree and his return to humanity.</p>
        <p>3  2  2  PAULA DEEN: IT AIN'T ALL ABOUT THE COOKIN', by Paula Deen with Sherry Suib Cohen. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) A memoir with recipes from the Southern cooking impresario (Food Network shows, restaurants, cookbooks, magazine).</p>
        <p>4  3  4  GRACE (EVENTUALLY), by Anne Lamott. (Riverhead, $24.95.) Essays about faith and forgiveness.</p>
        <p>5  4  10  INFIDEL, by Ayaan Hirsi Ali. (Free Press, $26.) A memoir by the Somali-born advocate for Muslim immigrant women.</p>
        <p>6  6  7  IN AN INSTANT, by Lee and Bob Woodruff. (Random House, $25.95.) The aftermath of the ABC co-anchor's traumatic brain injury in Iraq in 2006.</p>
        <p>7  7  26  THE AUDACITY OF HOPE, by Barack Obama. (Crown, $25.) The Illinois junior senator proposes that Americans move beyond their political divisions.</p>
        <p>8  8  37  I FEEL BAD ABOUT MY NECK, by Nora Ephron. (Knopf, $19.95.) A witty look at aging from a novelist and screenwriter (''When Harry Met Sally'').</p>
        <p>9  9  5  HOW DOCTORS THINK, by Jerome Groopman. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) A doctor and New Yorker staff writer describes how doctors arrive at diagnoses.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>1  KABUL BEAUTY SCHOOL, by Deborah Rodriguez with Kristin Ohlson. (Random House, $24.95.) To aid Afghan women, an American opens a beauty school in Kabul.</p>
        <p>11  5  3  THE NEW AMERICAN STORY, by Bill Bradley. (Random House, $25.95.) The former Democratic senator and presidential candidate presents a liberal-centrist agenda.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>99  FREAKONOMICS, by Steven D. Levitt and Stephen J. Dubner. (Morrow, $27.95.) A maverick scholar and a journalist apply economic theory to nearly everything.</p>
        <p>13  10  30  THE GOD DELUSION, by Richard Dawkins. (Houghton Mifflin, $27.) An Oxford scientist asserts that belief in God is irrational.</p>
        <p>12*  105  14  THE WORLD IS FLAT, by Thomas L. Friedman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $30.) A columnist for The Times analyzes 21st-century economics and foreign policy.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>1  BETTER, by Atul Gawande. (Metropolitan, $24.) A surgeon and New Yorker writer describes how doctors strive to improve their performance.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>1  THE LAST TYCOONS, by William D. Cohan. (Doubleday, $29.95.) The secret history of the Wall Street investment firm Lazard FrÃ</p>
        <p>res.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
