<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Environment, Rallies Great and Small (and Unusual Attire)</title>
    <meta content="15warming" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15warming.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Step It Up (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramirez, Manny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E7D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Environment, Rallies Great and Small (and Unusual Attire)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For the Environment, Rallies Great and Small (and Unusual Attire)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ; Carolyn Marshall contributed reporting from San Francisco and Katie Zezima contributed from Boston.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds of people form human shoreline at rim of lower Manhattan to warn of dangers of rising sea levels from global warming as part of national day of rallies held across nation; organizers of campaign, Step It Up, say it is largest environmental demonstration since Earth Day in 1970; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of people formed a human shoreline at the rim of Lower Manhattan yesterday, warning of the dangers of rising sea levels from global warming as part of a national day of environmental demonstrations.</p>
        <p>The roughly U-shaped line, a few blocks inland, was a sometimes-comical, sometimes-serious attempt to show what the tip of the island might look like if the sea level rose several feet from the melting of Greenland's ice sheets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of people formed a human shoreline at the rim of Lower Manhattan Saturday to warn of the dangers of rising sea levels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of people formed a human shoreline at the rim of Lower Manhattan yesterday, warning of the dangers of rising sea levels from global warming as part of a national day of environmental demonstrations.</p>
        <p>The roughly U-shaped line, a few blocks inland, was a sometimes-comical, sometimes-serious attempt to show what the tip of the island might look like if the sea level rose several feet from the melting of Greenland's ice sheets.</p>
        <p>Throughout the line, packed in some stretches and spread thin in others, were men, women and children dressed more for a maritime adventure than a windy spring day in New York City. They wore wet suits, scuba-diving flippers and blue sheets with hand-painted waves. Some tossed around beach balls. One man tried to make his way through the narrow streets with a long canoe hitched to his bicycle.</p>
        <p>''It's about human survival, and we all have to act now before it gets out of hand,'' said Eric Rodriguez, 17, a junior at Tottenville High School on Staten Island. He formed part of the imaginary water's edge outside a Starbucks cafe on Pearl Street as a fellow student, Raina Bedford, 18, held a sign reading: ''Hold your breath we're going under.''</p>
        <p>The event was one of roughly 1,400 rallies across the country. The campaign, called Step It Up, was described by organizers as the largest environmental demonstration in the country since Earth Day 1970, a gathering that helped start the modern environmental movement. Yet the many scattered Step It Up events seemed far smaller in comparison. Some drew a few hundred, others a few dozen. In Manhattan, organizers estimated a crowd of 1,200.</p>
        <p>Step It Up's lead organizer, Bill McKibben, a resident scholar at Middlebury College in Vermont and the author of ''The End of Nature,'' a 1989 book about global warming, said the widespread, do-it-yourself activities fit the campaign's unifying theme: urging Congress to cut carbon emissions 80 percent by 2050.</p>
        <p>He also explained one of the main reasons organizers did not call for a mass march in one location. ''We didn't want people spewing carbon behind them as they crossed the continent to come to Washington,'' said Mr. McKibben, 46, who, along with Representative Anthony D. Weiner of Queens, spoke at a rally at Battery Park in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The day's events were as varied as national weather patterns. There were film screenings and poetry readings, bicycle rides and hiking expeditions, drum circles and tree plantings. People dived underwater to wave a sign reading ''It's Getting Hot Down Here!!'' at a coral reef off Key West, Fla. In Jacksonville, Fla., demonstrators used an unusual visual aid to illustrate rising sea levels: Alltel Stadium, home of professional football's Jacksonville Jaguars, where they hoisted a boat 20 feet in the air outside an entrance.</p>
        <p>At a rally that drew about 400 people to Boston Common, dozens of schoolchildren and their parents carried ''recycling rope,'' blue twine decorated with milk cartons, egg cartons and aluminum cans. In the San Francisco Bay Area, thousands turned out in the rain at a series of demonstrations and town hall meetings. At the Presidio near the Golden Gate Bridge, Felicity Crush, 43, and other members of the group Main Street Moms Organize or Bust, or Mmob, attended a gathering promoting electric cars and other alternative fuel vehicles. They later joined a demonstration outside a Hummer dealership in San Rafael.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crush said she had become more involved in such rallies out of concern for her 9-year-old daughter. ''We're just leaving this dreadful mess for them,'' she said. ''They will have to pick up the pieces.''</p>
        <p>Many rallygoers said yesterday's actions reflected a widespread resurgence of the environmental movement, boosted in part by former Vice President Al Gore's documentary, ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' which was shown at many of the gatherings.</p>
        <p>In some places the demonstrators seemed concerned as much with the means as with the ends. In California, Matthew Lundin, 22, a college student, dreamed up a demonstration in which ice cubes would be tossed into the Pacific Ocean at a beach in Santa Barbara County. His idea prompted a debate over whether it was wise to waste ice cubes, which take refrigeration, and therefore energy, to produce.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, about 20 people met at Goleta Beach and tossed away nevertheless.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad that people understood the symbolism,'' Mr. Lundin said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
