<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Passion for Soccer and the Environment</title>
    <meta content="19boulder" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/soccer/19boulder.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Boulder</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Boulder (Colo)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Colorado Rapids</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Soccer</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Passion for Soccer and the Environment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Passion for Soccer and the Environment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT ANDREW POWELL</byline>
      <dateline>BOULDER, Colo.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In marketing terms, last year's slogan was a bit of a clunker. ''Boulder County's Most Competitive Soccer Team,'' as advertised on a side of the van that shuttles the Colorado Rapids under-23 players to practice, might have been accurate. But it failed to attract more than a couple of hundred fans to any of the team's home games.</p>
        <p>''I lose so much money with this team, $30,000 a year,'' said Rodrigo García, one of the team's two owners. The U-23s are an amateur, minor league team affiliated with the Colorado Rapids of Major League Soccer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Colorado Rapids U-23 team, a minor league soccer club in Boulder, Colo., is on a campaign to fight global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In marketing terms, last year's slogan was a bit of a clunker. ''Boulder County's Most Competitive Soccer Team,'' as advertised on a side of the van that shuttles the Colorado Rapids under-23 players to practice, might have been accurate. But it failed to attract more than a couple of hundred fans to any of the team's home games.</p>
        <p>''I lose so much money with this team, $30,000 a year,'' said Rodrigo García, one of the team's two owners. The U-23s are an amateur, minor league team affiliated with the Colorado Rapids of Major League Soccer.</p>
        <p>García, a lawyer from Argentina who has never practiced law, and his partner, Peter Ambrose, operate an indoor soccer facility in Boulder. They purchased the U-23 team three years ago as a way to market their business and to recruit coaches for their money-making summer youth clinics.</p>
        <p>They also enjoy developing soccer talent. Ambrose and García, who are the coach  and the assistant  for the team, are former players and are passionate about screening players for their M.L.S. partner club. But to survive at the lowest level of minor league soccer, they needed to stop losing money. They searched for a new sales pitch, something that would resonate in Boulder, a city so conscious of its ecology and karma that it is often described as 30 square miles surrounded by reality.</p>
        <p>Boulder was one of the first cities in the United States to do curbside recycling. Last year, its city council voted to adhere to the Kyoto Protocol on climate change, which was never ratified by the United States as a whole. The parking lot of Boulder's retail district, known as Twenty Ninth Street, has reserved spaces for alternative-fuel vehicles.</p>
        <p>''Boulder's really marketed itself as a central place for health and the environment,'' said Beth Powell, the marketing and communications coordinator for the Office of Environmental Affairs in Boulder. ''People have moved here specifically because they value health and the environment.''</p>
        <p>Forget about being the most competitive team in Boulder. This year, the U-23s have a new slogan, ''The World's First Carbon Neutral Soccer Team.'' Their warm-up jerseys implore fans to ''Kick Global Warming.''</p>
        <p>In a news release in April, the team announced that ''all the carbon emissions produced by the team (coaches, players, etc.) during their daily events (driving, cooking, etc.) are offset by modes of carbon reduction (reforestation, solar power, wind power, etc.).''</p>
        <p>The new campaign was the idea of Ben Bressler, the founder and director of Natural Habitat Adventures, an upscale environmental travel company based in Boulder. The company offers trips to see blue-footed boobies mate on the Galapagos Islands or to observe polar bears exploring the tundra of Manitoba.</p>
        <p>Bressler is also a serious soccer fan who managed to take a trip to the World Cup in Germany last year. García knew Bressler from the indoor soccer facility and often asked him for money.</p>
        <p>''I must have asked him a hundred times to: Sponsor us! Sponsor us! Sponsor us!'' García said.</p>
        <p>Bressler was reluctant; a sponsorship would set him back at least $10,000, and would return little more than a sign posted at the U-23's home field. Then he came up with an idea, inspired in part by his trip to the World Cup.</p>
        <p>The organizers of the World Cup, along with organizers of the most recent Super Bowl in Miami, declared their events carbon neutral. Any pollution generated by the games -- from travel to the burning of stadium lights -- was offset by donations to plant trees in Africa, or by replacing coal-powered stoves in Somalia with solar-powered grills.</p>
        <p>Bressler decided to make his travel company carbon neutral in this same way, paying a third party to cover carbon emissions from plane trips and the like. The switch has helped his travel business, he said, so why couldn't it work for a soccer team?</p>
        <p>''For the Colorado Rapids U-23s to say, 'Come to our game and jump in a bouncy castle,' that's old news,'' Bressler said in a recent telephone interview. ''To say, 'Come on a bike and get $2 off admission,' that's exciting.''</p>
        <p>In addition to sponsoring the U-23s, Bressler set up a foundation, Kick Global Warming, which aims to make carbon copies of his carbon-neutral soccer team. By clicking on the foundation's Web site, Kickglobalwarming.org, soccer players around the world can calculate a dollar amount for their team's carbon emissions. The site also links to a nonprofit organization to which teams can donate.</p>
        <p>Mitigating the carbon emissions of an average soccer team can cost as little as $5 a player, Bressler said. But the efficacy of these carbon offsets is a matter of debate.</p>
        <p>Roger Pielke Jr., a professor of environmental studies at the University of Colorado, said that the idea that ''you are doing something meaningful rather than emotional and symbolic'' by donating money to something like planting trees in Malaysia ''is a little misleading.''</p>
        <p>Pielke added: ''It allows people to continue doing what they were doing before, but if they pay a little money, their sins will be forgiven -- without changing their behavior. The reality is that dealing with global warming will require wholesale change.''</p>
        <p>As a resident of Boulder for the past 20 years, Pielke acknowledges the city's passion for recycling, which he compares with the passion some sports fans have for their favorite teams.</p>
        <p>At the Boulder Creek Festival during Memorial Day weekend, a woman held up a sign calling war ''the ultimate environmental horror.'' Another woman handed out fliers -- on 100 percent postconsumer recycled paper, of course -- for a local restaurant that said it was ''totally organic and zero waste, so it's cool.''</p>
        <p>''Boulder has a reputation, for a lot of reasons, for doing symbolic things on climate change,'' Pielke said. ''It's not at all unusual or surprising to see a soccer team in Boulder do something like this. When Nascar announces they're going carbon neutral, then we'll have something to talk about.''</p>
        <p>Bressler, the main sponsor for the Rapids U-23s, said that Nascar was the goal, ultimately. First the Y-23s, he said, then their parent team, then maybe  M.L.S. And after that, why not the English Premier League, the N.F.L., the N.B.A. and onward?</p>
        <p>''Right now we are a grain of sand on a vast beach,'' he said. ''But soccer is sexy and interesting. It's something that's so influential. Who would people rather listen to, George W. Bush or David Beckham? Next thing you know, other teams and leagues and companies will start buying into it. It'll reach a tipping point.''</p>
        <p>A week after the Boulder team declared itself carbon neutral, the Ipswich Town team in England, in a move that appears coincidental, announced that it had become ''the U.K.'s First Carbon Neutral Football Club.''</p>
        <p>The Rapids U-23s are part of the Premier Development League, which is an entry-level tier of the United Soccer Leagues.</p>
        <p>The leagues are considered to be a rung or two below Major League Soccer. The P.D.L. is a summer home for college players who want to retain their N.C.A.A. eligibility and play under international rules.</p>
        <p>''I see this summer as almost like a soccer internship,'' said Doug Edwards, a 22-year-old fullback from Tulsa who just finished his junior year at the College of Charleston. Half the team bunks in one small house. Adhering to the Boulder recycling program is a work in progress.</p>
        <p>''We try,'' Edwards said. ''It's hard with 13 of us in one house. And a lot of the guys come from other places, so they aren't used toseparating their papers and cans.''</p>
        <p>The U-23s are allowed to use the new practice fields for the Colorado Rapids parent club, located outside Denver.</p>
        <p>But they only go there about once a week. They usually practice in Boulder, on public open space along a Rocky Mountain foothill. Blue recycling bins stand at the entrance to the park, latched shut to deter mountain lions, which have been spotted in the area.</p>
        <p>The team runs keep-away drills on lumpy grass; the city will not allow them to paint end lines or penalty spots on the grass. At a recent practice, a goalie defending a portable net dived onto a three-foot-long bull snake.</p>
        <p>''This park is close and free,'' García said at the practice, after the snake slithered into a patch of wildflowers. He said that although the Rapids' facility in Denver was nice, it took an hour to travel there.</p>
        <p>García added: ''And with the price of gas! And then we have to pay for our carbon emissions on top of that. It's just easier to stay here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
