<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing Havoc With the Hellebores</title>
    <meta content="01ctcolCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01ctcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirshey, Gerri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3DC1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing Havoc With the Hellebores</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Playing Havoc With the Hellebores</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERRI HIRSHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hirshey, Gerri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerri Hirshey column on concerns among horticulturists, nursery managers and home gardeners over warm outdoor conditions across Connecticut this past winter, when flowering plants and bulbs bloomed far ahead of schedule; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>APRIL FOOL'S DAY dawned early -- months early -- for Connecticut gardeners. Some of us in the southwestern part of the state can date it to late December, when a few foolhardy forsythia blossoms, seduced by the unusual warmth, blazed a wanton yellow amid the jolly evergreen swags and wreaths -- and promptly shriveled. Just after New Year's, others noticed befuddled bulbs -- daffodils, hyacinths, narcissuses -- sending up tenuous shoots that now protrude, cracked and yellowed, like rows of neglected teeth. Lenten roses -- hellebores, named for their normal pre-Easter bloom time -- blasphemed against nature with unseemly display at Christmas.</p>
        <p>Even by mercurial New England weather standards in Connecticut's plant hardiness zones 5 and 6, it was a strange winter of low snowfall and extreme temperature fluctuations. And the question looms: Will there be much to smile about this blooming season? An informal poll of horticultural experts in the state reveals that even the pros are sweating it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>April Fool's Day dawned early  months early  for Connecticut gardeners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>APRIL FOOL'S DAY dawned early -- months early -- for Connecticut gardeners. Some of us in the southwestern part of the state can date it to late December, when a few foolhardy forsythia blossoms, seduced by the unusual warmth, blazed a wanton yellow amid the jolly evergreen swags and wreaths -- and promptly shriveled. Just after New Year's, others noticed befuddled bulbs -- daffodils, hyacinths, narcissuses -- sending up tenuous shoots that now protrude, cracked and yellowed, like rows of neglected teeth. Lenten roses -- hellebores, named for their normal pre-Easter bloom time -- blasphemed against nature with unseemly display at Christmas.</p>
        <p>Even by mercurial New England weather standards in Connecticut's plant hardiness zones 5 and 6, it was a strange winter of low snowfall and extreme temperature fluctuations. And the question looms: Will there be much to smile about this blooming season? An informal poll of horticultural experts in the state reveals that even the pros are sweating it.</p>
        <p>''We're very apprehensive about spring,'' admitted Judith King, president of the Connecticut Horticultural Society in Rocky Hill. She noted that in the central part of the state, ''some native wildflowers are out of whack.''</p>
        <p>''We had hepatica blooming in January -- which is unheard of,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In Plainville, the society's hardy plant specialist, Leslie Shields, reported: ''I'm seeing more winter damage to broadleaf evergreens. They never got that needed cold to harden off. Branches are snapping.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shields, who taught middle school biology, says she is most concerned for vulnerable riparian species: ''The worst thing I saw, in February, was a frog. It was sitting on a fence rail, months before it's safe to be out above ground. I don't know if he made it.''</p>
        <p>Could things be as strange in the state's chilliest region? I checked in with Barbara Pierson, greenhouse manager at White Flower Farm, the venerable nursery in Litchfield, an area otherwise known as ''the refrigerator of Connecticut.'' She says that in her home garden, the stinking hellebore (Helleborus foetidus) bloomed months early. Cycles were out of whack even in White Flower's well-controlled propagation buildings.</p>
        <p>''During the winter, we keep the greenhouses between 30 and 40 degrees using furnaces,'' Ms. Pierson said. ''But with the outdoor temperatures in December, some days we couldn't get them below 50 or 60. It's been a race to keep things from maturing too early for shipping.''</p>
        <p>The warm outdoor conditions had another, even less welcome effect. Ms. Pierson, who has long enjoyed winter respite from insect pests, has been waging frenzied warfare. ''Aphids!'' she hissed. ''They didn't sleep as usual. And I've been battling western flower thrips!''</p>
        <p>Known in the trade as W.F.T.'s, they are among the most feared pests in floriculture. Given their role as virus vectors, W.F.T.'s can inflict mass destruction on everything from tomato to impatiens seedlings. They were vanquished, but Ms. Pierson vows she will never let down her guard in winters to come.</p>
        <p>Though National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration data show that Northeast winter temperatures have increased by 2.8 degrees in the last 30 years, Ms. Pierson said: ''I hesitate to solely blame global warming for the plant anomalies. The most troubling factor is the wild fluctuations we're seeing. I worry about whether plants' hardiness will be able to adapt. Perennials that need a hard frost -- sedum, dianthus, dicentra -- may really suffer, or disappear.''</p>
        <p>Robert Durgy, a horticultural diagnostician at the University of Connecticut, shares her concerns. Fluctuations are stressful to plants, he explained, ''because it takes metabolic energy to prepare for the cold -- either by adding sugars or going dry. Desiccation and sugar prevent frost damage. But the warm-ups we've had makes things convert back. It takes energy to convert in both directions.''</p>
        <p>Thus blooms may literally be too pooped to pop? ''Depends on the species,'' he said, predicting that flowering bulbs that came up prematurely will probably bloom. ''There is usually a second bud in the bulbs -- maybe not as big, but it can flower.'' He is not so sanguine about the state's fruit trees. ''I'm expecting damage when the stone fruits -- peach, plum and cherry -- blossom,'' he said. ''I don't think flowering will be halted outright, but there will probably be some gnarled and stunted blossoms.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Durgy does have reason for some optimism: ''I'm hoping for a good outside insect kill.'' He explained that garden pests like Japanese beetles, which burrow beneath leaves during the winter, may, after a few false awakenings, have fatally exhausted their ability to produce a substance much like ethylene glycol, the active ingredient in antifreeze.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shields added an upbeat coda that hums subliminally in every beleaguered New England gardener dating back to Thoreau, ''The one good thing about a winter kill is that in spring, you get to go berserk in the nursery.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
