<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is America Just Too Big for Its Own Good?</title>
    <meta content="l17california" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1826726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rougeau, Vincent D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gibson, Edward L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Burt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5D9143EF934A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is America Just Too Big for Its Own Good?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three letters respond to Gar Alperovitz Feb 10 Op-Ed article contending that US may be too big to be meaningful democracy; Vincent D Rougeau and Burt Cohen support Alperovitz's article; Edward L Gibson says that before we get swept up by Alperovitz's enthusiasm for decentralization, we should remember two centuries of American history; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''California Split'' (Op-Ed, Feb. 10), Gar Alperovitz raises a serious question that our increasingly tense and polarized national politics may soon be forced to confront. Is the United States just too big?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''California Split'' (Op-Ed, Feb. 10), Gar Alperovitz raises a serious question that our increasingly tense and polarized national politics may soon be forced to confront. Is the United States just too big?</p>
        <p>Americans who want to see meaningful political action on any number of problems are frustrated by a Congress that is totally captured by elites that govern from the center, or, worse yet, ideologues who use slim majorities to force their agendas on a public they cannot persuade through political dialogue.</p>
        <p>Why should millions of people in the Northeast or California be prevented from moving in the direction of other developed nations on issues like global warming and international human rights because voters in Texas and Tennessee disagree?</p>
        <p>If the structure of the political community is undermining the democratic values it was designed to promote, then perhaps it is time for the structure to change.</p>
        <p>Vincent D. Rougeau  Notre Dame, Ind., Feb. 10, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an associate professor at Notre Dame Law School.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Before we get swept up by Gar Alperovitz's enthusiasm for decentralization, let's remember two centuries of American history.</p>
        <p>Democracy was delivered to the disenfranchised not by devolving power to local authorities, but by expanding central government powers. Similarly, economic development across the continental United States was given a major boost by federal stimulation and regulation of interstate commerce.</p>
        <p>California is a powerhouse because it is part of the largest and most dynamic national economy in the world.</p>
        <p>The vibrancy of any federal democracy (regardless of size) lies in its continuing ability to stimulate local dynamism and innovation while empowering a central government to safeguard the whole against the vices and parochialism of its parts.</p>
        <p>Edward L. Gibson  Evanston, Ill., Feb. 10, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an associate professor of political science at Northwestern University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The morning after the 2004 election, my daughter, then 8 years old, asked, ''Did Kerry win?'' We said no. Then she asked, ''Did Kerry win New England?''</p>
        <p>Yes, he did. After some thoughtful silence, she then asked, ''Well, can he be president of New England?''</p>
        <p>Consider these historical inevitabilities: Yugoslavia and the Soviet Union had to break up. Iraq was defined by Britain. Ireland will be united. Palestine will achieve statehood. Had the Union let the Confederacy go, more than 600,000 lives would have been spared -- and the South wouldn't dominate national elections today.</p>
        <p>In 2008, it is exceedingly difficult for one presidential candidate to appeal to the entire nation. We are half a dozen or so distinct regions. The Northeast could have elected John Kerry. The South could have invaded Iraq without us.</p>
        <p>Who would have thought that it would be Arnold Schwarzenegger leading this new rebellion?</p>
        <p>Burt Cohen  New Castle, N.H., Feb. 10, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer was a New Hampshire state senator, 1990-2004, and a candidate for the United States Senate in 2004.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
