<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Detroit Finds Agreement On the Need To Be Green</title>
    <meta content="01auto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/business/01auto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bunkley, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gettelfinger, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Detroit (Mich)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Automobile Workers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Detroit Finds Agreement On the Need To Be Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Detroit Finds Agreement on the Need to Be Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK BUNKLEY; Micheline Maynard contributed reporting from Detroit.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bunkley, Nick</byline>
      <dateline>MACKINAC ISLAND, Mich., May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Auto Workers union</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Labor and management in the auto industry are often at odds, but on Thursday they agreed on something critics have been telling them for years: Detroit must act to reduce its vehicles' impact on the environment.</p>
        <p>Ron Gettelfinger, the president of the United Automobile Workers union, and William Clay Ford Jr., executive chairman of the Ford Motor Company, told Michigan business leaders that cutting emissions and raising fuel economy standards are critical to the future of the industry and that of Michigan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Labor and management in the auto industry agreed that Detroit must act to reduce its vehicles’ impact on the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Labor and management in the auto industry are often at odds, but on Thursday they agreed on something critics have been telling them for years: Detroit must act to reduce its vehicles' impact on the environment.</p>
        <p>Ron Gettelfinger, the president of the United Automobile Workers union, and William Clay Ford Jr., executive chairman of the Ford Motor Company, told Michigan business leaders that cutting emissions and raising fuel economy standards are critical to the future of the industry and that of Michigan.</p>
        <p>Both men spoke at an annual policy conference sponsored by the Detroit Chamber of Commerce, held on Mackinac Island, a car-free retreat on the northern tip of Lake Huron.</p>
        <p>Such comments are no surprise from Mr. Ford, who said his environmental views once caused many colleagues to view him ''as some sort of crazy radical.'' But they are somewhat unexpected from Mr. Gettelfinger, whose environmental leanings have not been well known.</p>
        <p>Noting that he has come to believe that ''climate change is real,'' Mr. Gettelfinger said consumers were increasingly searching for more environmentally friendly vehicles. Detroit companies, he said, need to make more vehicles that meet those demands.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, there is an impression among the car-buying public that the Big Three build nothing but gas guzzlers, while Toyota is a division of Greenpeace,'' he said to loud applause.</p>
        <p>Detroit automakers, which have fought many attempts to enact stricter standards governing fuel economy and automotive emissions, need to change customer's minds, Mr. Gettelfinger said.</p>
        <p>''If the auto industry continues to be seen as dragging its feet on environmental issues,'' he said, ''it's going to hurt our brands and vehicles in the marketplace.''</p>
        <p>Mike Hudema, director of the Freedom From Oil coalition, a critic of the automakers, applauded Mr. Gettelfinger's comments.</p>
        <p>''We're definitely pleased to hear that labor is really getting behind this and starting to push the auto industry for some strong commitments,'' Mr. Hudema said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gettelfinger, the first U.A.W. official to speak at the Mackinac conference since 1988, suggested several proposals, including setting automobile fuel economy standards that vary based on a vehicle's size. He also called for tax credits to manufacturers who invest in the United States, repeating ideas he first floated in March.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford, meanwhile, proposed convening manufacturers, energy companies, governments and academics to develop a national energy policy. He said it was gratifying to see more concern about the environment from others in the industry.</p>
        <p>''When I talked about the environment 20 years ago, and frankly even 5 years ago, many people thought I was eccentric at best or perhaps incredibly naïve,'' Mr. Ford said. ''But in the past few years we demonstrated the business case for environmental stewardship.''</p>
        <p>Thursday's speeches came several weeks after General Motors' vice chairman, Robert A. Lutz, a longtime advocate of muscle cars and horsepower, showed his green side during the taping of a National Public Radio program in Ann Arbor, Mich. Mr. Lutz described the Chevrolet Volt, a battery-powered concept car, as being ''among the most important vehicles that G.M. has ever developed.''</p>
        <p>The conference also follows criticism of the Detroit automakers leveled by Senator Barack Obama, Democrat of Illinois, during a visit to the city. Mr. Obama, a presidential candidate, said that the auto companies were doing little to curtail the nation's dependence on imported oil and laid out a series of proposals, including one that would raise fuel economy standards to about 40 miles a gallon over the next few years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama's proposal is similar to one made by the Bush administration, which would increase fuel economy standards by about one mile a gallon each year. The current standard is 27.5 miles a gallon for cars and 24 miles a gallon for light trucks.</p>
        <p>Congress, however, has been considering more drastic proposals, to the alarm of some Detroit executives.</p>
        <p>With some kind of increase appearing inevitable, officials at the Detroit auto companies have said that they want to work with lawmakers on a plan that would minimize the financial impact.</p>
        <p>''Collectively we didn't move fast enough,'' Mr. Ford conceded in his speech. But he warned, ''Legitimate concerns about global warming, energy security and the cost of gasoline have created a rush toward arbitrary and poorly conceived solutions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
