<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Better Ways to Spend Our Money</title>
    <meta content="l09budget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1824875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, H Rex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buchanan, Todd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monaghan, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Wayne R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EED7113FF93AA35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Better Ways to Spend Our Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Five letters comment on Pres Bush's proposed budget (Feb 6 article and Feb 6 and 8 editorials); H Rex Greene says it makes no sense to squander US wealth on Iraq war and assure deconstruction of beleaguered social programs; Lou Erlanger holds there is no reason to believe Bush administration's goal is to balance budget by 2012 or any other year; Todd Buchanan and Howard Monaghan say bloated military spending could be better used for investing in economies of poorest countries and providing health, education and welfare of American citizens; Wayne R Knight says Pres Bush has audacity to say it will be up to Democrats to rein in federal spending after he has turned biggest budget surplus in history into biggest deficit in history</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Mr. Bush's Improbable Budget'' (editorial, Feb. 8):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Mr. Bush's Improbable Budget'' (editorial, Feb. 8):</p>
        <p>The Bush budget proves that the American empire is in decline. The Iraq war is now unaffordable. Even if it were a triumph of nation-building based on legitimate evidence of a threat to our security, it ravages our economic future. It makes no sense to squander our wealth on this war and assure the deconstruction of our beleaguered social programs.</p>
        <p>The Great Society is teetering. Medicare is in jeopardy. Medicaid is in free fall. Next target of the Bush radicals: the New Deal. We are letting this pointless war (which we won four years ago) catalyze the restoration of the Gilded Age.</p>
        <p>H. Rex Greene  Elida, Ohio, Feb. 8, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Regarding your Feb. 8 editorial about the Bush administration's new budget, there is no reason to believe that the administration's goal is to balance the budget by 2012 or any other year.</p>
        <p>This administration came into office in 2001 with a balanced budget and a surplus and immediately proceeded to plunder it. It would be foolish to believe that after bringing the country trillions of dollars into the red, these officials have changed.</p>
        <p>Louis Erlanger  Brattleboro, Vt., Feb. 8, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Other Defense Budget'' (editorial, Feb. 6):</p>
        <p>Thank you for specifying several weapons programs that we could afford to trim or delete. The money could be better spent addressing more plausible threats like climate change and infectious disease.</p>
        <p>If we hope to avoid intolerable costs of global warming, we need to be investing generously in clean energy technologies.</p>
        <p>Similarly, we need to be investing more in the economies of the poorest countries: until your basic needs are met, you can't fret about the environment. And without economic development and female education, population will not stabilize.</p>
        <p>Although global warming and poverty do not have the outrage factor of threats we can attribute to evil perpetrators, they are serious threats nonetheless.</p>
        <p>Todd  Buchanan  Eldora, Colo., Feb. 6, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush Releases Budget as Plan to Erase Deficit'' (front page, Feb. 6) and ''The Other Defense Budget'' (editorial, Feb. 6):</p>
        <p>Our government is addicted to military spending, and it has increased at alarming rates under this administration. At some point it must be examined.</p>
        <p>The budget is more about subsidizing an obscenely bloated military-industrial complex than it is about supporting our troops. How many more jets and attack submarines do we need? Will hundreds of billions spent on hardware make us more secure?</p>
        <p>If the United States halved its military spending, it would still have the world's biggest budget by far. Lawmakers looking for fat to cut should start here. And perhaps we could put that money to use elsewhere -- like the health, education and welfare of our citizens.</p>
        <p>Howard Monaghan  Kendall Park, N.J., Feb. 7, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The president's budget calls for eliminating the deficit in 2012, four years after he leaves office. But while in office, he turned the biggest budget surplus in history into the biggest deficit in history and borrowed more than a trillion dollars to pay for a frivolous war and reward his rich friends.</p>
        <p>Now he will leave his successor to repair the damage he has done to our foreign relations and our economy on top of the damage from Katrina and other natural disasters and the domestic problems he has ignored.</p>
        <p>To add insult to injury, he has the audacity to tell us that with his budget, it will be up to the Democrats to rein in federal spending. This sounds to me like the inebriated husband who after bingeing for eight years tells his wife she has to cut back on the groceries.</p>
        <p>Wayne R. Knight  McLean, Va., Feb. 7, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
