<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big</title>
    <meta content="Zernike.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Zernike.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Preston, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Wild Trees, The: A Story of Passion and Daring (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Big</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE WILD TREES</p>
        <p>A Story of Passion and Daring.</p>
        <p>By Richard Preston.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 294 pp.</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard Preston investigates the unknown world of redwood canopies and the oddball characters who explore them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE WILD TREES</p>
        <p>A Story of Passion and Daring.</p>
        <p>By Richard Preston.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 294 pp.</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>In October 1987, Steve Sillett, a 19-year-old college student, made a running leap into a California coast redwood tree and climbed some 300 feet to the top without rope or safety gear, nearly falling to his death several times.</p>
        <p>He was hooked.</p>
        <p>Back then, scientists believed the redwoods, among the world's oldest and tallest trees, to be bereft of all other life at the top. Standing more than 30 stories tall, with few branches on their lower levels, they were considered too tricky to climb. Sillett encountered a world apparently unknown to anyone else: giant redwood canopies filled with countless forms of animal and plant life stretching over several acres -- ''what amounted to coral reefs in the air,'' as Richard Preston writes in ''The Wild Trees.'' Branches and trunks had grown so close together that Sillett ''could climb around on them'' as if he were ''climbing in a jungle gym, without fear of falling'' -- even though he was acrophobic.</p>
        <p>Preston, who explored the world of deadly viruses in the trilogy that began with ''The Hot Zone,'' follows Sillett as he enters a career in botany, a career spent mostly up in the canopy. Even learning to climb himself, Preston describes this largely unknown world and the occasionally oddball characters who are obsessed with finding the unexplored beauties that are the ''wild trees'' of the title.</p>
        <p>He makes the redwoods characters, towering, miraculous figures living ''at the edge of what is possible in nature.'' The oldest living ones are thought to be 2,000 to 3,000 years old -- roughly the age of the Parthenon. With soil that can be more than a yard deep, their canopies sprout huckleberry plants, laurel trees, even a Sitka spruce. Redwoods do not die if they burn; 65 million years ago they survived an asteroid six miles across that crashed into the earth and caused the mass extinction of many species, including the dinosaurs. They can reverse the flow of water, sending it up or down their trunks to suit their needs.</p>
        <p>''Whatever happens to the great systems of nature will also be what happens to us,'' Preston writes. But however tall, dark and important the redwoods may be, a tree has only so much personality, and it takes more to sustain 300 pages. ''The Wild Trees'' is best when Preston portrays the collection of characters drawn to the canopy -- the Southern California skateboarder, say, or the coupon distributor who posits that global warming may be making the redwoods taller.</p>
        <p>Of these, the most interesting is Michael Taylor, the wayward son of a wealthy commercial real estate developer, a forestry school dropout who drives through Santa Barbara selling knives out of a Volkswagen Rabbit painted with zebra stripes.</p>
        <p>Taylor discovers his own obsession with finding the world's tallest redwoods at almost exactly the same time as Sillett does his. But similarly afraid of heights, he measures them from the ground with a 45-cent device he fashions out of a protractor, string, a thumbtack and a pencil. He develops ''almost a sixth sense'' for finding the tallest redwoods and makes many crucial discoveries, including a grove of trees considered by botanists to be ''the Sistine Chapel of the world's forests.'' But, Preston writes, he could never have gotten a grant from the big science foundations, ''since the highlights of his résumé were door-to-door knife sales and mini-grocery management, and his chief collaborator was a night-shift worker in the post office.''</p>
        <p>Sillett's second wife, Marie Antoine, a colleague, takes a typical bride's pains to plan their wedding, which takes place between two redwood spires -- ''Certainly a traditional gown wouldn't work with all the ropes.'' She sews lichens into the veil, and at the ceremony her groom pulls her along a rope to a minister waiting at the ''altar.''</p>
        <p>Oddly, in a book of vivid characters, Sillett, the protagonist, is the least vivid. Through Sillett's brother and first wife, Preston describes his intelligence, recklessness and self-absorption. (When his wife leaves him, he shaves his head in penance and gives nearly half his students F's.) But Preston depicts other significant developments in flat, unsatisfactory passages. Sillett's decision to enter botany shortly after his initial redwood climb is explained in merely one sentence: as he listens to a naturalist discuss the importance of ''what Lobaria, or lungwort, does in a forest,'' Preston writes, ''he decided that he wanted to spend the rest of his life studying Lobaria in the trees.'' End of chapter, end of insight. And it's not clear how Sillett reconciles that fear of heights with a career 36 stories up.</p>
        <p>It's probably unfair to compare this book with Preston's well-known earlier works -- for drama, it's hard to measure up to a lethal virus. But the subtitle promises ''A Story of Passion and Daring,'' and too little of that passion comes across. There is a sex scene 300 feet up, but even that is more of a well-executed plan: ''The fact that there would be safety ropes hanging around and getting in the way would also hinder or prevent what they wanted to do.'' (Apparently even tree sex has its prosaic aspects; Antoine kicks Sillett out of the hammock when he falls fast asleep and hogs too much space.)</p>
        <p>Preston can recognize a thriller moment. When a climber goes into free fall at 90 miles an hour, the ground rushes at him to create a kind of tunnel vision: ''Maybe he couldn't tear his eyes from the spot as it came up. On the other hand, maybe he didn't see anything, maybe he went inside himself, trying to escape inward and away from what was coming. He still didn't scream.'' But this is mainly a book of quieter drama, about men like Taylor, who ''could find beauty in the small, hidden places that still existed on earth, the lost places that nobody had ever noticed.'' He ''had been convinced,'' Preston writes, ''that there was something wonderful still to be found on the earth.'' ''The Wild Trees'' convinces the rest of us as well.</p>
        <p>Kate Zernike is a national correspondent for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kate Zernike is a national correspondent for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
