<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bloomberg Calls for National Energy Reforms</title>
    <meta content="12mayor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/12/nyregion/12mayor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1846743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DA1531F931A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bloomberg Calls for National Energy Reforms</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bloomberg Calls for National Energy Reforms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY RIVERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rivera, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, May 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sounding a lot like a presidential candidate, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg laid out the framework for a national energy policy on Friday and accused Washington lawmakers of ''passing the buck'' on meaningful energy reforms.</p>
        <p>In a 40-minute speech delivered at a luncheon with Houston business leaders, Mr. Bloomberg called for building wind farms and nuclear power plants, raising automobile fuel standards and creating market-driven incentives to produce cleaner energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg laid out the framework for a national energy policy and accused Washington lawmakers of “passing the buck” on meaningful reforms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sounding a lot like a presidential candidate, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg laid out the framework for a national energy policy on Friday and accused Washington lawmakers of ''passing the buck'' on meaningful energy reforms.</p>
        <p>In a 40-minute speech delivered at a luncheon with Houston business leaders, Mr. Bloomberg called for building wind farms and nuclear power plants, raising automobile fuel standards and creating market-driven incentives to produce cleaner energy.</p>
        <p>''We need to inject some old-fashioned American values and common-sense, practical thinking into our energy policy,'' Mr. Bloomberg said. ''That means a willingness to face up to our responsibilities and hold ourselves accountable for making incremental progress.''</p>
        <p>Many of the policies Mr. Bloomberg outlined here dovetailed with his recently released environmental blueprint for New York City, PlaNYC, which calls for reducing greenhouse gas emissions by 30 percent by 2030. But the tone and broad national scale of his Houston speech is sure to fuel further speculation that Mr. Bloomberg is planning a run for the White House, even as he again denied such ambitions in a meeting with reporters after the speech.</p>
        <p>That speculation was heightened earlier this week when he revived his old mayoral campaign Web site, mikebloomberg.com, with the stated intent of highlighting his professional and personal work.</p>
        <p>The mayor, a billionaire, has also kept a busy schedule on his private jet, which he pays for himself. In addition to Houston, he also went to Oklahoma City on Friday, where he visited the Oklahoma City National Memorial and Museum and delivered the commencement address at the University of Oklahoma.</p>
        <p>''I plan to serve for the next 960-odd days as mayor of New York City,'' Mr. Bloomberg told reporters outside the memorial.</p>
        <p>In his Houston speech, the mayor highlighted ways both large and small of meeting three major energy challenges: producing more power, more cleanly; using it more efficiently; and creating new, sustainable sources.</p>
        <p>Among his more simple energy-saving ideas was replacing incandescent light bulbs with fluorescent bulbs, which burn less energy and last about eight times longer. He pointed to plans by Canada and Australia to phase out traditional incandescent bulbs over the next few years.</p>
        <p>''Once again, the technology is there, the savings are real, and the tipping point is coming,'' he said. ''If Australia can do it in five years, we can, too.''</p>
        <p>His more ambitious suggestions included expanding profit incentives for reducing greenhouse gas emissions. The mayor pointed to the agreement by 10 Northeastern states -- including New York -- to create a market-driven cap-and-trade system for power plants.</p>
        <p>''This type of system was controversial when it was created to reduce acid rain -- but it worked,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg, a Republican, also urged Congress to raise automobile fuel standards, something it is already considering.</p>
        <p>''In 1975, Congress passed a law requiring fuel efficiency standards to double over 10 years, with incremental targets that auto manufacturers were required to meet,'' he said. ''That was the responsible approach, and it worked. But since 1985, we've done nothing -- even as technology has moved at light speed.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bloomberg has often crossed paths with fellow Republicans on issues like abortion and gun control, he said governments that wants to be catalysts for private investment in clean energy could learn a lesson from President Bush, who as governor of Texas signed a law creating a market for wind energy.</p>
        <p>''Which has made Texas the largest producer of wind energy in the United States,'' Mr. Bloomberg said.</p>
        <p>The mayor said that across the country scientists and engineers are leading a slow-motion revolution to head what he called the twin catastrophes: the potential economic problems that come with a volatile and finite supply of oil and the intensifying environmental threats that could come with continued global warming.</p>
        <p>But he had sharp words for lawmakers for talking about goals for 2050 or 2070 instead of what can be done right now.</p>
        <p>''I've always thought seriously that legislators that make promises to achieve something in the far-off distant future, but refuse to take steps now that would allow us to begin the progress are really very hypocritical,'' he said. ''That's not leadership, it's not what this country needs. It's passing the buck! And I think, unfortunately, for Washington today, it's what we call politics as usual.''</p>
        <p>Whether he is on the presidential path or not, Mr. Bloomberg appeared to win fans here yesterday. He was invited to speak by the Greater Houston Partnership, an umbrella chamber of commerce group for the Houston metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>A former deputy energy secretary under President Bill Clinton, Mayor Bill White of Houston praised Mr. Bloomberg's energy proposals. But he stopped short of saying whether Mr. Bloomberg sounded like a potential presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>''What he really sounded like was somebody who was just shooting straight about energy policy,'' Mr. White said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
