<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fringe, Now Embraced By Main Street</title>
    <meta content="28towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/28/nyregion/28towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Fitness and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Alternative and Complementary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Yoga</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alternative and Complementary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Yoga</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Dutchess County (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Omega Institute</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EEDD1F3EF93BA15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fringe, Now Embraced By Main Street</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Fringe, Now Embraced by Main Street</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>RHINEBECK, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of the two founders of the Omega Institute for Holistic Studies, a sort of New Age Sorbonne in Dutchess County, Elizabeth Lesser seems more aware of the risks of being grist for a Christopher Guest mockumentary -- something like ''A Mighty Wind'' with yoga and meditation instead of folk music.</p>
        <p>''Allow me to speak in New Age-ese, if I may,'' she said of what she sees as an evolving feminist consciousness entering the mainstream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Rhinebeck, N.Y., founders of the Omega Institute for Holistic Studies say they have grown enormously from their days as old crunchy granola stereotypes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of the two founders of the Omega Institute for Holistic Studies, a sort of New Age Sorbonne in Dutchess County, Elizabeth Lesser seems more aware of the risks of being grist for a Christopher Guest mockumentary -- something like ''A Mighty Wind'' with yoga and meditation instead of folk music.</p>
        <p>''Allow me to speak in New Age-ese, if I may,'' she said of what she sees as an evolving feminist consciousness entering the mainstream.</p>
        <p>Harking back to the early days of what has become perhaps the most prominent New Age institution in the country, Ms. Lesser said: ''Well, there are the old crunchy granola stereotypes, and stereotypes aren't for naught. It's where we came from, but we've grown enormously from those days.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the journey does have a built-in mockumentary appeal: how two children of the '60s, Ms. Lesser and her husband at the time, Dr. Stephan Rechtschaffen, lived the commune life under the direction of a Sufi master at the New Lebanon Shaker Village upstate, and then decided to form their own institute. The couple, inspired by their Sufi teacher, Pir Vilayat Inayat Khan, founded the institute in 1977, and in 1980 opened a permanent home on land that had once housed the Sholem Aleichem Folk Institute's Camp Boiberick.</p>
        <p>Alas, the stereotypes end where reality begins. Instead, 30 years on, there's a pretty intriguing tale of cultural change to be found in a place that has gone on to help define the ever-shifting space where alternative and mainstream cultures intersect.</p>
        <p>So when Al Gore won his Oscar this week for ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' his film on climate change, the Omega people felt a tiny bit of reflected glow. First of all, Mr. Gore is to be a featured speaker at Omega's ''Being Fearless'' conference, which is expected to draw 2,000 people to the Sheraton New York Hotel from April 13 to 15 -- a bit more evidence of how blurry the line between mainstream and alternative has become. And when Mr. Gore was hailed for 30 years of working to get his message out, the lesson and time frame felt totally familiar.</p>
        <p>The institute, named for the Christian mystic philosopher Teilhard de Chardin's concept of an Omega point where all thought converges, is not exactly a household name, but that depends on your household. It provides classes for more than 25,000 people a year, at a 190-acre campus here and at other sites. There is a year-round staff of 65, and 150 to 200 more workers when the campus is operating from April through October. The annual budget is $16 million, and many of Omega's regular teachers, like Dr. Andrew Weil and Deepak Chopra, have become megacelebrities.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rechtschaffen, a physician, said change was most obvious in programs on health, where Omega was once way out in the renegade wilds of herbal medicine and alternative healing that are now part of standard medical care. To that, you could add the yoga centers on every corner and the New Age philosophers in every public television pledge drive.</p>
        <p>SOME of Omega's offerings -- Tibetan Sound Healing, say, or Tree Whispering From the Plant's Point of View -- are probably for a committed core. But the fringe has permeated the core. There are Zen-like approaches to tennis, basketball and building garden structures. Tango With the Buddha! Songwriting With Jimmie Dale Gilmore! Tabla Drumming! Sessions on energy, autism, cancer and sustainability, and a meditation retreat for war veterans and their families.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lesser said that even if much still had a fringe quality, a similar consciousness has insinuated its way into the mainstream. ''If you watch Oprah, every single person in our catalog goes on the Oprah show,'' she said. ''I'm always amazed at how much her language is our language, and how much her audience understands it. I really don't think we're as isolated from the regular culture as you would think.''</p>
        <p>Still, Omega's founders also recognize that, until now, more evolved individuals haven't done much to produce a more evolved planet. Dr. Rechtschaffen said the goal has always been to go from personal transformation to social and community transformation. Omega's plans call for a new Center for Sustainable Living, including a futuristic Eco-Machine, a natural filtration system that treats, conserves and recycles water using minimal energy.</p>
        <p>But as for concrete signs of a kinder, gentler, more sustainable planet -- well, those are hard to come by. Maybe that particular point is out there somewhere in Omega's next 30 years. Or maybe the real inconvenient truth is that for all the yoga, tai chi and body work that evolved individuals can do, we don't have that much time.</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
