<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Obama Scolds and Soothes Automakers</title>
    <meta content="08obama" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/08/us/politics/08obama.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Detroit (Mich)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obama, Barack (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maynard, Micheline</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5D71631F93BA35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Obama Scolds and Soothes Automakers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Obama Criticizes Automakers on Fuel Economy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELINE MAYNARD; Nick Bunkley contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maynard, Micheline</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, May 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Barack Obama, Democratic presidential hopeful, scolds Detroit auto makers for having done little to lessen nation's dependency on foreign oil; proposes incentives to help General Motors, Ford and Chrysler out of lingering slump; proposes 4-percent-a-year increase in fuel economy standards beginning in 2009, with standard for both cars and light trucks rising to 40 mph by 2022; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Barack Obama of Illinois delivered a stern message to Detroit auto companies on Monday, saying they had done little to lessen the nation's dependence on foreign oil and needed to improve the fuel efficiency of their vehicles.</p>
        <p>Sounding at times like a teacher scolding a lazy but promising student, Mr. Obama at the same time proposed incentives to help General Motors, Ford and Chrysler out of a lingering slump that has resulted in dozens of plant closings and the elimination of tens of thousands of jobs this decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The senator said the Japanese had done far better than Detroit companies to develop energy efficient vehicles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Barack Obama of Illinois delivered a stern message to Detroit auto companies on Monday, saying they had done little to lessen the nation's dependence on foreign oil and needed to improve the fuel efficiency of their vehicles.</p>
        <p>Sounding at times like a teacher scolding a lazy but promising student, Mr. Obama at the same time proposed incentives to help General Motors, Ford and Chrysler out of a lingering slump that has resulted in dozens of plant closings and the elimination of tens of thousands of jobs this decade.</p>
        <p>Appearing before a luncheon held by the Detroit Economic Club, Mr. Obama, a Democratic presidential candidate, received a standing ovation when he was introduced by Mayor Kwame M. Kilpatrick, and again at the close of his remarks, which were broadcast live by local television stations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama, making his first campaign visit to Michigan, said he wanted to be blunt with Detroit auto companies on their home turf.</p>
        <p>Chief executives of the auto companies were not in attendance.</p>
        <p>''I'm making this proposal here today because I don't believe in making proposals in California and giving a different speech in Michigan,'' he said. His goal ''is not to destroy the industry, but to help bring it into the 21st century,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Obama's plan, which he said would save 2.5 million barrels of oil a day, he proposed a 4 percent a year increase in fuel economy standards beginning in 2009, or the equivalent of about one mile per gallon per year.</p>
        <p>By 2022, the fuel economy standard for both cars and light trucks would be 40 miles per gallon, according to the plan. The Bush administration has proposed a similar method to raise the fuel economy standard over the next few years.</p>
        <p>The current federal standards are 27.5 miles per gallon for cars and 24 miles per gallon for light trucks.</p>
        <p>While the American standard for cars has not increased in the last 20 years, both China and Japan have higher standards, Mr. Obama said. He maintained that cars in Japan typically achieved the equivalent of 45 miles per gallon.</p>
        <p>In fact, the average fuel economy in 2006 for cars sold by all manufacturers in the United States was slightly more than 30 miles per gallon, higher than the federal standard requires. But automakers' overall fuel economy was 24.2 miles per gallon, because light trucks, including S.U.V.'s, pickups and minivans, account for slightly more than half the vehicles sold in the United States.</p>
        <p>The discussion over the standards accelerated last month, when the Supreme Court ruled that the Environmental Protection Agency had the ability to regulate carbon dioxide emissions. The primary way to do so, experts say, is by raising fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama also proposed that fuel efficiency standards for cars be rewritten so that mileage requirements are set according to vehicle size, rather than one sweeping standard for all sizes of cars.</p>
        <p>The current method benefits Japanese auto companies, whose lineups are not as varied as their Detroit rivals, said Mr. Obama, whose state is home to a Ford assembly plant, as well as one owned by the Japanese automaker Mitsubishi.</p>
        <p>The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration took a similar step this decade in recalculating the fuel economy standard for light trucks. Detroit auto companies have backed that as an option for recalculating fuel economy standards for cars.</p>
        <p>As a carrot to the industry, Mr. Obama would provide up to $3 billion to Detroit auto companies and their suppliers to retool factories to produce more fuel-efficient vehicles.</p>
        <p>If the companies invest in these vehicles, Mr. Obama also would offer the Detroit companies assistance in dealing with their burden of paying for current and retired workers' health care expenses, estimated at $1,500 per vehicle.</p>
        <p>But a spokesman for G.M., Greg Martin, said the automaker preferred to see a broader approach to soaring health care costs. ''Health care is an issue that should be a national priority and not an issue unique to G.M.,'' Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Obama's sometimes harsh words Monday, the diverse audience interrupted him 10 times for applause. ''I think it took a lot of courage to come to Detroit and lay it on the line,'' said Peter Eckstein, a retired labor union economist from Ann Arbor, Mich.</p>
        <p>Leonard Mungo, a Detroit lawyer, said he was surprised to hear specific proposals for addressing the industry's problems. ''He's saying, 'You got yourselves into this mess, but now this is how we get out,' '' Mr. Mungo said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
