<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Regulatory Clearance Seen as Slow but Sure</title>
    <meta content="27regulate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/27/business/27regulate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070303T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Txu Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texas Pacific Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carlyle Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
        <org class="online_producer">TXU Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EED91E3EF934A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Regulatory Clearance Seen as Slow but Sure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Regulatory Clearance Seen as Slow but Sure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS and MATTHEW R. WALD; Clifford Krauss reported from Houston and Matthew R. Wald from Washington.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford; Wald, Matthew</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Feb. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sale of TXU Corp to private investors, including Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co and Texas Pacific Group, faces months of state and federal regulatory hurdles, but experts predict broad support for deal from environmentalists and other important interest groups should help it clear them with ease; bigger question is whether newly formed company will be able to keep all its constituents--consumers and shareholders, growth-oriented politicians and environmentalists--as happy in year to come as they appear to be now; Blackstone Group and Carlyle Group, among others, are considering offers either on their own or with corporate partner; agreement is greeted by everyone from Texas officials to national environmentalists, who view it as model for other states and utilities as well as call to action for Congress to legislate against spread of traditional coal power and its role in contributing to global warming (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sale of the biggest utility in Texas to private investors faces months of state and federal regulatory hurdles, but experts predict that the broad support for the deal from environmentalists and other important interest groups should help it clear them with ease.</p>
        <p>A bigger question, some experts say, is whether the newly formed company will be able to keep all its constituents -- consumers and shareholders, growth-oriented politicians and environmentalists -- as happy in the years ahead as they appear to be now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOUSTON, Feb. 26  The sale of the biggest utility in Texas to private investors faces months of state and federal regulatory hurdles, but experts predict that the broad support for the deal from environmentalists and other important interest groups should help it clear them with ease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sale of the biggest utility in Texas to private investors faces months of state and federal regulatory hurdles, but experts predict that the broad support for the deal from environmentalists and other important interest groups should help it clear them with ease.</p>
        <p>A bigger question, some experts say, is whether the newly formed company will be able to keep all its constituents -- consumers and shareholders, growth-oriented politicians and environmentalists -- as happy in the years ahead as they appear to be now.</p>
        <p>In their announcement of the merger agreement on Monday, the TXU Corporation and the lead buyers, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company and the Texas Pacific Group, promised a 10 percent rate decrease for consumers while sustaining service to an increasingly energy-hungry Texas. Along with reducing the planned coal-fired plants to 3 from 11, the new owners also vowed to invest more in renewable energy, including solar and wind power.</p>
        <p>It remains possible, however, that rival suitors could emerge. The Blackstone Group and the Carlyle Group, among others, are considering offers either on their own or with a corporate partner. Other private equity firms have been consulting Wall Street banks.</p>
        <p>Monday's agreement was greeted with satisfaction by everyone from Texas officials to national environmentalists, who viewed it as a model for other states and utilities as well as a call to action for Congress to legislate against the spread of traditional coal power and its role in contributing to global warming.</p>
        <p>Peter Altman, the coal campaign director of the National Environmental Trust, was equally effusive. But ''as welcome as the TXU deal is,'' he warned , ''it is still a wake-up call for Congress that there are more than 100 coal plants on the drawing board.''</p>
        <p>The utility's promises of sustained service, more renewable energy and lower prices should go far in satisfying the Public Utility Commission of Texas, the regulatory body with the power to review purchases and mergers of electric utilities to ensure that they are in the public interest.</p>
        <p>''There is a general expectation,'' said Terry Hadley, a spokesman for the commission in Austin, ''that the new owner would provide at least, if not a better, level of service quality.'' Mr. Hadley said the commission would take ''however long it takes to be comfortable'' with the deal and pointed out that ''we can take measures to require a higher level of service'' if necessary.</p>
        <p>The current management of the company has come under criticism from consumer groups and politicians for being too quick to cut off electricity to late payers and not keeping public lighting in downtown Dallas adequately serviced.</p>
        <p>In Washington, the challenges are relatively minor because there are few antitrust issues in the company's going private.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission will have some jurisdiction since TXU runs a nuclear power plant. ''What we tend to look for is if the successor company has the financial reserves and financial and technical knowledge and know-how to operate a nuclear power plant,'' said David McIntyre, an N.R.C. spokesman.</p>
        <p>The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission has less jurisdiction in Texas than other states, but it will probably review the company's limited operations out of state.</p>
        <p>Barbara Struck, an analyst with the Energy Intelligence Group, a research firm, predicted that the deal would be approved by regulators ''because of the environmental conditions associated with it'' and the promises to cut consumer rates.</p>
        <p>Peter Hartley, an economist at Rice University, said the utility would have a hard time keeping its promises to everyone. ''How can you make more for all these groups from the same assets and the same management?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>In their statement Monday, the company and equity firms promised the decrease in rates until September 2008. The company did not reply to telephone requests for more information.</p>
        <p>Representatives of environmental groups predicted that the TXU deal would make it harder for other companies to build pulverized coal plants. Eric Cane, an analyst at Innovest Strategic Value Advisors, said the settlement would make companies like Dynegy and Xcel think twice about building more coal plants that do not include a plan to keep carbon dioxide from entering the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>What the deal shows, more than anything else, they said, was a growing expectation of carbon taxes in the future. ''The economics might be there right now for a utility to build a pulverized coal facility,'' Mr. Cane said, ''but you have to question that company's decision, if they're looking forward past the near future.''</p>
        <p>That is not the way some big coal producers see it, though. And they say they still have basic economics on their side. Until a significant cost is imposed on each ton of carbon pumped into the atmosphere, coal will stand out as the most cost-efficient way to supply new electricity and most regulators will have a hard time agreeing to impose more expensive alternatives on consumers.</p>
        <p>''If what has been proposed takes hold and TXU does not advance with the construction of new plants, it will likely enable'' other coal facilities to be built, said Vic Svec, a spokesman for Peabody Energy, a coal mining company that has moved into power generation.</p>
        <p>The power will still be needed and the type of plant TXU has proposed, he said, is the cleanest, least expensive proven technology to get it.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 3, 2007, Saturday  An article in Business Day on Tuesday about possible regulatory hurdles for the acquisition of the TXU Corporation by Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company and the Texas Pacific Group misspelled the surname of an analyst at Innovest Strategic Value Advisors who discussed the effect of the deal on TXU rivals. He is Eric Kane, not Cane.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 3, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Tuesday about possible regulatory hurdles for the acquisition of the TXU Corporation by Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company and the Texas Pacific Group misspelled the surname of an analyst at Innovest Strategic Value Advisors who discussed the effect of the deal on TXU rivals. He is Eric Kane, not Cane.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
