<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Familiar Faces In the Crowd, And Why They're Rare</title>
    <meta content="15meet" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/thecity/15meet.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK OBSERVED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Margolick, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EED7133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Familiar Faces In the Crowd, And Why They're Rare</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Familiar Faces in the Crowd, and Why They’re Rare</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MARGOLICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Margolick, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vanity Fair contributing editor David Margolick New York Observed essay on improbability of bumping into someone serendipitously on street in New York City, and why it happens more frequently during just a few weeks in spring and fall; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETHING weird happened to me the other day, at least something weird for New York. And then it happened again the very next day. I ran into someone I knew on the street.</p>
        <p>A statistician, I suppose, could do the math. Take the number of people you're acquainted with in the city and the number of people who live in the city, plug these numbers into some complicated algorithm, and you'll come up with the probabilities. Whatever the figure you arrive at, divide it by four, because, for whatever reason, it -- ''it'' being bumping into someone serendipitously on the street rather than seeing someone you know at a social event, restaurant or the like, where the cast of characters is surprisingly predictable -- doesn't happen nearly as often as you'd think it would.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Yorkers bump into people they know far less often than you’d think. This is one of the few times of year such encounters are likely to occur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETHING weird happened to me the other day, at least something weird for New York. And then it happened again the very next day. I ran into someone I knew on the street.</p>
        <p>A statistician, I suppose, could do the math. Take the number of people you're acquainted with in the city and the number of people who live in the city, plug these numbers into some complicated algorithm, and you'll come up with the probabilities. Whatever the figure you arrive at, divide it by four, because, for whatever reason, it -- ''it'' being bumping into someone serendipitously on the street rather than seeing someone you know at a social event, restaurant or the like, where the cast of characters is surprisingly predictable -- doesn't happen nearly as often as you'd think it would.</p>
        <p>So why would it happen now, and twice in two days? Simple. It's the season. It comes around, like the equinoxes, twice each year, and at roughly the same time. These happenstance meetings are the interpersonal equivalents of meteor showers. And, like meteor showers, they can be charted with precision on your calendar.</p>
        <p>First, lop off June, July and August, when much of New York is out of town. In fact, you can extend that period beyond Memorial Day and Labor Day, for ''summer'' now includes large chunks of May and September. If many New Yorkers are on the streets then, those streets are as likely to be in Bridgehampton or Rhinebeck as in Manhattan. Then strike all of winter, and a bit beyond. Despite global warming, from November through March, New Yorkers may be in town, but not on the town. So you'll rarely run into anyone familiar then.</p>
        <p>That leaves, effectively, only a few weeks in the spring and fall. In the spring, encounters are likeliest just about now, in these first warm days, when New Yorkers have been sprung from their winter captivity but have not yet fled. In the fall, it happens two or three weeks after Labor Day, when the last stragglers from the beach or mountains have returned and the kids are back in school. When that period coincides with the Jewish High Holy Days, the odds peak.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it's a blessing that such rendezvous are so rare, for New Yorkers generally aren't very good at them. We are the wariest pedestrians on earth. For all our self-proclaimed curiosity, our allegedly quenchless thirst for knowledge and insight and experience, we don't look at, smile at or even acknowledge those around us. In fact, we have an odd contempt for them.</p>
        <p>Part of it is a holdover from the bad old days of street crime, but it goes far beyond personal safety. Friendliness is so, well, Midwestern, a sure sign you're not sophisticated. All of the time in New York, you see people you should know. Had your SAT scores been a bit higher or lower, the person walking toward you could have been your best friend in college, but you'd rather look away than seem like a hick or a sucker. Maybe that's why street meetings are so rare; people we know may well be all around us, but we're too busy staring straight ahead to see them.</p>
        <p>New Yorkers also have more on our minds, or at least we think we do, than do people elsewhere. A shrink once told me that therapy sessions actually begin at a quarter to the hour, when patients, walking or riding the subway, begin mulling over what they want to spill. And this is how most ambulatory New Yorkers behave, whether in therapy or not. Even when we're not attached to iPods, we are perpetually preoccupied. It's the same look we affect while jogging or working out: grim, purposeful, completely given to a higher cause -- ourselves.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, in part, because our homes are so small, the streets are an extension of them. They are our inner sanctums. To people who don't live here, it's unimaginable: walking along clamorous boulevards -- or riding below them -- to ruminate. But that's what we do. It's why the thought of cellphones on subways is so disturbing: don't these Philistines proposing them know that subways are our place for quiet contemplation?</p>
        <p>IT'S also why any unexpected encounter in New York can seem an intrusion (and, to those of us always running late, a potentially perilous delay). What's more jarring than when, lost in thought on a New York street, you suddenly hear someone shouting your name? Fortunately, at least if your name is common, the person is usually calling someone else.</p>
        <p>And who is it who's suddenly saying hello? Here, too, New York is special. In less populated places, the people you run into are invariably people you could reasonably expect to see. But here, the person you meet could be anyone from any stage of your life: a former lover (either still embittered, which is bad, or blissed out with whomever he or she ended up with, which can be worse), or someone you never thanked properly or to whom you promised something you never delivered, or someone who, for some reason, can never remember your name (though, naturally, you've already greeted him with his).</p>
        <p>It might be someone you haven't seen for years, whose weight gain or hair loss is dismaying until you realize with a start how you must look to him. It could be someone you'd forgotten until that very moment, or for whom you've framed for decades the caustic comment you'd casually drop at such a moment, only to be reminded, tongue-tied, that things rarely come out precisely as planned. On the streets of nowhere else on the planet do there lurk so many folks who can make your heart race, or drop, or harden. Fortunately, some of the scarier candidates are out-of-towners here only on vacation -- when you're very likely to be away yourself.</p>
        <p>Depending on your mood, the New York encounter can be joyful or be enough to keep you indoors, even as the weather warms. But not to worry: the season is short, and becoming ever shorter. In a few weeks it will be over -- that is, until the next time it comes around.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK OBSERVED David Margolick, a contributing editor at Vanity Fair, is the author, most recently, of ''Beyond Glory: Joe Louis vs. Max Schmeling, and a World on the Brink.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Margolick, a contributing editor at Vanity Fair, is the author, most recently, of ''Beyond Glory: Joe Louis vs. Max Schmeling, and a World on the Brink.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
