<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Well-Meaning But Misguided Stock Screens</title>
    <meta content="07nocera" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/business/07nocera.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TALKING BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tiaa-Cref</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Well-Meaning But Misguided Stock Screens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Well-Meaning but Misguided Stock Screens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE NOCERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nocera, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a small, packed meeting room at the Manhattan headquarters of TIAA-CREF, an earnest man named James W. Keady rose to make a speech. TIAA-CREF, as you probably know, is a huge financial services firm, with more than $400 billion in assets. Mr. Keady, 35, a former college soccer player with a master's degree in theology, is the founder of a group called Educating for Justice, which consists, essentially, of himself and his wife. It has a budget of $80,000.</p>
        <p>TIAA-CREF's primary mission is to manage the retirement accounts for over three million academics, researchers, hospital workers and other members of the nonprofit universe. (The initials stand for Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association-College Retirement Equities Fund.) Educating for Justice's mission is narrower: Mr. Keady wants to bring the giant Nike Corporation to its knees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Socially responsible investing oversimplifies the world, creating the illusion that the world is black and white, when its real color is gray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a small, packed meeting room at the Manhattan headquarters of TIAA-CREF, an earnest man named James W. Keady rose to make a speech. TIAA-CREF, as you probably know, is a huge financial services firm, with more than $400 billion in assets. Mr. Keady, 35, a former college soccer player with a master's degree in theology, is the founder of a group called Educating for Justice, which consists, essentially, of himself and his wife. It has a budget of $80,000.</p>
        <p>TIAA-CREF's primary mission is to manage the retirement accounts for over three million academics, researchers, hospital workers and other members of the nonprofit universe. (The initials stand for Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association-College Retirement Equities Fund.) Educating for Justice's mission is narrower: Mr. Keady wants to bring the giant Nike Corporation to its knees.</p>
        <p>Or at least to force Nike to drastically improve the pay and working conditions of the thousands of people in developing countries who work in the factories that produce its footwear. In 1997, Mr. Keady was forced off the St. John's University soccer coaching staff because he objected so strenuously to a multimillion-dollar deal the school was negotiating with Nike. He has made Nike his life's work ever since, even living in Indonesia for a while to better understand the working conditions of the factory employees.</p>
        <p>''Nike executives feel certain that the wages earned by people producing Nike products are sufficient for meeting an individual's basic needs in the local towns where goods are produced,'' he said Tuesday at the TIAA-CREF mutual funds shareholder meeting, his eyes ablaze with passion. ''Unfortunately, based on Educating for Justice's ongoing research of the same, we are not as convinced.''</p>
        <p>Like many activists, Mr. Keady was making his complaint to TIAA-CREF largely because of the firm's reputation for a kind of genteel activism. It also supports what's called socially responsible investing: that is, investing in companies that have strong records in areas like the environment and human rights, and avoiding companies with poor records. In 1990, in response to complaints by some of its academic clients who wanted to avoid investing in mutual funds that held oil, tobacco, military and other ''bad'' stocks, TIAA-CREF began offering its first ''socially screened'' investment product.</p>
        <p>It currently has two; one of them, the CREF Social Choice Account, is the largest socially responsible investing vehicle in the country, with $9 billion in assets. And it clearly plans to do more. A few weeks ago, TIAA-CREF came out with an updated policy statement on corporate governance that stressed its desire to ''engage with companies on governance, environmental, social and performance issues.'' One of its executives, John Wilcox, does nothing but manage the firm's work in this area.</p>
        <p>Indeed, after the meeting, Mr. Wilcox approached Mr. Keady, and they huddled for about 10 minutes. Mr. Wilcox listened respectfully, and offered to meet with Mr. Keady for a longer discussion.</p>
        <p>But then I spoke to Mr. Wilcox, and discovered something that surprised me. Nike, which had been kicked out of TIAA-CREF's socially responsible funds back when it was first engulfed in controversy over the treatment of workers in overseas factories, was reinstated in the summer of 2005. Which means that TIAA-CREF had come to the view that Nike had earned the right to rejoin the ranks of socially responsible companies. But what, exactly, was that judgment based on?</p>
        <p>I should concede right here that I've always harbored some suspicion about socially responsible investing. The longstanding complaint from skeptics is that it forces investors to accept lower returns -- because lots of rising stocks are excluded -- for dubious social good. But performance isn't really the problem. A number of socially screened mutual funds have done just fine, and the benchmark Domini 400 index, which is made up entirely of companies viewed as socially responsible, has actually outperformed the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index over the course of its 16-year existence. Besides, most mainstream mutual fund managers don't consistently beat the market, so why should socially responsible fund managers be held to a higher standard?</p>
        <p>No, my problem is that socially responsible investing oversimplifies the world, and in so doing distorts reality. It allows investors to believe that their money is only being invested in ''good companies,'' and they take foolish comfort in that belief. Rare is the company, after all, that is either all good or all bad. To put it another way, socially responsible investing creates the illusion that the world is black and white, when its real color is gray.</p>
        <p>Take oil companies. It's fair to say that the socially responsible crowd has no use for energy companies. For years, the only oil company such funds would even consider was BP, because of its early warnings about global warming and its embrace of environmental values. But in 2005, a BP refinery in Texas had a major explosion, killing 15 workers and injuring more than 100 others. And last year, the company spilled oil in the North Slope of Alaska. The world woke up to the fact that BP had a pretty shoddy safety and maintenance record.</p>
        <p>At the other extreme is Exxon Mobil, a company many socially responsible investors detest, because of its longstanding (and recently abandoned) reluctance to embrace the global warming consensus. Yet Exxon has a terrific worker safety record, and it hasn't had a serious oil spill since the Exxon Valdez in 1989. So which is the ''real'' good company here? You can probably guess which way I'd vote.</p>
        <p>The Nike case offers, I think, an even better illustration of the underlying contradictions of socially responsible investing. It turns out that the reason TIAA-CREF put Nike's stock back in its socially responsible portfolio is that a company in Boston, KLD Research &amp; Analytics, had given Nike its seal of approval. KLD is a small firm that constructs socially responsible indexes, including the Domini 400. Its 40-member staff includes about two dozen researchers who supposedly dig into companies and decide which should be included in its indexes -- and which should be excluded. Its biggest index, the KLD Broad Market Social Index, uses the Russell 3000 as its universe, which it has whittled down to 2,050 companies it deems acceptable.</p>
        <p>TIAA-CREF is a client of KLD. That means that in addition to licensing the KLD Broad Market Social Index and KLD's research products, the larger firm accepts KLD as its ultimate arbiter of which companies are socially responsible. Indeed, the prospectus for TIAA-CREF's socially responsible equity fund specifically states that its criteria for choosing companies are based on the KLD broad market index.</p>
        <p>Thus, last year, when KLD decided to toss Coca-Cola out of its indexes -- for reasons including ''controversies over how they market the product to schools,'' according to Eric Fernald, KLD's research director -- TIAA-CREF automatically followed suit. (I should point out that this applies only to TIAA-CREF's socially responsible funds, not its other investment products.) Although not every one of its clients accepts KLD's word as gospel, the firm's screening methodology is widely accepted among socially responsible fund managers, and it consequently has a great deal of sway.</p>
        <p>I spent a lot of time this week talking to people at KLD, including its co-founder and president, Peter Kinder. They are smart and likeable, and their heart is in the right place. But I came away thinking that that sway was undeserved.</p>
        <p>Consider, first, the size of the place. Two dozen researchers are monitoring 3,000 companies -- and writing in-depth reports? How is that even possible? It's not. Mr. Kinder told me that the employees almost never go abroad to do on-site inspections, but rely on media reports, blogs, interactions with activist organizations and conversations with the company itself. That hardly seems like enough to make a decision on whether a company is good or bad.</p>
        <p>Then there's the question of how KLD goes about reaching its conclusions. Nike's relationship with its manufacturers abroad was first brought to light by activists in the 1990s, who wanted to find a big brand that captured people's attention. As the largest seller of athletic shoes in the world, Nike was the obvious target. But Nike was using the same factories as Reebok and other shoe manufacturers, including Timberland, a darling of the socially responsible crowd. While Reebok and Timberland stayed, only Nike was ousted from the KLD index.</p>
        <p>When I asked Mr. Fernald to explain why Nike was bad, but Reebok was good, he said, ''We wrestled with that at the time.'' Reebok, he said, had taken some positive steps, but more than that: ''Nike was the market leader. And there is an extra burden for the market leader.'' In other words, Nike was being punished because it had beaten its competitors in the marketplace, not because its practices were any worse than anyone else in the industry.</p>
        <p>Today, a decade later, there is no doubt that Nike has done a lot to change its ways. It monitors its supply chain rigorously. It publishes data on its Web site. It has become a company deeply invested in corporate social responsibility, with 97 employees working solely on that division. Hannah Jones, who leads Nike's efforts, told me that corporate responsibility was now embedded in the fabric of the company.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones also said that the company has come a long way in helping those factory workers. And virtually everyone I spoke to, with the exception of Mr. Keady, agreed.</p>
        <p>But it is also true that for most of those workers, pay is still low, conditions are still less than ideal and change is slow in coming, something Nike is pretty forthright in conceding. There are still lots of problems at the factories that make Nike sneakers.</p>
        <p>Yet Nike is now back in KLD's good graces. Which is fine. But when I read a recent KLD report about Nike I had no sense that the firm had any deep knowledge of what is actually going on in those factories and how much of it is Nike's responsibility. Mostly, it was compiled from news clips and the like, much of which was from 2004 or even earlier.</p>
        <p>''To throw them out was a questionable decision,'' said Dara O'Rourke, an associate professor at the University of California, Berkeley, who has closely studied Nike's overseas outsourcing. ''And to put them back in was equally questionable.'' In his opinion, both decisions were based more on public perception than reality.</p>
        <p>Surely, he's right. It would be nice if we could invest our money only in companies that had terrific human rights record, fabulous environmental values and wonderful compassionate cultures.</p>
        <p>Too bad it's impossible.</p>
        <p>TALKING BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
