<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pipe Dreams</title>
    <meta content="18CImatthiessen" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/18/opinion/nyregionopinions/18CImatthiessen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1833896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York Harbor</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matthiessen, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willner, Andy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Backer, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Baykeeper</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hudson Riverkeeper</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Department of Environmental Protection</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Riverkeeper</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DA1F31F93BA25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pipe Dreams</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pipe Dreams</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Matthiessen, Andy Willner and Terry Backer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Matthiessen, Alex; Willner, Andy; Backer, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Hudson Riverkeeper Alex Matthiessen, New York-New Jersey Baykeeper Andy Willner and Long Island Soundkeeper Terry Backer supports capture and diversion of much of New York City's rainfall before it enters sewer system rather than end-of-pipe systems that have failed in past; calls on Mayor Michael Bloomberg to stick to his original vision of swimmable and fishable New York Harbor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MICHAEL BLOOMBERG deserves a lot of credit for his ambitious plans to make New York a sustainable city by 2030. With an initiative that he outlined last December, Mayor Bloomberg is anticipating the city's expansion and making tough decisions in order to meet the challenges.</p>
        <p>But of the mayor's 10 goals, his least ambitious is his plan to make New York Harbor safe for recreation. While he originally said that recreation included swimming and fishing, it's clear from conversations our staff had last week with his Office of Long-Term Planning and Sustainability that he is retreating from that goal and that recreation now means only boating. But boating in the harbor doesn't require improving water quality. Striving for a fishable and swimmable harbor, on the other hand, would be a far more meaningful goal, and one that every New Yorker could benefit from.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a clean harbor, keep rainwater from becoming sewage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MICHAEL BLOOMBERG deserves a lot of credit for his ambitious plans to make New York a sustainable city by 2030. With an initiative that he outlined last December, Mayor Bloomberg is anticipating the city's expansion and making tough decisions in order to meet the challenges.</p>
        <p>But of the mayor's 10 goals, his least ambitious is his plan to make New York Harbor safe for recreation. While he originally said that recreation included swimming and fishing, it's clear from conversations our staff had last week with his Office of Long-Term Planning and Sustainability that he is retreating from that goal and that recreation now means only boating. But boating in the harbor doesn't require improving water quality. Striving for a fishable and swimmable harbor, on the other hand, would be a far more meaningful goal, and one that every New Yorker could benefit from.</p>
        <p>Although water quality in New York Harbor has improved during the last few decades, most areas are still too hazardous to swim in, especially after it rains. The culprit? The city's outmoded sewer system, which combines sewage from buildings with dirty runoff from streets. When it rains even a little, the combined flow overwhelms the city's 14 sewage treatment plants. Raw sewage and runoff are then diverted into the harbor at more than 460 locations, amounting to over 27 billion gallons of combined sewage overflows each year.</p>
        <p>The city's Department of Environmental Protection regards the roughly 236 billion gallons of rainwater that fall on the five boroughs each year as waste that has to be disposed of rather than as a valuable resource that could be put to beneficial use before it picks up oil, grease, salt, solvents and other contaminants from city streets. As a consequence, the city has spent billions of taxpayer dollars, largely on massive concrete holding tanks and other ''end-of-pipe'' solutions, unsuccessfully trying to manage and treat huge volumes of storm water.</p>
        <p>In June, the department must submit to state regulators its long-term proposal for controlling discharges from combined sewage overflows. Regrettably, the department plans to spend more than $2.1 billion on more of the same end-of-pipe systems that have failed in the past. According to the department's own analysis, in 20 years the city expects to have to lower water quality standards in order to come into compliance. This is bad public policy, and no New Yorker should condone it.</p>
        <p>A more sustainable approach would be to capture much of the city's rainfall before it enters the sewer system and divert it to other uses. This captured water could be directed toward planted medians and sidewalk parks, street trees, permeable pavement, city parks, rain barrels and green roofs, as well as into storage tanks for commercial and residential use.</p>
        <p>Diverting the water in this way would do more than just help restore the city's polluted waterways. More vegetation means more shade, which means cooler streets and homes and lower energy bills for residential and business customers. A greener city would help offset the predicted two- to three-degree rise in average temperature from climate change. More trees -- and less energy consumption -- also mean reduced greenhouse gas emissions, cleaner air and less reliance on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, the United States Environmental Protection Agency acknowledged that diverting storm water to greenery often is more effective at reducing combined sewage overflows than end-of-pipe technologies. A recent study by Riverkeeper shows that a $1,000 investment in end-of-pipe solutions decreases these overflows by about 2,400 gallons. In contrast, $1,000 invested in a ''storm water source control'' like vegetated street medians or sidewalk parks reduces these overflows by 14,800 gallons or more.</p>
        <p>In the coming weeks, the mayor will roll out specific proposals for how to make the city more sustainable by 2030. The state should not accept the Department of Environmental Protection's plan until it includes a major commitment to storm water source controls.</p>
        <p>And Mayor Bloomberg should stick to his original vision of a swimmable and fishable New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Alex Matthiessen, the Hudson Riverkeeper; Andy Willner, the New York-New Jersey Baykeeper; and Terry Backer, the Long Island Soundkeeper; are founders of the Waterkeeper Alliance, a global network of 160 waterkeepers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alex Matthiessen, the Hudson Riverkeeper; Andy Willner, the New York-New Jersey Baykeeper; and Terry Backer, the Long Island Soundkeeper; are founders of the Waterkeeper Alliance, a global network of 160 waterkeepers.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
