<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Politics of Prose</title>
    <meta content="22kaku" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/22kaku.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huckabee, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obama, Barack (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDE1E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="3622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Politics of Prose</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Politics of Prose</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani article discusses what, if anything, books by 2008 Presidential contenders tell us about them; books by Hillary Clinton, John Edwards, Rudolph Giiuliani, Mike Huckabee, John McCain, Barack Obama, Bill Richardson, Mitt Romney and Al Gore discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BARACK OBAMA wrote ''very bad poetry'' in college. John McCain once contemplated joining the French Foreign Legion. John Edwards wanted to become a lawyer so he could defend the likes of the wrongfully accused Dr. Richard Kimble on ''The Fugitive.'' Rudolph W. Giuliani found the boxing skills his father taught him useful as a young Yankee fan, growing up blocks from the Dodgers' stadium in Brooklyn. Hillary Rodham Clinton was a Brownie, a Girl Scout and a Paul McCartney girl, and wanted to grow up to be a teacher or nuclear physicist.</p>
        <p>These are the sorts of personal tidbits a reader can find in books by these presidential candidates, along with lots of policy recommendations, boasts, platitudes, spin, the occasional mea culpa and yards and yards of self-promotion. Most books by politicians are, at bottom, acts of salesmanship: efforts to persuade, beguile or impress the reader, efforts to rationalize past misdeeds and inoculate the author against future accusations. And yet beneath the sales pitch are clues -- in the author's voice, use of language, stylistic tics and self-presentation -- that provide some genuine glimpses of the personalities behind the public personas. In short, when candidates decide to publish, they can still run, but they can't hide -- at least not entirely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What, if anything, do presidential contenders’ books tell us about them?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BARACK OBAMA wrote ''very bad poetry'' in college. John McCain once contemplated joining the French Foreign Legion. John Edwards wanted to become a lawyer so he could defend the likes of the wrongfully accused Dr. Richard Kimble on ''The Fugitive.'' Rudolph W. Giuliani found the boxing skills his father taught him useful as a young Yankee fan, growing up blocks from the Dodgers' stadium in Brooklyn. Hillary Rodham Clinton was a Brownie, a Girl Scout and a Paul McCartney girl, and wanted to grow up to be a teacher or nuclear physicist.</p>
        <p>These are the sorts of personal tidbits a reader can find in books by these presidential candidates, along with lots of policy recommendations, boasts, platitudes, spin, the occasional mea culpa and yards and yards of self-promotion. Most books by politicians are, at bottom, acts of salesmanship: efforts to persuade, beguile or impress the reader, efforts to rationalize past misdeeds and inoculate the author against future accusations. And yet beneath the sales pitch are clues -- in the author's voice, use of language, stylistic tics and self-presentation -- that provide some genuine glimpses of the personalities behind the public personas. In short, when candidates decide to publish, they can still run, but they can't hide -- at least not entirely.</p>
        <p>At the same time these candidates' books remind us that the ability to construct a powerful narrative is an essential skill for a politician, for it confers the ability to articulate a coherent vision of the world, to make sense of history and to define the author -- before he or she is defined by opponents and the news media. All the leading candidates in the 2008 race for president have published (often with the help of a professional writer or editor) at least one book, and most of the would-be candidates waiting in the wings -- from Al Gore to Fred Thompson to Newt Gingrich -- are published authors as well.</p>
        <p>Given their self-portraits in these books, who would these authors be if they weren't candidates for president of the United States, but candidates, say, for president of the student council? Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York and former Vice President Al Gore both emerge as A-student types, conscientious geeks, eager to prove themselves and acutely aware of what other people think. Former Senator John Edwards presents himself as the good Samaritan who wanted to become a defense lawyer from the time he was 11, so he could ''protect innocent people from blind justice.'' Senator Barack Obama of Illinois is the former rebel, who used to hang out with friends who smoked and wore leather jackets and stayed up late discussing ''neocolonialism, Franz Fanon, Eurocentrism and patriarchy.'' Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico is the jock and former frat boy, who, like George W. Bush, loves to dispense silly nicknames.</p>
        <p>Mitt Romney, the former governor of Massachusetts, is the self-assured business maven, fond of PowerPoint presentations and terms like ''strategic audits'' and ''wow moments.'' Rudy Giuliani, the former mayor of New York, comes across as one of those hall-monitor types, looking for bullies to take on and using lots of sports metaphors to make points about teamwork and leadership. And Senator John McCain of Arizona is the hell-raiser who hides an introspective bent behind his pose as a cocky flyboy.</p>
        <p>These candidates' choice of book genre in itself says something about their view of the world. Mr. Giuliani, Mr. Romney and Mr. Richardson, for instance, have all published odd hybrid volumes that are part memoir, part self-help book, offering advice on matters like leadership and the arts of negotiation and diplomacy. In addition the former Arkansas governor Mike Huckabee has written two 12-step-program books: one on how to ''end bad habits and begin a healthy lifestyle'' and one on how to restore ''America's greatness.''</p>
        <p>This book genre projects decisiveness, if not certainty. It depicts the author as an expert eager to dispense wisdom to the huddled masses and serves up lots of pep-talk admonitions and how-to recommendations. Mr. Romney on building a turnaround strategy for a business or political enterprise: ''Focus, focus, focus.'' Mr. Richardson on how to work a room: ''When you move around the room, don't head right for the center. If you do, you're liable to become surrounded and trapped. You should move counterclockwise beginning close to the wall.''</p>
        <p>Although George W. Bush, who was initially hailed as the ''M.B.A. president,'' turned out to be far more ideological and far less competent than this moniker might suggest, the managerial model for presidential candidates remains a popular one. The books by Mr. Richardson, Mr. Romney and Mr. Giuliani not only emphasize process over policy but also promote the proposition that government can be run like a business, that problem-solving and managerial efficiency -- rather than specific stands on issues -- are the keys to leadership.</p>
        <p>Bragging is a fundamental part of these books, helping to establish the authors' credentials to dispense advice. Mr. Romney's ''Turnaround'' touts his successful stewardship of the 2002 Olympics; Mr. Giuliani's ''Leadership'' dwells on his successful efforts to cut crime in New York City and his 9/11 heroics; Mr. Richardson's ''Between Worlds'' is filled with boasts, from his description of a 1995 negotiation session with Saddam Hussein as ''a typical adventure for me in more than 30 years of public service'' to his assertion that he ''shattered Theodore Roosevelt's long-standing record for handshaking and made it into the 'Guinness Book of World Records.' ''</p>
        <p>Both the serious policy book, which demonstrates expertise in a particular area (like Mr. Gore's two diligently researched books on the environment), and the high-decibel, openly partisan book (like Mr. Gingrich's 2005 ''Winning the Future,'' a kind of updated version of the Republicans' Contract With America) appear to be less in vogue these days. The full-scale autobiography, however, remains a perennial favorite of political candidates as a way to showcase a dramatic life story and highlight one's survival skills: in the case of Mr. McCain, surviving more than five years as a prisoner of war in Vietnam; in the case of Mrs. Clinton, surviving the eight-year roller-coaster ride of her husband's presidency.</p>
        <p>The arc of the political autobiography is usually that of a classic bildungsroman, gussied up with some political lessons: the callow (or rowdy or rebellious) young author goes to war (or suffers an identity crisis or private loss); slays a personal dragon (be it a political opponent or Kenneth Starr or the press); and somehow emerges from the labyrinth, older and wiser and more committed than ever to public service.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, books written years apart often display telling shifts in voice and inflection. While Mrs. Clinton's 1996 book, ''It Takes a Village,'' is animated by an earnest, do-gooding tone -- what the reporter Michael Kelly once called her ''Saint Hillary'' mode -- her 2003 memoir, ''Living History,'' written in the wake of her husband's impeachment and the couple's travails over Whitewater and Monica Lewinsky, has a far more self-conscious, defensive feel to it, as she parries accusations and insinuations and describes herself as a ''lightning rod for political and ideological battles,'' a ''magnet for feelings, good and bad, about women's choices and roles.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's tendency to mix up wonky policy asides with New Agey pronouncements, curiously, is shared by Mr. Gore's 1992 book, ''Earth in the Balance.'' In ''An Inconvenient Truth'' (the best-selling companion to his Academy Award-winning movie about global warming), which was written after he failed to capture the White House in 2000, Mr. Gore seems to have tamed his fascination with policy minutiae and found a new tone that's informative and educational without being condescending.</p>
        <p>It's the books written before the author decided to enter the political fray or after he decided to leave that feel the most earnest, the most authentic, the most genuinely compelling. Mr. Obama wrote ''Dreams From My Father'' in the early 1990s, before he ran for office, and while the book takes certain poetic license --''For the sake of compression,'' he writes, ''some of the characters that appear are composites of people I've known, and some events appear out of precise chronology'' -- it possesses the clarity, openness and ruminative sensibility of a literary memoir. His 2006 book, ''The Audacity of Hope,'' is an altogether more conventional work, filled with the cautious, consensus-building observations of a sitting senator and presidential hopeful.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. McCain's ''Worth the Fighting For'' (which was written after he lost the 2000 Republican nomination to Mr. Bush, and at a point when he said he doubted he would ''have reason or opportunity to try again'' for the White House), it reads like the freewheeling work of a man who revels in his independence, his personal idiosyncrasies and his self-styled role as a maverick -- a far cry from the more establishmentarian role he has assumed in the current race for president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama, Mrs. Clinton, Mr. Giuliani, Mr. Edwards and Mr. Romney all trained as lawyers and are adept at using their analytic skills to lay out an argument. Yet they take very different narrative tacks in their books. In ''Leadership,'' Mr. Giuliani dispenses management advice with the grinding, no-nonsense style of the prosecutor he once was. He writes about the importance, as a trial lawyer, of ''being able to communicate, being able to explain, being able to simplify.'' He notes that his basic campaign style is ''to wear down my opponent,'' talks about honing his ''ability to compartmentalize'' and acknowledges that his ''organizational style was to be on top of as much as possible.'' His writing style is prescriptive and proscriptive -- lots of advice about what to do and not do: ''Reflect, Then Decide,'' ''Underpromise and Overdeliver,'' ''Be Your Own Man.'' Some of this advice, like ''Surround Yourself With Great People,'' now has a bizarrely ironic ring, given recent revelations that Bernard B. Kerik (Mr. Giuliani's former police commissioner, whom he promoted as a candidate for homeland security secretary) had a relationship with a company suspected of having ties to organized crime.</p>
        <p>Though far less hectoring in tone than Mr. Giuliani, Mrs. Clinton also takes a decidedly linear approach in her books. ''It Takes a Village'' methodically intercuts personal reminiscences about being a mother with lots of research about childhood development and child health care. The proverbial overachiever, she notes that when she is stressed or upset -- whether over impeachment proceedings or her daughter's departure for college -- she goes into overdrive, throwing herself into work so there is little time for brooding.</p>
        <p>''I am not the sort of person who routinely pours out her deepest feelings, even to my closest friends,'' she writes. ''My mother is the same way. We have a tendency to keep our own counsel and that trait only deepened when I began living my life in the public eye.''</p>
        <p>In ''Living History'' this temperamental inclination is used by Mrs. Clinton to skirt uncomfortable questions about her marriage and the impeachment proceedings against her husband, while opening her to accusations from critics that she is calculating and guarded. Her books all employ the careful, deliberate language of someone trained as a lawyer, and they attest to an emotionally reticent outlook, ratifying the dynamic between Mrs. Clinton and her husband that has been noted by many reporters and administration insiders: that she is the organized, disciplined one, while he is the indecisive, forgiving one; that she is the analytic strategist, while he is the voluble retail politician.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards's narrative approach in ''Four Trials'' is very much that of the former trial lawyer, and like so many of his stump speeches, it shows off the polished storytelling skills he honed for many years in front of juries. With the exception of one affecting section dealing with the death of his teenage son in a car accident, the book focuses on his handling of personal injury cases, like that of a 5-year-old girl whose family was awarded $25 million after a defective swimming pool drain sucked out part of her intestines.</p>
        <p>These accounts read like the episodes of ''Perry Mason'' Mr. Edwards admired as a child and demonstrate his gift for dramatizing the plight of his clients. They also attempt to turn his liabilities as a candidate -- opponents have depicted him as a slick trial lawyer who got rich winning multimillion-dollar verdicts from hospitals, doctors, insurance companies and corporations -- into an asset, by depicting him as an advocate for the poor and disenfranchised, as a populist defender of the common man.</p>
        <p>Contemporary America doesn't have a lot of writers turned politicians like Vaclav Havel or politician-writer-historian hyphenates like Churchill, and few politicians since Robert F. Kennedy -- who used to cite Aeschylus and Emerson and Camus -- have managed to mix literary allusions with political charisma. But both Mr. Obama and Mr. McCain are in the habit of looking to books for insights into their own lives, and both have written books with a certain literary flair that reflect their love of reading. Mr. Obama writes about studying Baldwin, Ellison, Hughes, Wright and DuBois as a teenager in search of clues to his own identity, while Mr. McCain writes that Hemingway's doomed hero Robert Jordan, who dies fighting the fascists in ''For Whom the Bell Tolls,'' was for many years ''the man I admired above almost all others in life and fiction.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's instinctive storytelling talents seem to have been sharpened during his years as a prisoner of war. In solitary confinement, he writes, he ''reconstructed from memory books and movies'' he had once enjoyed and ''tried to compose books and plays of my own, often acting out sequences in the quiet solitude of my cell.'' Later, when he joined other United States P.O.W.'s in captivity, he was appointed ''entertainment officer,'' regaling his comrades with stories from more than a hundred movies, including ''Stalag 17'' and ''One-Eyed Jacks.''</p>
        <p>The limber, seemingly artless style of ''Worth the Fighting For'' and ''Dreams From My Father'' also mirrors the authors' campaign style. In contrast to Mr. Giuliani and Mrs. Clinton, who try to control their messages by withholding and steering the conversation, Mr. McCain and Mr. Obama have tried to shape the debate by presenting themselves as straight talkers who want to give voters access to their thought processes, their mindsets, their internal debates.</p>
        <p>In contrast to Mr. Romney and Mr. Gingrich, who have written books depicting themselves as authority figures with special know-how or ideas, Mr. Obama and Mr. McCain do not seem to want to strong-arm the reader into admiring their acumen or leadership skills. Rather, they seem eager to try to make the reader identify with their personal struggles and ideals and put trust in their overall character and judgment. And so, it seems, most of the candidates in the '08 race fall into two categories as authors: those who rely on teacherly claims of expertise to make their case, and who have written carefully controlled narratives meant to showcase their strengths; and those who place more emphasis on character and charm, and who have written more free-form narratives meant to showcase their candor and complexity.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. McCain and Mr. Obama describe themselves in their books as restless people who went through periods of serious adolescent rebellion. (Mr. Obama even talks about a time when he used pot, booze and ''maybe a little blow'' to ''push questions of who I was out of my mind.'')</p>
        <p>Both write at length about the compromises and temptations of big-time politics. And both devote considerable space to pondering existential questions about identity, honor, duty and self-doubt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama, often praised by supporters for his authenticity, writes that as a young man worried about his ''racial credentials'' he chose his friends carefully: ''The more politically active black students. The foreign students. The Chicanos. The Marxist professors and structural feminists and punk-rock performance poets.''</p>
        <p>He also writes that ''one of those tricks'' he learned in dealing with his mother and others worried about his teenage alienation was that ''people were satisfied so long as you were courteous and smiled and made no sudden moves. They were more than satisfied; they were relieved -- such a pleasant surprise to find a well-mannered young black man who didn't seem angry all the time.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. McCain's case he admits to craving ''renown and influence for their own sake.'' He observes that as a young child he developed such an ''outsized temper'' that his parents took to plunging him into a bathtub of cold water whenever he started a tantrum. He talks about trying to commit suicide while in prison in Vietnam. And he berates himself for saying during the 2000 presidential campaign in South Carolina that he saw the Confederate flag ''as a symbol of heritage,'' when he really felt that ''the flag should be lowered forever from the staff atop South Carolina's capitol.''</p>
        <p>Following in the footsteps of his father and grandfather, who were both four-star admirals in the Navy, Mr. McCain says he recognized his eventual enrollment in the United States Naval Academy as ''an immutable fact of life.'' Though he ''hated every minute'' of his first year there, he says, he was determined to win his father's respect; and that same desire for paternal recognition and a sense of ''the family creed'' would propel him to Vietnam in hopes of winning ''a creditable combat record.''</p>
        <p>''My father could often be a distant, inscrutable patriarch,'' Mr. McCain writes in ''Faith of My Fathers.'' ''But I always had a sense that he was special, a man who had set his mind to accomplishing great things, and had ransomed his life to the task. I admired him, and wanted badly to be admired by him, yet indications of his regard for me were more often found in the things he didn't say than in the things he did.''</p>
        <p>A similar longing for paternal approval surfaces in many of the candidates' books. Mr. Obama's ''Dreams From My Father'' is essentially a Telemachus-like quest to come to terms with his dad, who left home when the author was 2. Over the years the absent father -- a brilliant scholar ''full of high-blown ideals,'' in his mother's telling, who had left to pursue a doctorate at Harvard and return home to Kenya to help ''forge a new, modern Africa'' -- grew to mythic proportions in his son's mind, ''inspiring, rebuking, granting or withholding approval.''</p>
        <p>''It was into my father's image, the black man, son of Africa,'' Mr. Obama writes, ''that I'd packed all the attributes I sought in myself, the attributes of Martin and Malcolm, DuBois and Mandela.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Obama traveled to Africa in the wake of his father's death and met his extended family, the realization that his father was not this larger-than-life hero but a lonely and disappointed bureaucrat had a liberating effect: ''The king is overthrown, I thought. The emerald curtain is pulled aside. The rabble of my head is free to run riot; I can do what I damn well please. For what man, if not my own father, has the power to tell me otherwise? Whatever I do, it seems, I won't do much worse than he did.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson describes his father as a stern, demanding and withholding figure, who gave him reading assignments he would be quizzed about over meals. Mr. Giuliani recalls that his father impressed on him the duty of public service, and that for the first 18 years of his life he ''had two main vocations in mind -- medicine or the priesthood.'' And Mrs. Clinton writes in ''It Takes a Village'' that when she brought home straight A's from junior high, ''my father's only comment was, 'Well, Hillary, that must be an easy school you go to.' '' ''By raising the bar,'' she goes on, ''he encouraged me to study even harder, and in fact, comments like that spurred me on.''</p>
        <p>What else do these books tell us about their authors? That Mr. Edwards, Mr. McCain and Mr. Huckabee all say they are optimists by nature, while Mrs. Clinton notes that she is ''the designated worrier'' in her family. That Mrs. Clinton and Mr. Richardson grew up loving Mickey Mantle, while Mr. McCain idolized Ted Williams. That Mr. Giuliani is such an ardent researcher that he even studies up on hobbies like golf and cigar smoking by reading books on the subjects. That Mr. Romney says his wife, Ann, was probably right when she observed that ''he loves emergencies and catastrophes.'' That Mr. Richardson, growing up in Mexico, ''could speak English'' but ''thought and dreamt in Spanish.'' And that Mr. McCain's favorite movie is ''Viva Zapata!,'' the Marlon Brando biopic about the Mexican revolutionary -- a movie Mr. McCain describes as celebrating ''the heroism of one man,'' while acknowledging the futility of ''expecting one person to save us all from iniquity.''</p>
        <p>Reading List 2008</p>
        <p>Here are the books discussed in this article:</p>
        <p>HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON ''Living History'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 2003), ''It Takes a Village'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 1996).</p>
        <p>JOHN EDWARDS ''Four Trials'' (with John Auchard, Simon &amp; Schuster, 2003).</p>
        <p>RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI ''Leadership'' (with Ken Kurson, Talk Miramax Books, 2002).</p>
        <p>AL GORE ''An Inconvenient Truth'' (Rodale, 2006), ''Earth in the Balance''(Houghton Mifflin, 1992).</p>
        <p>MIKE HUCKABEE ''From Hope to Higher Ground'' (Center Street, 2007) , ''Quit Digging Your Grave With a Knife and Fork'' (Center Street, 2005).</p>
        <p>JOHN McCAIN ''Character Is Destiny'' (with Mark Salter, Random House, 2005), ''Worth the Fighting For'' (with Mark Salter, Random House, 2002), ''Faith of My Fathers'' (with Mark Salter, Random House, 1999).</p>
        <p>BARACK OBAMA ''The Audacity of Hope''(Crown, 2006), ''Dreams From My Father'' (Times Books/Random House, 1995).</p>
        <p>BILL RICHARDSON ''Between Worlds''(with Michael Ruby, G. P. Putnam's Sons, 2005).</p>
        <p>MITT ROMNEY ''Turnaround''(with Timothy Robinson, Regnery, 2004).</p>
        <p>BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
