<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="24biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A $1.7 BILLION ANNUAL PAYDAY -- A leading hedge fund manager, James Simons, earned more than $1.7 billion last year. Are he and his fellow hedge fund managers this generation's robber barons, using wealth to create wealth, or are they new-economy financiers providing liquidity to the markets? [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>BARCLAYS TO BUY ABN AMRO -- The biggest Dutch bank, ABN Amro, has agreed to be bought by Barclays of Britain for 67 billion euros (nearly $91 billion). The deal creates one of the world's biggest banks, but a new suitor could still swoop in with a higher bid and split up the bank. [C1.]</p>
        <p>ASTRAZENECA TO BUY MEDIMMUNE -- AstraZeneca has agreed to acquire MedImmune for $15.6 billion in a clear sign that big drug makers are making a push into biotechnology. The all-cash deal for MedImmune, worth $58 a share, may be the largest purchase ever of an American biotechnology company. [C3.]</p>
        <p>FACING SHAREHOLDERS AT THE TIMES -- The Ochs/Sulzberger family, which controls The New York Times Company, is bracing for a contentious meeting with shareholders today; up to 50 percent of them could withhold votes for the election of directors to express their frustration with the company's dual-ownership structure and performance. [C1.]</p>
        <p>ROOMS FOR EVERYONE -- Las Vegas is in the middle of yet another hotel building boom and there is no end in sight. Occupancy rates hover at about 90 percent -- higher on the weekends. [C1.]</p>
        <p>S.E.C. SUIT AT APPLE -- Apple Inc.'s former general counsel and its former chief financial officer expect to be sued this week by the Securities and Exchange Commission as part of a federal investigation into the company's backdating of employee stock options. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CHINA YIELDS TO INQUIRY -- China has relented and will allow American regulators inside the country to investigate whether Chinese suppliers exported contaminated pet food ingredients to the United States earlier this year, resulting in one of the largest pet food recalls ever. [C1.]</p>
        <p>AN UNEXPECTED ADMISSION -- The Ford Motor Company's chief executive, Alan R. Mulally has said he believes in global warming. [C3.]</p>
        <p>NEW SOURCE OF ETHANOL? -- A New Zealand company says it has secured financing from a Silicon Valley investor to produce ethanol from an untapped source -- carbon monoxide gas. [C3.]</p>
        <p>NEW BID FOR AFFLIATED COMPUTER -- Two partners making an unsolicited bid for the technology services company Affiliated Computer Services have increased their offer by 4.6 percent. [C2.]</p>
        <p>A FREE TEXT MESSAGE SERVICE -- Philips Electronics is using a its unusual ''sense and simplicity'' marketing campaign to let cellphone users send free text messages seeking information about popular destinations in major cities. The recommendations will be supplied by the content from Condé Nast Web sites.[C2.]</p>
        <p>TIME WARNER ALLOWS WI-FI -- Time Warner will let its home broadband customers turn their connections into public wireless access spots, a practice shunned by most Internet service providers in the United States. [C6.]</p>
        <p>TOY MAKER'S PROFIT RISES -- The toy maker Hasbro has reported a net income exceeding expectations of analysts, thanks to sales of Spider-Man toys and other brands. [C12.]</p>
        <p>GENERIC VERSION OF AMBIEN -- Federal regulators have approved generic versions of Ambien, the high-selling sleeping pill that has been linked to potential risks like driving while asleep and allergic reactions. The new generics will carry warnings on their labels. [C3.]</p>
        <p>SCRUSHY TO PAY MILLIONS -- The former chief executive of HealthSouth, Richard M. Scrushy, will pay more than $81 million in fines in a settlement with the Securities and Exchange Commission. [C4.]</p>
        <p>SELLING STAMPS FOR CHARITY -- Bill Gross, below, the manager of the bond powerhouse Pimco, who has a love of stamp collecting, will auction off his classic British stamps and donate the proceeds -- up to $5 million -- to Doctors Without Borders, the humanitarian charity. The auction will be in June. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PREFERRING THE TRAIN -- They may not take them in the United States, but some travelers find the rail services abroad to be efficient, civilized, fast and on time, making them an excellent alternative to flying. [C7.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>THE SWISS DRUG MAKER NOVARTIS posted an 11 percent increase in first-quarter earnings, led by strong sales of its hypertension and cancer treatments. (AP)</p>
        <p>AMGEN, THE BIOECHNOLOGY company, reported higher first-quarter profit and revenue on strong sales of its anemia-fighting drugs, but its revenue total for the quarter failed to meet Wall Street's expectations. (AP)</p>
        <p>KIMBERLY-CLARK, the consumer products maker, said that first-quarter profit jumped 64 percent, driven by growth in developing and emerging markets, and stood by its full-year profit view despite topping Wall Street's expectations. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>JUNIPER NETWORKS, the network equipment maker, reported a decline in quarterly profit as expenses rose despite higher sales to telecommunications companies. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A $1.7 BILLION ANNUAL PAYDAY -- A leading hedge fund manager, James Simons, earned more than $1.7 billion last year. Are he and his fellow hedge fund managers this generation's robber barons, using wealth to create wealth, or are they new-economy financiers providing liquidity to the markets? [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>BARCLAYS TO BUY ABN AMRO -- The biggest Dutch bank, ABN Amro, has agreed to be bought by Barclays of Britain for 67 billion euros (nearly $91 billion). The deal creates one of the world's biggest banks, but a new suitor could still swoop in with a higher bid and split up the bank. [C1.]</p>
        <p>ASTRAZENECA TO BUY MEDIMMUNE -- AstraZeneca has agreed to acquire MedImmune for $15.6 billion in a clear sign that big drug makers are making a push into biotechnology. The all-cash deal for MedImmune, worth $58 a share, may be the largest purchase ever of an American biotechnology company. [C3.]</p>
        <p>FACING SHAREHOLDERS AT THE TIMES -- The Ochs/Sulzberger family, which controls The New York Times Company, is bracing for a contentious meeting with shareholders today; up to 50 percent of them could withhold votes for the election of directors to express their frustration with the company's dual-ownership structure and performance. [C1.]</p>
        <p>ROOMS FOR EVERYONE -- Las Vegas is in the middle of yet another hotel building boom and there is no end in sight. Occupancy rates hover at about 90 percent -- higher on the weekends. [C1.]</p>
        <p>S.E.C. SUIT AT APPLE -- Apple Inc.'s former general counsel and its former chief financial officer expect to be sued this week by the Securities and Exchange Commission as part of a federal investigation into the company's backdating of employee stock options. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CHINA YIELDS TO INQUIRY -- China has relented and will allow American regulators inside the country to investigate whether Chinese suppliers exported contaminated pet food ingredients to the United States earlier this year, resulting in one of the largest pet food recalls ever. [C1.]</p>
        <p>AN UNEXPECTED ADMISSION -- The Ford Motor Company's chief executive, Alan R. Mulally has said he believes in global warming. [C3.]</p>
        <p>NEW SOURCE OF ETHANOL? -- A New Zealand company says it has secured financing from a Silicon Valley investor to produce ethanol from an untapped source -- carbon monoxide gas. [C3.]</p>
        <p>NEW BID FOR AFFLIATED COMPUTER -- Two partners making an unsolicited bid for the technology services company Affiliated Computer Services have increased their offer by 4.6 percent. [C2.]</p>
        <p>A FREE TEXT MESSAGE SERVICE -- Philips Electronics is using a its unusual ''sense and simplicity'' marketing campaign to let cellphone users send free text messages seeking information about popular destinations in major cities. The recommendations will be supplied by the content from Condé Nast Web sites.[C2.]</p>
        <p>TIME WARNER ALLOWS WI-FI -- Time Warner will let its home broadband customers turn their connections into public wireless access spots, a practice shunned by most Internet service providers in the United States. [C6.]</p>
        <p>TOY MAKER'S PROFIT RISES -- The toy maker Hasbro has reported a net income exceeding expectations of analysts, thanks to sales of Spider-Man toys and other brands. [C12.]</p>
        <p>GENERIC VERSION OF AMBIEN -- Federal regulators have approved generic versions of Ambien, the high-selling sleeping pill that has been linked to potential risks like driving while asleep and allergic reactions. The new generics will carry warnings on their labels. [C3.]</p>
        <p>SCRUSHY TO PAY MILLIONS -- The former chief executive of HealthSouth, Richard M. Scrushy, will pay more than $81 million in fines in a settlement with the Securities and Exchange Commission. [C4.]</p>
        <p>SELLING STAMPS FOR CHARITY -- Bill Gross, below, the manager of the bond powerhouse Pimco, who has a love of stamp collecting, will auction off his classic British stamps and donate the proceeds -- up to $5 million -- to Doctors Without Borders, the humanitarian charity. The auction will be in June. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PREFERRING THE TRAIN -- They may not take them in the United States, but some travelers find the rail services abroad to be efficient, civilized, fast and on time, making them an excellent alternative to flying. [C7.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>THE SWISS DRUG MAKER NOVARTIS posted an 11 percent increase in first-quarter earnings, led by strong sales of its hypertension and cancer treatments. (AP)</p>
        <p>AMGEN, THE BIOECHNOLOGY company, reported higher first-quarter profit and revenue on strong sales of its anemia-fighting drugs, but its revenue total for the quarter failed to meet Wall Street's expectations. (AP)</p>
        <p>KIMBERLY-CLARK, the consumer products maker, said that first-quarter profit jumped 64 percent, driven by growth in developing and emerging markets, and stood by its full-year profit view despite topping Wall Street's expectations. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>JUNIPER NETWORKS, the network equipment maker, reported a decline in quarterly profit as expenses rose despite higher sales to telecommunications companies. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
