<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Living Day to Day By a Gospel of Green</title>
    <meta content="08ball" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/08/garden/08ball.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1831349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AT HOME WITH JIM BALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric and Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ministers (Protestant)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vienna (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Evangelical Environmental Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ball, Jim (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ball, Kara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodstein, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ministers (Protestant)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D71531F93BA35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Living Day to Day By a Gospel of Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Living Day to Day by a Gospel of Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE GOODSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodstein, Laurie</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA, Va.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rev Jim Ball and his wife, Kara, evangelical Christians, practice 'creation care' by furnishing their town house in Vienna, Va, with used furniture, driving a hybrid car, and using flourescent lightbulbs in effort to reduce global warming; he considers himself a green minister and is spearheading movement of Christian environmentalists as director of nonprofit Evangelical Environmental Network; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Rev. Jim Ball is an evangelical Christian minister whose pulpit is parked in front of his townhouse. It's a deep blue hybrid Toyota Prius, but it is not just any Toyota Prius. It is the original ''What Would Jesus Drive?'' car.</p>
        <p>Four years ago Mr. Ball, the executive director of the nonprofit Evangelical Environmental Network, and his wife, Kara, drove the Prius from Texas east across the Bible Belt in a provocative stunt that, in keeping with the core mission of his organization, awakened evangelical churches to the threat of global warming. It also awakened Americans to the existence of the human hybrid known as a Green Evangelical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At home with Jim Ball, an evangelical Christian minister whose day-to-day activities incorporate what some Christian environmentalists call “creation care.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Rev. Jim Ball is an evangelical Christian minister whose pulpit is parked in front of his townhouse. It's a deep blue hybrid Toyota Prius, but it is not just any Toyota Prius. It is the original ''What Would Jesus Drive?'' car.</p>
        <p>Four years ago Mr. Ball, the executive director of the nonprofit Evangelical Environmental Network, and his wife, Kara, drove the Prius from Texas east across the Bible Belt in a provocative stunt that, in keeping with the core mission of his organization, awakened evangelical churches to the threat of global warming. It also awakened Americans to the existence of the human hybrid known as a Green Evangelical.</p>
        <p>It turns out that Jim and Kara Ball spend a lot of time thinking not just about what Jesus would drive, but also about how his people should wash their clothes, light their bathrooms, clean their windows, shop for groceries and furnish their living rooms -- the day-to-day elements of what some Christian environmentalists call ''creation care.''</p>
        <p>''We like to buy used -- we do that intentionally,'' Mr. Ball said, surveying a desk, television cabinet, dining room table and end tables that the couple bought at their favorite thrift shop in rural Maryland, run by a Navy veteran named Bill. ''Our stuff doesn't necessarily match, but it goes enough.''</p>
        <p>The end tables are made of mahogany. The Balls say they would never buy new mahogany furniture because the wood is often harvested from endangered rain forests, but they do not object to pre-owned mahogany.</p>
        <p>''You're not using up the resources again,'' said Mr. Ball, a ruddy 45-year-old in a chamois shirt and Levis, who looks like he would be more at home with the Sierra Club than Pat Robertson's ''700 Club.'' ''It's a form of recycling.''</p>
        <p>While running a household on eco-friendly Christian principles requires a chain of small interlocking choices, Mr. Ball's real gift is for large-scale strategizing. Raised in Texas as a Southern Baptist, he knew that conservative evangelicals had long been allergic to anything like environmentalism, associating it with hippies, communism, feminism, anti-corporatism, gun control and nature-worshipping paganism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ball spent the last seven years inviting evangelical pastors to sit down with climate scientists who shared the same born-again faith and corporate executives who were making an effort to reduce pollution. Progress was slow and he did not convince them all, but in the last year he has led an effort that has persuaded more than 100 influential evangelical pastors, theologians and organizational leaders -- many of them political conservatives -- to sign an ''Evangelical Call to Action'' on climate change.</p>
        <p>Since his leading role in the ''What Would Jesus Drive?'' campaign, Mr. Ball has preferred to stay out of the limelight while pushing his new converts forward as frontmen. He figured that the Rev. Rick Warren, the megachurch pastor and author of ''The Purpose Driven Life,'' could attract far more Christians to the climate-change cause by preaching about creation care than he could.</p>
        <p>But after some hesitation, Mr. and Mrs. Ball decided to allow a reporter to snoop around their modest two-bedroom townhouse, take notes in the basement and inspect their bathrooms, in the hope of getting across the point that you don't have to live in a straw bale house in New Mexico outfitted with $150,000 in solar panels in order to play a role in reducing global warming.</p>
        <p>''Do I really need all of this light?'' said Mr. Ball, squinting at the bar of bare bulbs over the bathroom mirror. The bar was outfitted with curly compact fluorescent bulbs, like every light in the house except for two old-fashioned fixtures, for which the Balls could not find fluorescents that fit. It was an unconventional look, especially since there was a bulb only in every other socket. Mr. Ball said: ''It's a basic principle. Just use what you need. But it's not do without.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ball, who is 42, put it this way: ''We have different habits, and once you have a habit it's as easy as any other habit.''</p>
        <p>They moved to this townhouse last August from a small town in Maryland, when Mrs. Ball got a job as the special assistant to the president of the National Wildlife Federation, a nonprofit organization focused on wildlife protection in Reston, Va. The house, in a development called Country Creek, has two bedrooms and 1,400 square feet, and cost them $435,000; they chose it because it was within walking distance of the Washington Metro.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ball can be in Washington, where he often meets with colleagues and visits Congressional offices, in about 45 minutes, although he works mainly at home, where the second bedroom is now a home office.</p>
        <p>On a cold February afternoon, the thermostat was set at 65 degrees. Mr. Ball said that he often turns on his Presto Heat Dish space heater when he starts the day at his desk. If he migrates to another room, the heater is light enough to carry around. ''If you're cold, heat the place you are, instead of the whole place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While Mrs. Ball prepared dinner, Mr. Ball gave a tour. The shower stall in the basement bathroom housed Iggy, a docile elderly iguana, five feet long from nose to tail. He was eating a salad of kale and bananas and sitting on a heat rock plugged into a timer. He is Mrs. Ball's pet, rescued from an animal shelter, as are the three black cats, Emma, Spit and Midnight.</p>
        <p>In the basement storage room, the hot water heater is swaddled in a blanket sealed with duct tape. There are shelves of Bi-O-Kleen laundry powder, Seventh Generation recycled paper towels, Trader Joe's paper towels, Whole Foods dishwasher detergent, Oxi-Clean -- a nonchlorine bleach -- and cans of Coke.</p>
        <p>''One thing about aluminum: it's very recyclable,'' Mr. Ball said.</p>
        <p>They clean bathroom and kitchen surfaces with a mixture of hydrogen peroxide, vinegar and baking soda. They wipe their windows with newsprint doused in vinegar.</p>
        <p>Over dinner, which began with a prayer, Mr. and Mrs. Ball recounted what they called their ''creation-care romance.'' They met in 2000 at a loud Christian music festival in Pennsylvania, called ''Creation Fest,'' where she was the chaperone for her church youth group and he was manning the table for the Evangelical Environmental Network, which he took over that year.</p>
        <p>At the time, she was living on 70 acres in central Pennsylvania with a flock of chickens and two rare six-horned Jacob sheep and organizing churches and farmers in a watershed conservancy program. On one of their first dates, the sheep escaped to the woods. The Balls were engaged in three months, married in a year.</p>
        <p>One of the first things he told her when they met was that he was devoted to the global warming issue, and probably would be for the rest of his life. In the seminary, he had dismissed environmentalism as unimportant compared to poverty and oppression and war. But while studying for a Ph.D. in theological ethics at Drew University, he was challenged by another student to reread what the Bible had to say about care for God's creation.</p>
        <p>''Colossians, chapter 1, verses 15 to 20 is the touchstone text for me,'' he said. '' 'All things have been created by Him and for Him. All things have been reconciled by His blood on the cross.' The Apostle Paul tells us we are called to be ministers of reconciliation, and that means caring for all things.''</p>
        <p>He read everything he could on energy policy, climate science and the history of environmentalism, but said one book in particular made him realize the connections between global warming and poverty. Asked what book, he said: ''I'll cop to it. It was 'Earth in the Balance,' '' the 1992 bestseller by Al Gore. ''That might get me in some trouble,'' he said. ''I'm a great admirer of the vice president, but some people in my community aren't.''</p>
        <p>On their ''What Would Jesus Drive?'' tour, Mr. and Mrs. Ball returned to the Creation Fest in their Prius. ''A few folks were hostile,'' he recalled. ''We got e-mails from people who thought we were being disrespectful to Jesus. They didn't understand we were taking the question seriously, that Christians should be concerned about this. They felt it was some cheap stunt by environmentalists.</p>
        <p>''I said to them, I'm literally taking Jesus as Lord of my life, of everything -- including how I get around,'' he said. ''There's nothing that falls outside that scope.''</p>
        <p>AT HOME WITH JIM BALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
