<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush, Feeling Ill and Resting, Attracts Notice by Absence</title>
    <meta content="09notebook" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/world/europe/09notebook.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Group of Eight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Heilgendamm (Germany)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarkozy, Nicolas (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkel, Angela (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Group of Eight</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush, Feeling Ill and Resting, Attracts Notice by Absence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush, Feeling Ill and Resting, Attracts Notice by Absence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>HEILIGENDAMM, Germany, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook: Pres Nicolas Sarkozy of France, newest addition to small club of leaders who make up Group of 8, emerged from his meeting with Pres Bush to greet press--sans Bush, who reportedly was feeling ill; Bush did not seem quite sure of body language protocol when he saw Chancellor Angela Merkel on summit's first day; international press corps had trouble covering summit because security in Heilgendamm, Germany, was so intense (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Was it something he ate?</p>
        <p>It seemed awfully mysterious when the new president of France, Nicolas Sarkozy, emerged from his meeting with President Bush on Friday morning to greet the press -- sans Mr. Bush.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A counselor to President Bush reported that the president had awakened “not feeling well to the stomach.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Was it something he ate?</p>
        <p>It seemed awfully mysterious when the new president of France, Nicolas Sarkozy, emerged from his meeting with President Bush on Friday morning to greet the press -- sans Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarkozy, the newest addition to the small club of leaders who make up the so-called Group of 8, sauntered down a well-manicured lane alone and stopped before the cameras, only to dismiss inquiries about his American counterpart.</p>
        <p>''I'm not his spokesman,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Soon, however, a spokesman appeared -- Dan Bartlett, counselor to Mr. Bush, who reported that the president had awakened ''not feeling well to the stomach.'' Mr. Bush met Mr. Sarkozy in his private quarters and then retired for the morning, skipping a meeting with African leaders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett suggested it was perhaps the food. Recalling when the first President Bush threw up at a state dinner in his honor in Japan, the aide said, ''I guess he didn't want to follow in the footsteps of his father in Asia.'' By lunchtime, the president was ''feeling rejuvenated,'' in Mr. Bartlett's words, and back on track, though he was caught on camera rubbing his belly.</p>
        <p>(Later in the day, before a dinner with President Lech Kaczynski of Poland at Mr. Kaczynski's Baltic Sea retreat in Jurata, Mr. Bush was asked how he was feeling. ''Fine, thanks,'' he said, flashing a thumbs-up sign, though after two helicopter flights and a plane ride to get there, he looked a little peaked.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett, by this time, had revised his diagnosis. The meeting's host, after all, was Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany, a strong Bush ally who perhaps would not have taken kindly to any inference that her accommodations were imperfect.</p>
        <p>''The suspicion is there is some sort of bug, probably viral in nature, highly unlikely related to the food,'' Mr. Bartlett declared, adding that the president ''feels terrible about any disruption he may have caused to Chancellor Merkel's proceeding.''</p>
        <p>Bush and Body Language</p>
        <p>Body language is everything when world leaders gather -- especially when one of those leaders is President Bush. But those who came to Heiligendamm expecting a reprise of the shoulder rub Mr. Bush gave to Mrs. Merkel at last year's Group of 8 meeting in St. Petersburg, Russia, were sorely disappointed.</p>
        <p>The president did not seem quite sure of the body language protocol when he saw Mrs. Merkel for lunch on the summit's first day. Prime Minister Tony Blair of Great Britain greeted the German chancellor in traditional European fashion -- with a kiss on each cheek. But Mr. Bush is not a kissy-kissy kind of guy, and anyway, how would a kiss look after the shoulder rub hubbub?</p>
        <p>So the president stood close to Mrs. Merkel -- but did not touch -- as the cameras rolled for their Heiligendamm debut. When they were done pledging mutual cooperation on climate change and exchanging the customary pleasantries, Mrs. Merkel extended her hand. Mr. Bush gave her a hearty shake and then, perhaps unable to resist, a couple of stiff claps on the shoulder.</p>
        <p>But not a rub.</p>
        <p>Transit Troubles</p>
        <p>It was planes, trains and automobiles -- or rather, helicopters, boats and a steam engine locomotive -- for members of the beleaguered international press corps, who tried valiantly to cover a summit that somehow always seemed just out of reach.</p>
        <p>The setting was idyllic: the sprawling Kempinski Grand Hotel here in Heiligendamm, the oldest seaside resort in Germany.</p>
        <p>The resort, in the former East Germany, is part of the region that serves as Mrs. Merkel's political base, and she hoped to showcase progress here since reunification.</p>
        <p>(Last year, in an effort to promote the place, she invited Mr. Bush to drop in on his way to St. Petersburg, and he did, dining on wild boar that had been especially prepared for him by a local restaurateur.)</p>
        <p>But showcasing progress this year meant bringing in the news media, and that proved a tricky business. Security was so intense that the village was all but sealed off, and the organizers planned for reporters to arrive from nearby Kühlungsborn via a steam-belching locomotive. If the trains got full, buses were on hand.</p>
        <p>But both Plan A and its backup fell apart quickly when demonstrators blocked roads and laid their bodies down on the railroad tracks Wednesday. So the organizers turned to Plan B: German Army boats.</p>
        <p>The sea, alas, was choppy, and some journalists got sick. By Thursday, it didn't much matter; the army boats were docked when the protesters took to the water, engaging in a speedboat chase with the police. With President Sarkozy of France on the verge of holding a press conference with no French reporters on hand, the organizers invoked Plan C: helicopters.</p>
        <p>No telling how all that fuel-consuming transport fit in with the theme of the summit: combating global warming.</p>
        <p>REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
