<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fighting the Tide, A Few Restaurants Tilt to Tap Water</title>
    <meta content="30wate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/30/dining/30wate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1850828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Filters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Filters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E6DB1430F933A05756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1302" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fighting the Tide, A Few Restaurants Tilt to Tap Water</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fighting the Tide, a Few Restaurants Tilt to Tap Water</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DON'T bother asking for Fiji, San Pellegrino or any other designer water at either Incanto, a restaurant that opened in San Francisco in 2002, or at Poggio, which opened in Sausalito, Calif., two years later.</p>
        <p>All their water comes out of the tap. It's filtered before it reaches the table, but it's from the public water system, just the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some restaurants have stopped selling bottled water as a way to reduce the environmental costs of manufacturing and transporting bottles of water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DON'T bother asking for Fiji, San Pellegrino or any other designer water at either Incanto, a restaurant that opened in San Francisco in 2002, or at Poggio, which opened in Sausalito, Calif., two years later.</p>
        <p>All their water comes out of the tap. It's filtered before it reaches the table, but it's from the public water system, just the same.</p>
        <p>''Serving our local water in reusable carafes makes more sense for the environment than manufacturing thousands of single-use glass bottles for someone to use once and throw away,'' Incanto explains at its Web site.</p>
        <p>These two Bay Area restaurants were pretty much alone in kicking the bottle habit until Alice Waters, the godmother of things organic, sustainable and local, banned bottled still water at Chez Panisse in Berkeley last year and started serving only house-made sparkling water this year. Then the press took notice. Now other California restaurants, like Nopa in San Francisco, are following suit. Even an ice cream shop -- Ici, in Berkeley -- has jumped on the non-bottled-water wagon.</p>
        <p>And now, with a little push from Ms. Waters, an important New York City restaurant is coming on board.</p>
        <p>It's a big move in the restaurant industry, which, if you extrapolate from the amount of water it buys, takes in at least $200 million to $350 million from bottled water a year, according to the restaurant consultant Clark Wolf.</p>
        <p>The ''eat local'' movement first became popular in California, so it makes sense that ''drink local'' is catching on there as a way to reduce the environmental costs of manufacturing and transporting bottles of water, as well as the mountains of plastic that end up in landfills.</p>
        <p>But soon the owners of Del Posto in New York, the most elegant and expensive of the restaurants in the empire of Joseph Bastianich and Mario Batali, will be joining the nascent movement -- once they decide on the proper containers for their filtered still and carbonated tap water. Etched on the glass will be an explanation of why bottled water is no longer available.</p>
        <p>''Filling cargo ships with water and sending it hundreds and thousands of miles to get it around the world seems ridiculous,'' Mr. Bastianich said. ''With all the other things we do for sustainability, it makes sense.''</p>
        <p>He added that of all their restaurants, Del Posto was best able to afford the change.</p>
        <p>Other restaurants, including the Farmers Diner in Quechee, Vt., have made the switch, but they have not made waves. Tod Murphy, who owns the diner and has gained a certain celebrity in the food world for serving local products, stopped ordering bottled water in February. ''It makes no sense, because we have great well water,'' he said, ''but I had no idea I was on the cutting edge.''</p>
        <p>For almost everyone else the idea is still in the talking stage, in part because there's a big profit in bottled water, even though some of it comes out of a tap before it goes into the bottle. Restaurants buy it for $1 or $2 and sell it for as much as $8, or even more, giving it the highest markup of any item on the menu. Most restaurants making their own sparkling water are not charging for it.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Zakarian, the chef and an owner of Country in Manhattan, described the ban as ''a worthy thing to do.'' But he added, ''You have to make a profit.''</p>
        <p>''Alice is very commendable and extraordinary, and we look to her,'' Mr. Zakarian said, ''but I think she gets carried away sometimes.'' He wondered where he would make up the lost revenue if he eliminated bottled water. ''Serving tap water is a great idea that we'd all love to be able to do, but it's not going to happen all at once.''</p>
        <p>Tom Colicchio, the chef and an owner of Craft restaurant and several spinoffs, was incredulous that restaurants would contemplate such a change. ''This is the first I've heard of it,'' he said. ''Why would you do that -- not from a money standpoint, but from a service and hospitality standpoint? Fifty to 60 percent prefer bottled water, especially sparkling.''</p>
        <p>Credit the bottled water industry with a brilliant marketing job, selling purity and convincing the public that its product tastes better, is more convenient and is safer than good tap water. From a trickle of Perrier in the early 1980s, consumption of bottled water in America rose to 27.6 gallons per capita last year, according to the International Bottled Water Association.</p>
        <p>On the West Coast, at least, tap water is looking more fashionable. Seltzer Sisters, a company in Redwood City, Calif., that sells seltzer made from local tap water in old-fashioned reusable glass bottles, says its sales in Berkeley have risen 20 percent in the last six months. The Berkeley school district replaced commercially bottled water with large containers of tap water and cups in all its schools last year.</p>
        <p>''The students were up in arms, but a year later no one says anything,'' said Ann Cooper, director of the district's nutrition services, who added, ''We have been marketed to the point that children believe they can't drink water out of the tap.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gina Solomon, a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, the environmental advocacy group, said there is no reason to believe that bottled water is safer than tap water, though there can be problems with either. The public water supply is much more stringently regulated by the Environmental Protection Agency than bottled water is by the Food and Drug Administration. The E.P.A. requires multiple daily tests for bacteria, for example, with the results available to the public; the F.D.A. requires weekly testing, which does not have to be reported to the agency, to the states or to the public.</p>
        <p>''The rationale for buying bottled water is a fantasy that has a destructive downside,'' Dr. Solomon said. ''These companies are marketing an illusion of environmental purity.''</p>
        <p>Her organization has calculated how much carbon dioxide -- a major greenhouse gas -- is emitted during the transportation of bottled water imported from France and Italy, the two largest exporters to the United States, and Fiji water, which travels much farther. Together they account for 4,000 tons of carbon dioxide, the equivalent, Dr. Solomon said, of the yearly emissions from 700 cars on the road. She called that ''a significant contribution to global warming, and fundamentally an unnecessary one.''</p>
        <p>But Stephen Kay, the vice president for communications at the International Bottled Water Association, said eliminating bottled water would have ''a negligible, nonexistent impact on protecting the environment.''</p>
        <p>Most restaurateurs seem unready to go cold turkey. Some have moved toward reducing their carbon footprint by switching to local bottled water instead of imported, as Dan Barber has done at Blue Hill at Stone Barns in Pocantico Hills in Westchester County, N.Y. A week ago he also added house-made seltzer, served from old-fashioned glass bottles.</p>
        <p>As part of its low-carbon plan Bon Appétit, the institutional food service company, is switching to domestic bottled waters from imported and is looking at a filtering system using local water and reusable glass bottles for some customers.</p>
        <p>Some restaurants make a point of serving tap water but still provide bottled water on request. ''Santa Monica is known for its terrible tap water,'' said Anastasia Israel, an owner of Abode, which opened there a month ago. Patrons are reluctant to drink the tap water, but after servers explain the filtration process, 80 percent of them give it a try. Carbonation will follow soon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf, the consultant, said he is confident that if restaurants are pressed to eliminate bottled water, they will figure out how to do it. ''No one is more adaptable than a restaurateur,'' he said, noting that they whined when smoking was banned but ''survived beautifully.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
