<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Voice of the Bottle Bill to Keeper of the Green</title>
    <meta content="04lives" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/04/nyregion/04lives.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070507T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Nature and Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Judith Enck</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3DC113EF937A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Voice of the Bottle Bill to Keeper of the Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Voice of the Bottle Bill to Keeper of the Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ODD, but the color green is nowhere present in the Capitol office occupied by a mountain range of paperwork and the tart-tongued Judith Enck, Gov. Eliot Spitzer's deputy secretary for the environment, who began her career as a bottle-bill lobbyist and Naderesque nag about government eco-insensitivity. Reprising the role she played during Mr. Spitzer's eight years as attorney general (it was her idea for him to hire her away from the New York Public Interest Research Group and bring his nascent environmental agenda up to snuff), Ms Enck is his adviser on all things green.</p>
        <p>Or all things potentially green, which is why she was gratified last month when New York State's first lady, Silda Wall Spitzer, embraced her whimsical but doable suggestion for a greening of the energy-guzzling governor's mansion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Judith Enck, Gov. Eliot Spitzer’s deputy secretary for the environment, says she decided to work for Mr. Spitzer because she wanted to make rather than influence environmental policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ODD, but the color green is nowhere present in the Capitol office occupied by a mountain range of paperwork and the tart-tongued Judith Enck, Gov. Eliot Spitzer's deputy secretary for the environment, who began her career as a bottle-bill lobbyist and Naderesque nag about government eco-insensitivity. Reprising the role she played during Mr. Spitzer's eight years as attorney general (it was her idea for him to hire her away from the New York Public Interest Research Group and bring his nascent environmental agenda up to snuff), Ms Enck is his adviser on all things green.</p>
        <p>Or all things potentially green, which is why she was gratified last month when New York State's first lady, Silda Wall Spitzer, embraced her whimsical but doable suggestion for a greening of the energy-guzzling governor's mansion.</p>
        <p>Or all things that should stay green, which is why she advised Mr. Spitzer to dig in and fight a 190-mile high-voltage transmission line through central New York that, as originally planned, would snake across seven counties, 154 streams or rivers and 155 mapped wetlands.</p>
        <p>''It would have an enormous aesthetic impact, while the economic benefits are not that clear,'' Ms. Enck says. Relocating the line alongside the New York State Thruway might be a viable compromise. As for her own personal environmental footprint, she shrugs: ''I'm sure it's huge. I'm a typical American.''</p>
        <p>Not exactly. Her transportation of choice is a Toyota Prius. Her small house is heated by two cords of wood and sunshine. She recycles and composts like a fiend. ''But I feel really guilty because I live a half-hour from where I work and I don't carpool,'' she says. (Maybe that's because she has only five neighbors at Common Farms, a 185-acre collectively owned preserve in the town of Poestenkill, where she built her house.) ''And I occasionally vote Republican,'' she stage whispers, ''but only for local candidates.'' Her nonpartisan weakness -- she is a nominal Democrat -- is female candidates with a sympathetic environmental stance and smart fiscal policies.</p>
        <p>The opportunity to make rather than simply influence environmental policy is why Ms. Enck left the advocacy side of the aisle to work for Mr. Spitzer: ''Rather than knocking on the door from the outside, I wanted to shape policy from the inside.'' The Pataki administration was aghast when she joined the attorney general's senior staff, and referred to her as ''a bomb thrower.'' It still annoys her. ''Since when is being an advocate for recycling equivalent to throwing bombs?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Enck wryly refers to her wing of the building as ''the unarmed side of the Capitol'' -- less security, but more recycling bins. There was just one on her floor in January. Now there are 25.</p>
        <p>THE highlight of her office ephemera, aside from plaques and bumper stickers with the slogan ''Well Behaved Women Rarely Make History,'' is an autographed black-and-white photograph of Jon Stewart, the irreverent talk show host. Two tickets, souvenirs of her visits as a member of the studio audience, are tucked into the frame.</p>
        <p>Ms. Enck, 47, makeup-free and unfussily attired in a black pantsuit, confesses to being a serious Stewart groupie. It is an addiction tolerated, if not shared, by her husband, Mark Dunlea, a lawyer and former state chairman of the Green Party who is now with the Hunger Action Network.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart's photograph arrived after a friend surreptitiously wrote to him describing Ms. Enck's decision to donate a kidney to her brother-in-law; the friend was hoping Mr. Stewart would call, but Ms. Enck seems comfortable settling for a picture with this inscription: ''Judith, Wow! I'm reluctant to donate used clothing. Kudos to you.''</p>
        <p>She blushes, and shares some organic brownies baked by her neighbor in Poestenkill, where she and her husband built their solar-and-wood-stove-heated house way before it was hip to be anti-McMansion.</p>
        <p>Ms. Enck, whose favorite film is ''The Way We Were'' (go ahead and call her a square; she revels in it), admits to hauling a bunch of interns to soak up Al Gore's sermon in ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' only to fall asleep. Not that global warming does not alarm her: It's just that she knows his message by heart.</p>
        <p>Uprooted, to her intense displeasure, by her parents -- her father was a truck driver, her mother a teacher's aide -- from an urban girlhood in Queens Village and transplanted with four younger, equally outraged siblings to bucolic Cairo in upstate Greene County, Ms. Enck was not an early convert to eco-activism. She hated the Catskills.</p>
        <p>As a teenager, her ambition was to become a pilot. ''My mother kind of pushed me into it,'' she says. ''She was a big fan of Amelia Earhart.'' At 14, Ms. Enck took flying lessons, but she quit when the money ran out, and went on to the College of Saint Rose in Albany, intending to become a social worker. ''I always get a little tickle when my adversaries dismiss me as an elitist environmentalist,'' she says. ''I grew up working class. I know about living paycheck to paycheck.'' Still does. ''Environmental advocacy is not a money maker; state government is high end for us,'' she says. She has a son at Vassar; he is a political science major, as she was.</p>
        <p>Her major preoccupation these days is the ''bigger, better bottle bill,'' an expansion of the original bill that she helped push Gov. Hugh L. Carey into signing 25 years ago. Then, as now, her opponent is the Republican-controlled Senate.</p>
        <p>''I'm much more pragmatic than I was 20 years ago,'' she says. ''What's really sad is that the issues are the same.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 7, 2007, Monday  A picture in some copies on Friday with the Public Lives column, about Judith Enck, deputy secretary for the environment for Gov. Eliot Spitzer of New York, was published in error. The picture was of Carol Ash, the new state parks commissioner -- not Ms. Enck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 7, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>A picture in some copies on Friday with the Public Lives column, about Judith Enck, deputy secretary for the environment for Gov. Eliot Spitzer of New York, was published in error. The picture was of Carol Ash, the new state parks commissioner -- not Ms. Enck.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
