<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Eat; Flour Power</title>
    <meta content="20food.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="109" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/20/magazine/20food-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Quebec Province (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siebert, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Quebec</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Desserts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chocolate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Desserts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chocolate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rubin, Maury</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EED91231F933A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Eat; Flour Power</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flour Power</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amanda Hesser</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Siebert article describes gradual decline of his wife's family's cabin in Quebec woods, which has now lost running water, working toilet and electric power; says they are now contemplating building some sort of structure that would free them completely from provincial power and water grid (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent afternoon, I met Maury Rubin, a baking impresario best known for serving hot chocolate with marshmallows the size of children's blocks and tasty, oddball pastries like the pretzel croissant, at Birdbath, one of two ''green'' bakeries he recently opened in New York -- this one appropriately in Greenwich Village. (The original Birdbath is located in the East Village.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even a bakery  especially a bakery!  can lower the wattage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent afternoon, I met Maury Rubin, a baking impresario best known for serving hot chocolate with marshmallows the size of children's blocks and tasty, oddball pastries like the pretzel croissant, at Birdbath, one of two ''green'' bakeries he recently opened in New York -- this one appropriately in Greenwich Village. (The original Birdbath is located in the East Village.)</p>
        <p>Rubin has long been a stylist and showman -- his City Bakery created the notion of a chocolate room and popularized lemon tarts decorated with a strand of melted chocolate as thin as a hair. For the past 15 winters he has held a hot-chocolate festival that is mostly attended by adults skipping out of work, and in 2005, he shut down the block on West 18th Street, trucked in snow and set up a portable ice-skating rink.</p>
        <p>Birdbath, then, has been an odd detour. There's a natural imbalance between the self-indulgent world of baking and the self-denying world of environmentalism. The shops themselves are small and spare. And let's be honest: environmentally sound muffins don't sound half as appetizing as a chocolate custard tart.</p>
        <p>Piled high in a display case are cookies and pastries in a variety of browns, proving that green products are rarely actually green. There is a pyramid of ''(save the polar) bear claws,'' whose pastry, made with organic flour from Pennsylvania and mascarpone cheese from Vermont, is filled with stewed organic apricots. There are apple-miso muffins containing spelt and kamut, ginger yogurt scones and ''what's your carbon footprint? cookies'' in butter and chocolate. If City Bakery's offerings are straight from Willy Wonka's chocolate factory, Birdbath's are born in Berkeley. (Sweet-tooth disclosure: I have twice hired City Bakery to cater parties, and my publisher gave a party for my last book at the bakery.)</p>
        <p>We sat on a window seat as customers streamed in and out of the bakery. Rubin, a man with quick eyes and a slow gait, was dressed in his customary palette of 70's earth tones. He had been planning an exit strategy from the baking business. (He is 47 years old.) But then a good space opened up on First Avenue, and like any respectable New York retailer, he snapped it up. Then he thought, I'm interested in green building, let's do it this way. Birdbath is Rubin's midlife-crisis venture, his red Ferrari. Who knew that spelt and recycled plastic had so much sex appeal?</p>
        <p>Rubin, who in his first career was a producer and director for Howard Cosell on ABC Sports, poured his energy into what he calls Birdbath's ''graphic identity.'' The new location has some classic Rubin touches. On the wall behind the display case is a grid of square cubbyholes -- each large enough for a stack of cookies or a loaf of bread. The cubbyholes frame the baked goods in a way that makes them seem first sculpture, then food. The wall behind the cubbies is made of wheatboard, an environmentally friendly equivalent of plywood containing processed wheat. The cubbies themselves are made with two layers of Ecoresin (recycled plastic) that sandwich a layer of grass cloth.</p>
        <p>Building Birdbath this way, Rubin said, cost about 15 percent more than if he had used conventional products. Pastries are displayed on a black surface called PaperStone (a surprisingly hard material made from recycled paper and resin), which rests on the shipping crate that held the cubbies. Rubin said this design decision was ''penance'' for shipping the cubbies all the way from Salt Lake City.</p>
        <p>Instead of a regular refrigerator, the energy guzzler in most commercial kitchens, Rubin opted for a small under-the-counter model and three low-power beverage machines (think orange soda at Denny's) dispensing high-end juices and teas. His delivery van for transporting baked goods between the original Birdbath location and this one is a bicycle-powered rickshaw -- ridden by an employee who deserves a good Christmas bonus. The cash register is secondhand. The Lower East Side Ecology Center composts the bakery's coffee grounds.</p>
        <p>I asked Rubin why the lights were on during a perfectly bright day, and he gave an amused sigh. ''I like the question a lot,'' he replied.</p>
        <p>When the bakery first opened, it had no name -- a stunt that made the place perfect bait for bloggers. He thought about naming it Barn Door or Backyard, but eventually settled on Birdbath. ''I like Birdbath,'' Sahar Cusack, a clerk, told me. ''I like to think of this as the birdbath,'' she went on, pointing to the counter filled with pastries, ''and all the little birds come in to feed at it. And I like the idea of birds and your carbon footprint -- birds have one of the tiniest footprints.''</p>
        <p>Although the first Birdbath has been open for more than a year, Rubin is still working to make its food more sustainable. He decided that the organic flour from Utah that he uses at City Bakery travels too far; six months ago he switched to purveyors in Pennsylvania and North Carolina. With each ingredient he weighs the environmental impact of shipping against its value as an organic product, which means that sometimes local but conventional ingredients win out. ''I want the best food, but I want to push the notion of sacrifice,'' Rubin said.</p>
        <p>Then again, it is a bakery, and if you are dedicating your life to conserving, should giant chocolate-chip cookies really make the cut?</p>
        <p>Rubin paused at the query.</p>
        <p>''You couldn't convince me that the meaning of life doesn't include waking up and having a perfect pastry and cup of coffee,'' he said. ''I'm not a religious person. It might be the closest I get.'' He surveyed the shop before continuing: ''I see the bakery as the lifeblood to civilization. Butcher, baker, candlestick-maker. I love the baker part of that,'' he added, ''that the baker makes that list.''</p>
        <p>(Save the Polar) Bear Claws</p>
        <p>Use organic ingredients where possible.</p>
        <p>For the dough:</p>
        <p>4 cups plus 2 tablespoons flour</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon salt</p>
        <p>1 pound (4 sticks) butter, softened</p>
        <p>1 pound (2 cups) mascarpone</p>
        <p>For the filling and topping:</p>
        <p>2 cups unsulfured dried apricots</p>
        <p>1/3 cup apricot preserves</p>
        <p>1 large egg yolk</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons heavy cream</p>
        <p>3 1/2 tablespoons turbinado sugar.</p>
        <p>1. Place the flour and salt in the bowl of an electric mixer fitted with a paddle attachment. With the mixer on low, add the butter, 2 tablespoons at a time, until incorporated. Then add the mascarpone, 2 tablespoons at a time, until blended.</p>
        <p>2. Divide the dough into 3 equal balls. Flatten each ball into a disc, wrap in plastic and refrigerate for 2 hours or overnight.</p>
        <p>3. Prepare the filling by bringing the apricots and 2 1/2 cups water to a boil. Boil for 2 minutes. Let cool completely, then drain apricots and roughly chop.</p>
        <p>4. Dust a work surface lightly with flour. Roll one disc of chilled dough into an 9-by-13-inch rectangle, 1/4 -inch thick. Then cut the rectangle into 3 (9-by-4 1/3-inch) smaller rectangles. Lay each rectangle vertically. Place 2 1/2 to 3 tablespoons apricots on the bottom half of the rectangle. Top with 1 1/2 teaspoons of apricot preserves. Fold the top half of the dough over the fruit and press down along the edges to seal. Using a paring knife, cut away a small amount of the sealed edge to tighten the seal. Cut 4 ( 3/4-inch-long) slits into the sealed end (opposite the fold) to make bear nails. Repeat with the remaining discs of dough. Refrigerate the bear claws for 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>5. Preheat the oven to 375 degrees. Line 2 baking sheets with parchment paper. In a small bowl, whisk together the egg yolk, cream and a few drops of water. Place bear claws on the baking sheets 2 inches apart. Brush the top of each bearclaw with the egg wash, then sprinkle with sugar.</p>
        <p>6. Bake until golden brown, about 30 to 35 minutes. Remove bear claws from the oven and let cool. Makes about 9 bear claws. Adapted from Maury Rubin, the owner of Birdbath bakeries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
