<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>During His Funeral, Falwell Is Praised for Activist Style</title>
    <meta content="23falwell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/23/us/23falwell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1849434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baptist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Moral Majority</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Falwell, Jerry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1D61F31F930A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>During His Funeral, Falwell Is Praised for Activist Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">During His Funeral, Falwell Is Praised for Activist Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>LYNCHBURG, Va., May 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rev. Jerry Falwell was eulogized Tuesday as a daring critic of American life, called by God to his role as a clergyman and political activist.</p>
        <p>''He was called at this particular time to raise high the Gospel banner in America,'' Dr. Jerry Vines, a former president of the Southern Baptist Convention, said at Mr. Falwell's funeral. ''He understood that as Christians, we cannot hide our light under a bushel. He said, 'I was called by our Lord Jesus Christ to confront the culture.' And did he ever confront it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rev. Jerry Falwell was eulogized Tuesday as a daring critic of American life, called by God to his role as a clergyman and political activist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rev. Jerry Falwell was eulogized Tuesday as a daring critic of American life, called by God to his role as a clergyman and political activist.</p>
        <p>''He was called at this particular time to raise high the Gospel banner in America,'' Dr. Jerry Vines, a former president of the Southern Baptist Convention, said at Mr. Falwell's funeral. ''He understood that as Christians, we cannot hide our light under a bushel. He said, 'I was called by our Lord Jesus Christ to confront the culture.' And did he ever confront it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Falwell died May 15 at age 73.</p>
        <p>He founded the Moral Majority almost 30 years ago, seeking to create a mass movement of evangelical Christians and people of other faiths, united by a conservative agenda on abortion, gay rights, patriotism and moral values. In 1980, the Moral Majority was credited with playing a role in the election of Ronald Reagan as president and in dozens of Congressional races.</p>
        <p>Mr. Falwell later disbanded the organization, saying its work was done, but he continued to speak out on the issues of the day.</p>
        <p>The first mourners at the church he founded, the Thomas Road Baptist Church here, began to arrive at 4 a.m., said Chief Charles W. Bennett Jr. of the Lynchburg police.</p>
        <p>Before the doors opened seven hours later for the 1 p.m. service, the line of students and the elderly, toddlers and parents had wrapped around the building and extended for blocks. The Bush administration sent a representative, Tim Goeglein, the deputy director of the Office of Public Liaison at the White House, and evangelical leaders active in Republican politics, including Pat Robertson, streamed into the church. Ralph Reed, a political strategist and former leader of the Christian Coalition, also attended.</p>
        <p>There were few politicians, however, and none of the current presidential candidates attended.</p>
        <p>The funeral also drew protesters from the Westboro Baptist Church of Topeka, Kan., which sent about a dozen members who claimed Mr. Falwell was a friend of gay men and lesbians, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>The A.P. also reported that a student at Liberty University, which was founded by Mr. Falwell, was arrested Monday night after telling a family member that he had made bombs and planned to attend the funeral.</p>
        <p>Officials were still trying to figure out why the man, Mark D. Uhl, 19, made the bombs, described as resembling napalm. Sheriff Terry Gaddy of Campbell County said the Falwell family members were never in any danger.</p>
        <p>At the service, the fond intimate memories of Mr. Falwell's old friends mingled with grand assessments of his legacy offered by his political allies.</p>
        <p>''He was controversial -- Jerry's goal wasn't to be popular,'' said the Rev. Franklin Graham, the son of the Rev. Billy Graham and the president and chief executive of Samaritan's Purse and the Billy Graham Evangelistic Association.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the new generation of evangelical pastors who have taken up issues like AIDS, poverty and global warming, Mr. Graham said: ''I pray to God that these new leaders will be champions of those values that made him controversial. He believed in the Gospel; that's controversial. He believed in the inerrancy of the Bible; that's controversial, the sanctity of life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Falwell had said that he accepted Jesus as his Savior in January 1952, and within a few months, decided he wanted to become a minister. He began Thomas Road Baptist Church in 1956, in Lynchburg, his hometown. Shortly afterward, he started a 30-minute daily radio broadcast, and six months later, a televised version called the ''Old-Time Gospel Hour.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Falwell's congregation grew, and by the early 1970s, he established Liberty University, originally Liberty Baptist College, hoping to make it a national university for evangelicals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goeglein said at the funeral that evidence of the university's success could be seen in the Bush administration. ''I was pleased to tell him that Liberty University had come to the White House,'' he said of Mr. Falwell, ''and that young men and women he had trained were serving as interns and staff.''</p>
        <p>About 10,000 people watched the service at the church and other venues at the university, where it was televised.</p>
        <p>The eulogy was given by Dr. Vines, who, in 2002, called the Prophet Muhammad ''a demon-possessed pedophile.'' Mr. Falwell defended him and then drew criticism himself for calling Muhammad ''a terrorist.'' He later apologized.</p>
        <p>After the efforts to define Mr. Falwell's place in history, his children stood at the pulpit and his daughter, Jeannie Savas, spoke of things that his supporters and critics both would understand: his unconditional love for his children, their worries about his health, his frequent phone calls when he told her how he had prayed for her.</p>
        <p>Once the last songs finished, the family walked behind the pallbearers who brought the rose-covered coffin to a waiting hearse.</p>
        <p>Macel Falwell, Mr. Falwell's widow, wept quietly and leaned on her older son, Jerry Jr. Dr. Savas held her mother's hand and leaned on the chest of her brother Jonathan, who will now become senior pastor of Thomas Road.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
