<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eating the Environment: A Literary Kitchen Cornucopia</title>
    <meta content="15food" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/books/15food.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McNamee, Thomas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Issenberg, Sasha</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Corson, Trevor</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1D6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eating the Environment: A Literary Kitchen Cornucopia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Eating the Environment: A Literary Kitchen Cornucopia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marks &amp; Spencer, the British department-store chain, recently started putting a new symbol on its packaged foods. The store already labels its food with the country of origin and often the name of the farmer. But shoppers who buy strawberries and beans, for example, now see a white airplane on a black circle with the words ''air-freighted.'' This means that the food in question was transported by airplane, leaving a big carbon footprint in the sky. In other words, go ahead and eat the beans, but you have been warned.</p>
        <p>The local-global conundrum, a thoroughly modern predicament, has found its way into a small shelf's worth of new food books. Two of them start with the same premise: that you can shorten the food chain by eating locally. Alisa Smith and her partner, J. B. MacKinnon, tested this hypothesis for a year, restricting their diet to foods found within a 100 miles of their humble cabin in British Columbia. ''Plenty'' is the logbook of their year of eating virtuously, told in alternating chapters. The book is a Canadian counterpart to Barbara Kingsolver's ''Animal, Vegetable, Miracle,'' a similar experiment carried out in the Appalachians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The local-global conundrum, a thoroughly modern predicament, has found its way into a small shelf’s worth of new food books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marks &amp; Spencer, the British department-store chain, recently started putting a new symbol on its packaged foods. The store already labels its food with the country of origin and often the name of the farmer. But shoppers who buy strawberries and beans, for example, now see a white airplane on a black circle with the words ''air-freighted.'' This means that the food in question was transported by airplane, leaving a big carbon footprint in the sky. In other words, go ahead and eat the beans, but you have been warned.</p>
        <p>The local-global conundrum, a thoroughly modern predicament, has found its way into a small shelf's worth of new food books. Two of them start with the same premise: that you can shorten the food chain by eating locally. Alisa Smith and her partner, J. B. MacKinnon, tested this hypothesis for a year, restricting their diet to foods found within a 100 miles of their humble cabin in British Columbia. ''Plenty'' is the logbook of their year of eating virtuously, told in alternating chapters. The book is a Canadian counterpart to Barbara Kingsolver's ''Animal, Vegetable, Miracle,'' a similar experiment carried out in the Appalachians.</p>
        <p>Ms. Smith and Mr. MacKinnon, both vegetarians, quickly make some unpleasant discoveries. Brimming with enthusiasm at the outset, they invite two friends over for a kickoff dinner in March. The strictly indigenous ingredients, purchased at the local organic market, come to $128.87. This is a couple who pride themselves on putting together a dinner for 50 cents back home in Vancouver. Dismay is followed by shock at the discovery that wheat is no longer grown in the region. That rules out a lot of food.</p>
        <p>Eating locally quickly devolves into a punishment diet of root vegetables and tough greens. ''Breakfast might be potato and parsnip fritters made with free-range eggs,'' Ms. Smith writes. ''For lunch, colcannon, the sexed-up name the Irish give to mashed potatoes with kale or cabbage.'' Dinner could be fancy: a rutabaga with grated beet and goat cheese, and sunchokes simmered in milk. Sound tempting?</p>
        <p>There is a dirty secret concealed within the eat-local imperative. In the past humans ate what was nearby because they had no choice. Whenever choice presented itself, they jumped at it. In ''A Movable Feast: Ten Millennia of Food Globalization,'' Kenneth F. Kiple charts the centuries-long push to vary the human diet by acquiring exotic ingredients through trade or conquest.</p>
        <p>Spices, along with lemons, oranges and eggplants, made their way by caravan to the ancient Persians, whose cuisine, disseminated by the Crusades, transformed the cooking of Western Europe. Neapolitan pizza makers rely on a decidedly nonlocal ingredient, the tomato, brought from the New World by Columbus. In a sense, then, eating locally is an intellectual, even alien concept.</p>
        <p>Gamely Ms. Smith and Mr. MacKinnon persist. Desperate for wheat, they buy flour from an old sack left in a farmer's barn and then spend hours separating mouse droppings from the wheatberries. Warmer weather brings more choices, but the local diet takes a toll. Tempers grow strained. The relationship suffers. This is good. It keeps the book from becoming a marathon script for National Public Radio.</p>
        <p>The lust for local flavor finds an eloquent spokesman in Russ Parsons, the food and wine columnist for The Los Angeles Times. ''How to Pick a Peach'' is his answer to the somber reality of the supermarket produce section: ''tomatoes that taste like cotton; peaches that will never drip; strawberries that could bend a fork.''</p>
        <p>Organized as a guidebook, with short chapters on fruits and vegetables from apples to winter squash, ''How to Pick a Peach'' is really a series of elegant biographies, a naturalist's version of Samuel Johnson's ''Lives of the English Poets.'' Practical readers will find value in the tips on, for example, how to size up a melon for ripeness and flavor potential. There are recipes for each ingredient too.</p>
        <p>More literary-minded culinarians will take pleasure in Mr. Parsons's flavorsome thumbnail histories of their favorite fruits, each one a living, idiosyncratic character, and each one threatened by scientists searching for a more durable, more evenly colored, thicker-skinned, longer-lived version of the original. Square, if possible, for easier shipping.</p>
        <p>The benign figure looming over this new food consciousness is Alice Waters, the creator of Chez Panisse in Berkeley, Calif., and the subject of Thomas McNamee's illuminating ''Alice Waters and Chez Panisse.'' Like most revolutionaries Ms. Waters began with a few very simple ideas and stuck to them until everyone around her came to see things her way -- the right way. As a college student she traveled to France, marveled at the taste of fresh ingredients artfully prepared and wondered why America could not have the same thing. The rest is history.</p>
        <p>Mr. McNamee's Alice Waters is a curious creature: shy and inarticulate but able to compel an extraordinary assortment of people to do her bidding. She comes across as maddening, insufferable and inspiring. Impulsive and calculating, intolerant and generous, she is a flower child with steel in her soul. The portrait is convincing.</p>
        <p>Mr. McNamee seems to have talked to everyone connected with Chez Panisse over the years. Too often he simply transcribes their monologues. The year-to-year evolution of any restaurant, even one as important as Chez Panisse, does not make for endlessly fascinating reading. Mr. McNamee's careful reconstruction of the restaurant's early days, however -- especially the chapters on the sparks-a-flying partnership between Ms. Waters and her first great chef, Jeremiah Tower -- sheds badly needed light on a pivotal moment in the history of American thinking about food.</p>
        <p>That thinking is conflicted. Consider sushi, one of the most globalized foods on earth, and one of the most popular too, especially with the sort of diner likely to worry about leaving carbon footprints.</p>
        <p>Sasha Issenberg, in ''The Sushi Economy,'' shrewdly anatomizes this delicacy with more frequent-flier miles than Bono. The infrastructure that puts toro on your plate is stupefying, a complex, technologically ratcheted network of freezer ships, jumbo jets, food conglomerates and fast-thinking brokers that gets fish from the ocean to market, and onward to sushi bars all over the world, at lightning speed.</p>
        <p>In one of his more memorable examples Mr. Issenberg notes that six weeks after the 2004 tsunami devastated Phuket, Thailand, at a time when the local airport's runways were still clogged with planes bringing in relief supplies, jets were already flying bluefin tuna from Phuket's harbor to the United States.</p>
        <p>Trevor Corson, the author of ''The Zen of Fish,'' concentrates on the end product, the small rectangle of fish and vinegared rice that rivals pizza in international appeal. Mr. Corson, the author of ''The Secret Life of Lobsters,'' hitches his narrative to one of the more unusual institutions of higher learning in the United States, the California Sushi Academy in Hermosa Beach, Calif.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corson follows one class through an entire three-month course. This is not a wise decision. True, three months is a mere blink of the eye when compared with the five or more years of training that is traditional in Japan, but it passes very slowly on the page. By the end of the book it's the reader who deserves a diploma.</p>
        <p>On the plus side, Mr. Colson interrupts each lesson to tell the history of sushi, the evolution of its various forms and its remarkable rise to world fame. The digressions make the book. Rarely has a Westerner written so knowledgeably, or entertainingly, about the subject.</p>
        <p>The sushi we know today, a Tokyo specialty of fairly recent invention, has its roots in an old Asian method of preserving fish by packing it in cooked rice and sealing it in a jar for 10 days to a month. The sugars in the rice, attacked by yeasts, produced alcohol, a preservative. After the fish was dug up, the rice, now horribly sour, was brushed away. The taste, according to one 12th-century Japanese source, was ''no different from the vomit of a drunkard.'' With the invention of rice vinegar in the 16th century, the rice itself became part of the dish, and in the 19th century street vendors in Tokyo began selling it in convenient finger-food rectangles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corson explores all this and more with an expert's command of the subject and an eccentric's instinct for the dumbfounding detail. (Sea urchins share 70 percent of their genetic code with humans.) This is the real sushi course, and after 12 weeks the reader emerges not only enlightened but a much better sushi eater.</p>
        <p>One searches in vain for ''sushi'' in ''The Oxford Companion to American Food and Drink.'' It is not, strictly speaking, American, of course. But neither are fish and chips, which have their own entry, and are far less popular. They serve sushi at Soldier Field in Chicago. That has to mean something.</p>
        <p>But this is a quibble. Creating a reference work on American food is inherently problematic because the national cuisine, like the country itself, is a mongrel creation. The development of authentic regional cuisines, a process that took centuries in countries like France and Italy, was cut short by the onslaught of industrialized agriculture and the railroads, which homogenized American food culture.</p>
        <p>Andrew F. Smith, the editor, has faced this task bravely. Working with a multitudinous team of writers, Mr. Smith, a food historian and the author of books on ketchup, popcorn and turkey, has labored mightily to corral America's complicated foodways. The result is a splendid browse-fest, condensed from Oxford's two-volume Encyclopedia of Food and Drink in America.</p>
        <p>Here is the national feast, spread before the reader in all its glory and all its horror. Apple pie and marshmallow fluff get equal billing. Corn bread sits next to Cracker Jack. Clambakes compete with TV dinners, Orville Redenbacher and Dave Thomas with Julia Child and Fannie Farmer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, who wrote many of the entries, holds the mirror up to our food culture, and the reflection is not always flattering. Deep-fried Twinkies? We have only ourselves to blame.</p>
        <p>Global and Local</p>
        <p>Here is information about the books mentioned in this article:</p>
        <p>ALICE WATERS AND CHEZ PANISSE, by Thomas McNamee (Penguin Press); 380 pages. $27.95.</p>
        <p>A MOVABLE FEAST: TEN MILLENNIA OF FOOD GLOBALIZATION, by Kenneth F. Kiple (Cambridge); 368 pages; $27.</p>
        <p>ANIMAL, VEGETABLE, MIRACLE: A YEAR OF FOOD LIFE, by Barbara Kingsolver, with Steven L. Hopp and Camille Kingsolver (HarperCollins); 370 pages; $26.95.</p>
        <p>HOW TO PICK A PEACH: THE SEARCH FOR FLAVOR FROM FARM TO TABLE, by Russ Parsons (Houghton Mifflin); 412 pages; $27.</p>
        <p>THE OXFORD COMPANION TO AMERICAN FOOD AND DRINK, edited by Andrew F. Smith; 693 pages; $49.95.</p>
        <p>PLENTY: ONE MAN, ONE WOMAN AND A RAUCOUS YEAR OF EATING LOCALLY, by Alisa Smith and J. B. MacKinnon (Harmony); 264 pages; $24.</p>
        <p>THE SUSHI ECONOMY: GLOBALIZATION AND THE MAKING OF A MODERN DELICACY, by Sasha Issenberg (Gotham); 323 pages; $26.</p>
        <p>THE ZEN OF FISH, by Trevor Corson (HarperCollins); 372 pages; $24.95.</p>
        <p>BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
