<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="09biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VYING FOR RADIO SPECTRUM -- Some of Silicon Valley's most powerful venture capitalists and technology investors have joined an investment group that is preparing to challenge cellphone carriers and cable and satellite companies for valuable radio spectrum that will be freed when television broadcasters convert to digital signals. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>THE FUTURE OF PRINTERS -- The Internet era has been good to makers of printers so far. But looking ahead, Vyomesh I. Joshi of Hewlett-Packard is concerned that if people find printing Web pages too hard and start printing less, he will have fewer coffee talks where he crows about record revenue, profit, margins and market share. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PRESS RIVALRY IN THE HAMPTONS -- This week perhaps the biggest story in The East Hampton Star involves the paper itself. The Southampton Press, the venerable paper one town over that belongs to the Louchheim family, will introduce a direct competitor, The East Hampton Press, which will come out a day earlier than The Star and will be free. (The Star costs $1.) [C1.]</p>
        <p>NO MORE SLOW BOATS FOR BOOKS -- The post office's decision to stop transporting goods via cargo ship for individual customers may not hurt big online retailers like Amazon.com, which can qualify for discounts. But thousands of smaller used- and rare-book merchants, like Rob Stuart, above, owner of Frenchboro Books in Maine, say they will suffer, because they rely on foreign demand. E-Commerce Report: Bob Tedeschi. [C6.]</p>
        <p>A MERGER COMES UNDONE -- Miles S. Nadal, the chairman and chief executive of MDC Partners, hopes to get ahead in the intensely competitive advertising industry with a contrarian strategy of almost continuous change. But following that philosophy can be fraught with risk, as was demonstrated last week with the unraveling of an acquisition and merger involving two New York agencies, which Mr. Nadal orchestrated less than two years ago. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PROXIES CLEAR AS MUD -- The Securities and Exchange Commission's new disclosure rules on executive pay were supposed to make it easier for investors to understand how top managers were being paid. But piles of new data and proxy statements that are about as easy to parse as the federal tax code have even experts scratching their heads. [C4.]</p>
        <p>A NEW XBOX 360 FEATURE -- Microsoft plans to announce today that it will make its Windows Live Messenger service available on its Xbox 360 game consoles, bringing instant messaging from the computer to the television. [C7.]</p>
        <p>FOUNDATION TAKES ON CLIMATE ISSUE -- The Doris Duke Charitable Foundation is creating a $100 million program to support research intended to encourage policies aimed at reducing the threat of global warming. [C6.]</p>
        <p>A FAKE MYSPACE PROMOTION -- The MySpace fan page with a hot pink background, tribute to Robin Sparkles, a one-hit Canadian teenage pop star from the early 1990s, was just gushing enough to be real. But it wasn't. The MySpace page was a plant, concocted by the producers of the CBS sitcom ''How I Met Your Mother,'' to play off a storyline in the show's Nov. 20 episode. [C8.]</p>
        <p>EXCLUSIVE TO THE CHICAGO TRIBUNE -- Samuel Zell, who has agreed to buy the Tribune Company, gave his first interview exclusively to The Chicago Tribune. There was no conference call with any other Tribune Company reporters who were tracking the deal, including those at The Los Angeles Times or Newsday, or in Baltimore or Hartford. [C8.]</p>
        <p>A STOCK TIP MISSES -- Jim Cramer, host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money,'' recommended on the March 28 episode that viewers sell shares of Dendreon, a biotechnology company in Seattle. The next day, Dendreon's shares tripled when its prostate cancer vaccine was endorsed by a Food and Drug Administration panel. Some viewers are upset. [C8.]</p>
        <p>PLASTIC DOUBLES AS FUEL -- A chemistry professor has developed a ''fuel-latent plastic'' that can be used like ordinary plastic, for packaging or other purposes, but when it is waste, can easily be turned into a substitute diesel fuel. [C5.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VYING FOR RADIO SPECTRUM -- Some of Silicon Valley's most powerful venture capitalists and technology investors have joined an investment group that is preparing to challenge cellphone carriers and cable and satellite companies for valuable radio spectrum that will be freed when television broadcasters convert to digital signals. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>THE FUTURE OF PRINTERS -- The Internet era has been good to makers of printers so far. But looking ahead, Vyomesh I. Joshi of Hewlett-Packard is concerned that if people find printing Web pages too hard and start printing less, he will have fewer coffee talks where he crows about record revenue, profit, margins and market share. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PRESS RIVALRY IN THE HAMPTONS -- This week perhaps the biggest story in The East Hampton Star involves the paper itself. The Southampton Press, the venerable paper one town over that belongs to the Louchheim family, will introduce a direct competitor, The East Hampton Press, which will come out a day earlier than The Star and will be free. (The Star costs $1.) [C1.]</p>
        <p>NO MORE SLOW BOATS FOR BOOKS -- The post office's decision to stop transporting goods via cargo ship for individual customers may not hurt big online retailers like Amazon.com, which can qualify for discounts. But thousands of smaller used- and rare-book merchants, like Rob Stuart, above, owner of Frenchboro Books in Maine, say they will suffer, because they rely on foreign demand. E-Commerce Report: Bob Tedeschi. [C6.]</p>
        <p>A MERGER COMES UNDONE -- Miles S. Nadal, the chairman and chief executive of MDC Partners, hopes to get ahead in the intensely competitive advertising industry with a contrarian strategy of almost continuous change. But following that philosophy can be fraught with risk, as was demonstrated last week with the unraveling of an acquisition and merger involving two New York agencies, which Mr. Nadal orchestrated less than two years ago. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PROXIES CLEAR AS MUD -- The Securities and Exchange Commission's new disclosure rules on executive pay were supposed to make it easier for investors to understand how top managers were being paid. But piles of new data and proxy statements that are about as easy to parse as the federal tax code have even experts scratching their heads. [C4.]</p>
        <p>A NEW XBOX 360 FEATURE -- Microsoft plans to announce today that it will make its Windows Live Messenger service available on its Xbox 360 game consoles, bringing instant messaging from the computer to the television. [C7.]</p>
        <p>FOUNDATION TAKES ON CLIMATE ISSUE -- The Doris Duke Charitable Foundation is creating a $100 million program to support research intended to encourage policies aimed at reducing the threat of global warming. [C6.]</p>
        <p>A FAKE MYSPACE PROMOTION -- The MySpace fan page with a hot pink background, tribute to Robin Sparkles, a one-hit Canadian teenage pop star from the early 1990s, was just gushing enough to be real. But it wasn't. The MySpace page was a plant, concocted by the producers of the CBS sitcom ''How I Met Your Mother,'' to play off a storyline in the show's Nov. 20 episode. [C8.]</p>
        <p>EXCLUSIVE TO THE CHICAGO TRIBUNE -- Samuel Zell, who has agreed to buy the Tribune Company, gave his first interview exclusively to The Chicago Tribune. There was no conference call with any other Tribune Company reporters who were tracking the deal, including those at The Los Angeles Times or Newsday, or in Baltimore or Hartford. [C8.]</p>
        <p>A STOCK TIP MISSES -- Jim Cramer, host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money,'' recommended on the March 28 episode that viewers sell shares of Dendreon, a biotechnology company in Seattle. The next day, Dendreon's shares tripled when its prostate cancer vaccine was endorsed by a Food and Drug Administration panel. Some viewers are upset. [C8.]</p>
        <p>PLASTIC DOUBLES AS FUEL -- A chemistry professor has developed a ''fuel-latent plastic'' that can be used like ordinary plastic, for packaging or other purposes, but when it is waste, can easily be turned into a substitute diesel fuel. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 12, 2007, Thursday  A report in the Today in Business column in Business Day on Monday, about a recommendation by James J. Cramer, the host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money,'' that investors sell Dendreon shares, misstated the timing of events after his comments. Dendreon shares began to rise two days -- not one day -- after the ''sell'' recommendation. (Trading was halted the first day, pending an announcement that Dendreon's prostate cancer vaccine had been endorsed by a Food and Drug Administration panel.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A report in the Today in Business column in Business Day on Monday, about a recommendation by James J. Cramer, the host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money,'' that investors sell Dendreon shares, misstated the timing of events after his comments. Dendreon shares began to rise two days -- not one day -- after the ''sell'' recommendation. (Trading was halted the first day, pending an announcement that Dendreon's prostate cancer vaccine had been endorsed by a Food and Drug Administration panel.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
