<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Be My Neighbor</title>
    <meta content="Morrow.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Morrow.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McKibben, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Deep Economy: The Wealth of Communities and the Durable Future (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Be My Neighbor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Be My Neighbor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LANCE MORROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morrow, Lance</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEEP ECONOMY</p>
        <p>The Wealth of Communities</p>
        <p>and the Durable Future.</p>
        <p>By Bill McKibben.</p>
        <p>261 pp. Times Books/Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill McKibben hopes for a localized, communitarian, small-scale world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEEP ECONOMY</p>
        <p>The Wealth of Communities</p>
        <p>and the Durable Future.</p>
        <p>By Bill McKibben.</p>
        <p>261 pp. Times Books/Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
        <p>Kurt Vonnegut's Billy Pilgrim (in ''Slaughterhouse-Five'') had a famous dream in which the film of time ran backward: bombs re-coalesced, sucking their exploding fire back into dark capsules that flew upward into the planes' bomb bays, while German fighters, as if by magic, closed up the bullet holes they had drilled in the bombers; the bombers flew backward to their bases, and the bombs were returned to America and disassembled and diffused into harmlessness. And Hitler became a baby again. All people became babies, a magic reversion down the ages, back to ''two perfect people named Adam and Eve.''</p>
        <p>There is such a thing as metaphysical sentimentality. Bill McKibben works our damaged planet Earth through a dimension of time reversal and what might be called the physics of Christian beatitude: The future shall be made past, and the big shall be made small; the global shall be restored to the local; the harm may be undone, the seas may recede, the temperatures may drop, the hurricanes may abate and humanity may be returned to its happier mind. At least, we should steer ourselves in that direction. The result, according to McKibben, would not be paradise; but it might be workable in the long term. The alternative, he thinks, is not.</p>
        <p>Actually, McKibben's aim in ''Deep Economy'' is relatively modest -- to change minds, to present ''a new mental model of the possible.'' It's a good time to try. Franklin Roosevelt was able to explore new paradigms of government (try something; if that does not work, try something else) because he took office amid the financial wreckage of early 1933. There may be an equivalent opportunity now -- not because the world economy has failed but because its pace of success (China growing at a rate of nearly 10 percent year after year, for example) and headlong consumption of the planet's resources, especially fossil fuels, may be setting the world up for disaster. Economic rationales (more = better) that came in with Adam Smith and are now achieving gaudy fruition in globalized hallucinations like the new Shanghai or the Palm Islands of Dubai seem spiritually threadbare -- spectacularly pointless. And not only pointless but something worse, stupid. The political and environmental crises of the 21st century may so reconfigure the world's outlook -- or make it so uneasy, anyway -- that basic rethinking becomes possible.</p>
        <p>McKibben says in effect, All right, we are two nations: 1) Wal-Mart Nation (gigantic, globalized, unsustainable in the face of climate change and the trashing of nature and the coming exhaustion of the world's fossil fuels), a world predicted half a century ago by Lucille Ball in the chocolate factory, desperately gobbling oversweet glut from the unstoppable assembly line; and 2) Farmers' Market Nation (manageably small, localized, communitarian, neighborly, calibrated to the human scale).</p>
        <p>McKibben lives and teaches in Vermont, and his vision, for better and for worse, is suffused with a certain Vermontlichkeit. Now and then he has a ghastly idea -- as when, discussing the advantages of public transportation over the (isolating and polluting) private car, he remarks of buses: ''And it wouldn't hurt ... if you could hand the driver one of your CDs and she'd slap it in the sound system. It makes the experience convivial.'' That's McKibben's Frank Capra communitarianism: After all, the folks on the bus in ''It Happened One Night'' had a wonderful time singing ''The Daring Young Man on the Flying Trapeze.'' (2007: Here, driver, I think the other passengers might enjoy one of my classic CDs, ''Reign in Blood,'' by the thrash metal band Slayer.)</p>
        <p>It would be unwise to dismiss McKibben's ideas as pipe dreams or Luddism. He makes his case on anecdotal, environmental, moral and, as it were, aesthetic grounds. An attentive, widely traveled writer and environmentalist, McKibben cites the success of local projects around the world, from a rabbit-raising academy in China to a Guatemalan cooperative that manufacturers farm machinery from old bicycles. He defends his ''economics of neighborliness'' against the charge that it is ''sentimental, nostalgic, some Norman Rockwell old-town-green fantasy.'' In fact, he insists: ''Given the trend lines for phenomena like global warming and oil supply, what's nostalgic and sentimental is to insist that we keep doing what we're doing now simply because it's familiar. The good life of the high-end American suburb is precisely what's doing us in.'' His alternative, an intelligent, socially responsible, nonideological localism -- essentially a readjustment downward of material expectations and therefore of our ''hyperindividualistic'' economic metabolisms -- ''might better provide goods like time and security that we're short of.'' People, he thinks, are ''overliberated. ... We need to once again depend on those around us for something real.'' Ratty and Mole and Badger live like sensible animals; runaway capitalism is Mr. Toad.</p>
        <p>McKibben focuses on questions about the ultimate purposes of economic activity and about how human beings might construct a future. His short-form thesis is: ''A single-minded focus on increasing wealth has driven the planet's ecological systems to the brink of failure, without making us happier.'' He asks: ''How did we screw up?''</p>
        <p>Answer: ''We kept doing something'' -- that is, making more and more money and more and more stuff more and more efficiently -- ''past the point where it worked. Since happiness had increased with income in the past, we assumed it would do so in the future.'' The trick on a global basis, of course, would be to improve the lot of those who have too little while scaling down the overconsumption of those who have too much.</p>
        <p>To attempt to alter the world by increments of local improvisation and conservation is to fight against a mighty tide. The world is flat, all right. It is also a toxic mess. Minds are usually changed on a mass scale only by some dramatic event -- Pearl Harbor, say: Americans, isolationist before Dec. 7, 1941, pitched wholeheartedly into the war thereafter. They mobilized themselves and ultimately won, with the help of a lot of powerful sentimentality. Right now, with the tsunami, Katrina, global melting, the world is cruising along -- somewhere around Munich and Czechoslovakia.</p>
        <p>Lance Morrow's latest book is ''Second Drafts of History,'' a collection of his essays. He is writing a biography of Henry R. Luce.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lance Morrow's latest book is ''Second Drafts of History,'' a collection of his essays. He is writing a biography of Henry R. Luce.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
