<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drive to Cut Emissions Creates Jobs Engine</title>
    <meta content="13starts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/13/business/yourmoney/13starts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: FRESH STARTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DC1531F930A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drive to Cut Emissions Creates Jobs Engine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Drive to Cut Emissions Creates Jobs Engine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE challenge of global warming is moving from rhetoric to the workplace, creating jobs as governments, businesses and environmental groups create markets aimed at reducing greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is that more obvious than in the trading of credits tied to emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases related to global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The job market for climate change experts has evolved as governments, businesses and environmental groups create markets aimed at reducing greenhouse gases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE challenge of global warming is moving from rhetoric to the workplace, creating jobs as governments, businesses and environmental groups create markets aimed at reducing greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is that more obvious than in the trading of credits tied to emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases related to global warming.</p>
        <p>''This is a very dynamic and fast-growing market,'' said Wiley Barbour, executive director of Environmental Resources Trust, a Washington nonprofit group that is working to foster emission markets. ''I can't even hire all the people I need. It's really hard right now to find climate change experts.''</p>
        <p>His group has set up a voluntary registry for companies that want to buy or sell greenhouse gas reduction credits (also called offsets). Environmental Resources would verify the emission credits.</p>
        <p>Emissions programs in the United States set a cap or limit on the amount of a pollutant that can be released. Companies that cannot stay under the limit buy credits from those that emit less than permitted.</p>
        <p>The market for these types of jobs has evolved much more in Europe, which has agreed to curb greenhouse gases under the Kyoto Protocol, a United Nations treaty. But in the United States, which has not agreed to the treaty, the job market is blossoming as businesses realize that more legislation to cap emissions is inevitable. Already, California has passed laws to limit greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>Voluntary efforts are growing as well amid heightened awareness of the dangers of global warming. For example, the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative, a group of Eastern states, is creating a program for trading emission credits.</p>
        <p>Jobs tied to the carbon markets include company project developers, who find ways to reduce emissions; brokers and traders, who bring together companies that want to buy or sell emission credits; and verifiers, who go to a business to validate the credits being offered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barbour said that the people he hires as verifiers typically have science or engineering backgrounds and have a broad understanding of climate change policy. Verifiers with limited experience typically start at an annual salary of about $50,000, he said, with salaries over $100,000 for experts.</p>
        <p>In the corporate world, there is growing demand for ''greenhouse gas coordinators'' and ''sustainability directors,'' whose jobs include managing how much carbon dioxide their company is generating.</p>
        <p>Environmental advocacy groups are looking for people to create programs that will ensure that the trading of carbon emissions credits meets standards and cuts emissions.</p>
        <p>Environmental Defense, for example, has an opening for a carbon market specialist who would help businesses track and reduce greenhouse gas emissions -- a job expected to pay $60,000 to $80,000. The group also has an opening for a carbon finance project team leader to work with the financial services industry to examine how a formal cap would affect current carbon credit markets. The salary is about $100,000.</p>
        <p>''There probably aren't people out there with that direct title in prior jobs, but there are people who have the skill sets that are necessary,'' said Marcia Aronoff, vice president for programs with Environmental Defense in New York.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Stack, a broker with CantorCO2e -- a subsidiary of Cantor Fitzgerald that trades in gases tied to global warming -- said he knew in college that he wanted a job protecting the environment. But only after taking a class at Vermont Law School in environmental law did he realize he wanted a job in trading of emission credits.</p>
        <p>The class examined how companies addressed climate change and studied emissions trading as a way to control the release of greenhouse gases. Mr. Stack read up on the subject and contacted Josh Margolis, a managing director with CantorCO2e, who subsequently hired him.</p>
        <p>''I want to be involved in climate change and doing what I can to stop it,'' said Mr. Stack, who works in the San Francisco office of CantorCO2e. ''I believe businesses will react more to carrots than to sticks.''</p>
        <p>MANY of the jobs related to greenhouse gas emission are evolving out of ones that already existed.</p>
        <p>Brian Anderson was recently named director of environmental management, regulatory affairs and sustainable development for the western division of the Vulcan Materials Company, a major producer of crushed stone, sand and gravel. In his previous job as manager of environmental affairs, he focused on carrying out environmental management systems.</p>
        <p>His new job, which he assumed about two months ago, makes him responsible for how the company responds to climate change. He will help assess Vulcan's carbon emissions and develop ways to manage them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson trained as a geologist and began his career as an environmental consultant in 2002. To prepare for his new responsibilities, he said, he sought training through professional associations. He also works closely with experts and engineers to help the company meet goals like taking inventory of emissions levels for the California Climate Action Registry.</p>
        <p>''Climate change is rapidly evolving and so new to most of us, really, I think time will dictate where the opportunities are in the job market,'' Mr. Anderson said.</p>
        <p>Fresh Starts is a monthly column about emerging jobs and job trends.</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: FRESH STARTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
