<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dinner Disappears, and African Penguins Pay the Price</title>
    <meta content="04robben" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/world/africa/04robben.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ROBBEN ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anchovies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sardines (Fish)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Robben Island (South Africa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crawford, Rob (Marine Scientist)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Africa</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0DF1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dinner Disappears, and African Penguins Pay the Price</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dinner Disappears, and African Penguins Pay the Price</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>ROBBEN ISLAND, South Africa, May 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>African penguins are disappearing for variety of reasons; population of 1.5 million century ago along coasts of Namibia and South Africa is down to 120,000, largely confined to sprinkling of islands off South Africa's tip, including Robben Island; penguin food--anchovies and sardines--is no longer plentiful there; they have relocated east, perhaps because of global warming, and penguins are not mobile enough to follow fish to new home; marine scientist Rob Crawford says experts will meet to decide whether African penguin, now classified as 'vulnerable' bird species, should be reclassified as endangered; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Striding across a barren patch of this windswept isle, Les Underhill paused, then bent down for a closer look at his discovery: one adult African penguin and two three-week-old chicks, huddled in an earthy depression about as big as the average bathroom basin.</p>
        <p>The three gazed upward and cocked their heads sideways, a sure sign of penguin anxiety. This time, at least, they had nothing to fear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Largely confined to a sprinkling of islands off South Africa’s tip, the African penguin, the continent’s only native penguin, is endangered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Striding across a barren patch of this windswept isle, Les Underhill paused, then bent down for a closer look at his discovery: one adult African penguin and two three-week-old chicks, huddled in an earthy depression about as big as the average bathroom basin.</p>
        <p>The three gazed upward and cocked their heads sideways, a sure sign of penguin anxiety. This time, at least, they had nothing to fear.</p>
        <p>''Here's a nest that's exposed to the sun, and exposed to the gulls,'' he said, a note of admiration in his voice. ''And nonetheless, they've managed to pull it off.''</p>
        <p>Lately, that is the exception. These are not good times for Spheniscus demersus -- literally, ''plunging wedge,'' reflecting the African penguin's chunky physique on land and surpassing grace underwater. Mr. Underhill, who holds the unusual title of avian demographer, has been charting the penguin population for years. All the arrows, he said, point down.</p>
        <p>A century ago, at least 1.5 million African penguins waddled and swam the coasts of Namibia and South Africa. Today they are largely confined to a sprinkling of islands off South Africa's tip, including Robben Island, well known as the site of Nelson Mandela's long imprisonment. Experts say there are 120,000 of these penguins at most.</p>
        <p>That number, like Spheniscus itself, is plunging. Since 2001, the number of adult penguins in the two largest colonies -- the other is on Dassen Island, about 40 miles north -- has plummeted by almost 60 percent, to fewer than 18,000 combined.</p>
        <p>''At the moment, the penguins are in real trouble,'' said Mr. Underhill, a statistics expert at the University of Cape Town and vice president of the International Ornithological Committee. ''There have been population movements like this in the past. But this one seems particularly extreme.''</p>
        <p>Were Spheniscus a seagoing crow or, say, a chicken, fewer people might care. But the African penguin, the continent's only native penguin, is adorable -- not two feet tall at adulthood, with large eyes set in a field of red and a distinctive black stripe circumnavigating its belly. Its calls range from a delicate trill to a loud nighttime bray, which leads some to call it the ''jackass penguin.''</p>
        <p>Though the blue crane is South Africa's national bird, the penguin clearly captures more hearts. Most penguins live on islands, shielded from land predators. But one colony on the Cape of Good Hope peninsula annually lures tens of thousands of gawkers, who revel in walking among throngs of the tolerant creatures.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists here have made the birds' rescue into a public crusade, contending, in effect, that the little penguin is the canary in the coal mine -- a barometer of problems besetting other seabirds and the oceanic chain of life.</p>
        <p>They could have a point. The penguins' travails have many mothers, but the biggest one is food. African penguins live mostly on anchovies and sardines, which loitered until recently in huge shoals off western South Africa, where Robben and Dassen Islands are situated.</p>
        <p>But starting around 1997, the sardines began to relocate east, closer to Cape Agulhas, Africa's southernmost point. The effect has been to reduce the penguins' main course to a few canapés, and their head count shows it: in some years, the adult penguin population on Robben and Dassen has slumped by as much as 25 percent. .</p>
        <p>More mobile species might simply follow the fish to a new home. The African penguins are prisoners to their island, though, limited to foraging for food in waters no more than about 25 miles offshore. When the sardines leave, the penguins have scant choice but to hunker down and wait for them to return.</p>
        <p>But the fish may not return for decades, if ever. The sardines' relocation may be part of a worldwide shift that occurs every 50 years or so, scientists say. Commercial fishing, which has depleted sardine stocks in other parts of Africa, could be a factor. So might climate change: this month, for example, several dozen scientists concluded that the sardine movements were related to changes in the Benguela Current, a vast, frigid flow of nutrient-rich ocean water from Antarctica up the southwest African coast.</p>
        <p>Some of those changes are cyclical, but others are related to global warming. In some locales, sardines have deserted hotspots to seek the cold waters they prefer. No one knows the long-term effects, said Rob Crawford, a marine scientist at South Africa's department of marine and coastal management.</p>
        <p>''It has to be either fishing or climate or a mixture of both,'' he said of the sardine shift, ''but my hunch is that it's environmental.''</p>
        <p>If so, it would not be the first time the bird had suffered at the hands of man. The first Europeans here wiped out the Robben Island penguin population in an orgy of egg-stealing by about 1800; the birds were reintroduced in 1983. Early settlers also scooped countless tons of penguin guano from islands to use as fertilizer, destroying the soft soil in which the birds dug their subterranean nests.</p>
        <p>Escaped European house cats became feral and feasted on thousands of penguin chicks. Modern man dumped oil in the ocean, killing thousands more; a vast spill off Robben Island in 2000 caused a huge bird-rescue operation, saving perhaps 38,500 penguins.</p>
        <p>Moving the penguins to where the food supply has gone is not considered a good option so far, in part because it might be hard to find a new island habitat to move them to.</p>
        <p>In June, Mr. Crawford said, experts here plan to meet to decide whether Spheniscus, now classified as a ''vulnerable'' bird species, should be reclassified as endangered. Meanwhile, the bird's supporters are trying to do their part, digging holes on Robben and other islands to plant fiberglass ''igloos'' that penguins turn into homes.</p>
        <p>Once covered in soil, the igloos give the birds a cool nesting place and protect their chicks from the penguins' nemesis, the hulking, aggressive kelp gull. Penguin lovers are seeking donations for more homes, a process explained on the Avian Demography Unit's Web site, http://web.uct.ac.za/depts/stats/adu/dyerislandconstrust.htm</p>
        <p>Mr. Underhill, who has disposed of all but a handful of the 100 or so feral cats on Robben Island, said the igloos are the next big thing in boosting the penguins' chances. ''The harsh reality,'' he said, '' is that they have no other defense.''</p>
        <p>ROBBEN ISLAND JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
