<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Complaints on Both Sides, Europeans Accept Open Skies Accord With U.S.</title>
    <meta content="23skies" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/23/business/worldbusiness/23skies.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1834910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Nicola</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bilefsky, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrot, Jacques</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF1530F930A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Complaints on Both Sides, Europeans Accept Open Skies Accord With U.S.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europe Approves Trans-Atlantic Air Pact</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLA CLARK and DAN BILEFSKY; Nicola Clark reported from Paris and Dan Bilefsky from Brussels.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Nicola; Bilefsky, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, March 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union transportation ministers approve deal with US to open $18 billion trans-Atlantic aviation market to greater competition, hoping to encourage growth and lower air fares; agreement quickly produces complaints from some European officials and airlines, who say it unfairly favors US carriers; environmentalists are concerned that it could undermine ambitious European climate change goals by encouraging more air travel; Jacques Barrot, European transport commissioner, predicts that over next five years, deal would increase trans-Atlantic traffic by 26 million passengers annually, to about 75 million, and generate billions in economic benefits, like lower fares; adds deal is likely to speed cross-border mergers in European airline industry; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>European Union transportation ministers approved a deal with the United States on Thursday to open the $18 billion trans-Atlantic aviation market to greater competition, hoping to encourage growth and lower air fares.</p>
        <p>But the agreement, years in the negotiating process, quickly produced complaints from some European officials and airlines, who said it unfairly favored United States carriers. Environmentalists expressed concern that it could undermine ambitious European climate change goals by encouraging more air travel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>European Union governments backed a deal with the United States that would open restricted airline routes to new rivals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>European Union transportation ministers approved a deal with the United States on Thursday to open the $18 billion trans-Atlantic aviation market to greater competition, hoping to encourage growth and lower air fares.</p>
        <p>But the agreement, years in the negotiating process, quickly produced complaints from some European officials and airlines, who said it unfairly favored United States carriers. Environmentalists expressed concern that it could undermine ambitious European climate change goals by encouraging more air travel.</p>
        <p>Under the so-called open skies agreement, European and American airlines will be allowed to fly any route between any European city and one in the United States. The change, which will take effect in March 2008, is expected to markedly increase competition in many European countries.</p>
        <p>The United States will be required to loosen foreign ownership rules governing the airline industry.</p>
        <p>While the accord retains a 25 percent limit on foreign ownership of voting stock in United States carriers, it allows European investors to acquire nonvoting majority stakes in American carriers, scrapping a rule that gave United States officials the right to block such purchases. The Europeans reserve the right to lower the limit on American investment in European carriers to 25 percent, from 49 percent now.</p>
        <p>The European transport commissioner, Jacques Barrot, predicted that over the next five years, the deal would increase trans-Atlantic traffic by 26 million passengers annually, to about 75 million, and generate billions in economic benefits, like lower fares.</p>
        <p>He added that the agreement was likely to speed cross-border mergers in the European airline industry. Shares of Lufthansa of Germany and Iberia Airlines of Spain have rallied in recent days as investors anticipated merger talks between the two.</p>
        <p>An American deputy assistant transportation secretary, John R. Byerly, said in Washington that he did not expect the deal to face serious trouble in Congress, which has the power to block it. But he offered no commitments that Washington would accede in coming years to politically difficult European demands, like a further relaxation of foreign ownership rules or granting European airlines access to domestic routes.</p>
        <p>Some European officials are unhappy that the agreement allows United States carriers to offer services between European countries while keeping European airlines from competing on almost all American domestic routes. For example, Lufthansa can fly from Frankfurt to Atlanta but cannot carry passengers from Atlanta onward to another American city. But a United States carrier could fly from Atlanta to London and then on to Rome.</p>
        <p>Under pressure from Britain, which initially lobbied against the agreement, European governments agreed that countries could restrict access to their airports if Washington did not agree to additional measures to open competition.</p>
        <p>The transportation ministers also agreed to delay putting the deal into effect, until next March, to give Britain time to finish a fifth terminal at the severely congested Heathrow Airport near London, which accounts for more than 40 percent of all flights from Europe to the United States.</p>
        <p>Risks of the deal unraveling remain. Labor groups in the United States have strongly resisted efforts to peel back American ownership restrictions, fearing job cuts.</p>
        <p>British Airways urged the government in London to exercise its right to withdraw from the accord if Washington refused to agree to a follow-up deal increasing foreign ownership rights in American carriers.</p>
        <p>The airlines' chief executive, Willie Walsh, asserted: ''The E.U. is naïve to believe that the U.S. will deliver on the next stage of liberalization without sanctions. Nothing short of an open-aviation area by 2010 will be acceptable.''</p>
        <p>But a competitor welcomed the accord. Virgin Atlantic, which has already started making plans to take advantage of the deal -- expanding its flights from European capitals to New York -- said it was a step in the right direction.</p>
        <p>Continental Airlines said it filed an application with the Transportation Department for rights to serve new routes in Europe once the agreement took effect. It said it planned to fly from Houston to Heathrow before summer 2008 if it gets the necessary takeoff and landing slots. It also plans to fly to Paris from a hub in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>The deal is expected to be signed at a European-American meeting of leaders on April 30.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
