<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rethinking the European Car; In Germany, a Question of Speed vs. Emissions</title>
    <meta content="08green" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/08/automobiles/08green.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1831451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mercedes-Benz</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Porsche Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Audi Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fiat Spa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Renault Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citroen (French Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkel, Angela (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Merkel, Angela</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4DE1231F93BA35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rethinking the European Car; In Germany, a Question of Speed vs. Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Europe, Germany May Have to Take the Wheel in Going Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, March 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European automakers BMW, Mercedes-Benz, Porsche and Audi will fall well short of emission reductions they and other European manufacturers pledged to reach voluntarily, from 1998 to 2008; European Union, stung by this failure, has proposed making cuts mandatory by 2012; under its plan, new cars could emit no more than 120 grams of carbon dioxide per kilometer; average emissions were 163 grams per kilometer in 2004; Fiat has reduced its carbon dioxide emissions by almost one third since 1997, and is not far above 120-gram target; Renault and Citroen are also within striking distance; environmentalists argue that simplest way to cut emissions would be to impose speed limit equivalent to 75 miles per hour on autobahn; Germany is only European country that permits drivers to go as fast as they want, though on limited stretches; German politicians, even Chancellor Angela Merkel, have come out in favor of speed limit; some German auto executives predict dire consequences if new limits become law; say strict emissions cap would rule out most of models that BMW, Mercedes, Audi and Porsche produce; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Europe prides itself on its pioneering approach to climate change -- a commitment that Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany aims to deepen in her term as president of the European Union.</p>
        <p>There is just one problem: her country, home of the autobahn and the Porsche sports cars that tear along it, is among Europe's worst offenders when it comes to cars that spew carbon dioxide into the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In getting European automakers to adhere to new limits on carbon dioxide emissions, Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany will have to take on the industry at home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Europe prides itself on its pioneering approach to climate change -- a commitment that Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany aims to deepen in her term as president of the European Union.</p>
        <p>There is just one problem: her country, home of the autobahn and the Porsche sports cars that tear along it, is among Europe's worst offenders when it comes to cars that spew carbon dioxide into the air.</p>
        <p>To persuade Europe to accept stringent new cuts in carbon dioxide emissions, as Mrs. Merkel plans to do at a European Union summit meeting in Brussels this week, she must also face down the German auto industry, which has, until now, done little to make its cars more climate-friendly.</p>
        <p>German auto executives concede that they will have to do more, especially since passenger car emissions account for 12 percent of Europe's total emissions, and are rising rather than falling, unlike overall greenhouse gases here. But the industry's reluctance to fully embrace the fears about climate change was palpable at the International Motor Show in Geneva this week.</p>
        <p>''We are at the moment in a hype phase, or you can say, a hysterical phase, and we have to wait until the smoke is gone,'' Norbert Reithofer, the chief executive of BMW, said in an interview. ''When we have all the facts on the table, we can have a realistic view about the future.''</p>
        <p>Skepticism aside, Mr. Reithofer said BMW was already equipping its cars with new technology that made their engines burn less fuel and emit fewer gases. The public would be surprised, he said, by the reduction in emissions that BMW will achieve by the end of next year.</p>
        <p>Still, BMW and its rivals Mercedes-Benz, Porsche and Audi, will fall well short of the reductions they and other European manufacturers pledged to reach voluntarily, from 1998 to 2008.</p>
        <p>Stung by this failure, the European Commission has proposed making those cuts mandatory by 2012. Under its plan, new cars could emit no more than 120 grams of carbon dioxide per kilometer (192 grams per mile). In 2004, average emissions were 163 grams per kilometer.</p>
        <p>''They had a long time to comply, and they didn't do it,'' said Stephan Singer, the head of the European climate and energy unit at the World Wildlife Fund in Brussels. ''It tells us that voluntary agreements don't work.''</p>
        <p>Not all European carmakers are climate offenders. Fiat of Italy, which has reduced its carbon dioxide emissions by almost a third since 1997, is not far above the 120-gram target. The French carmakers Renault and Citroën, which emphasize smaller cars, are also within striking distance.</p>
        <p>And the Germans do make some climate-friendly cars: DaimlerChrysler showed off its Smart minicar here, which falls under the emissions cap, while BMW's new diesel 1-series, a subcompact, comes close.</p>
        <p>The trouble is, Germany's auto industry derives most of its profit, not to mention its global renown, from its speedy high-performance cars. Unlike Toyota, which has turned hybrid vehicles like the Prius into a calling card, German carmakers emphasize engineering brawn.</p>
        <p>In Geneva, for example, Audi thrilled enthusiasts with its new R8, a two-seater that has more in common with a racecar than with other Audis. Across the hall, visitors mobbed Porsche's sports cars.</p>
        <p>''The top speed of an average new car made by BMW, Mercedes and Audi is 235 kilometers per hour,'' or 146 miles per hour, said Werner Reh, head of the transport department at Bund, a German environmental group. ''If you build racing cars, you can't really reduce consumption.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists argue that the simplest way to cut emissions would be to impose a speed limit equivalent to 75 miles an hour on the autobahn. Germany is the only European country that permits drivers to go as fast as their cars, or their nerves, will let them -- though on limited stretches.</p>
        <p>Yet few German politicians, even Mrs. Merkel, have come out in favor of a speed limit. To Germans, newspapers here say, a no-limit autobahn is like pasta to an Italian or a baguette to a Frenchman.</p>
        <p>Some German auto executives predict dire consequences if the new limits become law. A strict emissions cap of 120 grams, some note, would rule out most of the models that BMW, Mercedes and Audi now produce -- to say nothing of Porsche, the biggest emitter. That would have untold consequences for an industry that is one of Germany's largest employers.</p>
        <p>They also argue that it is unfair to penalize companies whose high-end cars may emit fewer gases, in the aggregate, than small cars.</p>
        <p>''A Lamborghini is driven maybe 3,000 kilometers a year, while a Volkswagen Polo might be driven 30,000 kilometers a year, generating more carbon,'' said Rupert Stadler, the chief executive of Audi, which, like the sports car maker Lamborghini, is part of the Volkswagen group.</p>
        <p>In fact, the European Commission is likely to impose the limits on an average basis for Europe's entire fleet of new cars. Under such a plan, Lamborghini could keep selling high-emitting cars, as long as Fiat sold enough low emitters to bring Europe's average under the limit.</p>
        <p>To achieve that, experts say, Europe could institute a trading regime like that used to limit emissions by power plants and chemical factories. Porsche, for example, could buy emissions points from a low emitter like Fiat, and pass them along to its customers in the form of a higher sticker price.</p>
        <p>The German car industry managed to extract a compromise from Brussels. Automakers will be required to get emissions down to only 130 grams through their own technologies. The commission said they could make up the remaining 10 grams, to reach the 120-gram goal, through other efficiency measures, like greater use of biofuels.</p>
        <p>Experts said Mrs. Merkel was unlikely to focus on cars at the Brussels meeting, instead pushing countries to accept a broader target of reducing carbon emissions by 20 percent from their 1990 levels by 2020.</p>
        <p>For their part, German auto executives are planning to live with lower emissions, even if some say the debate is overheated.</p>
        <p>In Geneva, the companies promoted new technologies that would make their cars more efficient. DaimlerChrysler is pushing a new generation of clean diesel engines, which it calls Bluetec. (European carmakers continue to emphasize diesel over hybrid gasoline-and-electric engines.)</p>
        <p>BMW uses the phrase ''efficient dynamics'' to refer to innovations like auto start/stop, which shuts a car's engine when it comes to a stop in a traffic jam, for example, or at a light. As soon as the driver pushes on the clutch or the gas pedal, the engine restarts.</p>
        <p>''I don't see BMW as a green company,'' Mr. Reithofer said. ''I see BMW as a very innovative company.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
