<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The D.J. Rocked, And TV Shook</title>
    <meta content="06brow" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/arts/television/06brow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DVD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WKRP in Cincinnati (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Loni</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reid, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDF103EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The D.J. Rocked, And TV Shook</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The D.J. Rocked, and TV Shook</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 1978-82 television program WKRP in Cincinnati, whose first season has just been released on DVD; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH it was never meant to be the stuff of conventional entertainment, too much rock 'n' roll has become just that. Rock stars are featured in reality shows and tabloids; previously sacrosanct Led Zeppelin and Nirvana songs are plugged into commercials and soundtracks; ''American Idol'' has devoted an entire evening to cluelessly sung renditions of British Invasion hits. The refrain of a Pink Floyd classic, ''Welcome to the Machine,'' has never stung more.</p>
        <p>As implausible as it may seem, there was actually a time when rock 'n' roll was deemed dangerous, or at least threatening. That long-ago world is evoked by the DVD release of the first season of ''WKRP in Cincinnati,'' the 1978-82 CBS sitcom about a loser easy-listening station that switches to a rock format. In the first episode a group calling itself Haters of Rock 'n' Roll protests the change. Settling into his office, the new program director, Andy Travis (Gary Sandy), immediately pins up a -- shocking! -- Kiss poster. The gonzo counterculture-leftover D.J. Johnny Fever (Howard Hesseman) makes the first of many not-so-veiled drug references.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was actually a time when rock ’n’ roll was deemed dangerous, or at least threatening. That long-ago world is evoked by the DVD release of the first season of “WKRP in Cincinnati,” the 1978-82 CBS sitcom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH it was never meant to be the stuff of conventional entertainment, too much rock 'n' roll has become just that. Rock stars are featured in reality shows and tabloids; previously sacrosanct Led Zeppelin and Nirvana songs are plugged into commercials and soundtracks; ''American Idol'' has devoted an entire evening to cluelessly sung renditions of British Invasion hits. The refrain of a Pink Floyd classic, ''Welcome to the Machine,'' has never stung more.</p>
        <p>As implausible as it may seem, there was actually a time when rock 'n' roll was deemed dangerous, or at least threatening. That long-ago world is evoked by the DVD release of the first season of ''WKRP in Cincinnati,'' the 1978-82 CBS sitcom about a loser easy-listening station that switches to a rock format. In the first episode a group calling itself Haters of Rock 'n' Roll protests the change. Settling into his office, the new program director, Andy Travis (Gary Sandy), immediately pins up a -- shocking! -- Kiss poster. The gonzo counterculture-leftover D.J. Johnny Fever (Howard Hesseman) makes the first of many not-so-veiled drug references.</p>
        <p>In another episode the station is the host of a concert by a nihilistic fictitious ''punk'' band called Scum of the Earth. With three-piece suits and ersatz hard rock, Scum is more like a cartoonish heavy metal band, but what matters is the idea that rock once unnerved people.</p>
        <p>In the world of ''WKRP,'' rock 'n' roll was still the province of Commie-pinko degenerates intent on undermining American values. (In one particularly quaint touch, especially in light of the Don Imus storm, Fever loses his job at another station by saying ''booger'' on the air.) ''It's the dungarees versus the suits,'' decries the leering, polyester-encased ad salesman, Herb Tarlek (Frank Bonner), a comment that sums up the show's recurring us-versus-them theme.</p>
        <p>During its run ''WKRP'' seemed as disreputable as the music itself. It was the work of MTM, which also created ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show,'' and the shows shared a basic premise: Outsider goes to work for media outlet and adjusts to wacky characters who toil there. Yet in a TV Guide interview at the time a former MTM executive sneered at ''WKRP's'' forays into slapstick (compared with the more adult humor of MTM shows like ''Rhoda''). And even though ''WKRP'' was nominated for 10 Emmys, it took home only one (for videotape editing).</p>
        <p>Yet as the DVD shows, ''WKRP'' was funnier than the muddled ''Rhoda,'' and the pinup-primed secretary Jennifer Marlowe (Loni Anderson) employed a sex-as-empowerment strategy that now seems a precursor to Madonna's.</p>
        <p>The show reveled in black humor (''Turkeys Away,'' about a Thanksgiving giveaway gone horribly, hysterically wrong) and had its share of somber moments (the pimp-dressing nighttime D.J. Venus Flytrap, played by Tim Reid, is discovered to be a Vietnam deserter). Speaking of solemn themes, one could spend hours pondering the impact on the ozone layer of all the hairspray used to keep Ms. Anderson's and Mr. Sandy's hair in all their immovable '70s glory.</p>
        <p>In one unfortunate regard, though, ''WKRP'' still gets no respect. At one point Johnny Fever cues up Blondie's ''Heart of Glass''; instead, what we hear is a generic rock instrumental. That is repeated through the DVD box. Thanks to the high cost of licensing oldies, the period rock, funk, new wave and soul records spun by Fever and Flytrap have largely been replaced with no-name music.</p>
        <p>Stripped of the original soundtrack that fueled it, ''WKRP in Cincinnati'' loses a bit of its soul on DVD. Then again, so has the music in the years since. ''WKRP'' brings back a time not only when rock was still somewhat underground, but also when radio stations had D.J.s with quirky personalities and individual tastes (instead of anonymous ''Jack'' formats). While it's a relief that the days of anti-rock censorship groups are history, ''WKRP'' makes you wish a few Haters of Rock 'n' Roll still hovered somewhere out there.</p>
        <p>DVD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
