<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Polk Awards Laud Coverage Of Darfur and Katrina's Toll</title>
    <meta content="20polk" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/20/nyregion/20polk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1827577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DD123EF933A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Polk Awards Laud Coverage Of Darfur and Katrina's Toll</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Polk Awards Laud Coverage of Darfur and Katrina’s Toll</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spike Lee's documentary on Hurricane Katrina, and journalists who covered the war in Darfur and exposed medical and environmental dangers and shady financial and political practices were among the winners of 12 George Polk Awards for 2006 announced yesterday by Long Island University.</p>
        <p>Nine awards went to reporters of The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal, The Los Angeles Times, The Baltimore Sun and four other newspapers and a news magazine, while an NBC Nightly News team and 11 journalism students at the University of California at Berkeley were cited for work in the tradition of George W. Polk, a CBS correspondent killed in 1948 covering the civil war in Greece.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The winners of the George Polk Awards for 2006 were announced yesterday by Long Island University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spike Lee's documentary on Hurricane Katrina, and journalists who covered the war in Darfur and exposed medical and environmental dangers and shady financial and political practices were among the winners of 12 George Polk Awards for 2006 announced yesterday by Long Island University.</p>
        <p>Nine awards went to reporters of The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal, The Los Angeles Times, The Baltimore Sun and four other newspapers and a news magazine, while an NBC Nightly News team and 11 journalism students at the University of California at Berkeley were cited for work in the tradition of George W. Polk, a CBS correspondent killed in 1948 covering the civil war in Greece.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee, the director, and Sam Pollard, his producer and supervising editor, were honored for their two-part, four-hour HBO documentary, ''When the Levees Broke: A Requiem in Four Acts,'' a panorama of the stories of many who lost everything in New Orleans and of the failures of government in the aftermath of the devastating hurricane.</p>
        <p>Lydia Polgreen of The New York Times won the foreign reporting Polk for her coverage of the war in Darfur in western Sudan and Chad, which has killed 200,000 people and driven 2.5 million from their homes. She was cited for ''courageous and often exclusive'' reports that ''gave voice to the victims of the conflict -- terrified villagers and displaced survivors -- alerting the world to their suffering.''</p>
        <p>From ''NBC Nightly News With Brian Williams,'' Lisa Myers, a senior investigative correspondent, and Adam Ciralsky, a producer, won the television reporting award for exposing what it called unfair preferential treatment in the awarding of a $70 million contract to Raytheon Company to develop a system to combat rocket-propelled grenades. An Israeli system had already been found to be effective. Congress is reviewing the circumstances.</p>
        <p>The military reporting Polk went to Lisa Chedekel and Matthew Kauffman of The Hartford Courant for a four-part series, ''Mentally Unfit, Forced to Fight,'' detailing a high rate of suicide among American troops, many of them under the severe stress of combat in Iraq, and flawed mental health screening and treatment by the military services.</p>
        <p>Robert Little, a national correspondent for The Baltimore Sun, won the medical reporting award for a three-part series, ''Dangerous Remedy,'' examining the use of an experimental blood-coagulating drug on more than 1,000 soldiers, although it had been linked to fatal clots in the heart, lungs and brain.</p>
        <p>The environmental reporting Polk went to Kenneth R. Weiss and Usha Lee McFarling of The Los Angeles Times. Their five-part investigative series, ''Altered Oceans,'' found that rashes among Australian fishermen, brain-damaged sea lions in California and red tides that sickened beachgoers in Florida were all linked to waste disposal, industrial pollution and other human activities that are harming the ecology of the oceans.</p>
        <p>The award for business reporting went to Charles Forelle, James Bandler and Mark Maremont of The Wall Street Journal. The reporters exposed a widespread practice of backdating stock options that allowed executives to unfairly spike their compensation. The articles set off federal investigations into more than 130 companies, prompted scores of resignations and led to various criminal charges.</p>
        <p>Jeff Kosseff, Bryan Denson and Les Zaitz of The Oregonian, in Portland, won the national reporting Polk for articles exposing failures in a $2.25 billion federal program intended to help blind and other disabled people find jobs. While the program enriched executives, it left many workers in jobs paying less than the minimum wage. The articles prompted a federal inquiry, lawsuits and resignations.</p>
        <p>Debbie Cenziper of The Miami Herald won the award for metropolitan reporting for ''House of Lies,'' a yearlong investigation that virtually toppled the Miami-Dade Housing Agency. She documented spending and mismanagement that allowed developers and consultants to amass fortunes while families suffered in shelters and rat-infested buildings. An inquiry led to the dismissal of housing officials and a reorganization of the agency, as well as emergency repairs and rent subsidies.</p>
        <p>The local reporting award went to the staff of Lakefront Outlook, a free Chicago weekly. Its editor, four reporters and an intern investigated the $19.5 million Harold Washington Cultural Center, hailed by a city alderman, Dorothy Tillman, as the cornerstone of a neighborhood's rebirth. The articles exposed it as deficit-ridden and staffed by Ms. Tillman's family, friends and political cronies.</p>
        <p>Ray Ring, the northern Rockies editor of High Country News, a biweekly news magazine based in Paonia, Colo., won for political reporting by following a money trail that financed campaigns for looser land-use regulations in six Western states. Much of the money, he discovered, came from a wealthy libertarian real estate investor. Voters in three of the six states last November rejected ballot measures that would have rolled back regulations aimed at controlling growth and protecting the environment.</p>
        <p>The radio reporting Polk went to ''Early Signs: Reports From a Warming Planet,'' a seven-month project in which 11 journalism students covered what they called the human miseries and ecological perils of global warming in diverse locales, including the slopes of Mount Kilimanjaro in Tanzania and the outskirts of Auckland, New Zealand. The reports were produced and edited by the Graduate School of Journalism at the University of California at Berkeley, American Public Media and ''Living on Earth,'' an independent media program.</p>
        <p>The Polk Awards are to be presented at a luncheon at the Roosevelt Hotel in Manhattan on April 12. Established in 1949, the awards are administered by Long Island University. Winners are selected by a jury of faculty members and alumni from entries submitted by journalists and news organizations and nominations by a panel of editors, reporters and journalism teachers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
