<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rush for Uranium; Mines in the West Reopen as Ore Prices Reach Highs of the 1970s</title>
    <meta content="28uranium" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/28/business/28uranium.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1836292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uranium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventories (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denison Energy Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moran, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">raup, anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shumway, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uranium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Utah</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDA1330F93BA15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rush for Uranium; Mines in the West Reopen as Ore Prices Reach Highs of the 1970s</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Uranium Ignites ‘Gold Rush’ in the West</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN MORAN and ANNE RAUP</byline>
      <dateline>LA SAL, Utah</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Revival of uranium mining in Western states has less to do with renewed interest in nuclear power as alternative to greenhouse-gas-belching coal plants than to convoluted economics and intense speculation surrounding metal that has pushed up price of uranium to levels not seen since heyday of industry in mid-1970's; prices for uranium ore, also called U308, or yellowcake, are rising rapidly; yellowcake is trading at $90 per pound, nearing record high, adjusted for inflation, or about $120 in mid-1970s; price has more than doubled in last six months; price was below $10 in late 2002; string of natural disasters, notably flooding of large mines in Canada and Australia, has set off most recent spike; hedge funds have accelerated price rally; more fundamental causes of uninterrupted ascendance of prices since 2003 can be traced to inventory constraints among power companies and drying up of excess supply of uranium from old Soviet-era nuclear weapons that was converted to use in power plants; surge in demand from China, India, Russia and other countries has led to price increases; Mike Shumway, who owns contracting business that is working on Pandora mine owned by Denison Mines in La Sal, Utah, comments; graph; map; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Given its connotations, Pandora is an oddly inappropriate name for an uranium mine.</p>
        <p>But that does not seem to bother Denison Mines, the company from Vancouver, British Columbia, that owns it. Denison recently reopened this mine about 30 miles southeast of Moab, along with several others in nearby western Colorado, after it lay dormant during the years when the nation shunned nuclear power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Convoluted economics and intense speculation have pushed up the price of uranium to levels not seen since the heyday of the industry in the mid-1970s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Given its connotations, Pandora is an oddly inappropriate name for an uranium mine.</p>
        <p>But that does not seem to bother Denison Mines, the company from Vancouver, British Columbia, that owns it. Denison recently reopened this mine about 30 miles southeast of Moab, along with several others in nearby western Colorado, after it lay dormant during the years when the nation shunned nuclear power.</p>
        <p>The revival of uranium mining in the West, though, has less to do with the renewed interest in nuclear power as an alternative to greenhouse-gas-belching coal plants than to the convoluted economics and intense speculation surrounding the metal that has pushed up the price of uranium to levels not seen since the heyday of the industry in the mid-1970s.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of staking going on,'' said Mike Shumway, a 53-year-old Vietnam veteran who owns the contracting business that is working the Pandora mine. ''It's like the gold rush.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shumway has personally amassed some 100 uranium claims, including four dormant but potentially rich mines. Some of the claims he bought quietly after less tenacious prospectors could not afford to hold theirs during the long drought while uranium was out of favor. Mr. Shumway's eyes light up and he cracks a grin as he ponders the fortune he now hopes to gain.</p>
        <p>''There's big money in it,'' he said as he probed piles of waste ore at Pandora with a Geiger counter. ''What other work do you know of where you can make millions in 30 days?''</p>
        <p>Not many. Prices for processed uranium ore, also called U308, or yellowcake, are rising rapidly. Yellowcake is trading at $90 a pound, nearing the record high, adjusted for inflation, of about $120 in the mid-1970s. The price has more than doubled in the last six months alone. As recently as late 2002, it was below $10.</p>
        <p>A string of natural disasters, notably flooding of large mines in Canada and Australia, has set off the most recent spike. Hedge funds and other institutional investors, who began buying up uranium in late 2004 to exploit the volatility in this relatively small market, have accelerated the price rally.</p>
        <p>But the more fundamental causes of the uninterrupted ascendance of prices since 2003 can be traced to inventory constraints among power companies and a drying up of the excess supply of uranium from old Soviet-era nuclear weapons that was converted to use in power plants. Add in to those factors the expected surge in demand from China, India, Russia and a few other countries for new nuclear power plants to fuel their growing economies.</p>
        <p>''I'd call it lucky timing,'' said David Miller, a Wyoming legislator and president of the Strathmore Mineral Corporation, a uranium development firm. ''Three relatively independent factors -- dwindling supplies of inventory, low overall production from the handful of uranium miners that survived the 25-year drought and rising concerns about global warming -- all have coincided to drive the current uranium price higher by more than 1,000 percent since 2001.''</p>
        <p>Strathmore controls more than three million acres of exploration projects in Canada and previously discovered sources in the United States, primarily around Grants, N.M. In its heyday, the Grants ''uranium belt'' provided 340 million pounds of uranium, making New Mexico an even larger producer than Utah or Wyoming. Some politicians in the area hope there will be a new wave of mines, mills and jobs.</p>
        <p>Strathmore, with a market capitalization of $300 million, is one of about 400 publicly traded uranium stock companies (most of them, like Strathmore, trade on the Toronto Stock Exchange). Many of the companies are much smaller. Some are essentially shells.</p>
        <p>''There's so much money pouring into this sector,'' said Julie Ickes, editor and publisher of StockInterview.com, which tracks uranium prices and companies. ''If you put 'uranium' in your company name, you can look like you're looking for property,'' he said. ''It's a lot of talk.''</p>
        <p>The feverish trading in speculative uranium company shares harks back to the early 1950s, when some 500 stocks traded on the Salt Lake City Penny Stock Exchange. Moab called itself ''the uranium capital of the world.''</p>
        <p>''You could say there were more millionaires than people here in Moab,'' said Sam Taylor, 73, who has been publisher of the local weekly, The Times-Independent, since he took it over from his father in 1956.</p>
        <p>Sitting stooped over his wooden desk at the newspaper's office downtown, Mr. Taylor recalls how he got ''the scoop of the century'' when a young, cocky geologist named Charlie Steen pulled up in his battered jeep asking if The Times-Independent would publish his six-page paper on his recent discovery of pitchblende, or high-grade uranium.</p>
        <p>Not long after, Moab lost its quietude and anonymity to the ore trucks roaring through town almost around the clock to deliver uranium to a mill on the north edge of town.</p>
        <p>Globally, 180 million pounds of processed uranium are consumed each year by nuclear power plants. Production worldwide from mines amounts to only 100 million pounds. Roughly 75 million pounds come out of utility company stockpiles. What is actually traded in the spot market is only about 35 million pounds.</p>
        <p>Some industry watchers fear the uranium market is entering the bust phase of another boom-bust cycle.</p>
        <p>''It's like the tech bubble,'' said James Finch, senior editor of StockInterview.com. ''We're waiting for the crash.''</p>
        <p>But others see plenty of room for prices to climb. One is Bob Mitchell, founder of Adit Capital, a small hedge fund in Portland, Ore. In December of 2004, he became one of the first hedge fund managers to start buying uranium.</p>
        <p>Since then other hedge funds and institutional investors have jumped into the market, some of them hoarding uranium while the price keeps rising. Even some established mining production companies are spinning off or becoming partners with hedge funds.</p>
        <p>Uranium executives, investors and analysts alike agree that a major underlying cause of the current bull market is that mines are not generating enough uranium to meet growing demand. The supply constraints can be traced back to the end of the cold war when the United States and the former Soviet Union started converting enriched uranium from dismantled atomic weapons into nuclear fuel for peaceful purposes.</p>
        <p>That program, and huge incentives offered to uranium companies by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, flooded the market with excess supply. At the same time, demand shrank. The price of uranium fell sharply.</p>
        <p>As a result, most uranium producers scaled back or closed their mines. Some companies sold themselves to French, Canadian and British corporations, which now dominate the industry. Some companies with nuclear power operations sold some of their inventories when the price was low to avoid storage costs.</p>
        <p>But by 2003 uranium inventories held by utilities in the United States were coming back into balance. Then a series of natural disasters -- flooding of the world's largest uranium mine, McArthur River in Canada, and more recently at other mines in Canada and Australia -- further pinched supply. Power companies now find themselves competing with aggressive institutional investors for high-price uranium.</p>
        <p>''For so long they'd been the buyer in a buyer's market,'' said Gene Clark, chief executive of TradeTech.com, a publisher of reports and data on the nuclear fuel market. ''Now they're like a wallflower. It's hard on their egos.''</p>
        <p>James Malone, vice president of nuclear fuels at the Exelon Corporation, the Chicago-based utility that owns 17 reactors at 10 sites, making it the largest nuclear operator in the country, said in a telephone interview that current market conditions were having a ''small impact'' on some of the company's contracts that were pegged to the market price. He declined to elaborate.</p>
        <p>The people staking claims and drilling underground are, in the meantime, happy to see the frothy market become frothier. So far this year, 2,700 new uranium claims have been filed with the Bureau of Land Management in Colorado alone. That is nearly half the claims filed in all of last year, and a big jump from the 104 claims for 2004.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty spectacular,'' said Jesse Broskey, a land law adjudicator with the bureau. ''It's tripled our workload.''</p>
        <p>But many people in the region, including leaders of the Navajo Nation, are not particularly excited to invite Pandora and other participants in the nuclear industry back into their communities. They say the mining and power companies poisoned workers and residents, in some cases fatally, with radon, silica and tainted groundwater.</p>
        <p>More stringent federal oversight means that mines built or refurbished today provide much better ventilation, which minimizes the underground risks. Mine operators are required to take readings of radon levels and air flow in the mines, and to measure miners' exposure doses.</p>
        <p>Another red flag, for environmentalists and utilities alike, is the lack of a national storage site for radioactive waste. The proposed home, Yucca Mountain in Nevada, has cost taxpayers billions over many years as it sits idly, waiting for a final decision.</p>
        <p>That is one of several factors holding back the revival of nuclear power in the United States. ''We won't build a new plant knowing there's nowhere to put the used fuel,'' Mr. Malone of Exelon said. ''We won't build one without community support, and we won't build until market conditions are in place where it makes sense.''</p>
        <p>But that is not holding back Kyle Kimmerle, owner of the Kimmerle Funeral Home in Moab. Mr. Kimmerle, 30, spent summers during his childhood camping and working at several of his father's mines in the area. In his spare time he has amassed more than 600 uranium claims throughout the once-productive Colorado Plateau.</p>
        <p>''My guess is that next year my name won't be on the sign of this funeral home anymore and I'll be out at the mines,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He recently struck a deal with a company to lease 111 of his claims for development. The company, new to uranium mining, has pledged $500,000 a year for five years to improve the properties. Mr. Kimmerle will receive annual payments plus royalties for any uranium mined from the area.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's jumping in while the price is going up,'' he said. ''Sure, it'll eventually go down. It's not going to be in three years. But after 10 years I'd say all bets are off.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
