<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="13biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1825930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2D71F3FF930A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STATES TRANSFORM HEALTH CARE -- State governors and legislatures are transforming the nation's health care system by putting affordable health insurance within reach of millions of Americans. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>JUST LIKE THE NINETIES? -- This decade's rate of growth has nearly mirrored the first five years of expansion in the 1990s, when corporate profits and the stock market surged. But as workers finally reap some of the spoils of a growing economy, many forecasters worry -- as they did a decade earlier -- that the expansion is running out of steam. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PUTIN DISCUSSES A GAS CARTEL -- In Qatar, President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia, below, discussed trade, security and the formation of a natural gas cartel on the second leg of a three-day Middle East trip thought to be an effort by Russia to expand its strategic role in the region. [A14.]</p>
        <p>TROUBLE IN IRAN'S OIL INDUSTRY -- Western political and economic pressure on Iran over its nuclear program has chilled foreign investment so much that it is now squeezing the country's long-fragile energy industry, straining a government that is both burdened by sanctions and trying to prevent unrest at home. [C1.]</p>
        <p>S.E.C. SEEKS TO LIMIT SUITS -- The Securities and Exchange Commission has begun to take steps on two fronts to protect corporations, one to make it harder for shareholders to prevail in fraud lawsuits against publicly traded companies and their executives and another to protect accounting firms from large damage awards in cases brought by investors and companies. [C1.]</p>
        <p>QUESTIONS FOR VODAFONE -- A day after Vodafone, the British telecommunications company, agreed to pay $11.1 billion to acquire control of Hutchison Essar, an Indian cellphone operator, analysts began wondering whether the British company's management could impose the proper cost discipline. [C1.]</p>
        <p>HOME DEPOT MAY SELL UNIT -- Home Depot said it would consider selling off its supply division, and several private equity firms said they were interested in buying the unit, a network of companies that supply professional builders. But can Home Depot manage its revival without its fastest-growing business? [C1.]</p>
        <p>CLIMATE CHANGE AND PROFITS -- Ceres, a coalition of investors and environmental groups, says that investors have filed 42 resolutions asking how a variety of companies are preparing to adapt to the impact climate change could have on their corporate bottom lines. [C3.]</p>
        <p>TRIBUNE SELLS HOY NEW YORK -- The Tribune Company sold Hoy New York, its Spanish-language newspaper, to ImpreMedia, a top Spanish-language publisher. [C3.]</p>
        <p>LAYOFFS AT MTV -- MTV Networks plans to dismiss 250 people, the company's chief executive, Judy McGrath, told employees in an e-mail message. [C7.]</p>
        <p>NEW AD CAMPAIGN FOR VISA -- Visa USA has a new advertising campaign for its wealthiest customers to raise awareness of its premium-rewards cards and to reposition itself as a contender in the high-end credit marketplace. [C7.]</p>
        <p>SAFETY AND DRUG-COATED STENTS -- Stents to prop open coronary arteries have produced ''enormous health benefits'' for millions of Americans, but the widespread use of the newer drug-coated version on patients who are sicker than those tested in clinical trials makes it hard to assess safety risks, a leading medical journal reports. [C3.]</p>
        <p>FOUR SEASONS HOTELS SOLD -- The directors of Four Seasons Hotels endorsed a $3.37 billion all-cash bid to take the company private. The offer came from the chain's founder, a Saudi holding company and Bill Gates's investment firm. [C6.]</p>
        <p>LET THE BIDDING BEGIN -- Boeing says it has it has tweaked the design of its long-range KC-767 refueling jet in its effort to win a $40 billion Air Force contact to replace 179 planes. But whether it will be enough to hold off Northrup Grumman, which is expected to offer its KC-30, a modified Airbus A330, remains to be seen. [C2.]</p>
        <p>LOVE IS IN THE AIR -- Workplace love affairs have been studied, but romances forged on business trips remain largely unexamined by psychologists. But Cupid hovers, arrow poised, in hotel lobbies, convention halls, airport bars and on planes, striking unsuspecting hearts at the most unlikely times. [C8.]</p>
        <p>IN THE NAME OF CHEAPER TRAVEL -- With its roadwarrior.com Web site, Orbitz is trying offer lower-cost travel to individuals or small companies, which spend up to $20,000 a year on travel without the benefit of discounts big companies can negotiate. On the Road: Joe Sharkey. [C8.]</p>
        <p>TOUGH BEING A TRAVEL WRITER -- How does 11 days in the Florida Keys sound? Not so good for this frequent flier. [C9.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>DAVID WITTIG, THE FORMER top executive of Westar Energy, was released from prison on bond Monday, pending the appeal of his sentence in a bank fraud case. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRICELINE.COM, THE ONLINE travel company, said that its quarterly profit rose sharply as Europeans booked more travel on the company's main site there. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STATES TRANSFORM HEALTH CARE -- State governors and legislatures are transforming the nation's health care system by putting affordable health insurance within reach of millions of Americans. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>JUST LIKE THE NINETIES? -- This decade's rate of growth has nearly mirrored the first five years of expansion in the 1990s, when corporate profits and the stock market surged. But as workers finally reap some of the spoils of a growing economy, many forecasters worry -- as they did a decade earlier -- that the expansion is running out of steam. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PUTIN DISCUSSES A GAS CARTEL -- In Qatar, President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia, below, discussed trade, security and the formation of a natural gas cartel on the second leg of a three-day Middle East trip thought to be an effort by Russia to expand its strategic role in the region. [A14.]</p>
        <p>TROUBLE IN IRAN'S OIL INDUSTRY -- Western political and economic pressure on Iran over its nuclear program has chilled foreign investment so much that it is now squeezing the country's long-fragile energy industry, straining a government that is both burdened by sanctions and trying to prevent unrest at home. [C1.]</p>
        <p>S.E.C. SEEKS TO LIMIT SUITS -- The Securities and Exchange Commission has begun to take steps on two fronts to protect corporations, one to make it harder for shareholders to prevail in fraud lawsuits against publicly traded companies and their executives and another to protect accounting firms from large damage awards in cases brought by investors and companies. [C1.]</p>
        <p>QUESTIONS FOR VODAFONE -- A day after Vodafone, the British telecommunications company, agreed to pay $11.1 billion to acquire control of Hutchison Essar, an Indian cellphone operator, analysts began wondering whether the British company's management could impose the proper cost discipline. [C1.]</p>
        <p>HOME DEPOT MAY SELL UNIT -- Home Depot said it would consider selling off its supply division, and several private equity firms said they were interested in buying the unit, a network of companies that supply professional builders. But can Home Depot manage its revival without its fastest-growing business? [C1.]</p>
        <p>CLIMATE CHANGE AND PROFITS -- Ceres, a coalition of investors and environmental groups, says that investors have filed 42 resolutions asking how a variety of companies are preparing to adapt to the impact climate change could have on their corporate bottom lines. [C3.]</p>
        <p>TRIBUNE SELLS HOY NEW YORK -- The Tribune Company sold Hoy New York, its Spanish-language newspaper, to ImpreMedia, a top Spanish-language publisher. [C3.]</p>
        <p>LAYOFFS AT MTV -- MTV Networks plans to dismiss 250 people, the company's chief executive, Judy McGrath, told employees in an e-mail message. [C7.]</p>
        <p>NEW AD CAMPAIGN FOR VISA -- Visa USA has a new advertising campaign for its wealthiest customers to raise awareness of its premium-rewards cards and to reposition itself as a contender in the high-end credit marketplace. [C7.]</p>
        <p>SAFETY AND DRUG-COATED STENTS -- Stents to prop open coronary arteries have produced ''enormous health benefits'' for millions of Americans, but the widespread use of the newer drug-coated version on patients who are sicker than those tested in clinical trials makes it hard to assess safety risks, a leading medical journal reports. [C3.]</p>
        <p>FOUR SEASONS HOTELS SOLD -- The directors of Four Seasons Hotels endorsed a $3.37 billion all-cash bid to take the company private. The offer came from the chain's founder, a Saudi holding company and Bill Gates's investment firm. [C6.]</p>
        <p>LET THE BIDDING BEGIN -- Boeing says it has it has tweaked the design of its long-range KC-767 refueling jet in its effort to win a $40 billion Air Force contact to replace 179 planes. But whether it will be enough to hold off Northrup Grumman, which is expected to offer its KC-30, a modified Airbus A330, remains to be seen. [C2.]</p>
        <p>LOVE IS IN THE AIR -- Workplace love affairs have been studied, but romances forged on business trips remain largely unexamined by psychologists. But Cupid hovers, arrow poised, in hotel lobbies, convention halls, airport bars and on planes, striking unsuspecting hearts at the most unlikely times. [C8.]</p>
        <p>IN THE NAME OF CHEAPER TRAVEL -- With its roadwarrior.com Web site, Orbitz is trying offer lower-cost travel to individuals or small companies, which spend up to $20,000 a year on travel without the benefit of discounts big companies can negotiate. On the Road: Joe Sharkey. [C8.]</p>
        <p>TOUGH BEING A TRAVEL WRITER -- How does 11 days in the Florida Keys sound? Not so good for this frequent flier. [C9.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>DAVID WITTIG, THE FORMER top executive of Westar Energy, was released from prison on bond Monday, pending the appeal of his sentence in a bank fraud case. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRICELINE.COM, THE ONLINE travel company, said that its quarterly profit rose sharply as Europeans booked more travel on the company's main site there. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
