<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Storm, Parking Tickets and an Outcry</title>
    <meta content="16parking" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/16/nyregion/16parking.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1826601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan, Sewell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farmer, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sanitation Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4DE143EF935A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Storm, Parking Tickets and an Outcry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Storm, Parking Tickets and an Outcry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN and MARIA NEWMAN; Ann Farmer contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell; Farmer, Ann; Newman, Maria</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Mayor Michael R Bloomberg faces harsh criticism from car owners over not suspending alternate-side parking rules after snowstorm; drivers say snowplows buried their cars while clearing streets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As drivers dug themselves out from Wednesday's modest but messy snowstorm, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg found himself on the defensive over the city's decision not to suspend alternate-side parking rules. That move had residents complaining that their cars were ticketed after plows buried them in snow.</p>
        <p>The mayor was at times curt, testy and defensive as he answered questions from reporters at a Sanitation Department garage in Woodside, Queens, yesterday, even suggesting that New Yorkers stop ''griping'' about the situation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg found himself on the defensive over the city’s decision not to suspend alternate-side parking rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As drivers dug themselves out from Wednesday's modest but messy snowstorm, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg found himself on the defensive over the city's decision not to suspend alternate-side parking rules. That move had residents complaining that their cars were ticketed after plows buried them in snow.</p>
        <p>The mayor was at times curt, testy and defensive as he answered questions from reporters at a Sanitation Department garage in Woodside, Queens, yesterday, even suggesting that New Yorkers stop ''griping'' about the situation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg said the Sanitation Department had done ''a spectacular job'' of clearing the streets. There were ''a lot of fender-benders,'' he said, but no major accidents. ''We want to get the snow and ice off the roads as quickly as possible so emergency vehicles can get through, so that you can get to work, so that the kids can get to school,'' he said. ''And if we all do it together rather than griping, we'll be better off.''</p>
        <p>But asking New Yorkers not to gripe is like asking for mayonnaise on a pastrami sandwich -- highly unlikely.</p>
        <p>Even if the situation did not approach the furor of February 1969, when parts of Queens were left unplowed for nearly a week after a crippling blizzard and Mayor John V. Lindsay bore the brunt of angry ridicule, complaints were prevalent yesterday, when the temperature ranged from 15 to 24 degrees.</p>
        <p>''I have to dig out the car, and where am I going to put it?'' Carol Jolley, 50, asked in frustration. A stay-at-home mother in Windsor Terrace, Brooklyn, she used a garden shovel to excavate her Volvo sedan from a two-foot snow mound.</p>
        <p>''Take a look around,'' she said. ''I have no place to put it. And then when I come back, this spot will be gone. All my good work for nothing.''</p>
        <p>In prior years, Ms. Jolley maintained, the city usually relaxed parking rules the day after a storm. ''This is cruel and unusual punishment,'' she said. ''I've lived here all my life, and I don't remember them doing this so soon after a snow.''</p>
        <p>Nearby, Eric Feldman, 50, a sound editor who was moving his Ford Explorer, said that enforcement of the rules served little purpose. ''It's going to make the roads more dangerous,'' he said, ''because you've got cars double-parked and some staying in place.''</p>
        <p>In Forest Hills, Queens, Paul Goldfarb, 29, who works at Columbia University, said he woke up at 5:30 a.m. hoping the parking rules would be suspended. ''I was sort of incredulous that they hadn't been,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Another driver, Lois C. Schwartz, said, ''I'm 71 years old and I did somehow manage to extricate my car today, but not without great effort, thanks to the snowbank left by a plow.'' She said that ''travel was treacherous" from her home in the West Village to Lincoln Center. ''And where were the plows yesterday afternoon?''</p>
        <p>After a storm, the Sanitation and Transportation Departments jointly decide whether to suspend parking rules, and the mayor said that officials, seeking to expedite cleaning, ''deliberately did not suspend'' them for the two inches of snow.</p>
        <p>Asked about irritated drivers, Mr. Bloomberg said: ''They're going to enjoy it tomorrow when the streets are cleaner than they would have otherwise been. And this was not a lot of snow. It was easy to move your car. I don't like to get up early in the morning and have to do anything, either. I'd like to sleep in, too. But it was the right thing to do.''</p>
        <p>The mayor, who typically takes the subway to work from his Upper East Side town house, dismissed complaints about the difficulty of moving cars. ''It wasn't like you had a couple of feet of snow, where you really couldn't physically move your car,'' he said. ''You had to put on galoshes and go out there and move it.''</p>
        <p>Michael T. Delfin, 24, a photographer in Clinton Hill, Brooklyn, said it was not so easy. It took him 20 minutes to move his Ford Explorer across the street. ''I cannot imagine what kind of city official would tell its residents, especially senior citizens and people with children, to go out on those unplowed ice sheets and move the car,'' he said. ''For street cleaning? Somebody call 311.''</p>
        <p>Many did, flooding the city's 311 help line yesterday with questions about parking rules and school closings. (The city's schools were open.)</p>
        <p>The situation may ease with temperatures rising to the low 30s by tomorrow and no more snow in the immediate forecast.</p>
        <p>Every street with alternate-side rules was to be plowed twice, the mayor said. Along with its fleet of vehicles, the Sanitation Department used workers with shovels to clear the areas around crosswalks and bus stops. ''The department, I think, once again showed that it can handle anything Old Man Winter can throw at us,'' the mayor said, praising the sanitation workers behind him.</p>
        <p>By yesterday afternoon, the department had placed workers on 12-hour shifts, sent out more than 2,000 pieces of equipment, plowed all of the city's more than 5,000 miles of streets at least once and used about 50,000 of the 185,000 tons of salt on hand. ''Salt has been spread on 100 percent of the major roads, 96 percent of the secondary streets and 76 percent of the tertiary streets,'' the mayor declared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg conceded that the patterns of the storm -- mild snow followed by freezing sleet and rain -- made the cleanup harder than usual. The plows are most effective, officials said, when at least two inches have accumulated. ''It probably would have been easier, actually, if we had six inches of snow,'' Mr. Bloomberg said. ''We probably could have plowed it right away.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
