<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tobacco Road</title>
    <meta content="Miles.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/books/review/Miles.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Cigarette Century: The Rise, Fall, and Deadly Persistence of the Product That Defined America (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDD133EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tobacco Road</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tobacco Road</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miles, Jonathan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE CIGARETTE CENTURY</p>
        <p>The Rise, Fall, and Deadly Persistence</p>
        <p>of the Product That Defined America.</p>
        <p>By Allan M. Brandt.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 600 pp. Basic Books. $36.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rise and fall of the cigarette in American culture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE CIGARETTE CENTURY</p>
        <p>The Rise, Fall, and Deadly Persistence</p>
        <p>of the Product That Defined America.</p>
        <p>By Allan M. Brandt.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 600 pp. Basic Books. $36.</p>
        <p>It is a familiar exchange: I step up to the counter at a convenience store and order my daily ration of Camel cigarettes, which I have been smoking since the Reagan administration and, as it happens, am smoking as I type this. Sliding the pack across the counter, the clerk -- female clerks, typically; male clerks are more laissez-faire -- sighs and says to me, ''You know you need to quit.'' My response, well honed over the years, goes like this: ''I know I should quit,'' I say, ''but there's one problem. I enjoy it.'' On rare occasions, the clerk startles and smiles -- that's how it played out this morning -- as if tickled by this forbidden admission. Far more frequently, however, I find myself at the receiving end of a uniformly bemused, pitying and faintly disgusted stare. I cannot possibly mean what I have just uttered, the stare says to me. The victim cannot confess to the crime. The cash register rings its tinny ring as the clerk slides the drawer shut and sadly wags her head.</p>
        <p>Allan M. Brandt's ''Cigarette Century,'' a fat chronicle of the rise and fall of the cigarette in the 20th century, delivers that same ruthful stare. Brandt, a professor of the history of medicine at Harvard Medical School, canvasses giant chunks of terrain here -- the culture, science, politics, law and global spread of the cigarette, to cite just his section headings -- without ever pausing to examine the central, vexing paradox of smoking: that in return for death, cigarettes give pleasure. Justifiable pleasure? Of course not. What Kant deemed ''negative pleasure''? Perhaps. But pleasure nonetheless. Smokers, in Brandt's view, are midwifed by an array of potent forces: ferocious tobacco advertising; peer pressure; cultural aesthetics (i.e., the imitable artfulness of Humphrey Bogart cupping a smoke); the addictive properties of nicotine; the tobacco industry's pernicious campaign to obfuscate the perils of smoking; youthful longing for easy rebellion; and even, as evidenced by the boom in smoking after World War I, the scalding stress of trench warfare. But the cigarette itself, outside of its chemical components, gets scant credit. ''One must not forget,'' Jean Cocteau once wrote, ''that the pack of cigarettes, the ceremony that extracts them, lights the lighter, and that strange cloud which penetrates us and which our nostrils puff, have with powerful charms seduced and conquered the world.'' To be immune to those charms is naturally Brandt's prerogative. To refuse or fail to acknowledge them in a history of the cigarette, however, is more problematic, and suggests the question: Is a cigarette sometimes just a cigarette? Or does the totality of its meanings -- up to and including its flavors, fragrance and neurological kick -- stem from a cultural moment, a peculiar and corporate-engineered hinge in time and place?</p>
        <p>''It seems striking,'' Brandt writes, ''that a product of such little utility, ephemeral in its very nature, could be such an encompassing vehicle for understanding the past. But the cigarette permeates 20th-century America as smoke fills an enclosed room.'' The cigarette came of age with, and thanks to, dramatic advances in manufacturing technology and marketing tactics, and was further helped along by the tectonic shifts in consumer culture and social mores that followed World War I. It was, pun intended, a breathtakingly fast rise. In 1904, cigarettes accounted for only 5 percent of the domestic tobacco market. By midcentury, nearly half of all adults smoked. Cigarettes were ubiquitous, with ashtrays freckling every room: nurseries, doctors' offices, TV news studios. The tobacco industry -- a bad seed from the beginning, as Brandt shows (as early as 1908, the American Tobacco Company was battling the feds, this time over antitrust regulations) -- nurtured and exploited that ubiquity. If the health hazards of smoking were not ''proven'' until midcentury, they were readily apparent. Yet scientists, early on, found themselves lumped together with antitobacco moralists in the public mind, which imbued their cautions with the shrill taint of Victorian finger-wagging. Carcinogenesis sounded a lot like degeneracy, and America was happy to blow a collective stream of smoke in the face of that charge.</p>
        <p>ll that changed in the early 1950s, when the causal relationship between smoking and lung cancer was finally ''proven,'' in scientific terms, and more formally ''alleged,'' in tobacco industry parlance. Faced with damning evidence, the industry devised a cagey defense: rather than denying the harms of smoking, it insisted there were ''two sides'' to the story, and corralled skeptical scientists -- perennially available on any subject -- to rebut or at least cast doubt upon the medical consensus. Journalists were urged to consider ''fairness'' and ''balance'' in covering the invented ''controversy.'' The industry's public relations arm, Brandt writes, was ''adept at taking a single dissenter and assuring widespread media coverage of his views.'' This purposeful agnosticism, which served the tobacco industry well, will sound eerily familiar to anyone following the global warming ''debate'' -- another case in which a few pedigreed skeptics, whose views align with those of a powerful industry, are framing consensus as controversy. ''The industry,'' Brandt writes, ''insisted on scientific criteria that it knew full well could not be attained then, or ever.''</p>
        <p>From this point on, ''The Cigarette Century'' morphs into combat history, into a meticulous record of the myriad courtroom clashes that defined the life of the cigarette in the latter years of the 20th century. Brandt's admirable skills as a researcher and analyst are in full flower here, though readers searching for courtroom drama and more human scale should refer to Richard Kluger's Pulitzer Prize-winning ''Ashes to Ashes,'' a silkier, smoother narrative that tracked the tobacco wars up through the mid-1990s. If the tobacco trials have yet to extinguish the industry, as antismoking advocates have been hoping for years, they've certainly delivered mortal wounds -- most effectively, perhaps, in the discovery process, which unearthed decades' worth of slimy industry documents (including one industry idea Brandt quotes, from a 1987 brainstorming session, to deal with health concerns: ''Create a bigger monster (AIDS)'') that has made every cigarette purchase since feel like a deal with the devil, on top of a dance with death. Additional tort action, and ramped-up regulation now that tobacco support has become more of a political liability than an advantage, seems likely to further chip away the number of domestic smokers until just a few of us will remain, huddled in the rain 500 feet away from any possible contact with others, impoverished from taxes and life insurance premiums and the inability to pass a nicotine-finding blood test in order to get a job. Yet the essential conundrum, succinctly stated in a 1961 tobacco-industry memo, will remain: ''There are biologically active materials present in cigarette tobacco. These are: a) cancer causing; b) cancer promoting; c) poisonous; d) stimulating, pleasurable and flavorful.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Miles contributes the ''Shaken and Stirred'' column to the Sunday Styles section of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Miles contributes the ''Shaken and Stirred'' column to the Sunday Styles section of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
