<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Battles at Bank Ended 'Second Chance' at a Career</title>
    <meta content="18worldbank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/18/washington/18worldbank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFDE1131F93BA25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Battles at Bank Ended 'Second Chance' at a Career</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Second Chance’ at Career Goes Sour for Wolfowitz</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven B</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Paul D Wolfowitz examines his career at Pentagon and at World Bank; details events leading to his resignation as president of bank; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz was ready to move on from the Pentagon in early 2005. He had been thwarted in his effort to become defense secretary or national security adviser. And the war in Iraq had deteriorated. So when the World Bank presidency came open, he jumped at the opportunity.</p>
        <p>It offered him a ''second chance'' to redeem his reputation and realize his ambitions, says a friend who has known him for decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Friends and critics wonder if Paul D. Wolfowitz’s tenure at the World Bank was doomed from the outset.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz was ready to move on from the Pentagon in early 2005. He had been thwarted in his effort to become defense secretary or national security adviser. And the war in Iraq had deteriorated. So when the World Bank presidency came open, he jumped at the opportunity.</p>
        <p>It offered him a ''second chance'' to redeem his reputation and realize his ambitions, says a friend who has known him for decades.</p>
        <p>Months later, another friend ran into the new bank president and asked how he was enjoying the job. Mr. Wolfowitz unleashed a torrent of bitter complaints about the bank's bureaucracy, saying it was the worst he had ever seen -- worse than at the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>Now, as friends and critics sort through the wreckage of Mr. Wolfowitz's bank career, they wonder if it was doomed from the outset. Supporters say he arrived at the bank, a citadel of liberalism, from a four-year stint at the Pentagon, where he was an early champion of going to war with Iraq and left bearing its stigma. He was determined to shake up the status quo by rooting out what he saw as corruption and waste, and demanding measurable results from the bank's many aid programs.</p>
        <p>''The bank leadership didn't like Paul challenging their assumptions,'' said Robert B. Holland III, a Texas businessman who represented the Bush administration on the bank board until last year. ''They have all been there a long time, and they are used to promoting each other's interests and scratching each other's back.''</p>
        <p>But others say Mr. Wolfowitz repeated the mistakes he had made at the Pentagon: adopting a single-minded position on certain matters, refusing to entertain alternative views, marginalizing dissenters.</p>
        <p>''Wolfowitz unsettled people from the outset,'' said Manish Bapna, executive director of the Bank Information Center, an independent watchdog group. ''His style was seen as an ad hoc subjective approach to punishing enemies and rewarding friends.''</p>
        <p>At the Pentagon, Mr. Wolfowitz began advocating going to war with Iraq just a few days after Sept. 11, 2001, and continued pressing over the next year to oust Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>His time at the Pentagon was characterized by infighting, especially with the Central Intelligence Agency, which he thought underestimated Iraq as a threat to the United States. He clashed with Gen. Eric K. Shinseki, the Army chief of staff, and others who warned -- correctly, it turned out -- that the United States would need more forces in Iraq. His vision of democracy in the Arab world also ran aground in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>Despite the administration's aversion to multilateral institutions, many at the World Bank had initially hoped that Mr. Wolfowitz -- a neoconservative intellectual, former academic dean and ambassador to Indonesia -- could help forge a new consensus with liberals on ways to aid poor countries more effectively.</p>
        <p>But his low-key intellectual approach to subjects belied a determination to get his way, bank officials say.</p>
        <p>These accounts, which came as Mr. Wolfowitz was negotiating the terms of his departure, are from friends and current and former colleagues who have remained in contact with him.</p>
        <p>The friend who saw Mr. Wolfowitz's term at the bank as a second chance said: ''It was not that he was looking for a redemption from Iraq per se. But he was certainly looking for something to do as a great man in foreign policy, which is how he has always seen himself.''</p>
        <p>Once Mr. Wolfowitz leaves the bank, friends say, he may join the legions of former colleagues, from George J. Tenet of the C.I.A. to L. Paul Bremer III, who led the post-invasion government in Iraq, who have written books and op-ed articles to defend their actions on the war.</p>
        <p>Bank officials say, in fact, that when he arrived there in 2005, Mr. Wolfowitz wanted to write a book about Iraq and accept fees for speeches. That set off his first fight with ethics officers, who told him he could not do so.</p>
        <p>When these proposals were rejected, he soured on the office of the general counsel, Roberto Dañino, a former prime minister of Peru and the first official who suggested to him that Shaha Ali Riza, his companion and a bank employee, could not remain at the bank because Mr. Wolfowitz would be supervising her.</p>
        <p>Recently released bank documents show that Mr. Wolfowitz rejected Mr. Dañino's advice on Ms. Riza and went directly to the bank board's ethics committee in search of a different ruling. He also refused to deal with the general counsel on all other matters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dañino, who was forced to resign last year, told a reporter at the time, ''He presumes that anyone who opposes him is incompetent or corrupt.''</p>
        <p>That battle laid the groundwork for battles with Ad Melkert, the chairman of the ethics committee, and Xavier Coll, a vice president for human resources, over the handling of Ms. Riza's case. The three men became Mr. Wolfowitz's main accusers, charging that he acted unethically in arranging pay raises, a promotion and a transfer for his companion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coll testified that Mr. Wolfowitz told him to keep the terms of Ms. Riza's pay package secret from Mr. Melkert and Mr. Dañino. Mr. Wolfowitz disputed that contention.</p>
        <p>Those disagreements might have faded into irrelevance if Mr. Wolfowitz had not waged other battles with the staff, many bank officials say.</p>
        <p>At an institution obsessed with process, consensus and respect for its civil servants, Mr. Wolfowitz rankled people by bringing in two close aides from the Bush administration, Robin Cleveland and Kevin Kellems, and used them not only as advisers but as managers who issued directives to senior officers.</p>
        <p>Among those with whom he tangled were Christiaan Poortman, a vice president for the Middle East, over Mr. Wolfowitz's demand that the bank establish a greater presence in Iraq. Mr. Poortman, ordered to transfer to Kazakhstan, resigned instead.</p>
        <p>Gobind Nankani, a vice president for Africa, also resigned after disputes with Mr. Wolfowitz over the size of his staff, according to several bank officials.</p>
        <p>One official recalled Mr. Wolfowitz's dressing down several top employees in the Africa division because they could not tell him whether the incidence of malaria among children had declined as a result of the bank's program distributing bed nets to families.</p>
        <p>Another official who left was Shengman Zhang, the top deputy to James D. Wolfensohn, Mr. Wolfowitz's predecessor. Mr. Wolfowitz charged that it was hypocritical for bank officials to allow Mr. Zhang's wife to work at the bank but to banish Ms. Riza.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhang, now a senior vice president at Citigroup in Hong Kong, was furious, several associates say, because bank rules permit husbands and wives to work at the bank under circumscribed conditions, which Mr. Zhang said he followed, but they bar bank employees from having a sexual relationship with a top bank official outside of marriage. A Bush administration official said Mr. Wolfowitz did not understand that a World bank president can be successful only if he can form alliances with the bank's many fiefs, something he failed to do.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cleveland, a former budget official who handled military matters when Mr. Wolfowitz was deputy defense secretary, sometimes delivered the news on major decisions to suspend aid to countries charged with corruption.</p>
        <p>In a dispute with Chad over its use of money from a bank-financed oil pipeline, Ms. Cleveland ordered a suspension of financing, according to several officials, who said it produced unpleasant negotiations and made people angry.</p>
        <p>A similar decision to suspend financing for a health program in India last year rankled the British, a partner in the program.It caused the British development minister, Hilary Benn, to retaliate last fall by withdrawing a nominal amount of funds from another bank program.</p>
        <p>That matter was eventually resolved, but it helped ensure that Mr. Benn and his ally, Gordon Brown, chancellor of the Exchequer and the future prime minister of Britain, would not be in Mr. Wolfowitz's corner in the fight over his future.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Wolfowitz's order to suspend financing for some countries alienated officials in Chad, Kenya, Congo and many other African nations, South Africa, Liberia and other African nations supported his advocacy of honesty in bank activities.</p>
        <p>But suspension of aid to Uzbekistan, which Mr. Wolfowitz said was on grounds of corruption, angered some at the bank who charged that the real motive was Uzbekistan's decision to suspend air rights for United States military operations in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>In his final appeal to the board to save his job, Mr. Wolfowitz promised to change his management style. Mr. Kellems had quit, and Ms. Cleveland had moved out of her office next to Mr. Wolfowitz's.</p>
        <p>In the end, however, his supporters said his willingness to resign came not because he had violated bank rules over the handling of his companion's compensation, but because his leadership style had impeded progress on world poverty and climate change. Whether or not the denouement was inevitable, Mr. Wolfowitz and his supporters came to see it as a result of the war within the bank, not the one in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
