<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First, Cure Malaria. Next, Global Warming.</title>
    <meta content="03stream" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03stream.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SLIPSTREAM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Amyris Biotechnologies</org>
        <org class="online_producer">World Health Organization</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Gates, Bill and Melinda, Foundation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First, Cure Malaria. Next, Global Warming.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">First, Cure Malaria. Next, Global Warming.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON PONTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pontin, Jason</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMYRIS BIOTECHNOLOGIES has almost finished developing a cheap cure for malaria that could save the lives of millions of the poor. Now, using the same technology, this start-up in Emeryville, Calif., wants to create new biofuels that may help save the planet.</p>
        <p>Even in an industry much attached to hyperbole, few companies have excited such high hopes. Investors include the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, which granted the Institute for OneWorld Health $42.6 million to finance Amyris's antimalarial drug, and two princes of Silicon Valley venture capital, John Doerr of Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers, and Vinod Khosla of Khosla Ventures, who, with the private equity group of Texas Pacific Group Ventures, invested $20 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Using a technology that could save the lives of millions of the poor, Amyris Biotechnologies wants to create new biofuels that may help save the planet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMYRIS BIOTECHNOLOGIES has almost finished developing a cheap cure for malaria that could save the lives of millions of the poor. Now, using the same technology, this start-up in Emeryville, Calif., wants to create new biofuels that may help save the planet.</p>
        <p>Even in an industry much attached to hyperbole, few companies have excited such high hopes. Investors include the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, which granted the Institute for OneWorld Health $42.6 million to finance Amyris's antimalarial drug, and two princes of Silicon Valley venture capital, John Doerr of Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers, and Vinod Khosla of Khosla Ventures, who, with the private equity group of Texas Pacific Group Ventures, invested $20 million.</p>
        <p>Explaining his interest in the start-up, Mr. Khosla told me: ''Amyris was using a very sexy technology and applying it in a radical way to malarial drugs. When I asked the question, 'Can you do the same for energy?' the surprising answer was, 'Yes, we can.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doerr said he thought that green technologies ''could be the largest economic opportunity of the 21st century.'' He called Amyris ''the best team to do this kind of work.''</p>
        <p>Amyris's technology derives from the research of Jay D. Keasling, a professor of chemical engineering at the University of California, Berkeley, and the director of the synthetic biology department of the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory. Mr. Keasling's lab is widely credited with making commercially practical an emerging technology called metabolic engineering.</p>
        <p>Until recently, genetic engineering of the sort associated with traditional biotechnology has been limited to modifying a cell's processes by inserting, mutating or deleting a single gene or a few significant genes. Genetic engineering has coaxed microorganisms like the common bacterium E. coli to produce drugs like human insulin, but has produced little else besides such protein drugs and a few antibiotics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Keasling's metabolic engineering is farther-reaching and, potentially, much more productive. His lab has invented techniques that rewrite the metabolisms of microorganisms. By modifying the structure of a microorganism's proteins and adding genes from other organisms, Mr. Keasling has designed microbial factories that can produce a tremendous variety of drugs, biofuels and other chemicals.</p>
        <p>Amyris was founded in the summer of 2003 by Mr. Keasling and three young postdoctoral students from his lab: Neil Renninger, Kinkead Reiling and Jack D. Newman. They received the large grant from the Gates Foundation a little more than a year later.</p>
        <p>To create an antimalarial drug, Amyris engineered bacteria to excrete a drug called artemisinin. Artemisinin is 100 percent effective against malaria, but it derives from a weed called sweet wormwood that only grows in China and Vietnam and costs $2.40 for a course of treatment -- a steep price for the world's poor.</p>
        <p>Every year, 300 million to 500 million people become infected with malaria, according to the World Health Organization; more than 1.5 million of those infected will die, most of them children in Africa and Asia. Amyris's technique would reduce the cost of artemisinin to less than 25 cents for a course of treatment, according to the company. OneWorld Health, a nonprofit pharmaceutical company, has pledged to give away the drug to poor countries. Amyris says the drug will be ready for mass production in 2008.</p>
        <p>It wasn't until January 2006, when a presentation by Mr. Keasling at the World Economic Forum in Davos caught the attention of Mr. Doerr and Mr. Khosla, that Amyris's founders began to consider seriously what other compounds their bioengineered bugs might produce. The two venture capitalists encouraged the scientists to think ambitiously.</p>
        <p>''At nights and on weekends we'd been working on what our for-profit projects could be at the end of the Gates grant,'' Mr. Reiling, the company's vice president for development, told me. ''One of those projects was using our engineering know-how to come up with novel biofuels.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doerr said: ''When I met them, it was truly an open question. Should they work on other pharmaceuticals? Chemicals? And while my passion -- and theirs -- was for fuels and solving global warming, it wasn't at all obvious that they could make a better fuel.''</p>
        <p>Cheap biofuels could eliminate or reduce the use of the fossil fuels whose combustion contributes to climate change. So far, most biofuel ventures have tried to create better ethanol fuels by converting different kinds of ''biomass'' -- everything from corn to sugar cane to switchgrass and jatropha trees -- to fermentable sugars. These sugars can then be brewed and distilled into conventional ethanol.</p>
        <p>Amyris chose to ask something more basic and more interesting: What would perfect fuels look like if they were designed from scratch? The start-up decided to concentrate on the second stage of creating a biofuel: fermenting sugars into fuel.</p>
        <p>The company wanted chemical compounds that could be fermented from sugars derived from any biomass. The fuels had to have an energy content higher than ethanol and be useable in today's automobile, diesel and jet engines. Finally, the company wanted fuels that were insoluble in water, and hence could be transported through the same pipelines that now move oil.</p>
        <p>Over the last year and a half, Amyris has created in its labs microorganisms whose metabolic pathways are yielding alternatives to diesel, jet fuel and gasoline. Now the company is working to make the conversion from sugars to fuel more efficient.</p>
        <p>''If you can get above 90 percent efficiency, you're competitive with ethanol and oil,'' Mr. Reiling explained.</p>
        <p>Most synthetic biologists familiar with Amyris's research say that while the company may have created some promising compounds, the real challenge will be achieving these efficiencies of conversion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doerr expresses the economics more bluntly. ''If you're smart enough,'' he said, ''you can make a better fuel. But to have a business, you have to make it at the right yield and at the right cost.'' Mr. Doerr says he believes Amyris's fuels will need to cost around $30 a barrel (at the moment, less than half the price of crude oil).</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists worry that the adoption of biofuels could lead to the diversion of agricultural land from food to biomass production, raising food prices and further despoiling the environment. In March, the British environmental activist George Monbiot warned in The Guardian that government programs to encourage biofuels were ''a formula for environmental and humanitarian disaster.'' There is some justification for such worries. Earlier this year, increases in the price of maize, caused by swelling demand for corn for ethanol production, led to food riots in Mexico.</p>
        <p>But Amyris's fuels can be fermented from sugars derived from a variety of feed stocks, including switchgrass and jatropha, that are grown on marginal soil that cannot be used for food production. So cultivation of such crops in poorer parts of Africa and Asia might represent an enormous economic opportunity for the regions' farmers.</p>
        <p>Amyris's new chief executive, John G. Melo, who was previously British Petroleum's president for fuel operations in the United States, said that Amyris plans to begin selling biodiesel in 2010, and biofuel replacements for jet fuel and gasoline sometime after that.</p>
        <p>Mr. Melo would not explain in detail how Amyris planned to sell its products. He says the biogas and biodiesel may be sold, blended with gasoline, in gas stations (as ethanol is sold today). But Mr. Melo said he hoped to sell biofuels through alternative channels like large retail chains like Costco. Richard Chavez, a senior vice president of Costco, confirmed that he and Mr. Melo are discussing using Amryis biofuels as an alternative to ethanol for blended fuels. Most intriguing, Mr. Melo also suggested that the Virgin Group, with which Amyris has been negotiating, might sell the start-up's biofuels under its own brand.</p>
        <p>WHILE it is Mr. Melo's job to make Amyris into a big business, Mr. Doerr says the company's scientists are not motivated solely by a desire to enrich themselves; instead, they are excited about Amyris's innovative science and the importance of curing diseases and developing renewable fuels.</p>
        <p>''They haven't been entrepreneurs before and so there's a nobleness and commitment they bring to these problems that I find really inspiring,'' Mr. Doerr said. ''If you told any of them, 'Guess what? You'll only make one-tenth of what you might,' they would continue to do this work.''</p>
        <p>SLIPSTREAM Jason Pontin is the editor in chief and publisher of Technology Review, a magazine and Web site owned by M.I.T. E-mail: pontin@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jason Pontin is the editor in chief and publisher of Technology Review, a magazine and Web site owned by M.I.T. E-mail: pontin@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
