<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Keeping Things Green, the Task Is to Handle More With Less</title>
    <meta content="10peopleliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10peopleli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PARKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ash, Carol (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2D91E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Keeping Things Green, the Task Is to Handle More With Less</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Keeping Things Green, the Task Is to Handle More With Less</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carol Ash, new parks commissioner under New York Gov Eliot Spitzer, comments on development and other issues she faces, particularly on Long Island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DURING George E. Pataki's three terms as governor, the amount of land managed by the State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation increased by 66,000 acres. At the same time, department staffing fell by about 250 and capital improvements languished.</p>
        <p>How to manage more land with fewer people epitomizes the challenges facing Carol Ash, 62, the new parks commissioner under Gov. Eliot Spitzer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>DURING George E. Pataki’s three terms as governor, the amount of land managed by the State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation increased by 66,000 acres. At the same time, department staffing fell by about 250 and capital improvements languished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DURING George E. Pataki's three terms as governor, the amount of land managed by the State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation increased by 66,000 acres. At the same time, department staffing fell by about 250 and capital improvements languished.</p>
        <p>How to manage more land with fewer people epitomizes the challenges facing Carol Ash, 62, the new parks commissioner under Gov. Eliot Spitzer.</p>
        <p>''When we did get the extra land for the parks department it was terrific because we got an extra 26 parks,'' she said. ''The downside is there isn't much infrastructure.''</p>
        <p>Two of those parks -- Brentwood State Park and Jamesport State Park and Preserve -- are on Long Island and will require significant work before they can be opened to the public.</p>
        <p>Brentwood, formerly the Pilgrim Psychiatric Center, is scheduled to include soccer fields, walking paths, parking and public bathrooms. Jamesport, on the site of a former boys' camp on Long Island Sound, will most likely be used for passive recreation like bird-watching and hiking.</p>
        <p>But beyond development issues, Ms. Ash faces a long list of problems, including the complex and costly task of remediation at Nissequogue River State Park, formerly the Kings Park Psychiatric Center. Officials said that although about $600,000 had been invested in creating playgrounds, drinking wells and trails there, it would cost tens of millions of dollars to remove old buildings and address environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>Many of the problems facing the park system were detailed in a 2006 report by Parks and Trails New York, an organization dedicated to protecting parkland.</p>
        <p>''That's what we're beginning to tackle right now,'' Ms. Ash said.</p>
        <p>The cost of the capital improvements outlined in the Parks and Trails' report, ranging from drinking-water issues to dam safety, is estimated at $300 million to $500 million.</p>
        <p>''We feel like the park system is fraying at the edges,'' said Robin Dropkin, executive director of Parks and Trails.</p>
        <p>But she expressed confidence that Ms. Ash, who was executive director of the Palisades Interstate Park Commission the last seven years, could help turn the system around.</p>
        <p>''In the job she just came from, she had to deal with two different state governments plus a very active friends group,'' Ms. Dropkin said. ''She also has a real passion for the issues, which for us is wonderful.''</p>
        <p>As head of the parks department, with a salary of $127,000, Ms. Ash is moving aggressively to assess what needs to be done while adding staff members. Through the $280 million operating budget for 2007, Ms. Ash said she would add 52 staff members; 10 to 12 of them would be tradespeople like masons, electricians and plumbers.</p>
        <p>With a capital budget of only $30 million, she will be examining new ways to finance projects, including grants, private partnership deals and sponsorship arrangements. Ms. Ash is also pushing for changes to the state's bottle bill that would expand the deposit levied on containers from noncarbonated beverages, including water and sport drinks, while channeling unclaimed deposit money to an environmental protection fund that could be used in state parks.</p>
        <p>With the Palisades Interstate Park Commission, Ms. Ash helped manage more than 100,000 acres in New York and New Jersey. Before that she was the New York State director of the Nature Conservancy, a nonprofit group that focuses on land and species preservation.</p>
        <p>In her new job, Ms. Ash, who succeeded Bernadette Castro at the beginning of the year, said she remained committed to creating open spaces that preserve natural species and foster an environment that will combat global warming.</p>
        <p>''We have been losing open space at a huge clip,'' she said. ''It's important to make sure land is protected and take care of what we have.''</p>
        <p>PARKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
