<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patagonia In a New Light</title>
    <meta content="04patagonia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/04/travel/04patagonia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1830303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Torres del Paine National Park (Chile)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Patagonia (Chile)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina/Patagonia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile/Torres del Paine National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Torres del Paine National Park (Patagonia, Chile)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Patagonia (Argentina)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DB1E3EF937A35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="3068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patagonia In a New Light</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Patagonia in a New Light</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Wong travel article on trek along rugged circuit in Torres del Paine National Park in Patagonia, Chile; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE end of the world is wet and cold and covered in mud. Not the kind of mud in which children like to play or the kind that signals a renewal of the earth after a rainfall. This is mud that sucks you into a mire, drags you into the ground, threatening to devour your body while forcing you to slog onward, foot over foot, simply to escape.</p>
        <p>''I can't do it,'' my friend Tini yelled through the rainstorm as she took another step on the trail -- and promptly sank to her thighs in black sludge. ''I can't go on.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeing the spectacular Paine Massif, near the bottom of the world, can be a demanding trek or, with new lodges, a walk in the park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE end of the world is wet and cold and covered in mud. Not the kind of mud in which children like to play or the kind that signals a renewal of the earth after a rainfall. This is mud that sucks you into a mire, drags you into the ground, threatening to devour your body while forcing you to slog onward, foot over foot, simply to escape.</p>
        <p>''I can't do it,'' my friend Tini yelled through the rainstorm as she took another step on the trail -- and promptly sank to her thighs in black sludge. ''I can't go on.''</p>
        <p>We were only an hour into the fourth day of our trek along the rugged Torres del Paine circuit in southern Chile, at the heart of the once mythical corner of the world called Patagonia.</p>
        <p>The borders of Patagonia are difficult to define, but the name generally refers to the glacier-studded, cone-shaped land mass that straddles Chile and Argentina at the tip of South America and tapers down to Cape Horn. For three days, we had been walking counterclockwise around the Paine Massif, circling around the rear of the imposing towers of granite at the center of Chile's premier national park, 30-pound packs on our backs.</p>
        <p>We had planned to spend nine days trekking the entire circuit last winter -- the Southern Hemisphere summer -- with side trips up the Valle Frances and Valle Ascencio, two valleys with some of the best views on the route. It all added up to more than 60 miles.</p>
        <p>This day, the fourth, turned out to be the toughest by far. Nothing in the trek's early stages had prepared us for the long slog up to the John Gardner Pass, where we would cross from the more remote and treacherous eastern-northern half of the circuit to the western and southern sides, where there were large campsites and lodges with bars, restaurants and, if we wanted, catamarans providing a waterborne exit from the trekking route.</p>
        <p>The pass, at 4,072 feet, wasn't high, and altitude sickness was not a concern, unlike in the northern Andes. Just eight months earlier, Tini and I had trudged to the summit of the highest mountain in Africa, Mount Kilimanjaro, at 19,340 feet. But the rain -- nonstop all night and morning -- had transformed the terrain into Mordor.</p>
        <p>So should this be read as a warning to those considering slipping on a backpack laden with a tent, stove and sleeping bag and hopping a flight to these southern reaches?</p>
        <p>Not at all. I have been trekking all over the world, from the High Sierras to the Himalayas, and no place I've been has, at such a low altitude, the jaw-dropping mountain scenery of Patagonia, whether in Torres del Paine National Park in Chile, Los Glaciares National Park in Argentina or any number of other wilderness preserves.</p>
        <p>More and more people are discovering this. Patagonia is no longer the far-flung destination it once was, only for the dedicated trekker or mountaineer. Tourism in Torres del Paine (pronounced PIE-nay) has boomed in recent years, with North Americans, Europeans and wealthy Latin Americans flooding the park in the high season, December to April. In 2005, more than 107,000 people visited the park, a 51 percent increase from 2000 and two and a half times as many as in 1995, according to statistics from the Chilean government.</p>
        <p>But with the crowds have come environmental pressures. In all my backcountry travels, I had never seen as many tents as there were pitched at one popular campsite on the northern shore of Lake Pehoé, south of the Paine Massif. I counted scores. Trekkers jostled for space in a cooking hut.</p>
        <p>The Chilean forest service, Conaf, has not placed a limit yet on the number of visitors. But park officials are doing a study to measure the ideal visitor numbers in areas of high use, said Pablo Retamal, the director of tourism at the Chilean embassy in Washington. That study, along with annual research into environmental impact, will help the government decide ''what actions will be taken to prevent and mitigate environmental impacts,'' Mr. Retamal said.</p>
        <p>Still, for those intending to go to the park, there is a strong argument to be made for making that trip now. Nowhere else are glaciers as accessible as they are in Patagonia. But glaciers there, as in many parts of the world, are retreating at what many scientists consider an alarming rate, because of global warming, they say.</p>
        <p>TINI and I circumnavigated the Paine Massif the hard way, carrying all our own gear and provisions. But people with less masochistic tendencies can see all the highlights of the park from the relative comfort of lodges, eating meals cooked for them at the end of a long day's hike and downing bottles of robust Chilean red wine. A friend recently spent a week in Torres del Paine at the Hotel Salto Chico, run by a company called Explora, where a customer could pay over $5,500 a week for a package with guided activities like horse riding, birding trips and nature walks.</p>
        <p>Yet Patagonia, which encompasses a territory equal to the combined surface areas of Texas and California, remains a lonely place, populated by ranchers whose families have raised livestock for generations. The land is consecrated not to humanity's achievements but to those of nature. Its Andean peaks are among the most glaciated in the entire range, supplying water for ecosystems across the vast, arid plains.</p>
        <p>It has always been a land of legend. After the explorer Ferdinand Magellan passed through on his circumnavigation of the globe, his chronicler Antonio Pigafetta wrote of a race of giants that inhabited the area. The author may have been referring to an indigenous people known as the Tehuelche. In any case, the territory soon acquired the name Patagonia, which my Moon Handbook to Patagonia said was possibly derived from a Spanish romance ''in which a giant named Patagon inhabits an island of fur-wearing hunter-gatherers.''</p>
        <p>From the airport in Punta Arenas, we climbed aboard a bus that took us on a three-hour ride up to Puerto Natales, the gateway town to Torres del Paine. Ranchers on horses galloped across rolling grasslands dotted with pink and purple wildflowers. The light had an intense clarity, as if a winter storm had just passed through. But it was the height of summer, which meant that darkness did not settle across the land until well after 10 p.m., leaving trekkers plenty of time to make it to their campsites each day.</p>
        <p>Puerto Natales surprised me. In the United States, towns at the edges of national parks are often chockablock with tacky souvenir shops, the kind that are lined with shelves of buffalo figurines. Puerto Natales felt much more down to earth, and poorer. Pickup trucks rolled through the town's few streets, and many houses had walls of tin sheeting. But the town, situated on the west coast, had stunning views over Last Hope Sound, with snow peaks rising from islands across the water.</p>
        <p>A large part of the romance of this part of the world is attributed to the popularity of ''In Patagonia,'' a classic 1977 novelistic travelogue by the British writer Bruce Chatwin. He passed through Puerto Natales while researching the book, and described how, during World War I, the English had built slaughterhouses along a four-mile stretch of the bay, complete with a railroad to transport workers here.</p>
        <p>''The Chilotes had their first taste of mechanized slaughter at the killing season,'' Mr. Chatwin wrote. ''It was something like their idea of Hell: so much blood and the floor red and steaming; so many animals kicking and then stiff; so many white-skinned carcasses and spilled-out guts, the tripes, brains, hearts, lungs, livers, tongues. It drove the men a little mad.''</p>
        <p>Tini and I spent a day stocking up on food for the trek, then caught a bus in the morning to the park. As we approached, I glimpsed guanacos, or wild llamas, springing through scrubland. A cowboy drove a herd of horses before him, mountains looming in the distance. The familiarity of these scenes, reproduced so often in postcards and coffee table books, did not diminish their impact.</p>
        <p>We got off the bus, registered at the park entrance and filled our water bottles. Then off we went, following a dirt road past Laguna Amarga and deeper into the park.</p>
        <p>From the entrance, we should have been able to see the three sheer granite peaks that form the central Paine Massif, possibly the most singular and breathtaking sight in all of Patagonia. But the weather spoiled it for us. Gray clouds cloaked the top halves of those mountains.</p>
        <p>I wondered about the chances of rain -- nothing ruins a trek more quickly than a downpour, no matter how much weatherproof gear you're packing.</p>
        <p>It took us a few hours to get used to walking with our packs. The trail was gentle this first day, meandering past an estancia where horses grazed by the path before dropping into a valley carpeted with white daisies. We walked into this valley in the last hour of our trek, when we were exhausted, and at a rest stop we almost literally fell asleep in a bed of daisies.</p>
        <p>The campsite had a flush toilet, hot-shower stall and a dining hall where cooks prepared hot food. And this was supposed to be one of the more spartan sites on the circuit. If this was roughing it, I was more than ready to handle a week of this, I thought as I curled up in my sleeping bag. Tini was already sound asleep.</p>
        <p>The next day's walk took us above expansive Lago Paine and up along the side of a valley where we could see the white sawtoothed Andean peaks dividing Chile and Argentina. We passed through a deformed forest of lenga trees, many blackened and twisted by a recent fire. But they were regenerating.</p>
        <p>That was the thing you learned after spending time in the mountains -- there was never any true destruction when nature was left to its own devices; everything was reborn somehow.</p>
        <p>We ended the day at a campsite by another lake, one with views across the water to an enormous patch of snow and ice called the Ventisquero Dickson. It was the tip of one of the largest icecaps in the Southern Hemisphere, the Hielo del Sur. If the many scientists who assert that these enormous icecaps are fading at an unnatural rate are right, their disappearance will not only rob nature enthusiasts of awe-inspiring views, but also entire ecosystems of fresh water needed for survival.</p>
        <p>For now, the glaciers are still in abundance. I had never seen anything like them outside Patagonia. Not in Tibet, not in Nepal, not even in northern Pakistan, where glaciers tumble to the very edge of one of the highest roads in the world, the Karakoram Highway.</p>
        <p>The next day, we walked up a small glacial moraine -- a mound of gray dirt and rubble pushed together by glacial movement -- and stared down into a turquoise lake with icebergs floating across the surface. The icebergs had broken off from the tip of a glacier that flowed right into the lake.</p>
        <p>That was when it got nasty. I mean really nasty. A fierce wind started up, and we had to partly shut our eyes just to keep out the dirt particles. The sky darkened. We hiked quickly into camp and set up our tent just as the first drops of rain began falling.</p>
        <p>It poured for the rest of the afternoon and did not let up at all during the night. It was quite possibly the heaviest rainfall I have experienced on any trek.</p>
        <p>The weather in Patagonia is temperamental even at the best of times, and people preparing for a trip there spend lots of energy figuring out what gear will keep them dry. I had just bought a new tent that was much lighter than my old one; it was untested, and I was worried whether it would keep out the water.</p>
        <p>It held up better than I expected. I had pitched the tent atop a small depression, so we found ourselves floating in a small pond when we awoke. But none of the water had leaked in.</p>
        <p>UNFORTUNATELY, the rain didn't let up in the morning, the day we were supposed to cross the John Gardner Pass. We took our time eating breakfast, hoping the rain would stop, but finally decided to start out at 11 a.m.</p>
        <p>We stumbled through the mud, steadily following the path as it climbed through a forest. Tini sank to her thighs twice. She gritted her teeth and pulled herself up with her wooden walking stick.</p>
        <p>Once we emerged above the tree line, icefalls appeared on mountainsides all around us. The final stretch to the pass involved a scramble over a steep incline of wet rocks.</p>
        <p>Even in the rain, with clouds hovering over much of the landscape, the top of the pass afforded the most spectacular view we had come across yet -- a sweeping panorama of Grey Glacier, an 11-mile-long sweep of snow and ice that stretched to the horizon.</p>
        <p>The trail leading down on the other side of the pass was so steep and slippery that park workers had fixed ropes along trees so trekkers would have something to hold on to. We still fell on our backsides more than once.</p>
        <p>The crossing of the pass brought us to the easier half of the circuit. The western and southern sides have their share of long-distance trekkers, but are also thronged with day hikers bedding down in expensive lodges like Explora's.</p>
        <p>Some of the park's most spectacular mountain vistas lie on this side -- the massive rock formations of the Cuernos del Paine at the edge of Lago Pehoé, the amphitheater in the French Valley, the three peaks of the Torres del Paine. From a lookout near the Lago Grey campsite, we watched chunks of ice the size of small apartment buildings tumble off Grey Glacier into the lake's turquoise waters.</p>
        <p>We decided to take it easy for the rest of the trek, waking up late and walking slowly along the crowded trails. On Day 6, we ran into Mai and Jaime, a couple whose wedding we attended in Santiago before our trek and who had come south on their honeymoon. It was a pleasant surprise.</p>
        <p>We hung out that night at the new Refugio Lago Pehoé, on the edge of the lake, eating a dinner of chicken, rice and red wine in the restaurant, the Cuernos looming right outside the windows.</p>
        <p>The dinner was a welcome break from the instant noodles I had been cooking every night on my stove. Afterward, we played dominoes and Jenga in an upstairs lounge.</p>
        <p>The lodge was warm, so was the wine. Outside, trekkers scrambled into their tents as a fierce wind swept in from the lake.</p>
        <p>HEADING SOUTH</p>
        <p>GETTING THERE</p>
        <p>My trip to Torres del Paine started with flights from New York to Santiago, Chile. A recent Web search found round-trip fares for that route in mid-March starting at $835 on Avianca via Bogota, Colombia.</p>
        <p>From Santiago, I flew on LAN Chile (www.lan.com) to Punta Arenas, at the southern tip of Chile. A round-trip ticket in mid-March runs about $650.</p>
        <p>Travelers can catch a bus directly from the airport in Punta Arenas to Puerto Natales, the gateway town for Torres del Paine. The ride is three hours and costs 4,000 pesos one way, 7,000 round trip -- about $7.25 and $12.75, at 550 pesos to the dollar. Buses from Puerto Natales to Torres del Paine take two hours and cost 7,000 pesos one way and 12,000 round trip.</p>
        <p>The entrance fee for Torres del Paine National Park is 15,000 pesos in high season (October to April), 10,000 other times.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY</p>
        <p>In Puerto Natales, we stayed at Hospedaje Teresa Ruiz (56-61-410-472), a warm, friendly bed-and-breakfast where the owner, Teresa, has five spacious rooms upstairs with shared bathrooms. The rates are 4,000 pesos a person for a shared bedroom or 4,500 in a private room.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most upscale place in town is the 74-room Hotel Costa Australis, right on the bay (Pedro Montt 262; 56-61-412-000; www.hoteles-australis.com). In high season, double rooms with an ocean view cost $250, others $205.</p>
        <p>Puerto Natales is a good town in which to stock up on food and gear before heading into the park. There are two main supermarkets and several gear shops. Rooms in popular guesthouses and hotels in Puerto Natales are often booked far in advance for the high season.</p>
        <p>On the Torres del Paine circuit, we stayed at campsites every night. Their costs vary, but average about 4,000 pesos a night to pitch your own tent.</p>
        <p>Many sites also have comfortable but basic wooden huts called refugios that charge $16 to $24 a person for a bunk bed and shower. The ones run by a private company called Fantástico Sur (56-61-710-050; www.lastorres.com/lodges) are reputedly better than those run by Conaf, Chile's national forestry agency (www.torresdelpaine.com). Some sites rent out camping gear like tents and sleeping bags.</p>
        <p>Trekkers aiming to walk the entire circuit should plan on carrying their own tents, sleeping bags and cooking gear. Trekkers who do not want to carry all that equipment will have to plan their itinerary carefully.</p>
        <p>The sites on the western-southern half of the circuit are better equipped than those on the less-trodden eastern half. The most upscale lodging in the park is at Hotel Salto Chico, widely known as Explora, on the south side of Lago Pehoé. Four nights run $2,170 to $3,110 a person, double occupancy, including all meals and guided activities like horse riding, birding trips and nature walks.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO EAT</p>
        <p>Pub Concepto Indigo, on Ladrilleros at the corner of Bories (56-61-413-609), is one of the better restaurants in Puerto Natales. Main courses are about 6,000 pesos, and I vividly recall a crab ravioli dish I had for lunch there.</p>
        <p>El Maritimo (Pedro Montt 214; 56-61-414-994) is a decent seafood restaurant with stunning views of the bay and snow-capped peaks across the water.</p>
        <p>In the park, I cooked almost every night but splurged twice by eating at refugios. Meals at the refugios cost from 3,600 to 7,500 pesos. Backpackers can buy foodstuffs at some campsites.</p>
        <p>EDWARD WONG</p>
        <p>EDWARD WONG is a correspondent for The Times in Baghdad.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">EDWARD WONG is a correspondent for The Times in Baghdad.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
