<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Save a Face, Save the World</title>
    <meta content="15CRITIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/15/fashion/15CRITIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1833019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CRITICAL SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Origins (Beauty Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Estee Lauder Companies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albo, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7D71131F936A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Save a Face, Save the World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Save a Face, Save the World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Albo</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Albo, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Critical Shopper column on Flatiron Building branch of Origins, Estee Lauder chain selling environmentally friendly, cruelty-free body-care products; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW I had forgotten the '90s: that optimistic decade when I walked around with my sticky mat and precious new cellphone, as obsessively yogic and introspective as Madonna. I attended Ashtanga classes and imagined peace while in pigeon pose, thinking it was an effective way to contribute to global reform.</p>
        <p>Now firmly in the post-you-know-what age, I had only vague memories of that serene decade until I walked into Origins, the quintessentially '90s body-care brand. Stepping into the narrow, embracing store at the base of the Flatiron Building, I remembered how easy it was to feel good back then.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A visit to Origins, one of the first botanical-based brands from a major company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW I had forgotten the '90s: that optimistic decade when I walked around with my sticky mat and precious new cellphone, as obsessively yogic and introspective as Madonna. I attended Ashtanga classes and imagined peace while in pigeon pose, thinking it was an effective way to contribute to global reform.</p>
        <p>Now firmly in the post-you-know-what age, I had only vague memories of that serene decade until I walked into Origins, the quintessentially '90s body-care brand. Stepping into the narrow, embracing store at the base of the Flatiron Building, I remembered how easy it was to feel good back then.</p>
        <p>More anxious now and disgusted with my own consumption, I didn't know what to do with myself there. So I decided to buy an exfoliating scrub for my dumb American face, which, like my country, often seems to be greedily hoarding oil.</p>
        <p>I explained this to my Origins ''guide'' (that's what they call salesclerks here), and a stripe of concern passed over her pretty natural face. She suggested I try Modern Friction ($36), which uses ''skin refining rice starch cushioned in cream'' to rub away dead skin cells. Swept Clean ($18.50) seemed more my style, because it had that fine-grain granular texture you look for in a scrub, and it was darkened with ''activated charcoal,'' which apparently will ''break through oil, purge pores and sweep away trouble-breeders.''</p>
        <p>Charcoal suddenly seemed the answer to all my problems, so I went a little coal-crazy at the Origins for Men section and bought the Skin Diver body scrub ($17.50), Skin Diver body wash ($16.50) and a bar of Skin Diver body soap ($10).</p>
        <p>I was given a little wooden apple basket to put my products in. While I perused the well-lighted items on the blond wood shelves, a guide was applying a cleanser to a woman sitting at one of the little islands outfitted with a sink. I tried to settle into the Origins aura, but that was hard for me now that I've replaced my Ray of Light-style inner life with a constant fear of apocalypse and personal carbon emissions and a concern that everything I do or buy is killing furry animals or enslaving children in Africa in some blood-diamond capitalist way.</p>
        <p>But that is what stores like Origins are for: to provide products that purport to use environmentally friendly natural remedies and ancient healing traditions so that Western consumers like me can feel they are guiltlessly moisturizing without destroying the planet like a human SUV.</p>
        <p>The arrival of Origins, one of the first botanical-based brands from a major company, in the early '90s was a turning point in the cosmetics industry. The green spawn of Estée Lauder, it was committed to preservation of earth, animals and environment -- a habitual mission for most beauty products now, but more of a challenge 17 years ago, when recycling was not mandatory and many brands were using animal collagen and placenta in their products.</p>
        <p>But Origins pressed on, eschewing animal products and testing, using that yellowy 20 percent recycled paper (now replaced with a better-looking 50 percent blend), creating an Origins Empties recycling program and finding a manufacturer willing to turn its leftover plastic caps into lawn chairs and a beekeeper who wouldn't gas the insects at the end of the season.</p>
        <p>The first Origins store opened in Cambridge, Mass., in 1991 with a shocking 200 products. Marking the end of the snooty '80s and the onset of the warmer '90s, it was, it says, the first major brand to use an ''open sell'' approach -- allowing customers to touch and test a product before buying it -- including its signature product, Peace of Mind ($10), an aromatherapy cream that delivers a lingering peppermint-patty zing when rubbed on the temples or earlobes. (Big white Peace of Mind gumballs are also available for 25 cents.)</p>
        <p>WHILE its tie to a major corporation may breed suspicion among the ecoconscious consumers it courts, being a rich daughter brand does give Origins the financial advantage to stay committed to its mission -- to pay for trips to far-flung countries to retrieve ingredients (like charred bamboo from Japan) and research indigenous healing traditions with shamans in Belize. It's impressive that the brand still holds up in a time when even Cameron Diaz is environmentally aware.</p>
        <p>Over the next few months, the company will be redoing its stores in an ''eco-chic'' design: more plants, terra cotta accents, sustainable woods. But its familiar tree silhouette logo and clean font, which looks both dynamic and soothing, will remain.</p>
        <p>And there is still satisfaction in reading the chummy product names and arcane label descriptions, learning, for example, that the skin-firming cream Youthtopia contains rhodiola, a ''legendary'' herb that flowers in Siberia's polar mountains.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the ingredient combos appear contrived, as in Calm to Your Senses Lavender and Vanilla Body Soufflé, which, upon opening, looked like a dessert from the Gramercy Tavern nearby and made me crave a spoon.</p>
        <p>My guide tried to persuade me to get a tonic, explaining it would return my face to a pH balance after I scrub it raw. But I just can't get into toners. In our shared fantasy of ''healing traditions,'' I can imagine a wrinkle-free Japanese elder or Hopi medicine woman cleaning themselves with charcoal, moisturizing with rice starch and exfoliating with jojoba beads, but I can't see them applying toner with a cotton ball.</p>
        <p>Before leaving, I noticed green placards depicting another icon of the '90s, the smiling bearded face of the cute, squeezable Dr. Andrew Weil. Dr. Weil has collaborated with Origins to create a line of mushroom-based products (which are supposed to reduce redness and inflammation), including Plantidote Mega-Mushroom Face Serum ($65), face cream ($60) and Nite-trition Restful Sleep Supplement, a liquid you squirt into your mouth ($35).</p>
        <p>At home I scrubbed and serumed and moisturized, daubed some Peace of Mind on my temples, took a dropper of Dr. Weil's sleep supplement and lay in my bed all smooth-faced and redolent in botanical clouds of fragrance. I slept really well, too, but that may have been because of another healing ingredient I use called shiraz.</p>
        <p>Origins  Flatiron Building, 175 Fifth Avenue (23rd Street); (212) 677-9100.</p>
        <p>VIBE -- Like the serene lobby of a '90s yoga studio, but with better products and no nasty Nag Champa smell.  DOTING EARTH MOTHERS -- Free consultations and ''wellness services'' available, tailored to specific problems like stress, lack of energy and sleep difficulties. A good pit stop for freaked-out commuters.  RENEWABLE ENERGY -- Backed by a Big Daddy company, Origins is always rolling out new products like its all-natural line for pets, including Doggie Dip Silky Coat dog shampoo, coming this month.</p>
        <p>CRITICAL SHOPPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
