<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Dutch National Pastime's Top Event, Mother Nature Wields the Starting Gun</title>
    <meta content="26skating" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/26/world/europe/26skating.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LEEUWARDEN JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Leeuwarden (Netherlands)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Netherlands</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D6113EF935A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Dutch National Pastime's Top Event, Mother Nature Wields the Starting Gun</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Dutch National Pastime’s Top Event, Mother Nature Wields the Starting Gun</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>LEEUWARDEN, the Netherlands, Feb. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Netherlands national event is 11-Cities Tour, grueling 125-mile ice skating race across frozen canals and lakes, which starts and ends in Leeuwarden; event takes place every 10 or 20 years, sometimes less frequently, when temperature is low enough and ice is thick enough; last race was in 1997, and many skaters are troubled by warm temperatures and no ice in recent years; map, photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is the town from which, when it is run, a grueling 125-mile race takes off across frozen canals and ice-locked lakes and under quaint bridges and past trim brick villages.</p>
        <p>When there is ice, that is. This northern Dutch city, population 90,000, of straight brick homes and meandering canals, is home to the 11-Cities Tour, or Elfstedentocht, which takes place only when nature says so. The race begins and ends here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Leeuwarden, where a grueling 125-mile ice skating race is a national event, the ice hasn’t frozen hard enough to allow the race since 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is the town from which, when it is run, a grueling 125-mile race takes off across frozen canals and ice-locked lakes and under quaint bridges and past trim brick villages.</p>
        <p>When there is ice, that is. This northern Dutch city, population 90,000, of straight brick homes and meandering canals, is home to the 11-Cities Tour, or Elfstedentocht, which takes place only when nature says so. The race begins and ends here.</p>
        <p>That is a national event for the Dutch, traditionally consummate skaters, and it takes place every 10 or 20 years, sometimes less frequently, when the temperature is low enough and the ice thick enough. The tour was held only 15 times in the past century.</p>
        <p>The last was in 1997, when a gaggle of 306 of the country's fastest, hardiest and perhaps foolhardiest skaters, followed by no fewer than 16,372 other skaters, cheered by even larger crowds, set off across a path that runs south through canals and across lakes, then west to the sea, then north, through villages with names like Sneek, Franeker, Hindeloopen, Workum and Dokkum, and back again to Leeuwarden.</p>
        <p>The first to cross the finish line that year was Henk Angenent, a 29-year-old sprout farmer who finished in under seven hours, and said it was the greatest day of his life. He joined the august circle of winners going back to 1909, when the first race was run by only 22 stalwarts, nearly half of them local farmers, now revered as giants hereabouts. One of them, Jacob Kaastra, a farmer, is said to have skated the tour while smoking his clay pipe.</p>
        <p>But this year has been different. The canals have not frozen, and the Royal Dutch Meteorological Institute, in nearby De Bilt, announced that last year had been the warmest year on average since the Dutch began recording temperatures in 1706, only about 40 years after they surrendered New Amsterdam to the English.</p>
        <p>The average temperature for the year, the institute said, was 52 degrees Fahrenheit, far too high to freeze a glass of water, much less an entire canal. As if that were not enough, one of the institute's scientists published a paper, available on the institute's Web site, that calculated weather patterns in the last century and considered the effects of global warming, concluding that in the present century, it might not be possible to run the race more than four times, or once every 25 years.</p>
        <p>The year 1997, said Geert Jan Oldenborgh, of the institute's global climate division, ''stuck out like a sore thumb.'' Normally, he explained, Dutch winter weather is made mild by westerly winds that come in off the water. But that year, a blocking low pressure center over Scandinavia brought cold air from Russia to the Netherlands. In 1985 and 1986, the last time the race was held in back-to-back years, he said, ''there was so much ice people were sick and tired of ice-skating.''</p>
        <p>This is all gloomy news to Jan Oostenbrug, 60, a retired civil engineer who skated in 1997 and who now spends much of his time working in the association that prepares for the next race.</p>
        <p>On a recent gray rainy afternoon, with crocuses popping up all around, Mr. Oostenbrug led a visitor to the one bridge, like those that Van Gogh painted, in the tiny village of Burdaard, which the skaters pass twice, once going north and again returning south. Rain fell, and the only creatures on the canals were ducks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oostenbrug carried a five-foot length of pole with a steel point like a harpoon. The device is used to measure the ice, which must be six inches thick to be safe. The decision to skate is never made until the last minute, forcing frantic preparations by thousands of volunteers like Mr. Oostenbrug.</p>
        <p>''We cannot organize anything unless it is minus 15 degrees,'' he said, about 5 degrees Fahrenheit. ''That is difficult this year. It is in December, January or February that it can happen.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, he said, the government is spending the equivalent of $650 million to dredge the canals of Friesland, the northern province, whose capital is Leeuwarden, to assure they are an even five to six feet in depth. That is because the canals are increasingly used for other events patterned after the 11-Cities Tour, even when there is no ice.</p>
        <p>''There are rolling-skating races, and bicycle races, rowing races, and even, last summer, a race of solar-driven boats,'' said Wiebe Wielling, 51, a university administrator who directs the volunteer committee that would organize the next race. ''There are 11-Cities Tours every year,'' he said. ''But not on ice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wielling, who raced in 1986, with his wife, and in 1997, is troubled by the total absence of ice in recent years.</p>
        <p>''The difference is, there used to be ice, but not enough,'' he said. ''Now we are wondering when it will start to freeze again. Of course, even though the weather is changing, there still can be exceptions.''</p>
        <p>What seems to trouble Mr. Wielling more than changes in the weather is a change in Dutch society, toward litigiousness.</p>
        <p>In the past, though hundreds of thousands of people swarmed over the canals, on the lakes and across little wooden bridges, many downing shots of Beerenburg, a juniper schnapps, to stay warm, the organizers were never sued when injuries occurred. In 1997, one skater even died, after suffering heart failure.</p>
        <p>''In 10 years, society has changed a lot, so our rule will be, no one on the ice,'' except for participants, he said. ''On the other hand, if there is a race, the enthusiasm is so great, and people are in a fantastic mood.''</p>
        <p>For Marga Waanders, an economic official in the provincial government, the race, with or without ice, is a cornucopia. Friesland's economy has been shifting for years now from industry and farming to tourism and recreation. In 1960, one-third of the population depended on farming; today, only 2 percent do.</p>
        <p>''The Frisian people, in general, are down-to-earth people,'' she said. ''But when the race is on, they go mad. It's the Mardi Gras of Friesland.''</p>
        <p>LEEUWARDEN JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
