<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Architecture Issue</title>
    <meta content="03letters.t-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">mcclain, steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">handler, barbara l</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">wickey, paula</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">martin, a r</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lerner, Andrea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">johnston, emily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fintz, Alan S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Architecture Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>May 20 Times Magazine issue on architecture and environment prompts letters from Alan S Fintz, Robert Baker, Emily Johnston, Andrea Lerner, A R Martin, Paula Wickey, Barbara L Handler and Steven McClain; photo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In James Traub's inspired portrait of Al Gore, NASA's James Hansen is quoted as having written that ''Al Gore may have done for global warming what 'Silent Spring' did for pesticides'' (''Al Gore Has Big Plans,'' May 20). And Traub continues that '' 'An Inconvenient Truth' did a great deal for Al Gore as well.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In James Traub's inspired portrait of Al Gore, NASA's James Hansen is quoted as having written that ''Al Gore may have done for global warming what 'Silent Spring' did for pesticides'' (''Al Gore Has Big Plans,'' May 20). And Traub continues that '' 'An Inconvenient Truth' did a great deal for Al Gore as well.''</p>
        <p>If Traub is right that ''Americans like their presidential candidates to be happy,'' then it may just be time to rewrite the '08 presidential playbook: any man who finds so much ''pleasure in the midst of work,'' simply striving to save our world, finally seems happy enough to be seated in the office to which we elected him seven years ago!</p>
        <p>Alan S. Fintz</p>
        <p>Brooklyn</p>
        <p>Traub cites a poll showing ''78 percent of Americans believe that global warming requires action 'right away.' '' However, the relevant poll would also ask how much more Americans are willing to pay for prompt action.</p>
        <p>Robert Baker</p>
        <p>Darien, Conn.</p>
        <p>As much as I enjoyed your eco-tecture issue, I found a distressing focus on all the reasons we won't really have to change our behavior, even if we really are in a crisis. The signal sentence was Mark Svenvold's: ''By installing a solar-hydrogen system, almost any house, it seems, could go seriously green -- and without a whiff of the sacrifice or changes in lifestyle that sometimes come from the more puritanical quarters of the environmental movement'' (''The Zero-Energy Solution''). The implication, of course, is that any ''whiff'' of sacrifice (or even change in lifestyle!) is by its very nature ''puritanical.''</p>
        <p>I'd refer him to Arthur Lubow's article, ''The Road to Curitiba.'' High-minded planning counts for little if, in the end, the residents of a place don't understand that their behavior is exactly what does have to change. We'll need to remember that driving half as much is, for the moment, by far the most efficient way to (in effect) get twice the mileage; environmentalism is not about getting a sexy new Prius. Solar, hydrogen, straw-bale: we need them all, in addition to houses designed so well they need little energy to begin with. But meanwhile, we need to think about all the stuff we use, and what we can do to reduce our impact on the planet.</p>
        <p>Emily Johnston</p>
        <p>Seattle</p>
        <p>What happened in Curitiba was the transformation of a city by a visionary and humanist who was also a city planner. The changes were not only about buses and recycling garbage; they were also about life, people, dignity and respect.</p>
        <p>Jaime Lerner's ideas were eco-friendly, but they went even beyond that. Today, they are worth studying because they are simple; they prove that simple interventions can have a great impact in cities' environments.</p>
        <p>As Jaime Lerner, who was my father, once told me, there are people who create problems and cannot see solutions, and there are those who see in problems a potential for new paths.</p>
        <p>Andrea Lerner</p>
        <p>New York</p>
        <p>Mark Svenvold's article on the solar-hydrogen-powered home illustrates the many virtues of distributed power generation. It mentions only in passing a defect of hydrogen as an energy-storage medium: using electricity to make hydrogen and then converting hydrogen back into electricity is wasteful. For every 100 kilowatts of electricity produced by the solar cells, only about 40 kilowatts is recovered from the hydrogen fuel cell. By contrast, as much as 80 kilowatts could be recovered from a storage battery.</p>
        <p>Given the concerns cited in the article about the ability of solar cells to produce enough energy for an uninterrupted year-round supply, storage efficiency is an important factor in the system, and batteries would seem to be more effective than hydrogen for this purpose.</p>
        <p>A. R. Martin</p>
        <p>Fort Myers, Fla.</p>
        <p>Svenvold details a hydrogen-based solution to storing and retrieving surplus energy generated in the summer. This is fine if you live in some remote location far from power lines. But if a home remains connected to the grid, a less complicated (and less expensive) solution exists: simply sell the surplus power generated in the summer to the power company (via enabling legislation) and buy it back in the winter. Let the power company ''store'' your surplus power for when you need it.</p>
        <p>Paul Wickey</p>
        <p>Ypsilanti, Mich.</p>
        <p>Ed Begley Jr. says he's ''just kidding'' about being composted in his backyard (Domains: ''Hollywood and Green''). Well, I have it in my will that my cremains will become part of the compost heap in the backyard of my son, who is a serious composter and gardener. What better way to stick around than as a part of a living, vital process? No jar on a mantel, thank you, or scattering on some remote site. I'd rather become part of a radish or tomato.</p>
        <p>Barbara L. Handler</p>
        <p>Evanston, Ill.</p>
        <p>Your attention to the issue of sustainable design is laudable, yet it omits a player in the green-building movement: historic preservation (''An Eco-House for the Future'').Rehabilitating existing buildings is almost always more environmentally efficient than tearing down and building anew. Maintaining and improving historic buildings and the neighborhoods in which they stand allows for the continued use of valuable infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Steven McClain</p>
        <p>President, National Architectural Trust</p>
        <p>Washington</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
