<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Pollock, in the Eyes of Art and Science</title>
    <meta content="04kennedy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/04/weekinreview/04kennedy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Drip Wars"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University Art Museums</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollock, Jackson (1912-56)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matter, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Harvard University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pollock, Jackson</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE3D7123FF937A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Pollock, in the Eyes of Art and Science</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Pollock, in the Eyes of Art and Science</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clash of cultures between art and science has come into sharp relief with advances in technology and growing desire among scientists to delve into art and conservation questions; differences are particularly pronounced in commercial art world, where tens of millions of dollars can hang on decision about painting's authenticity; clash was highlighted recently when Harvard University Art Museums study questioned authenticity of paintings found by Alex Matter and initially thought to be Jackson Pollock's; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE disciplines of art history and connoisseurship tend to conjure up images of hushed galleries, towering library stacks and an almost priestly corps of experts equipped not only with the knowledge of centuries but also with ''the eye,'' a sixth sense of whether a canvas is a Rembrandt or just an attractive also-ran.</p>
        <p>But increasingly, other things might be included in this tableau -- electron microscopes, infrared spectroscopes, radiocarbon dating, X-ray fluorescence technology first developed for the Mars Pathfinder and teams of white-coated people with mechanical engineering or physics doctorates poring over artwork.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The intuitive scholar faces the hard evidence from the electron microscope.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE disciplines of art history and connoisseurship tend to conjure up images of hushed galleries, towering library stacks and an almost priestly corps of experts equipped not only with the knowledge of centuries but also with ''the eye,'' a sixth sense of whether a canvas is a Rembrandt or just an attractive also-ran.</p>
        <p>But increasingly, other things might be included in this tableau -- electron microscopes, infrared spectroscopes, radiocarbon dating, X-ray fluorescence technology first developed for the Mars Pathfinder and teams of white-coated people with mechanical engineering or physics doctorates poring over artwork.</p>
        <p>Modern science employed in the cause of art world detective work is not exactly new; it was pioneered by scholars like Edward Forbes at Harvard beginning as early as the 1920s. But advances in technology and a growing desire among scientists to delve into art and conservation questions have made it a much more prominent part of the field in the last decade. And as this has happened, a clash of cultures between two very different worlds -- hard science and the more subjective, individualistic traditions of the art scholar -- has come into sharp relief.</p>
        <p>The differences are particularly pronounced in the commercial art world, where tens of millions of dollars can hang on decisions about a painting's authenticity. Probably no case in recent memory has highlighted this clash more than the mystery surrounding a group of 32 paintings and other pieces that Alex Matter, the son of the photographer Herbert Matter, said he found in 2002 among his father's possessions in a Long Island storage locker. Inside a dusty brown wrapper with handwriting saying, ''Jackson experimental works (gift &amp; purchase)'' and ''Pollock (1946-49),'' the paintings were in the unmistakably drippy, droppy, swirling style of Jackson Pollock, a close friend of the elder Matter's.</p>
        <p>Ellen Landau, a well-regarded Pollock scholar, once served on a board whose job was to sort out numerous fakes from genuine Pollocks. Using little more than her eyes and her extensive knowledge of the artist's work, she said she believed the paintings were authentic. But her pronouncement, one that might have been accepted as something close to gospel only a few decades ago, especially given the close friendship between Pollock and Matter, proved but an opening salvo in a public battle over who painted the works.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the Harvard University Art Museums released a long-anticipated scientific study, performed with the cooperation of Alex Matter, of the chemical properties of three of the paintings, finding that some paints and pigments used in the works were not patented and probably not available until long after Pollock died in 1956. Alex Matter and Dr. Landau, who has conducted extensive research into the connections between Herbert Matter and Pollock, have questioned some of the findings, and Mr. Matter stressed in a statement that he believes ''the authentication of works of art is still more art than science.''</p>
        <p>The team at Harvard responded the way that scientists generally do: by saying that there is no arguing with science. Drawing an analogy to what he said were Bush administration efforts to suppress NASA information about global warming because it was politically unpalatable, Narayan Khandekar, a conservation scientist at Harvard, said in an interview that he and others who conducted the study were ''absolutely sure'' of their results and that quibbles about what they found struck him as disingenuous.</p>
        <p>''I think it's very much dismissing information because it's inconvenient for their arguments,'' he said, adding that such an approach to scholarly debate is ''a little like Stephen Colbert's concept of truthiness, where you're almost there but you don't have the whole thing.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Landau said she did not reject science reflexively over her own experience, but added that she simply cannot reconcile the study's findings with the other information she has collected, like a handwriting study that confirms the notes on the package were in Herbert Matter's hands and evidence that the paintings had been corrected and retouched in a method that Pollock employed.</p>
        <p>''I can't construct an alternate scenario that makes any sense,'' she said. ''Science might not be wrong, but the research behind it might not be a 100 percent correct. And so more research needs to be done.''</p>
        <p>In the wider art world, traditional scholarship is beginning to accommodate science a little more willingly. But some experts say the friction between the two is not only about turf wars but also about fundamental differences in culture. In a 2005 discussion sponsored by the Getty Trust, Richard Stone, senior conservator at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, argued that part of the problem was that ''art historians basically do not collaborate'' while science demands it.</p>
        <p>''Collaboration is regarded by many in the humanities as equivalent to playing tennis with the net down, somehow an unsporting activity,'' Mr. Stone said.</p>
        <p>In the case of the possibly Pollock mystery paintings, whether science and the trained ''eye'' of connoisseurship will ever see eye to eye remains uncertain, at least as far as Dr. Landau is concerned. ''Ultimately I don't know what's going to happen,'' she said. ''Maybe it's going to end up being a big mystery, you know? 'C.S.I. Pollock.' ''</p>
        <p>Drip Wars</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
