<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cure for Chilling Words Could Be a Cooler Temper</title>
    <meta content="13chivers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/13/weekinreview/13chivers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Putin, Vladimir V</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Fried, Daniel</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rice, Condoleezza</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D91531F930A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cure for Chilling Words Could Be a Cooler Temper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Cure for Chilling Words Could Be a Cooler Temper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUCH of Vladimir V. Putin's second presidential term, which began in 2004, has been defined by his escalating opposition to American foreign policy and his revival of Russian influence.</p>
        <p>With criticisms at turns withering and cogent, emotional and petulant, he has made his name in part by presenting himself as a counterweight to the United States and its policies abroad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Russia memorialized the victory over Nazi Germany, and Vladimir Putin raised his insults to the United States to a new level.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUCH of Vladimir V. Putin's second presidential term, which began in 2004, has been defined by his escalating opposition to American foreign policy and his revival of Russian influence.</p>
        <p>With criticisms at turns withering and cogent, emotional and petulant, he has made his name in part by presenting himself as a counterweight to the United States and its policies abroad.</p>
        <p>He has accused the United States of hypocrisy, arrogance, colonialism, military recklessness and adventurism, and of interfering with the internal affairs of other states.</p>
        <p>So when he stood in Red Square last Wednesday, giving a Victory Day address in memory of soldiers who died defeating Nazi Germany, he sent some shivers across the West when he said this:</p>
        <p>''The number of threats is not decreasing. They are only transforming and changing the guise. As during the Third Reich era, these new threats show the same contempt for human life and claims to world exclusiveness and diktat.''</p>
        <p>Never before had he seemed to compare the United States to the Third Reich, even indirectly, which is what Sergei Markov, a political commentator close to the Kremlin, said he had done.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the foreign ministry told American diplomats that Mr. Putin did not have the United States in mind. American diplomats took that non-apology with a shrug, given the pace of Mr. Putin's recent verbal attacks.</p>
        <p>Lost in much of the din was a public address by a senior American diplomat on the same day.</p>
        <p>Speaking in Berlin, Daniel Fried, the assistant secretary for European and Eurasian Affairs, presented his own analysis of Russia's strained relations with much of the West, giving full recognition to the new tensions but counseling just the opposite of hysteria.</p>
        <p>The opposing speeches offered glimpses, through very different frames, of how the two former foes are struggling to define the terms of their new relationship.</p>
        <p>The current problems, Mr. Fried suggested, should be viewed through the lens of history, then managed methodically, a technique that could presumably dull the emotional edge of any bluster.</p>
        <p>''Russia and the West have dealt with one another -- sometimes well, more often uneasily -- since at least Peter the Great,'' Mr. Fried said.</p>
        <p>He added that what was needed was sustained engagement, mixed with firmness, to try to help influence Russia during its ''unfinished transformation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fried also made clear that the West need not be fully impressed by Mr. Putin's ambitious posturing. Russia remains in many ways underdeveloped and disconnected from Western values, he said, and should still be held to account.</p>
        <p>''We do not want a weak Russia, but a strong Russia must be strong in 21st-century, not 19th-century, terms,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''A strong center is part of this healthy mix,'' he added. ''But a strong center in a state of weak institutions, is not.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fried also called on Europe to stand against Russia's desire to continue to have influence over countries the Soviet Union once occupied, a reminder that even as Russia complains about what it calls interference in its own domestic affairs it openly supports separatists in Georgia and Moldova, and has tried to bully Ukraine and the Baltic states.</p>
        <p>''We should not pay a price for cooperation, nor indulge Russia when it behaves as if a residual sphere of influence over its neighbors is its due,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The next round in the ongoing struggle begins next week, when Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice is scheduled to visit that country -- in part to meet Mr. Putin and discuss the tensions between the two nations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice told a Senate panel on Thursday that she was worried about Russia's conduct both at home and abroad.</p>
        <p>''It's been a difficult period,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Just how difficult was clear in the amount of time Mr. Fried spent talking about it. In a speech that surveyed the world, with topics ranging from international terrorism to global warming, his call to calmly brace against Russia's behavior took up more than a third of the time.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
