<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Virgin Orders 15 Boeing Jets To Save Fuel And Cut Noise</title>
    <meta content="25virgin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/business/worldbusiness/25virgin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070508T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virgin Atlantic Airways</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boeing Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Virgin Orders 15 Boeing Jets To Save Fuel And Cut Noise</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Virgin Orders 15 Boeing Jets to Save Fuel and Cut Noise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLA CLARK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Nicola</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Virgin Atlantic Airways ordered 15 fuel-efficient Boeing 787 planes Tuesday as part of an environmental partnership with the company that includes joint research into biofuels for use in jet engines.</p>
        <p>The order by the British carrier, worth $2.8 billion at list prices, also includes options for additional 787s, Virgin Atlantic said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The order was part of an environmental partnership with Boeing that includes joint research into biofuels for use in jet engines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Virgin Atlantic Airways ordered 15 fuel-efficient Boeing 787 planes Tuesday as part of an environmental partnership with the company that includes joint research into biofuels for use in jet engines.</p>
        <p>The order by the British carrier, worth $2.8 billion at list prices, also includes options for additional 787s, Virgin Atlantic said.</p>
        <p>The planes will be the first twin-engine aircraft in the airline's 37-jet fleet, which is made up of four-engine Airbus A340s and Boeing 747s.</p>
        <p>Virgin Atlantic once used the slogan ''4 engines 4 long haul'' to promote its aircraft as a safer trans-Atlantic option to twin-engine planes operated by rivals. But it said Tuesday that the 787 would be 27 percent more fuel-efficient per passenger and produce 60 percent less noise than an A340.</p>
        <p>''The 787 Dreamliner symbolizes the environmentally kinder aircraft of the future -- cleaner, quieter and truly the best experience in the air,'' the chairman of Virgin Atlantic, Richard Branson, said at a briefing in Chicago.</p>
        <p>More than 50 percent of the 787, which Boeing says will enter service in 2009, is made of lightweight composite materials, theoretically reducing the amount of fuel the plane burns. But analysts said the fuel-efficiency claims remained to be proved, as Virgin Atlantic has yet to choose between Rolls-Royce and General Electric engines for the aircraft.</p>
        <p>Doug McVitie, managing director of Arran Aerospace, a consulting firm in Dinan, France, said the decision would ''probably put pressure on British Airways to follow them with their own order for greener aircraft.''</p>
        <p>British Airways, Britain's largest carrier, is looking to replace 34 aging Boeing 747 and 767 jets. It said last year that it was considering the 787 as well as the 777 and 747-800 from Boeing, and the Airbus A380, A350-XWB and the A330. A British Airways spokesman said Virgin Atlantic's order would have no influence on its decision, which it expects to make by the end of this year.</p>
        <p>In addition to the aircraft order, Virgin Atlantic and Boeing plan to test biofuel on one of the carrier's 747-400 jets sometime in 2008. Virgin Atlantic said it would be the first demonstration of its kind by a commercial airline.</p>
        <p>In January, Mr. Branson and former Vice President Al Gore announced a $25 million prize for an effective way of removing greenhouse gases from the atmosphere. Critics at the time accused Mr. Branson of hypocrisy in announcing the contest because of the role that Virgin Atlantic and other airlines play in contributing to carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 8, 2007, Tuesday  An article in Business Day on April 25 about a decision by Virgin Atlantic Airways to order 15 Boeing 787 planes misstated the model that another airline, British Airways, is considering. It is the 747-8, not the 747-800.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 8, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on April 25 about a decision by Virgin Atlantic Airways to order 15 Boeing 787 planes misstated the model that another airline, British Airways, is considering. It is the 747-8, not the 747-800.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
