<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hedging Hedge Funds</title>
    <meta content="05offline" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/05/business/05offline.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S OFFLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island/Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD9113EF936A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hedging Hedge Funds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hedging Hedge Funds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL B. BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Paul B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAN you hedge a hedge fund?</p>
        <p>An investment currently being marketed to the rich is trying in essence to do just that, and the approach is bound to be offered to the rest of us soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An investment currently being marketed to the rich is trying in essence to hedge a hedge fund, and the approach is bound to be offered to the rest of us soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAN you hedge a hedge fund?</p>
        <p>An investment currently being marketed to the rich is trying in essence to do just that, and the approach is bound to be offered to the rest of us soon.</p>
        <p>Often referred to as 130/30, the strategy calls for investment managers to buy undervalued stocks, while simultaneously shorting -- that is, selling borrowed shares -- those they believe to be overvalued.</p>
        <p>This is, of course, what many hedge funds do. The difference here is there is a limit on how much the manager can short. The percentage is typically capped at 30 percent (which gives the strategy its name.)</p>
        <p>The advantage of this approach is twofold, John Ferry writes in Worth.</p>
        <p>First, by permitting managers to ''go short,'' it allows them to profit from their ability to spot a stock that they think is going to fall in price. Most investment strategies restrict asset managers to going long, that is betting that an investment will increase in value.</p>
        <p>Second, money generated by shorting is used to buy additional shares of stocks the manager believes will rise.</p>
        <p>Here's one way 130/30 could work: The manager borrows shares he doesn't own, and sells them, using the proceeds to buy stocks he believes are undervalued.</p>
        <p>He hopes to make money in two ways: The stocks he buys go up in price and, if the stocks shorted go down in value, he makes money there as well. That happens because when it comes time to return the shares he borrowed, he can replace them with shares that cost less, profiting from the difference.</p>
        <p>As always, success in this strategy will occur only if the manager knows what to buy and sell and when.</p>
        <p>TOO HOT? -- Bloomberg Markets reports that hedge funds have been reducing their stakes in alternative-energy companies, a sign that the market segment may be overheated.</p>
        <p>The Citadel Investment Group and D. E. Shaw &amp; Company are among the firms that cut their holdings in solar-power equipment makers and ethanol producers in the fourth quarter, according to Securities and Exchange Commission filings, Daniel Hauck and Michael Tsang write.</p>
        <p>The move comes at a time when alternative-energy stocks are extremely hot.</p>
        <p>''A group of 184 alternative-energy stocks jumped 56 percent this year through March 7, according to data compiled by Bloomberg,'' the reporters write. ''The Morgan Stanley Capital International World Index lost 0.9 percent'' during that time.</p>
        <p>10 FOR 10 -- ''What do a dental equipment maker, a natural foods distributor and a manufacturer of water valves have in common,'' Smart Money asks. They are 3 of the 10 stocks that the magazine believes are the ones to own for the next decade.</p>
        <p>As James B. Stewart points out in the cover article, the stocks fit into four themes: health, wireless technology, global growth and clean water.</p>
        <p>While the case for the first three is self-evident, Mr. Stewart writes, ''though it hasn't gotten as much attention as global warming, fresh water looms as one of the planet's major challenges.''</p>
        <p>''In the U.S. alone,'' he continues, ''hundreds of billions of dollars are likely to be spent on water infrastructure over the next decade.''</p>
        <p>To identify the 10 stocks to buy, the magazine looked for companies worth $300 million to $2 billion in market value that had ''a low price-to-sales ratio relative to their peers,'' and had expanded sales by at least 10 percent a year over the last five years. That produced a list of 150 companies from which it selected the final 10.</p>
        <p>The list: Atlas Air Worldwide, Brightpoint, Harris Interactive, OSI Systems, Powerwave Technologies, Sirona Dental Systems, Tetra Tech, United Natural Foods, Viasys Healthcare and Watts Water Technologies.</p>
        <p>FINAL TAKE -- If you don't know what to do with that $75 million burning a hole in your pocket, Eamon Lynch in Golf Magazine Living offers a suggestion: You could buy a 20,000-square-foot home on 60 acres in Bridgehampton, N.Y. The 10-bedroom home has 14 gardens, and its own nine-hole golf course that comes complete with pro shop.</p>
        <p>PAUL B. BROWN</p>
        <p>WHAT'S OFFLINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
