<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Wake of Campus Killings, Talk Radio Tries for Humor and a Political Advantage</title>
    <meta content="20radio" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/us/20radio.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jacques</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boortz, Neal</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Savage, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Limbaugh, Rush</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Wake of Campus Killings, Talk Radio Tries for Humor and a Political Advantage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Talk Radio Tries for Humor and a Political Advantage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Talk radio hosts across spectrum are wrestling with how far they can go in sounding off, and even mining for several laughs, on Virginia Tech shootings; some of most prominent hosts, including Rush Limbaugh, Michael Savage and Neal Boortz, have shown little restraint; observers say incident has many themes that often serve as grist for these hosts and their callers that have coalesced (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Opie and Anthony,'' a radio show originating in New York that once broadcast the sounds of two people reportedly having sex in St. Patrick's Cathedral, did not take long to try to extract some humor from the massacre at Virginia Tech on Monday.</p>
        <p>Just after 8:30 a.m. Wednesday the show's two hosts -- Gregg Hughes (Opie') and Anthony Cumia -- staged an on-air reading of a play written by the killer, Cho Seung-Hui, and posted on the Internet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Broadcasters across the spectrum of talk radio have wrestled this week with how far they can go in sounding off on the violence at Virginia Tech.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Opie and Anthony,'' a radio show originating in New York that once broadcast the sounds of two people reportedly having sex in St. Patrick's Cathedral, did not take long to try to extract some humor from the massacre at Virginia Tech on Monday.</p>
        <p>Just after 8:30 a.m. Wednesday the show's two hosts -- Gregg Hughes (Opie') and Anthony Cumia -- staged an on-air reading of a play written by the killer, Cho Seung-Hui, and posted on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Titled ''Richard McBeef,'' the play is a tale of betrayal, murder and child molesting, subjects that the hosts and a supporting ensemble approached with little melodrama. Afterwards, they cheered themselves with cries of ''Bravo!'' before being interrupted by the clatter of what sounded like automatic gunfire.</p>
        <p>''What, too much?'' a participant could be heard saying, in a broadcast heard in New York on WFNY-FM, which is owned by CBS Radio.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, little bit, little bit,'' someone responded. ''Not enough time's gone by. Careful.''</p>
        <p>Only a week after Don Imus was taken off the air by MSNBC and CBS Radio for making a racially and sexually charged aside about the women's basketball team at Rutgers University, his former colleagues across the spectrum of talk radio have wrestled with how far they can go in sounding off (and even mining for a few laughs) on the violence at Virginia Tech. Some of the most prominent hosts -- including Rush Limbaugh, Michael Savage and Neal Boortz -- have shown little restraint.</p>
        <p>This, after all, is an incident in which many themes that often serve as grist for those hosts and their callers -- including immigration (Mr. Cho was Korean), gun control (he appears to have used legally bought handguns) and the aggressive coverage of the news media (NBC initially broadcast the suspect's ''multimedia manifesto'') -- have coalesced.</p>
        <p>Speaking on Wednesday on his syndicated program, which is heard on more than 600 stations, Mr. Limbaugh argued that tragedies could be prevented by ''a law banning political correctness.''</p>
        <p>''This guy was sending up flares,'' Mr. Limbaugh said of Mr. Cho, whose erratic and disturbing behavior had caught the attention of other students, the campus police, faculty members and others. ''Was everybody so concerned with the trumped-up global warming scare they didn't notice a real threat, for example?''</p>
        <p>''And how about this?'' Mr. Limbaugh added. ''The guy is Korean. He's Asian. How many people refused to do anything about it or even complain about it because they would be tagged as racists?''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the day after NBC News showed excerpts from material it had received from Mr. Cho after the killings, Mr. Limbaugh singled out that network and others in what he calls the ''drive-by media'' for what he called their irresponsibility.</p>
        <p>''If there are copycats who get ideas from the constant playing of these video clips and photos, who's going to be responsible for this?'' he asked. ''It will not be the National Rifle Association. It will not be the fault of the gun that the next user uses. And it will not be the fault of talk radio.''</p>
        <p>Of NBC he said, ''Let's set these people up, folks, for what might come after this.'' Then, in an effort to link the events of the last two weeks, Mr. Limbaugh said, ''The only thing that Virginia Tech and the Imus situation have in common is NBC.''</p>
        <p>Those comments, though, seem mild compared with others this week by Mr. Savage, whose program, originating in San Francisco, is heard on more than 300 radio stations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Savage, whose harsh comments about homosexuality resulted in his dismissal from MSNBC in 2003, sneered audibly as he referred to Mr. Cho as ''a senior in English,'' drawing out the word for emphasis, and as ''Comandante Cho.'' Mr. Cho, who was born in South Korea, moved to the United States with his family in 1992, when he was 8.</p>
        <p>''This kid was brainwashed over there,'' Mr. Savage said. Later he added that ''the only reason'' Mr. Cho ''was walking the streets was because liberal scum have for 30 years handcuffed the police and the people of this country and made us hostages in their drama.''</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Savage suggested that Mr. Cho ''uses the rhetoric of Al Qaeda when he rails against rich kids, debauchery and alcohol'' -- as he apparently did in a note found in his dorm room. After taking several calls, however, Mr. Savage began to backpedal from any possible terrorist connection in Virginia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boortz, whose program is broadcast from Atlanta to more than 150 stations, suggested that some responsibility for the extent of the shooting lay with some of the victims, most of whom were shot in classrooms and hallways.</p>
        <p>''When the history of this event is written,'' Mr. Boortz said Wednesday, ''we will have 25 students standing meekly waiting for this guy to execute them. Waiting for what? The government to come save them.''</p>
        <p>A few moments later, as a transition to a commercial break, Mr. Boortz paused to play a snippet of a pop song from the 1980s. His choice? ''Hit Me With Your Best Shot'' by Pat Benatar.</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
