<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Boomlet For Al Gore</title>
    <meta content="l02dowd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5D91631F931A35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Boomlet For Al Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Ozone Man Sequel,'' by Maureen Dowd (column, Feb. 28):</p>
        <p>I want Al Gore to run again because I am convinced that he would be the best president as well as the candidate most likely to be elected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Ozone Man Sequel,'' by Maureen Dowd (column, Feb. 28):</p>
        <p>I want Al Gore to run again because I am convinced that he would be the best president as well as the candidate most likely to be elected.</p>
        <p>When George W. Bush ran against Mr. Gore, the country knew far less about Mr. Bush, so he was far less vulnerable than when he ran against John Kerry. Even so, Senator Kerry lost both the popular and electoral vote.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Mr. Gore won the popular vote and would have been elected if it hadn't been for the scandalous Supreme Court decision and the even more scandalous Republican shenanigans in Florida.</p>
        <p>It's true that his campaign was not perfect -- the chief problems were his understandable but unfortunate sigh in the first debate and his attempt to counteract its effect by passivity in the second debate.</p>
        <p>But we have seen that he has become a far more effective speaker. And now he knows that it is not a good idea to sigh.</p>
        <p>Richard I. Sikora  Portland, Ore., Feb. 28, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Maureen Dowd contemplates whether Al Gore should become a candidate again and quotes him as saying that he went wrong because most of his career was spent investing in ''predawn'' ideas.</p>
        <p>Although it could be lamented that Mr. Gore's presidency was stolen from him, he has had a tremendous impact as a passionate advocate for a well-defined, important cause. One might even wonder if anyone could have accomplished this as president.</p>
        <p>After hearing one of his trainees, my young sons now move through the house turning off lights, saying ''global warming.'' No other issue has resonated so well, and I attribute that to a well-developed grass-roots movement.</p>
        <p>Beryl Koblin  Metuchen, N.J., Feb. 28, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Al Gore and other potential candidates for public office will soon have to face a new generation of voters: people like me, a high school student whose view on the world was profoundly influenced by 9/11.</p>
        <p>Maureen Dowd depicts Mr. Gore not as a candidate but as a man living in the shadow of his 2000 defeat while dwelling on his own ''prescience.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Gore wants my vote, he will have to show that he has not spent the last seven years lamenting his loss but considering plans that are relevant to our time.</p>
        <p>Unless he defends the presidential powers necessary in the war on terror, Mr. Gore will not get the support of this young voter.</p>
        <p>Jonathan G. Panter  Palisades, N.Y., Feb. 28, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It is surprising to read Maureen Dowd's glowing endorsement of Al Gore's qualifications to be president.</p>
        <p>As I recall, when Mr. Gore was actually working hard for that job, many of Ms. Dowd's columns lingered on such crucial items as his likability, his appearance and the fact that his handlers had persuaded him to wear -- horrors -- brown!</p>
        <p>While now promoting Mr. Gore, Ms. Dowd seems to have shifted her focus to belittling Hillary Rodham Clinton and Barack Obama, two candidates who are actually running.</p>
        <p>Marcia Amsterdam  New York, Feb. 28, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
