<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breaking Our Addiction to Oil</title>
    <meta content="l16friedman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6D91331F935A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breaking Our Addiction to Oil</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Only Halfway There'' (column, May 13):</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Friedman says that none of the current initiatives regarding moving to alternative energy go far enough (for example, Senator Christopher J. Dodd's call for a ''corporate carbon tax'' and Senator Barack Obama's call for tougher fuel economy standards). I agree.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Only Halfway There'' (column, May 13):</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Friedman says that none of the current initiatives regarding moving to alternative energy go far enough (for example, Senator Christopher J. Dodd's call for a ''corporate carbon tax'' and Senator Barack Obama's call for tougher fuel economy standards). I agree.</p>
        <p>If we can allow our military to sacrifice their very lives and their families to be devastated caring for brain-damaged young men and women, can we not, as a society, make a most inconvenient sacrifice and ration gas, as we did in World War II?</p>
        <p>The very inconvenience of such a move would generate serious dialogue and move this country to find the solutions to oil addiction quickly.</p>
        <p>If we are at war, we should take wartime measures.</p>
        <p>Katherine Rose  Ellicott City, Md., May 14, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I recently studied policy options to achieve energy independence and a clean environment for a lecture at Stanford. The most effective option was a combination of an across-the-board floor price on all forms of energy at $45 a barrel, and regulatory reform so that, all things being economically equal, clean goes ahead of dirty.</p>
        <p>Also helpful were ultra-fast permitting for ultra-clean projects; targeted federal research programs; incentives to sell power plants and heavy equipment while still in relatively good condition; and mandatory minimum renewable energy purchases by utilities.</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Friedman appropriately suggests an urgent need for a floor price on oil sold in the United States. This should be extended to all forms of energy so that all the alternatives can prosper.</p>
        <p>Bob Danziger  Carmel, Calif., May 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Friedman is certainly correct when he says, ''You can't be serious about getting out of Iraq if you're not serious about getting off oil.'' I would suggest, however, that there are two related but more immediate things we must be serious about if we're going to be serious about getting out of Iraq.</p>
        <p>We must make it clear to the world, first, that we are committed to getting along without Iraqi oil; and, second, that we have no intention of maintaining a permanent military presence in Iraq.</p>
        <p>What puzzles me is why our politicians and presidential aspirants never talk about these two pieces of the picture. Perhaps it's because such talk would reveal too much about the real reasons we went to war in Iraq in the first place -- and why we are so reluctant to leave without accomplishing our mission.</p>
        <p>Roy G. Smith  Denver, May 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Friedman wants us to ''radically reduce our dependence on oil.''</p>
        <p>The reality is that we need to reduce our dependence on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>The ''radical'' remedy is that we need to drill in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and along the outer continental shelf. The fact that we do not use our own natural resources, which would benefit us economically and strategically, is utterly perverse, and a testament to how we are held hostage by the environmental movement.</p>
        <p>Efficient and economical alternative sources of energy will take time to develop. In the meantime, let's not foolishly ignore the oil under our feet.</p>
        <p>Thomas D. Cramer  Ithaca, N.Y., May 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Friedman writes that you can't be serious about exiting Iraq without getting off oil. In other words, the personal is political. Right on. I'm getting a converted electric car next month.</p>
        <p>Steve McCrea  Fort Lauderdale, Fla.  May 14, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an editor of an advocacy Web site about vehicles converted to run on battery power.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
