<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="29diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/29/nyregion/29diary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3DE143FF93AA15752C0A9619C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>I was walking on West 72nd Street last month when I was approached by a tourist who spoke very little English. She asked, ''Where doctor's apartment?''</p>
        <p>I asked her to repeat her question, and she said, ''Where doctor's apartment?'' I started to be concerned because she was clearly looking for a doctor and I could not help her. I asked her, ''Which doctor?'' She replied, ''John Lennon.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A young woman, dressed appropriately for a day at the beach, is chatting on her cellphone: “I mean, like, what’s the point of global warming if you can’t wear flip-flops?”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>I was walking on West 72nd Street last month when I was approached by a tourist who spoke very little English. She asked, ''Where doctor's apartment?''</p>
        <p>I asked her to repeat her question, and she said, ''Where doctor's apartment?'' I started to be concerned because she was clearly looking for a doctor and I could not help her. I asked her, ''Which doctor?'' She replied, ''John Lennon.''</p>
        <p>My linguistic skills kicked in and I knew she wanted the Dakota Apartments. I pointed her in the right direction and she marched away happily, camera in hand.</p>
        <p>Trudy Zimmern</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Overheard in a diner on Second Avenue, on New Year's Day:</p>
        <p>An elderly man is having lunch when a friend, also quite elderly, arrives, takes off his coat, sits down and asks, ''So, how are you doing?'' The friend replies, ''I don't know -- how do I look?''</p>
        <p>Marian Miller</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>On a recent Saturday, I was in Prospect Park, skating with my mother and younger sister. After going several rounds, I decided to rest awhile on the grass near the parking lot and wait for my mother and sister to catch up. As I sat idly, I took to carefully surveying the people speeding down the track ahead of me.</p>
        <p>I observed the following: a cloud of up-and-coming Tour de France champions whizzing past one very irate elderly man passionately scolding them in fluent Cantonese; a pregnant woman power-walking her triple stroller down the runners' track; a youngish man swiveling expertly down the riders' path on his rather innovative two-prong, four-wheel scooter-cycle (patent surely pending); and a man on a bicycle, pulling a child on a tricycle, clutching a dachshund puppy strapped to a basket at the handlebars.</p>
        <p>Latoya Raveneau</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Commuting from my apartment in Washington Heights to my teaching job at the Lycée Français, I often chose the leisurely No. 4 bus, which provided door-to-door service, though at a slower pace than the subway.</p>
        <p>Another advantage was the occasional urban adventure, including a memorable moment when the driver came to a sudden stop at Columbus Avenue and 110th Street and darted out of the bus to help a very nontraditional commuter.</p>
        <p>I was sitting in the front seat, and the driver handed me the new passenger for safekeeping: a small, stunned bird that had apparently just flown into the windshield of the bus, and was groggy but otherwise unharmed.</p>
        <p>By the time we reached Fifth Avenue, my seatmate had started to recover; no longer in need of a special unscheduled stop, it waited patiently in my hands until the bus arrived at 96th and Fifth, and then exited, cheerfully fluttering just above the other passengers out the door. I couldn't help hoping that this was its intended destination all along.</p>
        <p>Jane F. Ross</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Date: Just before Christmas. Scene:  The lobby of a Central Park West building. Two brothers, ages 5 and 8, are waiting for the elevator while admiring the newly decorated Christmas tree.</p>
        <p>Boy, 5: ''I like to take the candy canes off the tree and eat them.''</p>
        <p>Boy, 8: ''I used to like candy canes but now I don't like them so much anymore.''</p>
        <p>Boy, 5: ''That's because your taste buds are changing.''</p>
        <p>Boy, 8: ''Yeah. You know how I knew my taste buds were changing?''</p>
        <p>Boy, 5: ''No.''</p>
        <p>Boy, 8: ''When I started to like the inside of sushi.''</p>
        <p>Rachel Melniker</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The Scene: The Union Square Greenmarket on a Saturday in early January when the temperatures reached the low 70s.</p>
        <p>Overheard: A young woman, dressed appropriately for a day at the beach, is chatting on her cellphone: ''I mean, like, what's the point of global warming if you can't wear flip-flops?''</p>
        <p>Brenda Fine</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>A couple of weeks ago, my husband, Steven, was on a Lexington Avenue bus when he heard the following announcement: ''No smoking or drinking on the bus.''</p>
        <p>At this point, a little boy, approximately 5 years old, got up from his seat and started to walk around the bus, much to the consternation of his baby sitter.</p>
        <p>When he reached my husband, he pointed his little finger and said, ''No smoking or drinking on the bus.''</p>
        <p>My husband asked good-naturedly, ''Why are you telling me this?'' The child replied, ''You look like you would smoke and drink!'' whereupon the bus exploded in peals of laughter.</p>
        <p>When my husband got off the bus there was a chorus of passengers yelling, ''No smoking or drinking on the bus.''</p>
        <p>Carol Rand</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
