<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Fat Nation, Are Thin Mints On Thin Ice?</title>
    <meta content="21towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/21/nyregion/21towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1827775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Girl Scouts</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4D8123EF932A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Fat Nation, Are Thin Mints On Thin Ice?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Are Thin Mints on Thin Ice?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's hard not to take one look at MeMe Roth's call for boycotting Girl Scout cookies and think, ''Lady, lighten up.''</p>
        <p>In the grand scheme of the world's horrors, those Thin Mints, Do-Si-Dos and Tagalongs don't quite register up there with Al Qaeda, global warming or the cable television coverage of Anna Nicole Smith's death as clear and present dangers to the general health and welfare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Girl Scouts were created today, would the ideal fund-raiser be something that makes all of us even fatter?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's hard not to take one look at MeMe Roth's call for boycotting Girl Scout cookies and think, ''Lady, lighten up.''</p>
        <p>In the grand scheme of the world's horrors, those Thin Mints, Do-Si-Dos and Tagalongs don't quite register up there with Al Qaeda, global warming or the cable television coverage of Anna Nicole Smith's death as clear and present dangers to the general health and welfare.</p>
        <p>And yet. Given the astronomical growth in childhood obesity and juvenile diabetes, the overall supersizing of the American body, the degree to which diet is about as mainstream a concern as there is, is it really so nutty to ask if the Girl Scouts need to be in the business of selling 200 million boxes of cookies a year -- and pushing madly for more? Or to put it another way, if the Girl Scouts were created today, as an organization devoted to helping raise healthy, empowered girls who make smart choices, would the ideal fund-raiser be something that makes all of us even fatter?</p>
        <p>Of course, it's not just Girl Scout cookies. Food is about emotional comfort as well as nutrition: think of all those church bake sales and school cookie sales and candy sales, each nestled in a warm spot in the national psyche. The Center for Science in the Public Interest, a Washington research group, released a study last week saying that of schools with fund-raisers, 76 percent sell chocolate, 67 percent sell baked goods, and 63 percent nonchocolate candy.</p>
        <p>But there's no iconic junk binge as beloved as Girl Scout cookies, one of those sugar-coated (and partially hydrogenated oil-laden) bits of Americana too mythic to be subject to rational analysis.</p>
        <p>Still, wading into the food wars is Ms. Roth, who was a mom from Milburn, N.J., who got slightly obsessed over the American Way of Junk and started National Action Against Obesity which, in truth, is essentially her and a Web site. She has since made herself enough of a nag to get her name out there, even appearing on ''The O'Reilly Factor.'' This week Ms. Roth called for a boycott of Girl Scout cookies and suggested that the organization come up with a five-year plan to move away from high-calorie morsels as its primary fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>''The Girls Scouts are a civic organization that does good things, but they shouldn't be using children to sell junk food when we're in the midst of an obesity epidemic,'' she said. ''Hopefully they will see this as an opportunity to take a leadership role for all civic organizations to move away from junk foods.''</p>
        <p>Of course, nothing stays the same, least of all the Girl Scouts, now 95 years old. The cookies have been around for 90 years, starting out with scouts baking sugar cookies at home with their mothers, wrapping them in wax paper and selling them door to door, a dozen for 25 cents.</p>
        <p>You're just as likely to buy your cookies from some girl scout's father at work as from some 9-year-old coming to the door, and the Scouts, too, have ginned up their marketing for the Internet age. They hired Ripple Effects Interactive to design a Web site (girlscoutcookies.org) and to post vintage cookie clips on 14 sites like MySpace and YouTube, a far cry from the early days when girl scouts actually baked Girl Scout cookies.</p>
        <p>''They want to use the Web to really grow their audience and get a presence in those niches where they might not be a household name yet,'' said Natalie DiPasquale of Ripple Effects Interactive.</p>
        <p>Denise J. Pesich, vice president of the Girl Scouts, said the cookie program taught girls entrepreneurial and personal skills as well as raising money. ''What we're really doing through the free enterprise system is selling items to the American public that they have come to expect, to enjoy and to love over 90 years.'' As for obesity, she says, ending Girl Scout cookies won't end obesity.</p>
        <p>It's hard to beat the cookies, even in their slightly slimmed-down guise this year: no trans fats, or at least few enough to meet federal labeling standards. And it's almost certainly impossible to beat the revenues: $700 million to support Girl Scout activities. Try selling enough carrots and broccoli to match that.</p>
        <p>Who's enough of a Grinch to really want to go to the mat over this one?</p>
        <p>Still, Dr. Susan Rubin, a dentist-turned nutritionist and a former Girl Scout leader who founded the Westchester Coalition for Better School Food, asked: Where do you start changing the food culture? It's not likely to be Girl Scout cookies, but it's not clear where it would be.</p>
        <p>''This is just another part of this toxic food chain that kids are awash in,'' she said. ''At some point, communities are going to have to walk away from the Do-Si-Dos.''</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS Email: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Email: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
