<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Al Gore and the Climate Debate</title>
    <meta content="20mlett-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Movies; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1834359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DC1730F933A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Al Gore and the Climate Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''From a Rapt Audience, a Call to Cool the Hype'' (March 13): Al Gore's critics are quick to pounce on his use of science. And yet they apparently have no qualms about implicitly employing pop theories of social change and labeling forecasts of dire biophysical change as scaremongering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''From a Rapt Audience, a Call to Cool the Hype'' (March 13): Al Gore's critics are quick to pounce on his use of science. And yet they apparently have no qualms about implicitly employing pop theories of social change and labeling forecasts of dire biophysical change as scaremongering.</p>
        <p>If these scientists spent a tiny fraction of the time Mr. Gore has spent studying natural science studying social science, history and policymaking processes, they might understand that he is not ''doing'' science. He is ''doing'' social change, a far messier and possibly more uncertain enterprise than any scientific enterprise.</p>
        <p>Thomas Princen  Ann Arbor, Mich.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The National Academy of Sciences, the American Geophysical Union, the American Meteorology Society and the American Association for the Advancement of Science have all issued statements stating that climate change is: a) occurring, b) largely caused by humans and c) likely to continue with large negative consequences for natural and human socioeconomic systems unless we rapidly decarbonize our global energy systems.</p>
        <p>People who have evidence that contradicts these statements can publish their findings in scientific journals, after which the public might expect to see this work discussed in Science Times. In the meantime, if you feel obligated to publish what are simply opinions, please use the opinion pages rather than the science section.</p>
        <p>James J. McCarthy  Cambridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>The writer is the president-elect of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was delighted to read a fairly balanced report in ''From a Rapt Audience, a Call to Cool the Hype.''</p>
        <p>NASA's Mars orbiter has recorded changes that indicate that Mars may be emerging from an ice age. Might we consider that solar forces are a bit more significant than putative anthropogenic influence on Earth?</p>
        <p>Is Earth warming? Maybe. If so, benefits may outweigh detriments. We can plan, change, modify.</p>
        <p>I know that scientific publications tend toward ''positives.'' But negative results represent balance, thoughtfulness, scope and the essence of science. Science eternally questions. There is never a consensus among scientists. Nor should there be.</p>
        <p>Anne Fennell  Austin, Tex.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>William J. Broad states that the latest I.P.C.C. report has lowered its estimate of future sea level rise, apparently exposing Al Gore as a ''shrill alarmist.'' This is dead wrong. The reason for the lower estimate is that the I.P.C.C. report now excludes the full effects of ice sheet melting. What they're saying is not, ''Sea level rise is going to be less than we thought.'' They're saying, ''We just can't predict what the ice sheets are going to do.''</p>
        <p>The article concludes that the I.P.C.C. portrays climate change as a ''slow-motion process.'' The I.P.C.C. estimates that under a business-as-usual scenario, global temperatures may rise more than 7 degrees by 2100. That's more than half a degree per decade.</p>
        <p>Phil Mitchell  Seattle</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>With regard to Al Gore's claims, reasonable people should have only two questions: What are the consequences if he is wrong and we clean up our act? What are the consequences if he is right and we do nothing as the skeptics advocate? Or even a third question: What if he is wrong by being too conservative in his warning (as I believe he is) and we do nothing?</p>
        <p>Glenn Mazzei  Niantic, Conn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
