<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Existential</title>
    <meta content="08wwln--safire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-08-07: ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDF1F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Existential</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column on three quite different meanings for word 'existential' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The threat that's represented by the extreme elements of Islam on a global basis now,'' Vice President Dick Cheney told Newsweek, is ''a problem that I think will occupy our successors maybe for two or three or four administrations to come. It is an existential conflict.'</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The threat that's represented by the extreme elements of Islam on a global basis now,'' Vice President Dick Cheney told Newsweek, is ''a problem that I think will occupy our successors maybe for two or three or four administrations to come. It is an existential conflict.'</p>
        <p>He has used that word before, as has his daughter Liz, in a Washington Post op-ed column. Jan Freeman noted in The Boston Globe that Bill Frist, Senate majority leader in 2005, called bioterror ''the greatest existential threat''; also, Prime Minister Tony Blair told Britons the year before that the global threat ''is real and existential,'' and two years before that Condoleezza Rice warned of terrorism's ''existential threat.'' Taken together, suggested Freeman, ''maybe they're hoping that 'existential conflict' sounds more profound and meaningful, given its philosophical associations, than 'death struggle' or 'fight for survival.' ''</p>
        <p>That resonance of the word in the field of philosophy also caused some puzzlement to Robert Walsh in e-mail land, who sends me this query: ''I thought existential had something to do with the need to find personal meaning in existence, because there is no God or we aren't sure. Now it is being applied to issues like global warming and terrorist attacks that threaten the very existence of our country, planet, culture. Is it worth a look in On Language?''</p>
        <p>Yes, because the profoundly serious word has now developed two quite different meanings, plus a third of special interest to word mavens. Start with the geopolitical sense:</p>
        <p>Existence is a state of being -- in the specific sense most important to us, of ''being alive.'' As noted in The Globe, weeks after the 9/11 attacks I wrote in this space that ''suicide hijackers and bombers do not pose what is coolly called an existential threat to -- that is, a danger to the very existence of -- the United States. . . . Terror-sponsoring states use these human missiles to implant that debilitating dread in individual American minds.'' (Hold the thought about the word dread.)</p>
        <p>What, then, is an existential conflict? Prof. Geoffrey Nunberg, a University of California linguist and the author of a new book, ''Talking Right,'' tracks the political use of the phrase to a 1960 review by the Rand Corporation's Paul Kecskemeti: ''existential conflicts such as duels and wars.'' The Harvard psychologist Herbert Kelman noted in 1999, ''For parties engaged in an existential conflict, such as that between Israelis and Palestinians,'' the parties fear ''ultimately losing everything, including their national identity and national existence.'' When Iran's president talks of ''wiping Israel off the map'' and makes no secret of nuclear ambitions, it is hard not to define that as an existential threat.</p>
        <p>Describing a conflict as existential, says Max Boot at the Council on Foreign Relations, ''is done for emphasis -- a way of saying this is a 'really really' important conflict that threatens substantially our peaceful existence. This is meant to distinguish it from what are sometimes called 'wars of choice' . . . almost all U.S. wars except for the Civil War and the War of Independence have been 'wars of choice' that did not threaten our existence.''</p>
        <p>Literally, then, nuclear or biological attacks killing tens of millions would not end the life of the U.S. -- but figuratively, they would end the existence of the way of life of its remaining citizens. If you look at Iraq, Afghanistan and African wars as local or civil wars, they are existential to only the people and nations therein; contrariwise, if you look at them as fronts in a global war against a growing terrorist threat, then such war can be defined as part of an existential conflict.</p>
        <p>Now to the cheerful philosophy of existentialism, which Walsh summed up as ''there is no God or we're not sure.'' In 1846, the Dane Soren Kierkegaard set forth Existents-Forhold, holding that the need to make painful ethical decisions was the source of mankind's dread and despair; that man was solitary, existing in isolation. The fact of being totally free -- therefore, uniquely responsible -- scares us in the most profound way, requiring a ''leap of faith'' to find God.</p>
        <p>Friedrich Nietzsche later worked it over into his God-is-dead nihilism. Jean-Paul Sartre in the 1940s retained that atheism but stressed that the sources of dread -- the key word in existentialism -- were our denials of personal responsibility, our failure to fight for ourselves in a hostile universe and our craven flight from ''inescapable freedom'' (that last is a great oxymoron). The existential way to live was to ''stand as if on a trap door'' that might spring open at any moment.</p>
        <p>I have compressed great gobs of heavy theo-thinking into two impenetrable paragraphs because this is a language column and I want to make a pass at existential forms in linguistics.</p>
        <p>Sometimes we want to grab the reader by the throat by putting the subject of the sentence right up front. I am tempted to do this many times. Now let's take that italicized sentence and soften it a little by putting a ''dummy subject'' up in front; that will help the reader ease into the whole proposition in the sentence and not just get hit in the kisser with the arrogant opening ''I.'' Here goes: There are many times that I am tempted to do this.</p>
        <p>That's an existential sentence, beginning with an unstressed there, followed by a verb tense of to be, showing that temptation exists. It's gentle; nice for a change of pace, but too many uses of dummy subjects like ''there are, one finds, we have'' take the writer down the primrose path of dull dalliance. As the reader, you may disagree; you may even use the singular there's to introduce a plural noun: ''There's guys out there who make that mistake allatime.'' If so, you are not isolated in existentialism's hostile universe. Nor is grammatical dispute an existential conflict.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-08-07: ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
