<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nature Girl Richard Tumang</title>
    <meta content="Royte.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/11/books/review/Royte.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1825242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Wild: An Elemental Journey (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1D9153FF932A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nature Girl Richard Tumang</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nature Girl</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH ROYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Royte, Elizabeth</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILD</p>
        <p>An Elemental Journey.</p>
        <p>By Jay Griffiths.</p>
        <p>374 pp. Jeremy P. Tarcher/</p>
        <p>Penguin. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A passionate plea for the preservation of wilderness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILD</p>
        <p>An Elemental Journey.</p>
        <p>By Jay Griffiths.</p>
        <p>374 pp. Jeremy P. Tarcher/</p>
        <p>Penguin. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Like Henry David Thoreau, Jay Griffiths wants to live deep and suck out all the marrow of life. Following a period of depression and tired of ''tamed thinking,'' the author of ''Wild: An Elemental Journey'' leaves her home in Britain and seeks wisdom in solo passage. Her singular interest is wildness. In the Amazon, the Arctic, the Australian desert, the mountains of West Papua and on the Indonesian seas, she travels almost exclusively with indigenous people, her conduits to telluric wisdom.</p>
        <p>This sounds promising, both in its physical scope and its intellectual curiosity, but Griffiths can be a little intense -- the sort of person you might want to avoid at a cocktail party. An immersionist, she wants to let her blood course into the earth, to lie naked in the sun, to feel the tides flood her body, ''inside and out.'' Fine, but Griffiths's bracing prose is too often stoked with anger, with a hair-trigger contempt for anything that epitomizes the bridled world, including indoor sex, maps, clean fingernails, golf (''greenery made stupid''), missionaries and the measurement of land, money or time. She's enraged by adventurers who risk infecting indigenous people by contacting them, and convulsed by 19th-century Europeans who called the Arctic a ''hideous blank.''</p>
        <p>So what does Griffiths like? Native people who live in harmony with nature. She's for animals, for plants, for wildness in any form. Her worldview is so simplistic -- and naïve -- it's sometimes hard to take her seriously. The arrogant West, she writes, ''cannot manage to respect other human societies' epistemologies, let alone accept that an animal can think.'' When she quotes an elder saying ''everything was good'' for Amazonian tribes before contact with missionaries -- ''there were no illnesses, worries or problems'' -- it seems she believes this literally.</p>
        <p>Griffiths's research is impressive. She quotes novelists, anthropologists, naturalists, poets, environmentalists, philosophers, dictionaries, bibles and scholars from around the world. And we learn some interesting things: polar bears are so well insulated they don't show up on infrared cameras; more people have been to space than to the deepest parts of the ocean. But Griffiths doesn't know when to quit. We get long etymological exegeses, and she riffs endlessly on the links between wisdom and trees, light and darkness, intelligence and gathering, hairiness and smoothness. Can you guess which she prefers, dry learning or wet? Unable to resist just one more phrase, example, echo, joke, Griffiths comes off as an overly analytical killjoy on speed.</p>
        <p>There's great material here -- Griffiths did go to the ends of the earth, alone -- but she rarely settles down to tell a story with a beginning, middle and end. The book has no narrative arc and zero plot. Griffiths materializes -- in a village, on a mountain -- then reappears elsewhere without apparent linkage. Her vagueness bothered me. In the desert, she ''heard hooves in the night,'' but we never learn whose. Of the number of Inuit children abused and raped by priests, she writes: ''The figures are overwhelming. A whole generation.'' But how many is that? For a chapter on water, she drops in on the Bajo, who live at sea in Indonesia, but records only a catalog of marine creatures. The section on trekking in West Papua is, for my money, the best because the author lets up, temporarily, on the rants, distracted by her physical discomforts (it's extremely difficult terrain), and because she was thrust into company with someone (a white, male scientist) she wanted to strangle. And vice versa.</p>
        <p>The book's structural shortcomings are felt all the more because Griffiths's writing is dexterous and lush. On the sexuality of nature: ''To every monkey an erection; to every insect, sackfuls of eggs; ... mushrooms conjugally fungal; every parrot on the squawk for it; every peccary rutting for it; every tendril internally sprung for it. Nothing unthrust.'' On depression: there ''is no particularity, no peony, no pip, no piano, no parsley, no play.'' On global warming: ''Ice melts, language melts, a culture melts, a climate melts, and all the music, the songlines of ice-alive melt to the engineered unmusic, the silence of a melting world.''</p>
        <p>The lesson of ''Wild'' is simple: Our bland consumer culture is not only killing any wildness within us, but also turning wilderness into suburbia. Millions of indigenous people are ''in limbo,'' caught between nature and the city as corporations pursue their land, minerals and plants. Having lost knowledge of their land, adults become alcoholics, and 13-year-olds ''careless with their one-dollar lives'' sniff gas.</p>
        <p>The remedy, Griffiths says, is a return to the garden. ''The human mind developed in wilderness and needs it still,'' she concludes. ''Coolness cools your mind and clear air brings a clarity of thought.'' It does indeed, but somehow when Griffiths went to set it all down, the heat and the riot came back.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Royte, whose ''Garbage Land: On the Secret Trail of Trash,'' has recently been published in paperback, is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Royte, whose ''Garbage Land: On the Secret Trail of Trash,'' has recently been published in paperback, is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
