<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Iraq War as a Backdrop, Speakers Reflect on the Future</title>
    <meta content="10commencement" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/us/10commencement.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070612T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENT SPEECHES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finder, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Gates, Robert M</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brokaw, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Alito, Samuel A Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinem, Gloria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grisham, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gomes, Peter J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lewis, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sachs, Jeffrey D</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Shirley Ann</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordy, Berry Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, Laura</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kamen, Dean</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Walker, Alice</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stephanopoulos, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Smiley, Tavis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="3338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Iraq War as a Backdrop, Speakers Reflect on the Future</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Iraq War as a Backdrop, Speakers Reflect on the Future</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FINDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finder, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>War in Iraq was on mind of many commencement speakers as seniors graduated from thousands of colleges and universities in recent weeks; some criticized its prosecution, others commended sacrifices of hundreds of thousands of volunteers serving in armed forces, but few ignored continuing struggle; excerpts from some speeches; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many if not most members of the class of 2007, the war in Iraq has been the constant background of their college years. And so as seniors graduated from thousands of colleges and universities in recent weeks, the war was on the mind of many commencement speakers. Some criticized its prosecution, others commended the sacrifices of the hundreds of thousands of volunteers serving in the armed forces, but few ignored the continuing struggle.</p>
        <p>''Most of you were juniors in high school when terrorists attacked America in September 2001, and it became clear we were a nation at war,'' Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates told graduates at the United States Naval Academy. ''With your credentials, you could have attended another prestigious university, and subsequently pursued a private life, with all its material rewards, your freedom and safety assured by other young men and women who volunteered to serve in the American military.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many if not most members of the class of 2007, the war in Iraq has been the constant background of their college years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For many if not most members of the class of 2007, the war in Iraq has been the constant background of their college years. And so as seniors graduated from thousands of colleges and universities in recent weeks, the war was on the mind of many commencement speakers. Some criticized its prosecution, others commended the sacrifices of the hundreds of thousands of volunteers serving in the armed forces, but few ignored the continuing struggle.</p>
        <p>''Most of you were juniors in high school when terrorists attacked America in September 2001, and it became clear we were a nation at war,'' Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates told graduates at the United States Naval Academy. ''With your credentials, you could have attended another prestigious university, and subsequently pursued a private life, with all its material rewards, your freedom and safety assured by other young men and women who volunteered to serve in the American military.''</p>
        <p>Some speakers offered a critical view of the war and its consequences. Anthony W. Marx, the president of Amherst College, spoke at Amherst's commencement of the lessons of the Roman empire, which he said declined when leaders turned away from civic action toward private pursuits, abdicating civil authority to the military.</p>
        <p>''Always, our political reach, our cultural persuasion, our economic integration and our military might are bounded,'' Dr. Marx said, drawing analogies between Rome's decline and the present. ''At those boundaries, smugness is challenged. If we fail to heed that challenge, if we do not learn from the limits of our victories, we risk the fate of Rome.''</p>
        <p>Boyd Tinsley, an electric violinist in the Dave Matthews Band, told graduates at the University of Virginia, his alma mater, ''I hope that you will once again bring us back to a time when a person's patriotism was judged by how much they loved their country, and not by how much they loved war.''</p>
        <p>Still, there was plenty of customary commencement fare. Graduates were exhorted to be bold and public spirited, to confront environmental degradation and global warming, to end poverty in the United States and curb it internationally. They were urged to find their inner voice, to leap confidently over obstacles in their careers, to avoid apathy and the lure of personal enrichment over civic engagement.</p>
        <p>''Times like these call for people like you to stand up and get to work,'' Kamala D. Harris, the San Francisco district attorney, told graduates at San Francisco State University. ''To break barriers, to drive change, roll up your sleeves instead of throwing up your hands.''</p>
        <p>There was also the usual complement of confessions. Brian Williams, the anchor of the NBC Nightly News, confided to students at Tulane that he had not earned a college degree, which he described as ''one of the great, great regrets of my life.'' The mystery novelist Mary Higgins Clark told graduates of Quinnipiac University that she could not sing, dance, cook or sew, though she acknowledged she could tell a story.</p>
        <p>And Tom Brokaw, the former news anchor at NBC, said at the Skidmore College commencement that his mentor at the University of South Dakota had characterized his undergraduate career this way: ''We always thought his first degree was an honorary degree.''</p>
        <p>Then, too, a number of speakers worried aloud that they might be going on too long. The presidential historian Michael Beschloss reminded graduates at Lafayette College that former Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey was known for giving speeches that lasted as long as three hours.</p>
        <p>''Once Humphrey did this, and even he knew he was overdoing it,'' Mr. Beschloss said. ''He yelled at the audience, 'Anybody here got a watch?' and someone yelled back, 'How about a calendar?' ''</p>
        <p>Robert M. Gates  Secretary of defense  The College of William &amp; Mary</p>
        <p>Some of you may know the story of Ryan McGlothlin, William &amp; Mary class of 2001: a high school valedictorian, Phi Beta Kappa here and Ph.D. candidate at Stanford. After being turned down by the Army for medical reasons, he persisted and joined the Marines and was deployed to Iraq in 2005. He was killed leading a platoon of riflemen near the Syrian border.</p>
        <p>Ryan's story attracted media attention because of his academic credentials and family connections. That someone like him would consider the military surprised some people. When Ryan first told his parents about joining the Marines, they asked if there was some other way to contribute. He replied that the privileged of this country bore an equal responsibility to rise to its defense.</p>
        <p>It is precisely during these trying times that America needs its best and brightest young people, from all walks of life, to step forward and commit to public service. Because while the obligations of citizenship in any democracy are considerable, they are even more profound, and more demanding, as citizens of a nation with America's global challenges and responsibilities -- and America's values and aspirations.</p>
        <p>Tom Brokaw  Former anchor, NBC News  Skidmore College</p>
        <p>You've been told during your high school years and your college years that you are now about to enter the real world, and you've been wondering what it's like. Let me tell you that the real world is not college. The real world is not high school. The real world, it turns out, is much more like junior high. You are going to encounter, for the rest of your life, the same petty jealousies, the same irrational juvenile behavior, the same uncertainty that you encountered during your adolescent years. That is your burden. We all share it with you. We wish you well.</p>
        <p>Samuel A. Alito Jr.  Supreme Court justice  St. Mary's College</p>
        <p>Decades from now, you may be different than you are today in a lot of significant ways. You may have a lot more than you have today. You may have more money and more status and more power and more accomplishments. You may also have more responsibilities, more worries, more regrets and more bruises. But underneath all of that, you will still be the same person who is here today graduating from college, and it will be good for you to stay connected with the people who know the real you.</p>
        <p>Gloria Steinem  Writer  Smith College</p>
        <p>In my generation, we were asked by the Smith vocational office how many words we could type a minute, a question that was never asked of then all-male students at Harvard or Princeton. Female-only typing was rationalized by supposedly greater female verbal skills, attention to detail, smaller fingers, goodness knows what, but the public imagination just didn't include male typists, certainly not Ivy League-educated ones.</p>
        <p>Now computers have come along, and ''typing'' is ''keyboarding.'' Suddenly, voila! -- men can type! Gives you faith in men's ability to change, doesn't it?</p>
        <p>Kamala D. Harris  San Francisco district attorney  San Francisco State University</p>
        <p>As you grow in your career, you may hit another barrier -- the limits that others set for you. A ceiling on what you can accomplish and who you can be. That happened to me. When I decided to run for district attorney, it was considered a man's job even here in San Francisco. No woman had ever been elected district attorney in San Francisco. No person of color had ever been elected district attorney in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>I remember the day I got my first poll results back. I was sitting in a small conference room, a little nervous, but very hopeful. Then I read them. I was at 6 percent. And that wasn't good. So I was told what you all have probably heard in your life, and that you will certainly hear in your future. I was told that I should wait my turn. I was told that I should give up. I was told that I had no chance.</p>
        <p>Well, I didn't listen.</p>
        <p>And I'm telling you, don't you listen either. Don't listen when they tell you that you can't do it.</p>
        <p>John Grisham  Novelist  University of Virginia</p>
        <p>Thirty years ago this week, I graduated from college, class of 1977. I don't recall much about my commencement. I do remember that the speaker was dull and long-winded, and he did inform us that the future was ours and the world was at our feet. I do remember sitting through my commencement being pretty smug: I was graduating from college, I had been accepted to law school and I knew exactly what I was going to do. I was going to study tax law. I wanted to be a tax lawyer because I was convinced I could make a lot of money representing wealthy people who did not want to pay all their taxes. That was my dream, and I had it all planned. I knew the day I was going to start law school, the day I was going to finish. I had a pretty good idea where my office was going to be. It was all planned.</p>
        <p>I don't know where this idea came from. I did not like tax law. I sure didn't know any wealthy people. Looking back, I cannot begin to remember where this idea was planted, but that was my dream. I had everything planned. The idea of writing a book had never crossed my mind. I had never written anything that had not been required by school. I had never dreamed of it.</p>
        <p>Lesson No. 1: You cannot plan the rest of your life.</p>
        <p>Rev. Peter J. Gomes  Professor, Harvard University  Augustana College</p>
        <p>Around this time of year I have an annoying habit of asking people, like you seniors, ''Do you have a job?'' You resist answering that question, but I repeat it, ''Your mother and I want to know, do you have a job?'' By job we don't mean simply something that gives you a salary; I think we really mean: ''Do you have a purpose? Do you have a calling? Do you have a vocation?''</p>
        <p>I want to suggest to you that whether or not you have a job, everyone has a vocation, and that vocation is to live a life that is worth living. The best advice I can give is that which St. Paul gives us in Romans 12, where he says to the likes of you, who all look alike from here, ''Be not conformed to this world.'' Do not join the throng. Don't get lost in the crowd. Don't be a part of the cookie-manufactured college generation, but stake out for yourselves some extraordinary, maybe even eccentric, piece and place of the world, and make it your own.</p>
        <p>Representative John Lewis  Democrat of Georgia  Adelphia University</p>
        <p>Sometimes I hear some young people say nothing has changed. I feel like saying, come and walk in my shoes. In 1956, at the age of 16, being so inspired by Dr. King along with some of my brothers and sisters and first cousins, we went to the little library in Pike County, Alabama, a public library in the little town of Troy trying to get library cards, trying to check out some books. And we were told by the librarian that the library was for whites only and not for coloreds.</p>
        <p>I never went back to that library until July 5, 1998. By that time I was a member of Congress, and I went there for a book signing of my book. Hundreds of blacks and white citizens showed up. I signed many books. In the end, they gave me a library card. It says something about the distance we've come and the progress we've made in laying down the burden of race.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey D. Sachs  Director of the Earth Institute,  Columbia University  Ursinus College</p>
        <p>It's all about choice, graduates, it really is. There is nothing about fate. It's all about choice. It's all about values, creativity, leadership. Let me give you just one small example of choice: the choice we are making, the choice we should be making. Malaria is a disease we don't know very much in this country, but it is a disease that will kill two million children this year, overwhelmingly in Africa. Two million children. Now this is a disease that is largely preventable and 100 percent treatable. And the treatment costs 80 cents. But people are so poor that two million kids are going to die this year because they don't even get access to the simplest things, like a bed net treated with insecticide that would protect them from this disease.</p>
        <p>Now here's the basic arithmetic of our time: There are 300 million places in Africa, sleeping sites where people are vulnerable to being bitten by this disease. 300 million. Each bed net costs five bucks. I trust your economics course was sufficiently good so you could quickly calculate this, it's why I went for a Ph.D. I know that's $1.5 billion. Or you could take out Excel if you want to do it that way. $1.5 billion. And yet almost none of these children sleeps under a bed net because they are too poor. But what is $1.5 billion in today's world? That is what we spend every day on the Pentagon. That's our daily military budget. So here is the calculation and here is the choice. One day's Pentagon spending would provide all sleeping sites in Africa with five years of bed net coverage, to fend off a disease which kills millions every year. That's a choice. We haven't made it. My suggestion is, the Pentagon take next Thursday off.</p>
        <p>Shirley Ann Jackson  President, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute  University of Rochester</p>
        <p>I am an optimist. I am short, and short people can only see the glass as half full. So optimize who you are and what you are. Optimize your experiences and what you have learned. Optimize others. Optimize your opportunities. Seize them and do meaningful things.</p>
        <p>Berry Gordy Jr.  Founder of Motown Records  Occidental College</p>
        <p>I was a songwriter, I was struggling, and I loved it. I wanted to be the greatest songwriter. I was writing about everything -- everything I saw. But I was not making money, and I finally agreed with everyone I ever talked to who knew me, who said, ''Boy, you need to get a job -- a real one.'' So I got a job on the Ford assembly line. And every day I watched how a bare metal frame rolling down the line would come off the other end a spanking brand-new car. Wow, I thought. What a great idea. Maybe I can do the same thing with my music -- create a place where a kid off the street can walk in one door an unknown and come out another door a star. That little thought that came to me while running up and down that assembly line at Ford Motor Company became a reality you now know as Motown.</p>
        <p>Laura Bush  First lady  Pepperdine University</p>
        <p>Today starts a period of incredible liberty and adventure -- a time to demand the most of life, before life makes specific demands on you. And as you work to make the most of what you've received, I can tell you one thing for sure: You won't waste your talents and education if you freely give them in service to others.</p>
        <p>This is especially important for the class of 2007. More than any other generation of Americans, yours is tasked with resolving challenges that lie far beyond your doorstep -- even far beyond America's borders. Between cellphones and the Internet, you have a world of information literally at your fingertips. And because our world is so small, you can't ignore the genocide in Darfur, or the human-rights abuses in Burma. You can't turn away as pandemic diseases torment an entire continent. And you can't look aside as American communities lie in ruin.</p>
        <p>Dean Kamen  Inventor and entrepreneur  Bates College</p>
        <p>We're moving from a world of stuff, from the idea that there's a finite amount of gold out there, a finite amount of almost anything out there. Throughout all of history, people fought over stuff: land, fuel, stuff. But in your generation, the most value that will be created isn't stuff anymore. It really is ideas. The Internet is an abstraction, and the value of Google exceeds the value of all the car makers. In a world that's about ideas, it's not a zero-sum game. You don't have to win by someone else losing, where you have the gold or oil or water, and somebody else doesn't.</p>
        <p>Angela Davis  Professor, University of California,  Santa Cruz  Grinnell College</p>
        <p>I hope that you will treasure the approaches and ways of thinking that you have learned more than the facts you have accumulated. For you will never discover a scarcity of facts, and these facts will be presented in such a way as to veil the ways of thinking embedded in them. And so to reveal these hidden ways of thinking, to suggest alternate frameworks, to imagine better ways of living in evolving worlds, to imagine new human relations that are freed from persisting hierarchies, whether they be racial or sexual or geopolitical -- yes, I think this is the work of educated beings. I might then ask you to think about education as the practice of freedom.</p>
        <p>Alice Walker  Novelist and poet  Naropa University</p>
        <p>When it is all too much, when the news is so bad meditation itself feels useless, and a single life feels too small a stone to offer on the altar of peace, find a human sunrise. Find those people who are committed to changing our scary reality. Human sunrises are happening all over the earth, at every moment. People gathering, people working to change the intolerable, people coming in their robes and sandals or in their rags and bare feet, and they are singing, or not, and they are chanting, or not. But they are working to bring peace, light, compassion to the infinitely frightening downhill slide of human life.</p>
        <p>George Stephanopoulos  Chief Washington correspondent, ABC News  St. John's University</p>
        <p>Solidarity and love are needed more than ever in a world that confounds us with contradictions and confronts us with the challenge of living with its paradoxes.</p>
        <p>We live in the strongest military power the world has ever known. No country in the world can match that arsenal, but years of war have taught us the painful limits of military force. And we all have been marked by the day when 19 men armed only with box cutters and a death wish struck at the heart of our culture and consciousness.</p>
        <p>You are about to enter one of the biggest economies the world has ever known. We are creating more billionaires and millionaires than ever before, but the gap between our richest and our poorest is bigger than ever before. One out of every eight Americans is living in poverty, with millions more struggling to get by. You'll be shaping a culture that for better or worse, is copied all over the world. The liberties and opportunities we take for granted make us a magnet for people from all over the world. But the power we project also makes us a target. A country with the reach of an empire cannot avoid the envy of those who have less, or the duty to help care for them.</p>
        <p>Tavis Smiley  Radio and television talk show host  Rutgers University</p>
        <p>The tragedy of life does not lie, young folk, in not reaching your goal. The tragedy lies in having no goal to reach. It is not a calamity to die with dreams unfulfilled, but it is a calamity not to dream. It is not a disaster to not be able to capture your ideals, but it is a disaster to have no ideals to capture. It is not a disgrace to not be able to reach all the stars, but it is a disgrace to have no stars to reach for.</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENT SPEECHES</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 12, 2007, Tuesday  An article on Sunday about commencement speeches at colleges around the country referred imprecisely to comments by Boyd Tinsley, an electric violinist in the Dave Matthews Band, at his alma mater, the University of Virginia. He spoke the day before graduation at the university's valedictory exercises, not at the commencement. As the roundup of speeches noted, the novelist John Grisham was the commencement speaker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 12, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about commencement speeches at colleges around the country referred imprecisely to comments by Boyd Tinsley, an electric violinist in the Dave Matthews Band, at his alma mater, the University of Virginia. He spoke the day before graduation at the university's valedictory exercises, not at the commencement. As the roundup of speeches noted, the novelist John Grisham was the commencement speaker.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
