<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: April 08, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Bestpaper.nonfiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: April 08, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 24, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 24, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>FICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>TWO LITTLE GIRLS IN BLUE, by Mary Higgins Clark. (Pocket, $7.99.) A small girl communicates telepathically with her kidnapped twin.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>JUDGE &amp; JURY, by James Patterson and Andrew Gross. (Warner, $9.99.) An aspiring actress and an F.B.I. agent join forces against a powerful mobster.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>40</p>
        <p>THE MEMORY KEEPER'S DAUGHTER, by Kim Edwards. (Penguin, $14.) A doctor's decision to secretly send his newborn daughter, who has Down syndrome, to an institution haunts everyone involved.</p>
        <p>4*</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>SHIVER, by Lisa Jackson. (Zebra, $7.99.) A New Orleans detective tracks a serial killer.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>MORNING COMES SOFTLY, by Debbie Macomber. (Avon, $7.99.) A reprint of a romance involving a librarian from Louisiana and a Montana rancher.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>True believer, by Nicholas Sparks. (Warner, $12.95.) A hip young New Yorker finds love with a beautiful librarian who lives in a North Carolina town.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>PRIOR BAD ACTS, by Tami Hoag. (Bantam, $7.99.) Two Minneapolis detectives search for a kidnapped judge who has been trying a murder case.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A WICKED GENTLEMAN, by Jane Feather. (Pocket Star, $7.99.) A cryptic nobleman takes curious interest in a woman's shabby London home (and in her).</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>HEY, GOOD LOOKING, by Fern Michaels. (Pocket, $7.99.) Family feuds and forgiveness in Baton Rouge.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>MCKETTRICK'S PRIDE, by Linda Lael Miller. (HQN, $7.99.) A fiery Chicagoan stirs long-buried feelings of romance in Rance McKettrick.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>DEADLY GAME, by Christine Feehan. (Jove, $7.99.) Two Ghostwalkers, one a warrior and assassin, join forces to save victims of a wicked breeding program.</p>
        <p>12*</p>
        <p>112</p>
        <p>THE KITE RUNNER, by Khaled Hosseini. (Riverhead, $15.95 and $14.) An Afghan-American returns to Kabul to learn how a childhood friend has fared.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>SNOW FLOWER AND THE SECRET FAN, by Lisa See. (Random House, $13.95.) The lives of two women in 19th-century China.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE NAMESAKE, by Jhumpa Lahiri. (Mariner/Houghton Mifflin, $14.) Tracing the fortunes of a Bengali-American, Gogol Ganguli.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>THE TRAITOR, by Stephen Coonts. (St. Martin's, $7.99.) A C.I.A. officer develops a strategy to infiltrate Al Qaeda and tracks a French agent with Middle Eastern entanglements.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>MY SISTER'S KEEPER, by Jodi Picoult. (Washington Square, $14.) A girl sues her parents after learning they want her to donate a kidney to her sibling.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>THE MEASURE OF A MAN, by Sidney Poitier. (HarperSanFrancisco, $14.95.) The movie actor's spiritual autobiography.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>63</p>
        <p>THE GLASS CASTLE, by Jeannette Walls. (Scribner, $14.) The author recalls a bizarre childhood during which she and her siblings were constantly moved.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>EAT, PRAY, LOVE, by Elizabeth Gilbert. (Penguin Books, $15.) A writer's yearlong journey in search of self takes her to Italy, India and Indonesia.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING, by Joan Didion. (Vintage, $13.95.) The author's attempts to come to terms with the death of her husband.</p>
        <p>5*</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>90 MINUTES IN HEAVEN, by Don Piper with Cecil Murphey. (Revell, $12.99.) A minister's otherworldly experience after an accident.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>STUMBLING ON HAPPINESS, by Daniel Gilbert. (Vintage, $14.95.) A Harvard professor explores why people can't predict what will make them happy.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>70</p>
        <p>DREAMS FROM MY FATHER, by Barack Obama. (Three Rivers, $13.95.) Life as the son of a black African father and white American mother.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>57</p>
        <p>NIGHT, by Elie Wiesel. (Hill &amp; Wang, $9.) The horrors of Auschwitz and Buchenwald.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>THREE CUPS OF TEA, by Greg Mortenson and David Oliver Relin. (Penguin Books, $15.) A former climber builds schools in Pakistan and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>136</p>
        <p>THE TIPPING POINT, by Malcolm Gladwell. (Back Bay/Little, Brown, $14.95.) A journalist's study of social epidemics, otherwise known as fads.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>ZODIAC, by Robert Graysmith. (Berkley, $7.99.) An account of the hunt for a serial killer in California; the basis for the movie of the same title.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>137</p>
        <p>RUNNING WITH SCISSORS, by Augusten Burroughs. (Picador, $14 and $7.99.) In the 1970s, a young boy lives with a crazy psychiatrist in a squalid household.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>THE POLITICALLY INCORRECT GUIDE TO GLOBAL WARMING AND ENVIRONMENTALISM, by Christopher C. Horner. (Regnery, $19.95.) Debating the causes, extent and effects of climate change.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>DON'T MAKE A BLACK WOMAN TAKE OFF HER EARRINGS, by Tyler Perry. (Riverhead, $12.95.) The man behind ''Diary of a Mad Black Woman'' muses on life.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS, by Chris Gardner with Quincy Troupe and Mim Eichler Rivas. (Amistad/HarperCollins, $14.95.) Gardner's life story, from a grim childhood to homelessness to success.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>THE FREEDOM WRITERS DIARY, by the Freedom Writers with Erin Gruwell. (Broadway, $13.95.) Students considered ''unteachable'' write about their lives; the basis for the movie ''Freedom Writers.''</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Hardcover</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>THE SECRET, by Rhonda Byrne. (Atria/Beyond Words, $23.95.) The law of attraction as a key to getting what you want.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>YOU: ON A DIET, by Michael F. Roizen and Mehmet C. Oz et al. (Free Press, $25.) Weight-loss tips, from the authors of ''You: The Owner's Manual.''</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>WOMEN &amp; MONEY, by Suze Orman. (Spiegel &amp; Grau, $24.95.) How women can achieve financial security.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE FIBER35 DIET, by Brenda Watson with Leonard Smith. (Free Press, $26.) The health benefits of fruits, vegetables, legumes and whole grains.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>GO PUT YOUR STRENGTHS TO WORK, by Marcus Buckingham. (Free Press, $30.) A guide to being more productive, focused and creative at work.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Paperback</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>EVERYDAY FOOD. (Clarkson Potter, $24.95.) Recipes from Martha Stewart Living's sister magazine.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>306</p>
        <p>WHAT TO EXPECT WHEN YOU'RE EXPECTING, by Heidi Murkoff, Arlene Eisenberg and Sandee. Hathaway. (Workman, $13.95.) Advice for parents-to-be. ()</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>318</p>
        <p>RICH DAD, POOR DAD, by Robert T. Kiyosaki with Sharon L. Lechter. (Warner, $16.95.) Teaching one's children how to get rich and stay rich. ()</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE PURPOSE-DRIVEN LIFE, by Rick Warren. (Zondervan, $14.99.) The meaning of life through God. ().</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>THE LAW OF ATTRACTION, by Esther and Jerry Hicks. (Hay House, $14.95.) Using the laws that govern the universe to improve your life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
