<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats' Rise Has Pluses, Say G.O.P. Centrists</title>
    <meta content="07moderates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/washington/07moderates.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats' Rise Has Pluses, Say G.O.P. Centrists</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Democrats’ Rise Has Pluses, Say G.O.P. Centrists</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many Republicans from swing districts in Northeast are finding that life under Democratic rule has its advantages; moderate Republicans were stepchildren of their party during 12 years that Republicans controlled House; they were expected to vote with their conservative leadership on crucial issues, even if it meant taking positions that could anger centrist voters back home; Democrats made some of their deepest inroads last year in Northeast; Republican moderates remaining in House are vowing to pursue their centrist positions more assertively, even if it means endorsing Democratic initiatives; Republican House leadership, concerned about losing even more seats in 2008, appears to be showing pragmatic streak by allowing moderates to stray more freely from party fold (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Democratic ascendance on Capitol Hill was supposed to usher in dark days for Republicans, it is hard to tell from talking to moderate ones like Mike Ferguson, who represents a suburban district in central New Jersey.</p>
        <p>As the new Democrat-led House rushed to complete its business before adjourning for spring break this week, Representative Ferguson was marveling at the many bills that had been passed in Congress's first 100 days, including one that would make it easier for unions to organize and another that would increase the minimum wage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many Republicans from swing districts in the Northeast have voted with Democrats on some bills in the House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the Democratic ascendance on Capitol Hill was supposed to usher in dark days for Republicans, it is hard to tell from talking to moderate ones like Mike Ferguson, who represents a suburban district in central New Jersey.</p>
        <p>As the new Democrat-led House rushed to complete its business before adjourning for spring break this week, Representative Ferguson was marveling at the many bills that had been passed in Congress's first 100 days, including one that would make it easier for unions to organize and another that would increase the minimum wage.</p>
        <p>''Under the Republican majority, those bills would have never gotten to the floor,'' he explained before heading back to his district. ''Now they have been brought to the floor, and I've voted for them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferguson's enthusiasm captures a peculiar political reality in the Capitol: many Republicans from swing districts in the Northeast are finding that life under Democratic rule has its advantages.</p>
        <p>During the 12 years that Republicans controlled the House, moderate Republicans were the stepchildren of their party, expected to vote with their conservative leadership on crucial issues, even if it meant taking positions that could anger centrist voters back home.</p>
        <p>In fact, the Democrats made some of their deepest inroads last year in the Northeast. A total of 10 Republican incumbents in the House were defeated in four states -- New Hampshire, Connecticut, New York and Pennsylvania -- where the challengers aggressively tried to tie the incumbents to President Bush and his conservative allies on the Hill.</p>
        <p>Now, with those losses still fresh in their minds, Republican moderates remaining in the House are vowing to pursue their centrist positions more assertively, even if it means endorsing Democratic initiatives.</p>
        <p>And the new Republican House leadership, concerned about losing even more seats in 2008, appears to be showing a pragmatic streak by allowing moderates to stray more freely from the party fold.</p>
        <p>''If there's a good idea, we should work to get it done, regardless of whether it's a Republican or a Democrat who came up with the idea,'' said Mr. Ferguson, who was re-elected last year with just 49.5 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>Since taking control of the House in January, Democrats have pushed through bills that would raise the federal minimum wage, overturn President Bush's restrictions on embryonic stem cell research, cut interest rates on college loans and implement Sept. 11 commission security recommendations.</p>
        <p>Many moderate Republicans joined the Democrats in supporting those measures, including Representative Christopher Shays of Connecticut, who won his own re-election campaign with 51 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>''Democrats basically grabbed the center and ran with it politically,'' Mr. Shays said, adding that he would continue working with the Democrats provided they did not veer from the political center.</p>
        <p>Representative Peter T. King, a Republican from Long Island who regularly sides with conservative Republicans on abortion and immigration issues, said there were ''definitely positives'' in the direction in which Democrats had taken the House.</p>
        <p>''For a pro-labor Republican like me, it's been very beneficial,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a measure of how competitive the Northeast could be next year, White House political strategists have put together a list of vulnerable House Republicans that includes five from the region: Mr. Shays, Mr. Ferguson, Representatives John Randy Kuhl Jr. from New York's Southern Tier, James T. Walsh from the Syracuse region and Jim Gerlach of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The list was obtained and circulated by Congressional Democrats, who are making plans to single out Northeastern Republicans for defeat in 2008, in the hopes of completing what many in their party see as an inevitable Democratic realignment in the region.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Walsh's 25th Congressional District, for example, Dan Maffei, a Democrat who came within about 3,400 votes of defeating Mr. Walsh, is planning to run again next year and has been meeting with party leaders and donors in Albany and Washington.</p>
        <p>And in the neighboring 29th Congressional District, Eric Massa, a Democrat, has told party leaders in Washington that he plans to challenge Mr. Kuhl, who defeated him last November with just 52 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Mr. Maffei argued that his prospects of winning in a Democratic state like New York were greatly improved in 2008 because the presidential election would draw thousands of additional voters to the polls, most of them Democrats.</p>
        <p>''The climate of a presidential year will carry us,'' said Mr. Maffei, who announced his candidacy on Friday.</p>
        <p>Yet, paradoxically, the agenda that House Democratic leaders have been advancing over the last few weeks may actually give moderate Republicans political cover -- certainly more than when conservative leaders ran the House.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Walsh's case, he has already sided with Democrats on several major pieces of legislation, including a nonbinding resolution opposing President Bush's call for sending additional troops to Baghdad.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walsh's assistants say the votes reflect a centrist point of view that Mr. Walsh has held for years, but Mr. Maffei has described Mr. Walsh's votes as opportunistic.</p>
        <p>''It has nothing to do with ideology,'' Mr. Maffei said. ''It's purely political.''</p>
        <p>The House's Republican moderates are a relatively cohesive bunch of about 30 lawmakers who meet as a caucus (called the Tuesday Group) each week to discuss issues like health care and jobs.</p>
        <p>Recently, eight members of the group called on President Bush and Democratic leaders on the Hill to make climate change a top environmental issue this session. Increasingly, moderate Republicans have been reaching across the political aisle without fear of retribution from their own leaders.</p>
        <p>The situation is a far cry from previous Congresses, when the Republican leadership squelched internal divisions and passed bill after bill on party-line votes, including budget cuts to popular programs. The leadership also pushed ideologically freighted legislation that had little chance of becoming law.</p>
        <p>Last summer, for example, the Republican House leadership embarked on a legislative drive to highlight conservative causes like gun rights and new abortion restrictions. The effort was aimed at rallying conservative voters in advance of the fall elections. But moderates complained that it threatened their re-election prospects.</p>
        <p>This is not to say that the Republican leaders are completely passive these days. They managed to hold their party together in opposition to a recent Democratic proposal to bring most American combat troops home from Iraq next year. The proposal passed on a vote of 218 to 212, with all but two Republicans opposing it. All of the Northeastern moderates voted against the measure.</p>
        <p>But by and large, Mr. Shays said, leaders of his party are giving members greater leeway to pursue divergent views more assertively.</p>
        <p>''You don't have a Tom DeLay coming in with an ideology,'' he said, referring to the former Republican majority leader whose tight control over rank-and-file members of the House earned him the nickname the Hammer.</p>
        <p>''They're picking their battles,'' Mr. Shays continued. ''Leaders are not trying to push their own individual agenda or their own individual ideology.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walsh said that part of the reason Republican leaders had loosened their grip was that they no longer had the burden of producing the 218-vote majority needed to govern in the House.</p>
        <p>''When you are in the majority, you have to produce votes; so there's tremendous pressure,'' he said. ''That's not the case today. It's a very different environment.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. King said Republican House leaders had another reason for going easy on members.</p>
        <p>''They don't want to lose seats,'' he said. ''They're not pushing members to take suicidal votes or take a bullet for the team.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
