<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer Weekends: Get Out and Go</title>
    <meta content="25weekend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070601T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1849708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mummert, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E5DA1630F936A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2391" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer Weekends: Get Out and Go</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER MUMMERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mummert, Roger</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article offers variety of choices for brief summer vacation escapes in New York, Long Island, Pennsylvania, New Jersey and Connecticut; photos; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MEMORIAL DAY triggers a series of inexorable actions. Beach romances fly off bookshelves. White pants and Hawaiian shirts tumble out of closets. Pools are opened, rooftop parties commence and patio umbrellas are unfurled in a backyard chorus of cranks and squeaks.</p>
        <p>And, just as surely, directions from Mapquest shoot out of printers as we plan explorations under sunny, soon to be summery skies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MEMORIAL DAY triggers a series of inexorable actions. Beach romances fly off bookshelves. White pants and Hawaiian shirts tumble out of closets. Pools are opened, rooftop parties commence and patio umbrellas are unfurled in a backyard chorus of cranks and squeaks.</p>
        <p>And, just as surely, directions from Mapquest shoot out of printers as we plan explorations under sunny, soon to be summery skies.</p>
        <p>In the New York metropolitan area, the choices for brief summer escapes are rich indeed -- from visiting a string of 11 old lighthouses on the New Jersey coast to churning butter in a 19th-century village on Long Island. And in this era of concern about being carbon neutral, there's a lot to be said for not burning jet fuel on every family vacation. Some of the following destinations can easily be reached by public transit, as well.</p>
        <p>So whether you're exploring with family in tow, as a couple or even solo, here are some opportunities to time-travel back to life in a Pequot village or milk a cow on a Mennonite farm of today. And as the endless summer unfolds, nothing beats riding a bike through a fragrant meadow where steam locomotives once blackened the skies, or paddling down a lazy river just contemplating nature as cows eye you suspiciously from muddy banks.</p>
        <p>New York State</p>
        <p>THE HARLEM VALLEY RAIL TRAIL -- A century and a half ago, it was the northern route of the New York and Harlem Railroad. Today, it is the Harlem Valley Rail Trail, where bicyclists of all skill levels can pedal through the cool forests and sweet-scented farmlands of the Taconic Hills. There is bicycling now on 4- and 12-mile public stretches of paved rail bed, united by country roads where riding is fairly easy. When it is eventually completed, the trail will stretch 46 miles from Wassaic in Dutchess County to Chatham in Columbia County.</p>
        <p>Before heading out, visit the Web site of the Harlem Valley Rail Trail Association (www.hvrt.org) for descriptions of trail conditions and rich details on the nature that surrounds the trail. The site also tells the history of the area, where train lines between Albany and New York City brought commerce and development. To give your bottom a break, lock up the bikes in Taconic State Park in Copake Falls, and hike up the ridge to the dramatic Bash Bish Falls, in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The Harlem Valley Rail Trail meanders through interesting towns where you can stop for a bite to eat. Millerton, which holds a parade this Memorial Day, has two such spots on Main Street: Taro's Pizzeria (518-789-6630) and Irving Farm Coffee House (518-789-2020) for a grilled chicken sandwich or vegetable panini. Millerton also will be the start/end point of the Harlem Valley Rail Ride on July 29, organized by Bike New York (www.bikenewyork.org).</p>
        <p>Simmons' Way Village Inn (www.simmonsway.com) at 53 Main Street in Millerton is a nine-bedroom Victorian mansion run as a country inn and restaurant. Sit and enjoy the breeze on the large porch of this 1854 home. The contemporary American cuisine restaurant, Martha's, serves dinner Wednesday through Saturday and makes use of local farm products. A movie house is across the street, and the rail trail is two blocks away. Room rates begin at $189 and go to $225.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
        <p>OLD-TIME FARMING AND BASEBALL -- Old Bethpage Village Restoration (www.nassaucountyny.gov/agencies/parks) is a 165-acre village and working farm that recreates a 19th-century Long Island hamlet, assembled from more than 50 period homes and commercial structures from surrounding towns. Children can churn butter or scribble on a slate in the one-room schoolhouse, pet farm animals and buy penny candy in the Layton General Store (1866).</p>
        <p>This weekend there will be period crafts like sheep shearing and carding, as well as concerts. Each Sunday in summer, ''old time baseball'' is played in the uniforms of Abner Doubleday's era. A Model A Ford show is scheduled for June. In July, an Independence Day celebration typical of 1865 includes a meeting of a temperance society, and a Civil War battle is staged. A cafeteria has vending machines, but for real dining, fast-forward to the present at La Piazza (516-938-0800), a local favorite in nearby Plainview, for wood-oven pizza and Italian specialties.</p>
        <p>The Inn at Fox Hollow (www.theinnatfoxhollow.com) at 7755 Jericho Turnpike in Woodbury is a luxury all-suites hotel. Breakfast is included each day, as is dinner Sunday through Thursday. There are an outdoor pool and a hot tub as well as a workout room. The hotel is across from a park and next to a public golf course. Studio suites begin at $269 and one-bedroom suites at $289.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM ROW, FOR CHILDREN -- It's totally hands-on at the Cradle of Aviation (www.cradleofaviation.org), one of a trio of family-oriented museums in Garden City. The aviation museum offers children a chance to climb into a jet simulator and experience G-force. An IMAX theater has eye-popping programs like ''Hurricane on the Bayou,'' which simulates the fury of Hurricane Katrina, and ''Magnificent Desolation: Walking on the Moon,'' which relates the sensation experienced by the 12 men who have set foot on the moon's surface. Over the summer, there are aerospace minicamps devoted to weekly themes like astronomy or space exploration.</p>
        <p>Entire families can take part in folk art workshops at the Long Island Children's Museum (www.licm.org). A summer arts series has live performances and films, and children can explore flowers in garden workshops. An interactive exhibit called AirPlay presents the science of air and wind.</p>
        <p>The vital message of fire safety and prevention is a hands-on experience at the Nassau County Firefighters Museum and Education Center (www.ncfiremuseum.com). Visitors learn to stop, drop and roll, and to crawl to safety beneath a simulated cloud of smoke. A run-through of a 911 call makes the experience of a fire emergency very real. Once the education is done, kids can don real firefighter's turnout gear and climb atop a 1934 Mack firetruck.</p>
        <p>There's dining at the Red Planet Cafe in the Cradle of Aviation. Eat burgers, wraps, pizzas and fresh salads with spaceships and satellites hanging overhead.</p>
        <p>The Garden City Hotel (www.gardencityhotel.com), at 45 Seventh Street in Garden City, is a luxury hotel dating from 1874, but it has been renovated and updated. There is an indoor pool, and movie theaters, shopping, sports events and beaches are nearby. The hotel's Polo Restaurant offers fine dining, and its Rein Bar &amp; Bistro accommodates youngsters' culinary desires. Room rates begin at $250, suites start at $689.</p>
        <p>Pennsylvania</p>
        <p>DOWN THE BRANDYWINE -- The placid waters of Brandywine Creek provide a welcome respite from life's pressures. On a hot day, nothing beats floating downstream Huck Finn style and dangling your toes in the water as cows moo and blue skies peek through a canopy of oak and maple trees. The Northbrook Canoe Company (northbrookcanoe.com) near West Chester, Pa., rents canoes (beginning at $35), kayaks ($25) and inner tubes ($15). There are seven routes on the meandering west branch of the Brandywine. The shortest trip is an hour, and more ambitious paddlers can journey six and a half hours and end up in Delaware. Paddlers often spot trout and minnows, as well as birds, frogs, turtles and, on rare occasions, foxes. While toweling off back at headquarters, you can order cheeseburgers, hot dogs and chicken nuggets from the Food Shack. There's a picnic grove for those who prefer to pack a lunch.</p>
        <p>The Brandywine River Hotel at 1609 Baltimore Pike at Routes 1 and 100 in Chadds Ford (800-274-9644; www.brandywineriverhotel.com), is a European-style hotel with 40 rooms and suites. Breakfast and afternoon tea are included, and the hotel, which is pet-friendly, is near the Brandywine River Museum and Longwood Gardens. Rates begin at $129 and suites at $159.</p>
        <p>LANCASTER COUNTY FARM STAYS -- Here's your chance to don some overalls and be a farmer for a weekend. More than 30 working farms in Lancaster County, Pa., participate in a farm stay program (www.padutchcountry.com), many in the heart of Amish country, where you can skip across wooden bridges, wave to kids in buggies and spot one-room schoolhouses as you drive through fertile farmlands.</p>
        <p>Verdant View Farm (www.verdantview.com) in Paradise is a fourth-generation family-run dairy farm, where visitors in the nine guest rooms are welcomed into the family -- and into the barn, as well. The owners, Ginny and Don Ranck, invite guests to collect eggs in the henhouse (they'll be used for the farm breakfast), help milk cows twice a day in the milking parlor and bottle-feed newborn calves. You also can leash a resident lamb or goat and lead it around the farm, if you promise to keep it out of Ginny's garden. There are bass to be fished for in the pond, hay tunnels to be crawled through and wagon rides to be taken around the farm's 118 acres. Rooms start at $65 and go up to $340 for an entire house.</p>
        <p>Get used to hearing the whistle of passing trains from the nearby Strasburg Railroad. The railroad's vintage steam locomotives chug across the farm's fields en route to Paradise; (www.strasburgrailroad.com). Tickets are $11 ($6 ages 3 to 11) for coach class to $18 ($13 for children) in a Victorian-style first-class parlor car; lunch and dinner are available on the train.</p>
        <p>For a quick bite (sandwiches and soups) nearby, there's Isaac's Restaurant and Deli (717-687-7699). For more belly-filling fare (and a petting zoo, too), try the grand smorgasbord at the Hershey's Farm Restaurant and Inn (800-827-8635).</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
        <p>LIGHTHOUSE TRAIL -- You can get a lofty view of New Jersey's rich maritime history by visiting the lighthouses that dot the shoreline from Sandy Hook Lighthouse overlooking Lower New York Bay to Cape May at the southern tip of the state. Eleven lighthouses are open to the public, and New Jersey Tourism (www.visitnj.org) issues a free 17-page booklet outlining their history.</p>
        <p>At some lighthouses, you can climb to the top for majestic views. One rewarding stop is the Barnegat Lighthouse (609-494-2016) on Long Beach Island. ''Old Barney,'' 165 feet tall, dates from 1858, when it replaced the original 1834 lighthouse. Its 217 steps require 10 to 15 minutes to climb. An interpretive center outlines the history of shipwrecks and the role that lighthouses played in steering sailors away from treacherous shoals. Many lighthouses are endangered by coastal erosion, and the shifting topography of barrier islands is explained here.</p>
        <p>Before lacing up your climbing shoes, visit the Web site of the New Jersey Lighthouse Society (www.njlhs.org), a preservation organization. It has photos and historical accounts of lighthouses open to the public, as well as those privately owned, and also ''lost lights'' of yesteryear.</p>
        <p>The Sand Castle, at 710 Bayview Avenue in Barnegat Light (www.sandcastlelbi.com), is walking distance from Old Barney. The hotel offers bicycles and beach tags to guests. There is no restaurant, but a full breakfast is served. Room rates begin at $275.</p>
        <p>Connecticut</p>
        <p>DINOSAUR AND OTHER BONES -- A bronze torosaurus, standing two stories high and 21 feet long, guards the entrance to the Peabody Museum of Natural History (www.peabody.yale.edu) at Yale University in New Haven. The torosaurus has friends there, too. Poised in the museum's great hall are full-size skeletons of a brontosaurus and stegosaurus and the head of a triceratops. Also notable are the 110-foot long ''Age of Reptiles'' mural and its companion, the 60-foot-long ''Age of Mammals'' by Rudolph F. Zallinger, whose work is being celebrated there his year. The Discovery Room has hands-on specimens like real dinosaur teeth, as well as live snakes and poison dart frogs that visitors distinctly do not touch. An exhibit called ''Fossils Fragments: The Riddle of Human Origins'' features a skeleton of one of the early members of our genus, Homo, discovered in Kenya. The many questions about evolution that are posed here will probably fuel a family discussion all the way home.</p>
        <p>During the summer the Peabody holds science camps.</p>
        <p>Many good restaurants are within walking distance, and the museum provides a handout listing them. On Whitney Avenue are Clark's Dairy Luncheonette (203-777-2728) for burgers, grilled cheese and ice cream, as well as Anna Liffey's Irish Pub and Restaurant (203-773-1776) and Sandra's Place Soul Food (203-787-4123). A short drive away is New Haven's Little Italy. Clam pizzas are the rage at Frank Pepe's Pizzeria Napoletana (203-865-5762), one of many dining options along the highly aromatic Wooster Street.</p>
        <p>The Omni New Haven Hotel at Yale (www.omninewhaven.com) at 155 Temple Street in New Haven, Conn., is a luxury hotel with a traditional New England design. It is within walking distance of the campus and the New Haven Green, as well as a wealth of cultural sites. Children receive backpacks with toys and activities at check-in, as part of the Omni Sensational Kids program, which also includes a scavenger hunt. There are sweeping views of New Haven from John Davenport's, a contemporary New England-style restaurant on the hotel's 19th floor. Room rates begin at $229.</p>
        <p>POWWOWING -- Visitors can experience life in a coastal Pequot village of the 16th century and learn to speak a few Algonquin phrases at the tribally owned Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center (www.pequotmuseum.org) in eastern Connecticut. The 85,000-square-foot museum claims to have more exhibition space than any other American Indian center in the country. There are computer-interactive exhibits, dioramas, a children's library, documentary films and live events. The surrounding countryside can be viewed from an 18-story tower and observation deck. A current exhibition, ''Fifty Years of Powwow,'' intersperses photographs with displays of Native American dance regalia.</p>
        <p>Coming up this summer are a powwow festival (July 11 and 12) with native dances, songs and crafts, as well as a field day (Aug. 4) where kids compete in native games and sports such as lacrosse, shinny (something like field hockey) and spear tossing with an atlatl, a kind of sling. The family fare in the museum restaurant includes American Indian specialties like Indian pudding and fry breads and also buffalo burgers.</p>
        <p>For entertainment and accommodations from the present century, the Foxwoods Resort and Casino (www.foxwoods.com) is on the Mashantucket Reservation in Mashantucket. Foxwoods has three hotels and more than 30 restaurants. Indoor pools and a video arcade are popular with kids. Weekend rates at the Two Trees Inn begin at $225.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 1, 2007, Friday  An article last Friday, about summer weekend destinations in and near New York City, misstated the age of the Garden City Hotel in Garden City, N.Y. The hotel dates to 1983, not 1874. No part of any of the three previous Garden City Hotel buildings was used in the construction of the current building, which is in a different location on the property.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 1, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article last Friday, about summer weekend destinations in and near New York City, misstated the age of the Garden City Hotel in Garden City, N.Y. The hotel dates to 1983, not 1874. No part of any of the three previous Garden City Hotel buildings was used in the construction of the current building, which is in a different location on the property.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
