<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up North, Looking For Direction</title>
    <meta content="17yardley" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/weekinreview/17yardley.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS: COLD SPELL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alaska</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up North, Looking For Direction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Up North, Looking for Direction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM YARDLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCOURING the tundra for the source of the next big boom is the Alaskan way.</p>
        <p>Skin it, mine it, fish for it, drill for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alaska, the frontier boom state, is looking at scandal, waning political clout and maybe even a bust.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCOURING the tundra for the source of the next big boom is the Alaskan way.</p>
        <p>Skin it, mine it, fish for it, drill for it.</p>
        <p>It has all paid off, at least for a while. It has also propped up the state's place in the national mythology -- the alluring frontier detached on the map but also a critical supplier of the world's wants.</p>
        <p>Now, as oil production continues its steady decline, and the temperature creeps higher, it is far from clear what the next big boom might be, or what Alaska might become without one. Nearing a half-century of statehood, the wildest and most mysterious of American places could use a reliable map to the future. Fog seems to be rolling in instead.</p>
        <p>Political scandal has erupted, leading to indictments for state lawmakers and even raising questions over the dealings of Senator Ted Stevens, ''Uncle Ted,'' the great provider for the Great Land. Global warming is puddling the permafrost and threatening coastal villages. The federal government, which spends more money on Alaska per capita than it does on any other state, may no longer be such a sugar daddy. The population, which once surged and plummeted with fortunes found and dashed, now relies more on trusty old biological reproduction for replenishment than some new rush of speculators.</p>
        <p>''It's sort of like this dance that keeps on changing, but it keeps us dancing,'' said Neal Fried, an economist with the state's Department of Labor. ''In some ways you just have to sit back and say, wow, this is pretty amazing.''</p>
        <p>Or you could confront it.</p>
        <p>''Alaskans are kind of saying, What is the next boom?'' said Senator Lisa Murkowski. ''I think it is a hard question to answer and I think it's wise for us to talk kind of beyond the boom-and-bust path we've been on. Why does it have to be a boom and bust? When will we get ourselves on a more sustainable path?''</p>
        <p>Or you could drop all diplomacy.</p>
        <p>''We're basically divorced from reality up here,'' said Andrew Halcro, a Republican who ran for governor last year as an independent. ''People say: 'Wow, we got a Gap or a Banana Republic, everything must be cool.' But what you don't look at is the big picture.''</p>
        <p>In Alaska, of course, the picture is really big. In a state with 663,000 square miles and barely one person for each of them, it is easy to see things from a different point of view.</p>
        <p>''We've been saying disaster is around the corner for years and we've been wrong many times,'' said Gregg Erickson, an economist in Juneau who writes a newsletter about the state budget.</p>
        <p>Asked what the future might hold once the oil finally does dry up, Mr. Erickson said: ''Who knows? But we can see some outlines.''</p>
        <p>Many ideas come straight out of the old extraction-economy playbook. The new Republican governor, Sarah Palin, a former suburban mayor, beauty pageant queen and exponent of something previously untranslatable in Alaska politics, ''transparent government,'' is pushing for a new pipeline that would pump trillions of cubic feet of natural gas from the North Slope to the lower 48 states, potentially delivering another Alaska boom, or at least a boomlet.</p>
        <p>Still, even if that happens, and virtually everyone in Alaska hopes it does, most experts say the benefits will be far less than those of the Trans Alaska Pipeline, whose construction, completed 30 years ago, transformed the state.</p>
        <p>Since the oil bust of the mid-1980s, the economy has been growing, slowly but steadily. A Target store, the first in Alaska, is set for construction outside downtown Anchorage, a stamp of retail arrival. But the backbone of the growth has been oil and federal money.</p>
        <p>The underlying challenges are only expected to sharpen: The state has a small, aging population. It depends on oil for more than 80 percent of state revenue. While tourism, fishing and cargo shipping are growing, they are not about to supplant oil, and there is no other obvious source for major revenue that could. Not only is there no state income tax or many other fees, nearly every Alaskan gets a check each year from the state based on investments from oil revenues. Last year, the checks were for $1,107.</p>
        <p>That tension is not new, but there is more. Beginning in the late 1990s, as Mr. Stevens, a Republican, became chairman of the Senate's Appropriations Committee, federal spending in Alaska eventually doubled, going from $4.2 billion in 1995 to $8.4 billion in 2004. Now that Democrats have taken control of Congress, the senator is no longer chairman.</p>
        <p>''They see about three years' worth of federal projects in the pipeline, and then after that there's nothing,'' said Mr. Halcro, the former candidate for governor. ''I've heard from very credible sources that the people of Alaska are going to be surprised at how little federal money is coming in.''</p>
        <p>One of those sources was Senator Murkowski, also a Republican. She was appointed to office in 2002 by her father, Frank, who held the seat for 22 years before he left to run for governor. Ms. Murkowski said last week that with Democrats in control and so-called earmarks under greater scrutiny in both parties, ''the way we have typically done business or operated as a state is changing.'' Big building projects like, say, Ted Stevens Anchorage International Airport, may be on the way out.</p>
        <p>''When you think about how the monies have come to the state, so much of it has been because we needed to build a certain capacity that states in the lower 48 have had for generations,'' Ms. Murkowski said. ''We were in that catching-up period. It wasn't more than our fair share, it was our fair share. We were maturing as a state.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Murkowski, 50, is among a younger generation of politicians, along with Ms. Palin, 43, and Mayor Mark Begich of Anchorage, a Democrat, who cast themselves as more inclined to find common ground than make deals behind closed doors.</p>
        <p>Senator Murkowski uses words like ''sustainable'' when she talks about developing natural resources, and she expresses interest in alternative energy like ocean, wind, geothermal and solar. But like Senator Stevens and Don Young, the state's sole representative in the House and also a Republican, she supports drilling for oil in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, a proposal that would increase oil revenues but has little support in the Democratic Congress.</p>
        <p>Alaska has an emergency option should it ever need one, and it is like no other: the Permanent Fund, a $39 billion colossus built on oil revenues over the course of 31 years. The account earns the interest that provides residents with their annual dividend.</p>
        <p>But the few politicians who publicly support tapping it for other purposes are usually met with an icy public response. Few are standing up for big new taxes, either. Calls for a ''long-range plan'' are drowned out in the search for a new resource boom. How about a controversial gold mine in Bristol Bay? The natural gas pipeline? Drilling in the refuge?</p>
        <p>''People keep punting because they hope the next big development is going to bail us out,'' said Stanley E. Senner, executive director of Audubon Alaska, who spends much of his time working to protect wilderness areas from some of those proposals. ''That constant pressure is there. You have a lot of Alaska sort of collectively holding its breath.''</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS: COLD SPELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
