<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Perennial Search for Perfect Wheat</title>
    <meta content="05wheat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/science/05wheat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wheat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFDC1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1262" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Perennial Search for Perfect Wheat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Perennial Search for Perfect Wheat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>PULLMAN, Wash.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a gleaming prize for wheat farmers, and environmentally correct, to boot: a perennial food plant that requires plowing only once every three to five years and prevents dust storms, stems soil erosion and even absorbs carbon to help mitigate climate change.</p>
        <p>The latest search for perennial wheat, which comes up each year, began a decade ago here at Washington State University, said Dr. Stephen Jones, a geneticist, with a big question: What are the genetics that govern a plant's annual nature?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The quest to perennialize everything from sorghum to chickpeas to sunflowers has taken on new urgency for a variety of reasons, like climate change and soil loss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a gleaming prize for wheat farmers, and environmentally correct, to boot: a perennial food plant that requires plowing only once every three to five years and prevents dust storms, stems soil erosion and even absorbs carbon to help mitigate climate change.</p>
        <p>The latest search for perennial wheat, which comes up each year, began a decade ago here at Washington State University, said Dr. Stephen Jones, a geneticist, with a big question: What are the genetics that govern a plant's annual nature?</p>
        <p>''That life-and-death question was fairly simple to answer,'' Dr. Jones said recently, standing in a thicket of greenhouse-raised experimental wheat plants that towered over him. ''It's only a single gene that convinces a plant not to die.'' Once that gene is bypassed through breeding, ''the question is, Does it have what it takes to live?''</p>
        <p>That answer is considerably more difficult. A successful perennial wheat not only has to live, but it also has to do it in the right ways: it has to enter a dormant cycle in the fall and then return to life in the spring; it has to look like wheat, have a satisfactory yield and thresh cleanly.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jones and his graduate students overrode the ''death'' gene in the late 1990s -- through old-fashioned breeding techniques that crossed wheat with wild grass, not genetic modification -- but it takes years, allowing plants to breed at their natural pace to make sure the wheat ends up with the right characteristics.</p>
        <p>''We stick them together like putting a certain bull and a certain cow together in a certain corral,'' Dr. Jones said. As the plants create offspring, the scientists select for the traits they wish to perpetuate and plant them. Some test plants have been planted by farmers and still need some work. The key is not yield but predictable survivability. As the first plants prove themselves, they will be planted in erodible areas, like hilltops.</p>
        <p>Erosion is the big problem. Scientists say that an average of 12 tons of soil are lost per acre per year to water erosion, and high winds can take a whopping 50 tons of top soil from an acre of bare wheat field in just 24 hours.</p>
        <p>The quest here is one of several around the world, to perennialize everything from sorghum to chickpeas to sunflowers. It has taken on new urgency for a variety of reasons, like climate change and soil loss.</p>
        <p>''You talk about a cure for the common cold,'' said Ken Warren, managing director of the Land Institute in Salina, Kan., which is in the process of breeding a mix of perennial crops, like wheat, sunflowers and sorghum. ''You name an abuse from farming,'' Mr. Warren said, ''from soil erosion to the use of hydrocarbons to pesticides and herbicides, and we can get rid of it with perennial crops.''</p>
        <p>In Australia, researchers have a well-financed project to breed a perennial wheat to reduce salinity in annual wheat fields. In Texas and Oklahoma, researchers are working on perennial wheat as a crop and for grazing cattle. In Nepal, where farming is terraced, farmers want it for erosion control.</p>
        <p>Farmers in eastern Washington have pushed for the new, longer-growing wheat. ''It fits the bill real well to lower our cost as producers,'' said Mark Schoesler, a wheat and cattle farmer near Ritzville, Wash. ''It could be the ultimate conservation tool.''</p>
        <p>Because it needs less plowing and planting, he estimates it would lower his fuel costs by 75 percent. Seed costs would also drop.</p>
        <p>The problem with annual wheat is that farmers selected it for domestication because of its high grain yield, which means the plant sacrificed other attributes to maximize the amount of seed.</p>
        <p>Annual wheat, for example, needs help from herbicides to ward off invasive species, because it cannot compete with weeds, and it is less naturally pest resistant. It does not use nitrogen efficiently, so half of the nitrogen fertilizer applied runs off, polluting streams and groundwater.</p>
        <p>There are high stakes involved in a perennial wheat here. The soil in the Palouse, as this region is known, was dumped west of here by large-scale outburst flooding from Glacial Lake Missoula, which last occurred about 12,000 years ago. After the flood, soil called loess, made by glaciers grinding volcanic rock into powder, was blown in great dunelike waves. As a result, the millions of acres of nearly treeless landscape are covered with soil as much as 100 feet thick.</p>
        <p>''It's a gift of the ice age and a wonderful cocktail of different rocks and minerals, and if you add organic material, great for plant growth,'' Mr. Warren said of the soil. ''Without it, we'd be Australia, which didn't have a good ice age.''</p>
        <p>Thanks to the soil and cool nights, Whitman County is the richest wheat region in the United States, with per-acre yields at 75 bushels, more than twice those of Kansas.</p>
        <p>But the soil is disappearing. When the soil has no cover of vegetation -- a period of months to more than a year -- the wind blows across the rolling hills here and sucks the fine-grain soil into the sky. It creates giant clouds and an eerie brown darkness in the middle of the day. Traffic accidents are not uncommon, and road signs warn of blowing dust. The drifts pile up against fences, like snow.</p>
        <p>On many exposed hilltops here, all of the soil has been stripped away down to clay. The soil washes into small streams that feed eventually into the Columbia River, where they choke salmon spawning beds.</p>
        <p>Crops on the ground throughout the year would also bank substantially more carbon than a field that is plowed every year would, which helps global warming. Researchers at the Land Institute estimate annual crops cause the loss of about 40 percent of the total carbon in the soil.</p>
        <p>Perennial plants, which have bigger roots and can find water that is deeper in the soil, are more able to survive warming climates.</p>
        <p>The key has been to move back to a more natural wheat. ''All breeders have been working under a high-input system,'' Dr. Jones said. ''The diet of their plants is luxurious. If we make plants that are tougher, we can use water and nutrients more efficiently. We're trying to make wheat more like a weed.''</p>
        <p>Land Institute scientists believe a crop of several kinds of perennial plants, with wheat in the mix, would solve even more problems than a lone perennial wheat. ''Perennial roots don't allow annual weeds to take hold,'' Mr. Warren said. ''And diseases don't fare as well in mixed cropping systems as they do in a monoculture.''</p>
        <p>In spite of the role perennial crops could play, federal research grants have been stingy. Washington State University wheat researchers lost their main source of financing in the brouhaha over Congressional earmarks.</p>
        <p>Researchers have searched for these kinds of plants before. Beginning in the 1940s, a large amount of research was conducted at the University of California, Davis, but was abandoned in the 1960s because the yield was only 70 percent of annuals. ''Our farmers would take that in a second,'' Dr. Jones said. ''If we can get 50 percent, that would be great because it solves so many other problems.'' In the 1920s and '30s, a researcher here, Hannah Aase, also researched perennial wheat. In both cases, the research was lost or destroyed.</p>
        <p>Researchers are still years away from replacing annuals with perennials, because of the slow nature of such breeding programs. ''It won't be in my lifetime,'' said Dr. Jones, who is 50.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
