<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irish Green Party To Support Deal That May Give It Governing Role</title>
    <meta content="14irish" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/world/europe/14irish.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quinn, Eamon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ahern, Bertie (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Ireland</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Green Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ahern, Bertie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="363" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irish Green Party To Support Deal That May Give It Governing Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Irish Green Party to Support Deal That May Give It Governing Role</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EAMON QUINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Quinn, Eamon</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leadership of Ireland's Green Party agrees to support deal with Prime Min Bertie Ahern that could make it part of government for first time; party leaders say Ahern has made concessions in exchange for Green Party entering coalition with his party, Fianna Fail; deal faces obstacles before vote in Parliament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The leadership of Ireland's Green Party agreed Wednesday to support a deal with Prime Minister Bertie Ahern that could make it a part of the government for the first time.</p>
        <p>The party leaders said Mr. Ahern had made concessions on issues like climate change, education and political reform of local government in exchange for entering a coalition with Mr. Ahern's party, Fianna Fail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The leadership of Ireland’s Green Party agreed to support a deal with Prime Minister Bertie Ahern that could make it a part of the government for the first time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The leadership of Ireland's Green Party agreed Wednesday to support a deal with Prime Minister Bertie Ahern that could make it a part of the government for the first time.</p>
        <p>The party leaders said Mr. Ahern had made concessions on issues like climate change, education and political reform of local government in exchange for entering a coalition with Mr. Ahern's party, Fianna Fail.</p>
        <p>But the deal faced obstacles before an expected vote on Thursday in Parliament, including a vote by 1,000 party members requiring a two-thirds majority for approval. Eamon Ryan, one of the party's six members in Parliament, called the deal ''a hard sell,'' and political commentators noted that some party members questioned whether Fianna Fail had made enough concessions.</p>
        <p>In national elections held three weeks ago, Fianna Fail, with 78 seats, remained by far the largest party in Parliament but was still left needing the support of smaller parties like the Greens to achieve a majority in the 166-member chamber. Mr. Ahern, who has governed in coalition since 1997, has said his goal is to establish a ''stable government'' that could last another five years.</p>
        <p>Political analysts said another major issue for the Green Party was the use of Shannon Airport in southwest Ireland. The party has opposed the use of Shannon by American troops en route to Iraq and elsewhere, and it contends that the airport has been used by the C.I.A. in taking people it seizes either to Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, or to secret prisons elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Green Party leaders said they had been told Wednesday that there would be ''specialized training'' for the Irish police to monitor possible instances of stopovers in connection with the seizures.</p>
        <p>''The Green Party had always been against the use of Shannon and wanted U.S. troops using Shannon to end altogether,'' said Sean Donnelly, a pollster and political analyst. ''But there was no way that Fianna Fail would give in to that. Ireland is pro-American, and there are many American businesses here.''</p>
        <p>Michael Marsh, professor of political science at Trinity College, Dublin, said the key for Greens would be how much real influence they would bring to bear in the government.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
