<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology Group Seeks to Save Power</title>
    <meta content="13chip" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Business Machines Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hewlett-Packard Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dell Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Advanced Micro Devices</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sun Microsystems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Wildlife Federation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Intel Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFD6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology Group Seeks to Save Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif., June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Google and Intel are leading consortium of major technology companies in effort to sharply reduce amount of power wasted by personal computers and servers; energy-saving effort is called Climate Savers Computing Initiative; companies agreeing to effort's standards will try to build machines that are at least 90 percent efficient in their power use by promoting new technologies, setting new standards and encouraging more efficient use by consumers; initiative has received support of IBM, Hewlett-Packard, Dell, Advanced Micro Devices, Sun Microsystems and Microsoft among others; it is also supported by National Wildlife Federation and Environmental Protection Agency; Intel is expected to cut prices on some of its higher-end processors in July to make room for new power-saving chip technology expected in second half of year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Google and Intel are leading a consortium of major technology companies in an effort to sharply reduce the amount of power wasted by personal computers and servers.</p>
        <p>In a separate development, Intel is expected to cut prices on some of its higher-end processors in July to make room for new power-saving chip technology expected in the second half of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Google and Intel are leading a consortium of major technology companies in an effort to sharply reduce the amount of power wasted by personal computers and servers.</p>
        <p>In a separate development, Intel is expected to cut prices on some of its higher-end processors in July to make room for new power-saving chip technology expected in the second half of the year.</p>
        <p>The energy-saving effort, announced yesterday, is called the Climate Savers Computing Initiative. It will also include a large-scale campaign to educate consumers and corporate computer managers about technology's role in the emission of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Companies agreeing to Climate Savers standards will try to build machines that are at least 90 percent efficient in their power use by promoting new technologies, setting new standards and encouraging more efficient use by consumers.</p>
        <p>''I think we can make a very large impact very quickly,'' said Larry Page, who founded Google with Sergey Brin.</p>
        <p>''All of this is doable today,'' he said. ''We're just taking the opportunity to shoot for a higher bar.''</p>
        <p>The initiative has received the support of I.B.M., Hewlett-Packard, Dell, Advanced Micro Devices, Sun Microsystems and Microsoft, among others. It is also supported by the National Wildlife Federation and the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>The group envisions better power management in computers, roughly equivalent to taking 11 million cars off the highway, according to Patrick P. Gelsinger, senior vice president in charge of Intel's digital enterprise group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelsinger said that the new technologies could result in price increases for consumers of about $20 a computer, but that customers would make up for the extra expense in energy savings within a year or two. Proposed rebates from utility companies will probably allow customers to recoup the additional expense even more quickly, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelsinger declined to comment on the reports of impending price cuts, but company officials said that Intel routinely reduced prices throughout the year. Intel will cut prices of high-performance server processors sometime in July. The price cuts will come as Intel is preparing to introduce a new chip family this fall called Penryn, which promises a significant increase in performance without consuming more power.</p>
        <p>But unlike the price cuts of last year, which set off a price war with Advanced Micro Devices, these price cuts are more routine, analysts say.</p>
        <p>Henri Richard, executive vice president of Advanced Micro, said that his company had announced its own plans for price reductions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
