<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Singing the Praises of a New Asia</title>
    <meta content="19summers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/business/worldbusiness/19summers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Summers, Lawrence H</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EED91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Singing the Praises of a New Asia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Harvard’s Former Lightning Rod Is a Hit in Asia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HEATHER TIMMONS</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawrence H. Summers, the former Harvard president, has maintained a low profile in the United States since he stepped down from the university post last year amid controversy and criticism.</p>
        <p>But in Asia, Mr. Summers appears to be the man of the hour. His views on the importance of Asia's growth, the challenges of globalization and the danger of the United States' huge trade deficit are widely promoted by policy makers and economists. He is eagerly solicited for lectures and keynote speeches, where his characteristically unvarnished opinions creep into discussions of fiscal policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawrence H. Summers has been stressing economic themes that resonate in India, China, Hong Kong and Singapore but have yet to take hold in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawrence H. Summers, the former Harvard president, has maintained a low profile in the United States since he stepped down from the university post last year amid controversy and criticism.</p>
        <p>But in Asia, Mr. Summers appears to be the man of the hour. His views on the importance of Asia's growth, the challenges of globalization and the danger of the United States' huge trade deficit are widely promoted by policy makers and economists. He is eagerly solicited for lectures and keynote speeches, where his characteristically unvarnished opinions creep into discussions of fiscal policy.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Summers spoke to an audience that overflowed a ballroom at the Taj Mahal Hotel in New Delhi, telling hundreds of economists, government officials and business executives that most of the action on global warming needed to ''take place in the developing world.''</p>
        <p>The industrial world was responsible for much of the problem, he said, but most of the solutions must come from the developing world, where emissions are growing the fastest and infrastructure is still unbuilt. The developing world should ''demand'' that it be compensated and supported for taking actions ''in the interest of all,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Larry is very stimulating intellectually and an 'out of the box' thinker,'' said Isher Judge Ahluwalia, the chairwoman of the Indian Council for Research on International Economic Relations, the group that invited Mr. Summers to speak.</p>
        <p>''There is a wisdom in the way that he looks at problems which are global,'' Ms. Ahluwalia said, adding that Mr. Summers listens to other people's ideas, particularly when the topic is developing countries.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ahluwalia and Mr. Summers recently served on a small panel given the duty of mapping the future of the Asian Development Bank, where Mr. Summers was the only American participant. The six-member panel decided that by 2020 a ''new Asia'' will need a ''radically'' different development bank with a global focus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers's participation in and influence on Asian economic policy dates back to his role as the chief economist at the World Bank in the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>While eminent Indian economists like Jagdish Bhagwati, a proponent of unfettered free trade, were arguing against regional trade alliances in the mid-1990s, India and other South Asia countries were pushing for them, in part because Mr. Summers supported the alliances, said Saman Kelegama, the executive director of the Institute of Policy Studies of Sri Lanka and co-editor of The South Asia Economic Journal.</p>
        <p>''Larry was one of the main proponents'' of regional trade alliances, Mr. Kelegama said, ''and his view was considered seriously.''</p>
        <p>On that issue, ''South Asia generally goes along with Summers,'' Mr. Kelegama added, which is why the region has pursued the South Asian Free Trade Alliance and other bilateral alliances while negotiating in the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>In a series of visits to China, India, Singapore and Hong Kong since early 2006, Mr. Summers has reiterated several themes that have special resonance in Asia, but have yet to be widely accepted in the United States.</p>
        <p>Among them are the idea that growth and changes in Asia are the most important thing to happen during our lifetimes, that the United States and Europe have not yet appreciated the impact of these changes and that the global imbalances from the United States' current-account deficit -- nearly $1 trillion in 2006 -- could have severe consequences.</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers has been sharply critical of current American fiscal policy and the way that Asia sustains borrowing by the United States by continuing to purchase government debt. During a visit to Mumbai in March last year, Mr. Summers warned the Reserve Bank of India of the United States' ''unsustainable and dangerous'' current-account deficit.</p>
        <p>In Beijing this January, he asked hundreds of economists and policy makers at a Global Development Network conference to consider the fact that $2 trillion from developing Asia, invested in United States Treasury bills, was making a ''zero real return.'' Imagine instead, he said ''all the opportunities in these countries for productive investment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers also visited Singapore for the International Monetary Fund conference in September, then stopped in Hong Kong, where he told those attending an Asia Society dinner that 300 years from now, what will be seen as the most important event of these times will not be the end of the cold war, the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, or the war in Iraq, but ''the rise of Asia and all that it meant for people in Asia and all that it meant for the world system.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers did not attend a New Delhi conference in March about new ways to finance Asian infrastructure, but he was cited so often by government ministers and development specialists there that he might as well have been.</p>
        <p>Ramgopal Agarwala, the senior adviser to R.I.S., or the Research and Information System for Developing Countries, quoted Mr. Summers extensively in a proposal that all Asian countries contribute to a fund that diverts money away from United States Treasury bills and into Asian infrastructure.</p>
        <p>''If exposure to the United States deficit is not managed well, we cannot rule out a possible global recession, even depression,'' said Mr. Agarwala, a former World Bank economist based in China, adding that Asia has a crucial role to play in correcting these imbalances.</p>
        <p>The governments of China and India have both announced that they will invest their foreign exchange reserves in new areas, which will divert them from United States Treasury bills.</p>
        <p>Subir Gokarn, the chief economist at Crisil, a ratings agency in India, said that Mr. Summers's remarks about ''the race to the bottom, and the adverse effects of globalization'' strike a chord in Asia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
