<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As California Moves Up Its Primary, Its Issues Gain New Prominence</title>
    <meta content="07campaign" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/07/us/politics/07campaign.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries and Caucuses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0DB1E3EF934A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1449" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As California Moves Up Its Primary, Its Issues Gain New Prominence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">California Gains Clout With Earlier Primary</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY; Ben Werschkul contributed reporting from Stanford, Calif., and Jennifer Steinhauer and Ana F. Contreras from Los Angeles.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California--by its sheer size, its concentrations of both liberals and conservatives, its status as money tree for candidates and its role for fertile ground for policy making--has altered dialogue of presidential contest in substantive ways since advancing its primary to Feb 5; is forcing candidates to turn their attention to issues, debates and controversies that have historically drawn little attention in early primaries; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, finished a speech on foreign policy recently in Northern California, he was surrounded by reporters who wanted to ask about another topic: global warming and how it was contributing to the state's water shortage.</p>
        <p>''There is an across-the-board effort that's going to have to be made in the face of climate change, which is real,'' Mr. McCain said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Its size, concentrations of liberals and conservatives, and role as fertile ground for policy innovation make California likely to wield additional power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, finished a speech on foreign policy recently in Northern California, he was surrounded by reporters who wanted to ask about another topic: global warming and how it was contributing to the state's water shortage.</p>
        <p>''There is an across-the-board effort that's going to have to be made in the face of climate change, which is real,'' Mr. McCain said.</p>
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, Democrat of New York, spoke about Iraq and health care in a speech to a huge audience of Democrats last Saturday in San Diego. But she received some of her biggest applause when she paid tribute to -- and endorsed -- the tough fuel efficiency measures California had embraced to cut the nation's dependency on oil from the Middle East. Mrs. Clinton boasted that she held up the measures as a model of energy policy in her campaign trips from Iowa to New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>And Senator Barack Obama, Democrat of Illinois, speaking from the pulpit at a church in South Los Angeles on the 15th anniversary of the riots here, talked about job creation, race relations and his commitment to balance environmental concerns against the need for economic development -- crucial issues, he said, in a community identified with urban poverty and strife.</p>
        <p>In the months since California moved its presidential primary to Feb. 5 from June, the major presidential campaigns have sought to measure how the early nominating contests being held here and in about 20 other states that day will shape their tactical calculations: where to travel, whom to hire, how to spend money.</p>
        <p>The primary calendar -- and, potentially, the relative influence of the states -- is still very much in flux. Just this week, Florida voted to move its primary up to Jan. 29 in an effort to ensure that it would play a vital role in the nominating process and that the candidates would pay attention to the issues its residents deem important. Other states with important early roles, like Nevada and South Carolina, are also hoping to draw attention to issues rooted in their regions or in the makeup of their populations.</p>
        <p>But its sheer size, its concentrations of both liberals and conservatives, its status as a money tree for candidates and its role as fertile ground for policy innovation make California especially likely to wield additional clout this time around. The result is not just a change in tactics; it is altering the dialogue of the presidential contest in substantive ways. It is forcing candidates to turn their attention to issues, debates and controversies that have historically drawn little attention on the early playing fields of Iowa and New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>The most striking example is global warming, an issue that was rarely raised in the past two presidential campaigns. Mike Huckabee, the former governor of Arkansas, was reminded of this on Thursday night when he was asked on national television at the first Republican presidential candidates' debate, in Simi Valley, if he thought global warming existed. (Yes, Mr. Huckabee said, though he skirted the issue of whether humans were primarily responsible for it.)</p>
        <p>That is hardly the only issue California is putting on the table, as became clear as the presidential candidates from both parties campaigned through the state this week. In their travels they heard about, and talked about, issues that are dominating the politics of this polyglot state: immigration, stem-cell research, protecting public lands and -- reflecting the acute concern of the influential Silicon Valley software industry -- the so-called Net neutrality debate over the allocation of Internet bandwidth.</p>
        <p>Analysts from both parties said that given the political tides here, and what appeared most likely to surface in California's public and political dialogue by Feb. 5, the candidates should be prepared to offer opinions about whether illegal immigrants should be eligible for drivers' licenses or health care coverage; whether Congressional redistricting should be stripped from political leaders and put in the control of judges; and whether they supported another effort by the California Legislature to legalize same-sex marriage in a state with a large and influential gay population.</p>
        <p>To some extent, this surfeit of issues reflects what has always been California's reputation as being slightly ahead of the curve -- some might argue off the curve -- on all kinds of social and domestic issues. It also reflects the influence of this state's sizable community of active Democrats, many of them more liberal than their counterparts in places like Iowa, and also its often-outspoken conservatives, especially in the southern part of the state.</p>
        <p>But it is just as much testimony to the energetic efforts by its governor, Arnold Schwarzenegger, a Republican who has broken with the national party on a series of issues, to shape the discussion of the presidential campaign. In an interview, Mr. Schwarzenegger said he intended to use the platform of this primary to affect the course of his party's presidential debate by pressing candidates to talk in detail about how, for example, to curb reliance on ''fossil fuel and Middle East fuel'' and how to respond to the flood of illegal immigrants, an issue that has confounded Republican politicians here for nearly a decade.</p>
        <p>''They've got to tell people what they would do,'' Mr. Schwarzenegger said, smoking a cigar in his sprawling private office in Santa Monica, which is bigger than most Manhattan apartments. ''I'm interested in solving this immigration problem. Environmental issues. I will be relentless in the next year, almost two years, talking about these issues.''</p>
        <p>''I am only interested in one thing,'' he continued, ''That we do everything that we can do here to use that opportunity that came of us having moved the primary date to our advantage. How can we make this work really well for California.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzenegger could well complicate life for Republicans seeking the presidential nomination, which he is constitutionally barred from seeking. Mr. Schwarzenegger is pushing, for example, to provide health care benefits to illegal immigrants, an idea that probably does not have much political currency in places like South Carolina or Iowa, whose nominating contests precede California's. And Mr. Schwarzenegger challenged the notion of turning to ethanol to wean the nation off Middle Eastern fossil fuels, a declaration that a candidate for president from either party would be unlikely to make to, say, an audience of farmers in Iowa.</p>
        <p>''It's a mistake to promote just ethanol,'' he said. ''Maybe the future is in hydrogen? Is it biofuel?''</p>
        <p>On the other side of the ledger, the issue of same-sex marriage might complicate life for Democrats: the Legislature is likely to renew efforts to enact legislation allowing it, which will mean the Democratic candidates will no doubt be asked to weigh in on it. Similarly, there is talk here of putting on the ballot an initiative calling for an immediate withdrawal of troops from Iraq, which could put Democrats more squarely on the spot over how the United States should end the war.</p>
        <p>Immigration is a particularly tough issue here for both parties, in a state that has been transformed by an influx of Hispanic voters. It has created political cross-pressures on Republicans, who are trying to deal with voters who see the influx of immigrants as a threat to their safety, cultural identity and economic well-being; and Democrats, who have benefited in the past decade from the perception among many legal immigrants that Republicans are anti-immigration. The latest debate here is whether illegal immigrants should be granted drivers' licenses.</p>
        <p>The issue most likely to shape the presidential contest here, though, is the environment. ''Top of the list: global warming,'' said Garry South, a longtime Democratic strategist in California. ''I don't know how that plays in Iowa or how that plays in New Hampshire, but it is hot here. The governor has made it the centerpiece of his whole administration.''</p>
        <p>Last September, California enacted a law calling for reducing heat-trapping emissions by 25 percent. Nearly every Democrat who spoke at the party's convention here last weekend referred to it as a crucial issue.</p>
        <p>In the past, candidates for president have been wary of explicitly calling for tougher fuel conservation measures, afraid of drawing the ire of auto-worker unions and inviting criticism that such measures would raise the cost of automobiles and cost American jobs. But Senator Christopher J. Dodd, a Connecticut Democrat running for president, drew cheers from California Democrats when he called for the establishment of a 50-mile-per-gallon fuel standard for cars, by 2017.</p>
        <p>''We all understand how important these issues are,'' Mr. Dodd said, ''and no one understands that more than the people in this state.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
