<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Meet the Neighbors</title>
    <meta content="Itzkoff3.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/11/books/review/Itzkoff3.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1832005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ACROSS THE UNIVERSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science Fiction</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science Fiction</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Seti Institute</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDF1631F932A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Meet the Neighbors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying to Meet the Neighbors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ITZKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Itzkoff, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is there anybody out there? Give the question some thought before you answer, because it's more perilous than it seems. Deny the possibility of a universe populated with intelligent extraterrestrials that can speak and mate and battle with humanity, and the science-fiction canon collapses; more than a century's worth of novels, from ''The War of the Worlds'' to ''Old Man's War,'' would find their speculative foundations swept out from underneath them. But admit to a sincere belief in the remotest potential for alien life, and prepare to be fitted for a straitjacket; a recent survey conducted by Baylor University found that more Americans believe in ancient civilizations like the lost continent of Atlantis than in U.F.O.'s.</p>
        <p>If intelligent humans think the existence of aliens is a perplexing notion, the idea that a small group of astronomers and physicists are attempting to determine if aliens exist is even more so. To the uninitiated and the ignorant (and those of us who fall into both camps), the science of SETI, the Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence, is as inscrutable as the phenomenon it seeks, conjuring up images of mad scientists out of old EC comic books, their ears trained to intricate listening devices as they scan the interstellar static for unearthly broadcasts -- or worse, of hapless crackpots chasing down every report of alien abduction they read in Weekly World News.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Are we alone in the universe? Seth Shostak suspects we will know the answer by 2025.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is there anybody out there? Give the question some thought before you answer, because it's more perilous than it seems. Deny the possibility of a universe populated with intelligent extraterrestrials that can speak and mate and battle with humanity, and the science-fiction canon collapses; more than a century's worth of novels, from ''The War of the Worlds'' to ''Old Man's War,'' would find their speculative foundations swept out from underneath them. But admit to a sincere belief in the remotest potential for alien life, and prepare to be fitted for a straitjacket; a recent survey conducted by Baylor University found that more Americans believe in ancient civilizations like the lost continent of Atlantis than in U.F.O.'s.</p>
        <p>If intelligent humans think the existence of aliens is a perplexing notion, the idea that a small group of astronomers and physicists are attempting to determine if aliens exist is even more so. To the uninitiated and the ignorant (and those of us who fall into both camps), the science of SETI, the Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence, is as inscrutable as the phenomenon it seeks, conjuring up images of mad scientists out of old EC comic books, their ears trained to intricate listening devices as they scan the interstellar static for unearthly broadcasts -- or worse, of hapless crackpots chasing down every report of alien abduction they read in Weekly World News.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, the science-fiction community (which knows a thing or two about being misunderstood and dismissed) is not unequivocally supportive of SETI's work. In a 2003 lecture entitled ''Aliens Cause Global Warming,'' Michael Crichton declared, ''SETI is unquestionably a religion.'' And authors free of Crichton's political baggage do not cast SETI's mission in particularly upbeat terms, either: in his short story ''The Puzzle,'' the Serbian author Zoran Zivkovic writes of a scientist pursuing a SETI-like experiment, whose ''gloomy exultation'' can end only with irrefutable evidence of extraterrestrial intelligence -- only ''with contact made would he be able to say that his life's work had meaning.''</p>
        <p>The truth of SETI is more nuanced and more complicated, but at least it's easier to find. Since 1991, Seth Shostak has been engaged in this ambitious, arduous and often frustrating endeavor, as the senior astronomer of the SETI Institute, a foundation that studies the nature and origins of life wherever it might turn up. While his years of observation have yet to detect a blip of alien communication, Shostak is more interested in the repercussions that would follow if the slightest evidence of extraterrestrial life -- or the faintest arrow pointing to it -- were someday discovered. ''If you could find even dead pond scum on Mars, it tells you biology's not a miracle,'' he said during a recent interview at his Mountain View, Calif., office. ''It means there's got to be life all over the place.''</p>
        <p>Conspiracy theorists would be disappointed by the SETI Institute's sedate headquarters, in a corporate park it shares with the software maker Symantec, a few miles from the campus of the Internet giant Google. I found no evidence of any alien autopsies during my visit, and saw no little green men wandering the halls, aside from the occasional action figure or inflatable toy decorating a desk or cubicle.</p>
        <p>Established in 1984, the institute has been almost entirely privately financed since the 1990s (though its sister organization, the Carl Sagan Center, still receives NASA grants for its astrobiology research). The small fraction of its staff involved in actual SETI experiments knows that the work does not necessarily inspire the awe and admiration of the general public, a stigma that has been around at least since the publication of Sagan's novel ''Contact'' in 1985: to be a scientist who believed in the possibility of alien intelligence, he wrote, was to possess a flaw, the way your other colleagues ''had topless bars, or carnivorous plants, or something called Transcendental Meditation.''</p>
        <p>Shostak is no social deviant (as far as I know): a gregarious 63-year-old with a Ph.D. in astronomy from the California Institute of Technology, he taught for 13 years at the Rijksuniversiteit Groningen in the Netherlands and conducted SETI experiments there in the 1980s, using the nearby Westerbork Synthesis Radio Telescope, before joining the institute. But he can understand how his research might appear to outside observers like an empty endeavor. ''It's like pulling the lever on a slot machine,'' he said. ''The next quarter might be it.''</p>
        <p>There is some persuasive data to suggest that ours isn't the only world capable of beating the odds. While astronomers once thought planets were rare, they now believe that anywhere from 5 percent to 90 percent of all stars are orbited by them, meaning there could be as many as 10,000 billion billion other solar systems in the observable universe.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, experiments on Earth have found micro-organisms in harsh conditions -- extreme temperatures, pressures and altitudes -- thought to be adverse to biology, suggesting that bodies as nearby as Mars and some moons of Jupiter could have the right stuff to cook up alien life.</p>
        <p>Using massive radio telescopes, SETI hopes to detect electromagnetic transmissions coming from these potential neighborhoods. In the past decade, Shostak estimates, the institute has looked at 750 star systems, but within the next 25 years it should be able to scan one million to two million more. And he is fond of betting his interrogators a cup of Starbucks that the question of whether mankind is alone in the universe will be settled by the year 2025.</p>
        <p>Though he occasionally sits on panels at science-fiction conventions, where authors and readers quiz him about whose depictions of imaginary beings are the most realistic, Shostak tries not to weigh in on questions about what extraterrestrial life looks like or how it behaves. ''This is all alien sociology,'' he said with a grin, ''and I have to tell you the data set is small.''</p>
        <p>To his mind, the sci-fi traditions of hominid aliens with insectoid features (think of the buglike Formics of Orson Scott Card's ''Ender's Game'' novels) or serpentine qualities (say, the reptilian members of the Race in Harry Turtledove's ''Worldwar'' books) probably say more about earthbound writers than actual extraterrestrials. ''We're hard-wired not to like insects very much, and the same is true for snakes,'' Shostak explained. ''You turn on Animal Planet, you don't see many shows on gerbil behavior. Anything that can hurt you, you're much more interested.''</p>
        <p>Yet some of the wilder ideas about alien life that Shostak's fellow scientists have contemplated in their own fiction could be within the realm of possibility. From his own reading, he describes as fanciful but impossible to dismiss completely the physicist Robert L. Forward's novel ''Dragon's Egg'' -- which imagines tiny creatures on the surface of a neutron star, whose lives elapse a million times faster than our own -- and the title character of the astrophysicist Fred Hoyle's novel ''The Black Cloud,'' a diffuse organism as wide as the orbit of Venus.</p>
        <p>Underlying all these conjectures is a single, basic assumption (proponents of intelligent design should stop reading here): no matter where life is found, it will obey Darwinian tenets of evolution. ''It's hard to avoid evolution,'' Shostak said, ''because all it says is that if you survive, then you must be good, so whatever traits you have tend to propagate.''</p>
        <p>To the extent that SETI is modest about its expectations, it has found philosophical support in unexpected quarters. When Richard Dawkins sniffs around the underlying science of SETI in ''The God Delusion,'' he writes that he doesn't ''immediately scent extreme improbability.'' And Dawkins concedes that ''there are very probably alien civilizations that are superhuman, to the point of being godlike in ways that exceed anything a theologian could possibly imagine'' -- an idea he acknowledges cribbing from Arthur C. Clarke, whose so-called Third Law of prediction states, ''Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic.''</p>
        <p>Shostak has as much use for magic as Dawkins has for the Almighty, but the two are in agreement on this point. ''The universe is three times as old as the earth, so there's opportunity for civilizations that are billions of years ahead of us,'' Shostak said. ''Our radio transmitters are a million times more powerful than Marconi's were, and we've done that in a hundred years. What could they do in a billion?''</p>
        <p>One thing he believes they could do is build thinking machines to rival human intelligence. ''The trouble with Darwinian evolution is, we don't change very fast,'' Shostak said. ''But machines are on time scales of decades, not hundreds of thousands of years.'' Should he ever intercept a text message from E.T., Shostak has his own guess about who will be transmitting it on the other end: ''My bet is, they're not soft and squishy.''</p>
        <p>In his own sporadic attempts at science fiction, Shostak seems even less confident about what SETI might someday find. In an imaginative, somewhat cynical story entitled ''In Touch at Last,'' originally published in a 1999 issue of Science, he writes of a scientist some 50 years in the future who is the first to identify the communications of an extraterrestrial intelligence -- neither a benign message of peace nor a bellicose threat, but simply an interstellar buzz repeating itself at regular intervals. Self-deprecating on a cosmic scale, the narrator refuses to believe he has tapped the mother lode of scientific discoveries. ''I just stumbled on a loose nugget,'' he says.</p>
        <p>The story left me slightly depressed: given Shostak's scientific expertise, another half-century of progress and the infinite canvas of a work of fiction, this was the most hopeful scenario he could think of? Then again, he told me, the situation could be worse: maybe the aliens know we're here, and they just don't care. ''It's sort of like your attitude toward mollusks,'' he said. ''Are you hostile to them? Are you in favor of them? Do you try and support their work? Maybe intelligent life is so common that, aside from people on Phi-2 Orionis making a catalog of all the intelligent critters around, it's of little consequence.''</p>
        <p>I left our meeting unnerved by these lonely forecasts, and it took an unlikely source to cheer me up. Robyn Asimov, the daughter of the science-fiction master Isaac Asimov, has become a friend of the SETI Institute despite her upbringing: Dad was more of a robot guy than an alien guy, and agnostic on the subject of extraterrestrial intelligence, except for one instance when father and daughter mistook the Goodyear blimp for a U.F.O. (''He nearly had a heart attack,'' she told me in a telephone interview. ''He thought he saw his career going down the drain.'')</p>
        <p>In our conversation, she explained to me why SETI research is still valuable, even if scientists like Shostak never find any Daleks, Vulcans or Wookiees. ''My father knew he wouldn't live to see space travel as he wrote about it, or robots acting in the way he wrote about them, and he was fine with that,'' Asimov said. ''His major thrust, and I think Seth's and SETI's as well, is to get people interested in science, and doing something about it, and then handing the baton over to the next generation. It's an almost egoless outlook, because the intellectual curiosity is what takes priority.''</p>
        <p>Insert the name of your favorite science-fiction author in place of Shostak's in the previous quotation, and I think her formulation still holds true. Like the science-fiction community whose support, suspicion and occasional provocation it can always expect, the SETI field inspires the same intense loyalty, from followers who regard such pursuits less like a hobby than a calling. ''I suppose I could have been a C.P.A.,'' Shostak said, ''but here you get to work on a really big-picture question. I don't feel cursed -- I feel privileged.''</p>
        <p>And I don't think Shostak, like a good science-fiction author, can truly accept a universe devoid of the possibility for transcendence -- where extraterrestrials know humanity exists, but are merely indifferent to it. At the end of ''In Touch at Last,'' his fictional scientist decodes the mysterious alien transmission and is humbled to discover that the repetitious buzz is a kind of universal clock. ''I didn't expect them to give us the time of day,'' the narrator says. ''But they did.''h</p>
        <p>'If you could find even dead pond scum on Mars, it tells you biology's not a miracle.'</p>
        <p>ACROSS THE UNIVERSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
