<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Suburban Shepherdhess With a Heart of Green</title>
    <meta content="22peopleweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22peoplewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FARMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sheep</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hilltop Hanover Farm (Yorktown, NY)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yorktown Heights (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bianco, Shirley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Hudson Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hudson River Valley (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Suburban Shepherdhess With a Heart of Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Suburban Shepherdhess With a Heart of Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA MAGRIEL WETZLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</byline>
      <dateline>YORKTOWN HEIGHTS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Shirley Bianco, who practices strict organic farming and raises sheep at Hilltop Hanover Farm, Westchester County-owned environmental resource center in Yorktown Heights, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHIRLEY BIANCO lugged a bale of hay in a hand truck and dumped it in the midst of her hungry flock of bleating sheep in their outdoor pen -- 23 fluffy, cream-colored American Delaine Merino ewes, three darker Shetlands and one 200-pound Merino ram with curled horns. Sixteen lambs born last spring huddled together in a pen nearby, waiting for breakfast.</p>
        <p>''I'm breeding for genetics,'' Ms. Bianco said recently at Hilltop Hanover Farm here, a county-owned environmental resource center on 183 acres of open pastures and woodlands where she leases land and keeps her flock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>YORKTOWN Heights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHIRLEY BIANCO lugged a bale of hay in a hand truck and dumped it in the midst of her hungry flock of bleating sheep in their outdoor pen -- 23 fluffy, cream-colored American Delaine Merino ewes, three darker Shetlands and one 200-pound Merino ram with curled horns. Sixteen lambs born last spring huddled together in a pen nearby, waiting for breakfast.</p>
        <p>''I'm breeding for genetics,'' Ms. Bianco said recently at Hilltop Hanover Farm here, a county-owned environmental resource center on 183 acres of open pastures and woodlands where she leases land and keeps her flock.</p>
        <p>''The ram's wool is ultrasoft, like a big pillow, and will produce superior fleece,'' she said. ''I'm wondering, though, if he really likes the ladies. He's not showing much interest. But then some are looking bred -- or else I'm feeding them too much.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Bianco, farming sheep provides a way to live out her commitment to the conservation of open land in the county.</p>
        <p>''My sheep are truly well taken care of, like indoor pets,'' she said. ''No pesticides or chemicals are ever used in their hay, feed or wool processing.''</p>
        <p>A little brown-and-white ewe with a heart face lifted its head to be rubbed, and Ms. Bianco leaned down to caress its cheek. ''This is Penelope, a Shetland and Merino mix,'' she said. ''These sheep are lovely to be around. Some are bold, some are shy. And they're docile. You could put them in a backyard with a fence. I love them.''</p>
        <p>Idling over to Ms. Bianco, a long-necked llama stood tall amongst the sheep. ''He guards against coyotes and raccoons,'' she said. ''What he does is spit at them and then pounce with his front legs.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bianco practices rotational grazing to maintain the richness of the pastures and the grasses. ''Healthy grasses in their growth phase consume twice the carbon dioxide, a large component of greenhouse gas pollution, as a forest,'' she explained. Strict organic farming practices prevent soil pollutants from filtering into the Croton watershed, where the farm is located.</p>
        <p>Inside the barn, sparrow nests-in-progress, lined with bits of fleece, sit up in the rafters. Barely audible classical music from a radio fills the space. ''Maybe I should find something romantic for the ram,'' Ms. Bianco said.</p>
        <p>In two former dairy stalls at the top of the barn stairs are stacks of yarns in bright blues, brick reds, as well as an array of the undyed natural colors of the sheep. Ms. Bianco started Hudson Valley Woolworks (HudsonValleyWool.com) in 2005 when she purchased her flock. The sheep are sheared in March, just before lambing time in April, and the fleece is sent to mills in Red Hook, N.Y., and Putney, Vt., to be cleaned, carded and spun. Ms. Bianco then hand-dyes the yarn herself in small kettles using natural pigments.</p>
        <p>The Manhattan designer Mary Jaeger uses Ms. Bianco's yarns, and the Organic Knitting Company in Armonk knits designs with Ms. Bianco's wool for the Nili Lotan Design Studio in Manhattan. The yarns are also sold at the farm and in the fall at the greenmarkets in SoHo and Tribeca in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''One of my customers said she could feel the farm while knitting with this wool,'' Ms. Bianco said. It's a feeling she understands well. ''During lambing season, if I'm here at night alone, it's so quiet and serene,'' she said, ''I could be one of the sheep.''</p>
        <p>FARMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
