<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F. Y. I.</title>
    <meta content="13fyi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/13/nyregion/thecity/13fyi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="F. Y. I."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">79th Street Boat Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boardwalks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marinas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Coney Island (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Aquarium</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/F.Y.I.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDD1531F930A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F. Y. I.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Boat Basin Bilge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions on whether owners of boats in 79th Street Boat Basin are permitted to dump untreated sewage into Hudson River, meaning of symbols on wall on Coney Island Boardwalk at Aquarium and apparent decrease in steam rising from manhole covers in New York City; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boat Basin Bilge</p>
        <p>Q. Are boat owners permitted to dump untreated sewage into the Hudson? This occurs to me whenever I notice that a number of people are living on their boats in the 79th Street Boat Basin. I see electric and telephone lines connected to many boats, but no sewer lines.</p>
        <p>A: Fear not. Boat owners are forbidden by state and federal law to dump untreated sewage into the Hudson River, the East River and any other New York City adjacent waterways. The Boat Basin, one of 11 marinas under the jurisdiction of the Department of Parks and Recreation, provides a free boat pump-out station where boats can empty sewage debris.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Can boat owners dump untreated sewage into the Hudson?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boat Basin Bilge</p>
        <p>Q. Are boat owners permitted to dump untreated sewage into the Hudson? This occurs to me whenever I notice that a number of people are living on their boats in the 79th Street Boat Basin. I see electric and telephone lines connected to many boats, but no sewer lines.</p>
        <p>A: Fear not. Boat owners are forbidden by state and federal law to dump untreated sewage into the Hudson River, the East River and any other New York City adjacent waterways. The Boat Basin, one of 11 marinas under the jurisdiction of the Department of Parks and Recreation, provides a free boat pump-out station where boats can empty sewage debris.</p>
        <p>In partnership with the city's Department of Environmental Protection, the Parks Department has installed free pump-out stations at seven of its marinas, with at least one in each borough. The Parks Department also works closely with Going Coastal NYC, a nonprofit group that promotes clean marina activities and distributes information about the 29 free pump-out stations in the New York and New Jersey areas.</p>
        <p>As for the full-time residents, there are 39 year-round customers, at the Boat Basin only. In the early 1990s, the Parks Department stopped issuing new year-round permits, said Ashe Reardon, a Parks Department spokesman.</p>
        <p>Concrete Symphony</p>
        <p>Q. On the Coney Island Boardwalk at the Aquarium there is a beautiful wall called ''First Symphony of the Sea.'' Can you explain what all the symbols mean?</p>
        <p>A. The 332-foot long, 10-foot tall sculpture wall, made of four tons of cast concrete, is perhaps the most well-known artwork by Toshio Sasaki, who died on March 10 at age 60.</p>
        <p>Decorating the free-standing wall, which faces the beach, are terrazzo and ceramic shapes depicting waves and fish along with abstract geometric shapes, like capsules and inverted cones that might be drifting in the waves.</p>
        <p>''As the viewer travels the length of the piece, the images become more and more primitive, suggesting the evolution of marine life,'' the Parks Department Web site says of the work, which was installed in 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sasaki, who was one of eight finalists in the design competition for the World Trade Center Memorial, once said of his intentions for the sculpture: ''It will provide a physical and visual separation between the artificial and arranged sea world inside the Aquarium and the natural world outside, including the sea, the sunshine, and people enjoying the boardwalk.''</p>
        <p>Missing Steam</p>
        <p>Q. I often used to see steam rising from manhole covers in the city, but I don't recall seeing it recently. Is it global warming or something else?</p>
        <p>A. Neither Consolidated Edison nor the city's Department of Environmental Protection can verify that there is less steam rising these days, but it does seem that way.</p>
        <p>Manhattan from the Battery to 96th Street is the only borough with an underground system of steam pipes for heating, hospital sterilization and air-conditioning. (Steam drives chilling equipment for air-conditioners, explained Chris Olert, a Con Ed spokesman.)</p>
        <p>Steam rising from manholes means either that there is a steam leak or that cold water leaking from somewhere else is coming into contact with a hot main steam pipe.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL POLLAK</p>
        <p>F. Y. I.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
