<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Internet Barons, Uncharted Investment Territory</title>
    <meta content="07venture" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Business of Green" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/07/business/businessspecial2/07venture.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1831214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEW CONQUESTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Startup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5DA1531F934A35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Internet Barons, Uncharted Investment Territory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Internet Barons, Uncharted Investment Territory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROBERT M. METCALFE, Silicon Valley legend, creator of the Ethernet standard, founder of 3Com and now a venture capitalist, makes a bold prediction about technology investors' next conquest.</p>
        <p>''We're going to solve the energy problem in 30 years, just like we solved the Internet problem in 30 years,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to Energy 2.0, are some of the nation’s most successful investors in over their heads?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROBERT M. METCALFE, Silicon Valley legend, creator of the Ethernet standard, founder of 3Com and now a venture capitalist, makes a bold prediction about technology investors' next conquest.</p>
        <p>''We're going to solve the energy problem in 30 years, just like we solved the Internet problem in 30 years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For that to happen, many hurdles must be overcome, including, for Mr. Metcalfe, a personal one. Until recently, he didn't know much about the field or its markets. He said he was still struggling to figure it out.</p>
        <p>There lies a conundrum for the Internet barons who have turned, of late anden masse, to investing in solar, wind, biofuel and other energy startups. Does their expertise with technology qualify them to take on the world of alternative fuel and power?</p>
        <p>When it comes to Energy 2.0, are some of the nation's most successful investors in over their heads?</p>
        <p>Mr. Metcalfe, 60, and other venture capitalists say they are getting up to speed on the subject by meeting with academics and experts, hearing pitches from entrepreneurs seeking financing, partnering with energy investors and applying the same methodology that created giants like Amazon and Yahoo to take on the oil juggernaut.</p>
        <p>The key to success, they say, is the Silicon Valley investment vetting process. The venture capital model, they contend, pits great entrepreneurs against one another, invests in the best technologies and creates focused, streamlined companies and new industries.</p>
        <p>But their certainty, which can spill into bravado, has stirred criticism even within their own ranks.</p>
        <p>''They're completely wandering in with no clear idea'' of how the energy industry works, said Paul Kedrosky, a venture capitalist and the executive director of the von Liebig Center for Entrepreneurism and Technology Advancement at the University of California at San Diego.</p>
        <p>He argued that the party line -- that good investment strategists can apply their principles across industries -- did not acknowledge the peculiarities and complexities of energy technology.</p>
        <p>''The downside? They're going to blow up this sector before it has a chance to get established,'' Mr. Kedrosky said. But, he added, ''You won't find out that today's investments were nonsense for at least 24 and maybe 36 months.''</p>
        <p>There are many investments; one of the hottest in the business world has been the rush of interest into alternative energy by venture capitalists. In 2006, they put at least $727 million into 39 alternative-energy startups, compared with $195 million in 18 such firms in 2005, according to the National Venture Capital Association.</p>
        <p>The investment reflects not just the changing political and public policy sentiment toward energy but changing dynamics within the venture capital business. Because it has gotten harder to take technology companies public and reap big paydays, investors are directing their discipline and seed capital to new industries.</p>
        <p>None are potentially bigger than energy's $1 trillion annual market. Plus, energy has the benefit of creating potentially environmentally friendly technologies. The mantra in the venture capital world has become, ''Do well by doing good.''</p>
        <p>Some venture capitalists argue that the shift from the information and biotech industries to energy startups is not that big. Take Samir Kaul, who made the change from sequencing DNA to building companies that make car fuel from wood chips.</p>
        <p>A biochemist by training, Mr. Kaul, now 33, was working at the Institute for Genomic Research in 2000, where he oversaw a pioneering project that sequenced the genome of Arabidopsis thaliana, a member of the mustard family and an important organism in biological research. He went to Harvard Business School, then worked as a venture capitalist in Boston financing and creating companies that focused on DNA sequencing and synthetic biology, which involves programming biological cells.</p>
        <p>In early 2006, he joined Khosla Ventures, a Silicon Valley venture firm started by Vinod Khosla, a founder of Sun Microsystems. The firm's concept was to emphasize the emerging world of alternative energy, and Mr. Kaul said the fit was more natural than it appeared.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the basic principles of understanding the genetic blueprint are very, very relevant in the clean fuels and the clean tech area,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For example, he said that sequencing and engineering processes that might yield a cell better equipped to fight disease could also yield an organism that creates ethanol from plant refuse more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Generally, Mr. Kaul argues that venture capitalists steeped in other technologies are finding that their expertise applies to energy. For instance, he noted, investors in material sciences might be equipped to invest in clean-water startups.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Parker, the chairman of the Cleantech Group, an energy-investing trade and research organization, agrees. ''Silicon is used to make semiconductors, and it is used to make solar cells,'' he said. To be successful in energy, venture capitalists ''need to come at it from their existing strengths.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Parker said that some investors appeared to be jumping in hastily or without doing the proper diligence.</p>
        <p>''It's very hip to be saying you're doing this stuff,'' he said. Of the more than 1,000 venture capitalists getting involved, he added, there are ''well over 100 V.C.'s that are for the first time indicating an interest but that don't yet have a lot of depth in their teams'' on alternative energy.</p>
        <p>Technical expertise is only part of the challenge for venture capitalists making the transition to energy, said Charles J. McDermott, a general partner with RockPort Capital Partners in Boston. Mr. McDermott, who has spent about 25 years involved with energy companies, said there were peculiarities to nurturing them.</p>
        <p>For instance, ''If you've never tried to sell technology to a utility, you will definitely experience a learning curve,'' Mr. McDermott said, adding that some customers of energy were regulated monopolies that did not necessarily play by the same profit-and-loss rules as free-market competitors.</p>
        <p>One way in which traditional venture firms are learning about energy is by investing as partners with RockPort and other more experienced firms.</p>
        <p>RockPort has already entered into deals with some major venture firms. One is an investment with Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers in Lilliputian Systems, a Wilmington, Mass., company that makes tiny fuel cells for portable electronic devices. Mr. McDermott said that Kleiner was lending expertise on how to manage and build a startup.</p>
        <p>''Nobody knows better than Kleiner how to groom a company,'' Mr. McDermott said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McDermott said he was generally optimistic about venture capitalists' chances for success in energy investing.</p>
        <p>Yet his own optimism is belied by RockPort's investments. The firm has not put any money into biofuel companies partly because, Mr. McDermott said, it fears that many will fail unless they get government subsidies. Meanwhile, more than a third of new alternative energy financing from venture capitalists in 2006 went to such startups, according to the National Venture Capital Association.</p>
        <p>The lure of the payoff from investing in energy is too great to ignore for Mr. Metcalfe, who in 1973 invented the Ethernet standard for connecting computers, and in 1979 founded 3Com, which makes computer networking equipment.</p>
        <p>Six years ago, he became a venture capitalist at Polaris Venture Partners, focusing on information-technology startups. Last year, he said he became convinced that energy investments were worthwhile. ''You'd have to be an idiot not to notice the huge opportunity in energy,'' he said. ''The markets are huge.''</p>
        <p>Last April, in one of its first such investments, Polaris put $6.8 million into GreenFuel Technologies Corporation. The company develops algae bioreactor systems that capture carbon dioxide from smokestack emissions, producing more algae that can be converted into biofuels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Metcalfe says he spends a lot of time learning about new energy technologies. One day he might hear about wind power, the next about refining of metallurgical silicon for use in solar cells. ''I'm really on the steep part of the learning curve,'' he said, adding, ''There's no proof yet I'm good at it.''</p>
        <p>But he said he felt the challenge was worthwhile. And it's what he is paid to do.</p>
        <p>''My job is to create innovative high-tech companies and get venture returns,'' he said. ''In the energy market, there's a huge need, and lots of technology to fill that need.''</p>
        <p>NEW CONQUESTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
