<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Powerfully Mixed Messages at the Show</title>
    <meta content="08SHOW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/automobiles/autoshow/08SHOW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070415T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Powerfully Mixed Messages at the Show</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Powerfully Mixed Messages at the Show</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE ULRICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ulrich, Lawrence</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST as automakers prepared to parade their signature V-8 models with 300, 400 and even 500-plus horsepower last week at the opening of the New York International Auto Show, a landmark Supreme Court ruling on greenhouse gas emissions wafted a message to the petrol-fueled party in Manhattan: enjoy the fun while it lasts.</p>
        <p>Certainly, there were plenty of examples of the industry's effort to steal back some of Toyota's competitive (and public relations) edge in all matters green: General Motors rolled out a trio of tiny hatchback design studies -- the Trax, the Beat and the Groove, all designed in its South Korean studio -- that could top 50 miles per gallon if equipped with small diesel engines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A landmark ruling on greenhouse gas emissions sent a message to the petrol-fueled party in Manhattan: enjoy the fun while it lasts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST as automakers prepared to parade their signature V-8 models with 300, 400 and even 500-plus horsepower last week at the opening of the New York International Auto Show, a landmark Supreme Court ruling on greenhouse gas emissions wafted a message to the petrol-fueled party in Manhattan: enjoy the fun while it lasts.</p>
        <p>Certainly, there were plenty of examples of the industry's effort to steal back some of Toyota's competitive (and public relations) edge in all matters green: General Motors rolled out a trio of tiny hatchback design studies -- the Trax, the Beat and the Groove, all designed in its South Korean studio -- that could top 50 miles per gallon if equipped with small diesel engines.</p>
        <p>Ford's green entry, an Edge crossover with the HySeries powertrain, is purely a technology test bed, but the $2 million plug-in hybrid utility wagon is exactly the kind of vehicle that might someday eliminate tailpipe emissions entirely. The Edge HySeries combines a hydrogen fuel cell with a lithium-ion battery pack to create the equivalent of 174 horsepower, while emitting not a trace of carbon dioxide or pollutants, only a steamy blast of water vapor.</p>
        <p>Naming carbon dioxide as a heat-trapping gas that the Environmental Protection Agency must regulate is exactly the game-changing result of the Supreme Court's judgment, even if the fallout for automakers won't be clear for years. America's fleet of roughly 220 million cars and trucks currently contributes about a quarter of the nation's carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Toyota might have felt like holding its breath at the show. First, General Motors stole the green thunder at the Detroit auto show in January with its plug-in hybrid Chevy Volt concept car; meanwhile, Toyota featured its San Antonio-built, big-as-Texas Tundra pickup. And as the environmental talk swirled in New York, Toyota was busy stuffing the Tundra's thirsty 381-horsepower V-8 into its latest plus-sized S.U.V., the Lexus LX 570.</p>
        <p>For that, Toyota suffered the ignominy of being protested by some particularly agile environmental activists, who scaled the glass structure over the front entrance of the Javits Center to unfurl a banner proclaiming Toyota's truckish misdeeds.</p>
        <p>The banner and the protesters are gone, but visitors to the auto show will see close to 1,000 cars and trucks in the convention center, models from Detroit and Tokyo, from Seoul and Stuttgart. They'll also see a distinctly New York exhibit: Taxi 07, which combines taxi prototypes of the future with historical models and displays.</p>
        <p>Some show highlights among models destined for dealerships included:</p>
        <p>SUBARU TRIBECA After receiving a tepid welcome from the market, Subaru's flagship crossover vehicle was rushed back into the design studio, where the aeronautical-theme grille was replaced with a more conventional design. The flat 6 engine is now a 3.6-liter with more torque; there's a more refined five-speed automatic; and the cramped third-row seat has been reconfigured for better access. The 2008 model goes on sale early this summer.</p>
        <p>BENTLEY BROOKLANDS A brawny coupe derived from the Arnage platform, the limited-edition Brooklands is powered by a twin-turbo V-8 producing 530 horsepower.</p>
        <p>AUDI S5 The S5 is a coupe -- a category Audi has virtually ignored for years -- based on the next-generation A4 chassis, and like the current S4 packs a 4.2-liter 354-horsepower V-8, all-wheel-drive and a six-speed manual transmission. Audi cites 0-60 times of just over five seconds.</p>
        <p>MERCEDES C-CLASS The larger, redesigned version of Mercedes's entry-luxury sedan arrives at dealers in August. Starting around $32,000, the C-Class will battle competitors including the BMW 3 Series, Infiniti G35 and the coming second-generation Cadillac CTS. The sedan will offer dual models, Sport and Luxury, the former with a three-pointed star embedded in the grille and the latter with the traditional hood ornament. Both are available as a C300, with a 228-horsepower 3-liter V-6, or as the C350 with a 268-horsepower 3.5-liter V-6.</p>
        <p>FORD FLEX Looking like a cross between a chopped Range Rover and a stretch-limo Mini Cooper -- up to and including the optional white roof -- the Flex is in fact a three-row, full-size crossover wagon. Second-row legroom is indeed limolike, the third row folds flat and an optional rear console houses a refrigerator and freezer. The Flex goes on sale in summer 2008 with a 260-horsepower V-6.</p>
        <p>INFINITI G37 On sale in August, the racy G37 coupe seeks to build on the success of its predecessor, the G35, with the first use of Nissan's new 3.7-liter 330-horsepower V-6.</p>
        <p>SATURN ASTRA Perhaps the most intruiging new small car shown in New York, the Astra takes its name and overall design from an Opel that G.M. sells in Europe. The handsome, modern hatchback -- at a base price of around $16,000 -- will offer three- and five-door versions and a 1.8-liter 4-cylinder engine when it goes on sale this fall.</p>
        <p>JEEP LIBERTY Jeep fans who shed a tear for the departed Cherokee can see some resemblance in the squared-off styling of the latest Liberty, which goes on sale this fall as a 2008 model. The all-new Liberty ditches its four-cylinder engine, leaving only a 210-horsepower V-6.</p>
        <p>LEXUS LX 570 Lexus' latest deluxe off-roader has a 381-horsepower 5.7-liter V-8 engine, 10 air bags, blind-spot cameras and a tot-size third row. Towing capacity is a mighty 8,500 pounds. The LX goes on sale early next year at a base price above $65,000. It will be followed at some point by a new Toyota Land Cruiser based on the same sturdy truck platform.</p>
        <p>VOLVO V70 Volvo's safe Swede eliminates its five-cylinder engine for an in-line 6 with 232 horsepower. Based on the new S80 sedan platform, the wagon features Volvo's first-ever two-stage child booster seats in back, which rise to two set levels to safely accomodate children of various sizes. A future R version of the V70 will get 311 horsepower from a Yamaha-built V-8. The wagon goes on sale early next year at a price likely to start around $32,000.</p>
        <p>BMW 5 SERIES The mildly restyled luxury sedan sees bigger changes under the hood, especially the 535i model, which borrows the 300-horsepower twin-turbocharged in-line 6 from the smaller 335i. This 2008 model is on sale now.</p>
        <p>MERCEDES-BENZ CLK63 AMG BLACK SERIES The current safety car for Formula One racing -- minus the body graphics and roof lights -- is the latest fearsome AMG high-performance model. It features a 500-horsepower 6.2-liter V-8 and a top speed of 186 miles an hour; buyers intent on track compeition can delete the back seat to hold the car's weight down. Only 500 to 700 will be produced, with sales starting in July.</p>
        <p>In addition to automakers' showroom-ready models, a number of concept creations provided peeks at coming styles, features or technology, including:</p>
        <p>CHEVROLET TRAX, BEAT AND GROOVE G.M.'s South Korean studio designed these three conceptual takes on a mini-hatchback theme. One of the designs will certainly reach production in Asia and other markets around 2010 as G.M.'s new global small car; the company is gauging public reaction to decide whether it will come to the United States, too. The Trax features a frugal 1-liter 3-cylinder engine; the sportier Beat has a turbocharged 1. 2-liter 4-cylinder; and the Groove is envisioned with a 1-liter diesel 4.</p>
        <p>HYUNDAI GENESIS This design study heralds a production version of Hyundai's first Korean-built V-8-powered luxury sport sedan. With well over 300 horsepower, the Genesis will challenge Lexus and other luxury makes head-on when it goes on sale in the second half of 2008, at an expected price of less than $30,000.</p>
        <p>INFINITI EX Billed as a concept, the EX is in fact fairly faithful to the production luxury crossover wagon that Infiniti will begin selling by year-end. That model will feature Infiniti's new Around View monitor, which uses multiple cameras to beam a bird's-eye view of the car and its surroundings into the cabin.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 15, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about the New York auto show misidentified a new Volvo model introduced there. It was the XC70 crossover, not the V70 station wagon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 15, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about the New York auto show misidentified a new Volvo model introduced there. It was the XC70 crossover, not the V70 station wagon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
