<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Google and Utility to Test Hybrids That Sell Back Power</title>
    <meta content="19electric" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/technology/19electric.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Batteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric and Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Google Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacific Gas and Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">A123Systems (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Batteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Google Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Pacific Gas &amp; Electric Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Google.org</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Google and Utility to Test Hybrids That Sell Back Power</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Google and Utility to Test Hybrids That Sell Back Power</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER and MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity; Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif., June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Google and Pacific Gas &amp; Electric unveil their vision of future in which cars and trucks are partly powered by country's electric grids, and vice versa; companies display six Toyota Prius and Ford Escape hybrid vehicles modified to run partly on electricity from power grid, allowing vehicles to go up to 75 miles on gallon of gas, nearly double number of miles of regular hybrid; they also modified on vehicle to give electricity back to power company; highly unusual test takes hybrid step further by using extra batteries to hold energy made and distributed by power company; Google's philanthropic foundation, Google.org, leads conversion and announces it will be investing or giving away about $10 million to accelerate development of batteries, technology, plug-in hybrids, and vehicles capable of returning stored energy to grid; Google is using batteries from A123Systems, company that sells aftermarket kit to convert Prius to plug-in vehicle; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Google and Pacific Gas &amp; Electric have unveiled their vision of a future in which cars and trucks are partly powered by the country's electric grids, and vice versa.</p>
        <p>The companies displayed on Monday  six Toyota Prius and Ford Escape hybrid vehicles modified to run partly on electricity from the power grid, allowing the vehicles to go up to 75 miles on a gallon of gas, nearly double the number of miles of a regular hybrid.  They also  modified one vehicle to give electricity back to the power company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Google and Pacific Gas &amp; Electric have unveiled their vision of a future in which cars and trucks are partly powered by the country&amp;#8217;s electric grids, and vice versa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Google and Pacific Gas &amp; Electric have unveiled their vision of a future in which cars and trucks are partly powered by the country's electric grids, and vice versa.</p>
        <p>The companies displayed on Monday  six Toyota Prius and Ford Escape hybrid vehicles modified to run partly on electricity from the power grid, allowing the vehicles to go up to 75 miles on a gallon of gas, nearly double the number of miles of a regular hybrid.  They also  modified one vehicle to give electricity back to the power company.</p>
        <p>The highly unusual test takes the hybrid, which is now familiar on American roads, a step further  by using extra  batteries to hold energy made and distributed by a power company.  The technology is eagerly awaited by energy experts and environmentalists, but is not yet ready to go commercial because the additional batteries are not yet durable enough.</p>
        <p>Google's philanthropic foundation, Google.org, headed by Larry Brilliant, led the conversion and announced that it would be investing or giving away about $10 million to accelerate the development of battery technology, plug-in hybrids, and vehicles capable of returning stored energy to the grid.</p>
        <p>Speaking on a sun-splashed dais in Google's parking lot to an audience well shaded by one of its new solar arrays, Mr. Brilliant described the vehicle designed to give energy back to the grid as ''a bit of a science project.''</p>
        <p>But some observers, like the Stanford professor Stephen Schneider, who was one of the authors of the recent United Nations report on climate change, said that just getting this embryonic technology demonstrated by a company with Google's heft was a victory in itself. ''These guys have clout with hundreds of millions of young and middle-aged people,'' he said, adding that what was necessary to jump-start a new type of car was a combination of reliability, affordability and ''cool.''</p>
        <p>The six vehicles are used by Google employees near the company's  Mountain View headquarters, and sit under a carport with a roof of solar cells. The cells are connected to the power grid, so they make energy whether the cars are charging or not.  Dan Reicher, Google.org's director for climate change and energy initiatives,  said the carports were meant to demonstrate a switch from fossil fuels to solar power.</p>
        <p>Google is using batteries from A123Systems of Watertown, Mass., a company that sells an aftermarket kit to convert the Prius to a plug-in vehicle.</p>
        <p>The Prius that has been converted to allow two-way flows of electricity is a more speculative project. PG&amp;E, the utility serving Northern California, will send wireless signals to the car while it is parked and plugged in to determine its state of charge. It can then recharge the batteries or draw out power.</p>
        <p>The transactions will be tiny, a few kilowatt-hours at a time, worth a few cents each, but if there were thousands of such vehicles, a utility could  store power produced in slack hours until it was needed at peak times, said Brad Whitcomb, PG&amp;E's vice president for customer products and services.</p>
        <p>Some researchers say that utilities pay billions a year to power plants to stand by,  ready to produce extra power or to provide small quantities of energy to maintain the frequency of the system at precisely 60 cycles a  second. Plug-in hybrids could fill those roles, annually earning thousands of dollars each, some experts say.</p>
        <p>But if a car gave all of its energy back to the grid, it would be left to run on gasoline, giving up the environmental benefit.</p>
        <p>A plug-in hybrid can  lower emissions of carbon dioxide and smog-causing gases. It  can go three to four miles on a kilowatt-hour, experts say. If that electricity came from natural gas, that may mean under a quarter-pound of carbon dioxide is emitted each mile. In contrast, a car that gets 20 miles a gallon on unleaded gas emits  about a pound of carbon dioxide each mile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
