<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="18forsumms" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EEDD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>Ethiopian Army Is Accused Of Brutality in Desert War  As Ethiopia fast becomes the United States' closest ally in the Horn of Africa, an emerging concern for the Bush administration is the way the American-trained Ethiopian military operates inside its own borders, especially in its counterinsurgency campaign near the border with Somalia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>24 Die in Kabul Explosion  A mammoth explosion tore through a police bus in the heart of Kabul, killing at least 24 people, 22 of them police academy instructors, in one of the deadliest insurgent attacks in Afghanistan since the fall of the Taliban in 2001.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Abbas Swears In New Rule  The Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah, swore in an emergency government at his headquarters in Ramallah, reasserting his authority over the West Bank.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Sarkozy's Party Wins in France  The conservative party of President Nicolas Sarkozy of France won a solid victory in parliamentary elections, but failed to trounce the opposition on the left as both the polls and politicians had predicted.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Body of Iraqi Editor Is Found  The body of Falieh Mijthab, the political editor of a government-financed newspaper who was kidnapped three days ago by armed men in a Shiite neighborhood of Baghdad, was found in the city's main mortuary.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.N. Peacekeepers to Darfur  The United Nations Security Council and the Sudanese government hammered out the major details of a proposal to send more than 20,000 peacekeeping troops to Darfur, clearing the way for a joint force with the African Union, which will be led and paid for by the United Nations.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Terror in Indonesia Limited  Long before the arrests of its two top militants last week, Indonesia's major terrorist group had been moving away from the tactic of large-scale attacks, according to experts.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Arms Inspection Unit Near End  The United States and Britain have circulated a new proposal to the members of the United Nations Security Council to ''terminate immediately the mandates'' of weapons inspectors in Iraq.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Rising Radicalism in Venezuela  A radical pro-Chávez group that leapt into the Venezuelan consciousness in recent weeks after defacing the headquarters of the country's only remaining opposition television network is one of 40 such groups based in a sprawling housing complex in Caracas.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-16</p>
        <p>Autism Debate Strains A Family and a Charity  Fissures that have long roiled the autism community have made their way into the Wright family, founders of the mega-charity Autism Speaks. Father and daughter are not speaking after a public battle over the pathology and appropriate treatment of the neurological disorder, familiar to thousands of families with autistic children.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>McCain's Fund-Raising Stress  Senator John McCain, who has spent decades fighting to minimize the influence of money on politics, is under extraordinary pressure to raise tens of millions of dollars in a hurry to prove his political viability. Mr. McCain's presidential campaign may be paying the price for a career of positions seemingly calculated to alienate constituencies that according to Washington custom should be prime sources of campaign cash.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Moth Threatens Crops  Over the years, California has faced a number of threats to its agriculture, but sightings of the light brown apple moth, a native of Australia that voraciously feeds on flowers and fruits in nine counties, has state and federal officials in California worried and taking precautious measures to curb any chance of infestation.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Energy Tax Reversal Bill  Senate Democrats are seeking a major reversal of energy tax preferences, with a bill that would raise about $14 billion from oil companies over 10 years and would shower about the same amount of money on new incentives for solar power, wind power, cellulosic ethanol and other renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Edwards Campaigns in Iowa  Four years ago, John Edwards came within a few thousand votes of victory in the Iowa Democratic caucuses. Mr. Edwards's latest trip to Iowa offers evidence of the extent to which the rhythms of Iowa Democratic politics have shaped his decidedly populist pitch to the left this time around</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Teacher's Merit Pay Initiative  Minnesota's $86 million teacher professionalization and merit pay initiative has spread to dozens of the state's school districts, and it got a lift last week when teachers voted to expand it in Minneapolis. A major reason it is prospering, Gov. Tim Pawlenty said in an interview, is that union leaders helped develop it and sell it to teachers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-6</p>
        <p>Albany's Nightlife Suffers Under Tightened Rules  About 15 years ago, Albany was full of bars and restaurants that were a second home to the lawmakers during legislative sessions. But Albany's political nightlife has suffered under new rules on fraternization and lobbyist spending and since Gov. Eliot Spitzer took office. A1</p>
        <p>Coney Island Plan Revised  The developer who wants to remake Coney Island's amusement district has a new plan: A looming 40-story tower planned for the Boardwalk is gone, as are hundreds of rental apartments and luxury condominiums, replaced by hotels. The new proposal has more of the rides and attractions that America's first resort was once known for.  B1</p>
        <p>After-School Programs Cut  The after-school program at Lower East Side Preparatory High School, which provides students with extra hours of tutoring in any subject, is among 207 statewide that are about to run out of government support. Facing the financial crunch in New York City are 118 after-school programs serving almost 20,000 children. B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-12</p>
        <p>Old Banking Name Renewed  Taking advantage of its $3.3 billion purchase of U.S. Trust, Bank of America is expected to announce that the division serving its wealthiest customers will be called U.S. Trust, Bank of America Private Wealth Management.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Airbus Pins Hopes on A350  Production delays for the much-publicized A380 superjumbo has caused Airbus outsize woes. But it is another aircraft, the twin-engine A350, that Airbus hopes will grab the headlines at the Paris Air Show.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Table for Two With a Click  OpenTable is making it easier for restaurants to manage reservations and improve customer service online. Some 7,000 restaurants around the world now use it, and hundreds more are signing on every month.  C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Two cheers on global AIDS: muddy waters; the best judges business can buy: Francis X. Clines on a veteran patrolling the home front.</p>
        <p>Column: Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY D1-7</p>
        <p>Fight Over Big Ten Network  The Big Ten Athletic Conference and Comcast are headed for a clash over the cost of carrying the newly created Big Ten Network. The collegiate athletic conference vows the network will satiate its member universities' fans and alumni, but Comcast says the network is too expensive and too provincial to be broadly distributed. D5</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A17</p>
        <p>Gianfranco Ferré  An Italian fashion designer noted for his singular vision in his signature ready-to-wear collection and for opening the doors of French haute couture to foreign-born designers, he was 62.  A17</p>
        <p>Sir Wally Herbert  The first man to walk across the icebound Arctic Ocean and, some contend, the first to reach the North Pole on foot, a feat long credited to Rear Adm. Robert E. Peary, he was 72.  A17</p>
        <p>Robert Tracy  A prolific dance writer who wrote about dance, theater, music, art and film for newspapers and magazines including The New York Times, Vanity Fair, Dance, Elle and Vogue, he was 52.  A17</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E2  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E10  Weather D8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>Ethiopian Army Is Accused Of Brutality in Desert War  As Ethiopia fast becomes the United States' closest ally in the Horn of Africa, an emerging concern for the Bush administration is the way the American-trained Ethiopian military operates inside its own borders, especially in its counterinsurgency campaign near the border with Somalia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>24 Die in Kabul Explosion  A mammoth explosion tore through a police bus in the heart of Kabul, killing at least 24 people, 22 of them police academy instructors, in one of the deadliest insurgent attacks in Afghanistan since the fall of the Taliban in 2001.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Abbas Swears In New Rule  The Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah, swore in an emergency government at his headquarters in Ramallah, reasserting his authority over the West Bank.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Sarkozy's Party Wins in France  The conservative party of President Nicolas Sarkozy of France won a solid victory in parliamentary elections, but failed to trounce the opposition on the left as both the polls and politicians had predicted.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Body of Iraqi Editor Is Found  The body of Falieh Mijthab, the political editor of a government-financed newspaper who was kidnapped three days ago by armed men in a Shiite neighborhood of Baghdad, was found in the city's main mortuary.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.N. Peacekeepers to Darfur  The United Nations Security Council and the Sudanese government hammered out the major details of a proposal to send more than 20,000 peacekeeping troops to Darfur, clearing the way for a joint force with the African Union, which will be led and paid for by the United Nations.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Terror in Indonesia Limited  Long before the arrests of its two top militants last week, Indonesia's major terrorist group had been moving away from the tactic of large-scale attacks, according to experts.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Arms Inspection Unit Near End  The United States and Britain have circulated a new proposal to the members of the United Nations Security Council to ''terminate immediately the mandates'' of weapons inspectors in Iraq.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Rising Radicalism in Venezuela  A radical pro-Chávez group that leapt into the Venezuelan consciousness in recent weeks after defacing the headquarters of the country's only remaining opposition television network is one of 40 such groups based in a sprawling housing complex in Caracas.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-16</p>
        <p>Autism Debate Strains A Family and a Charity  Fissures that have long roiled the autism community have made their way into the Wright family, founders of the mega-charity Autism Speaks. Father and daughter are not speaking after a public battle over the pathology and appropriate treatment of the neurological disorder, familiar to thousands of families with autistic children.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>McCain's Fund-Raising Stress  Senator John McCain, who has spent decades fighting to minimize the influence of money on politics, is under extraordinary pressure to raise tens of millions of dollars in a hurry to prove his political viability. Mr. McCain's presidential campaign may be paying the price for a career of positions seemingly calculated to alienate constituencies that according to Washington custom should be prime sources of campaign cash.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Moth Threatens Crops  Over the years, California has faced a number of threats to its agriculture, but sightings of the light brown apple moth, a native of Australia that voraciously feeds on flowers and fruits in nine counties, has state and federal officials in California worried and taking precautious measures to curb any chance of infestation.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Energy Tax Reversal Bill  Senate Democrats are seeking a major reversal of energy tax preferences, with a bill that would raise about $14 billion from oil companies over 10 years and would shower about the same amount of money on new incentives for solar power, wind power, cellulosic ethanol and other renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Edwards Campaigns in Iowa  Four years ago, John Edwards came within a few thousand votes of victory in the Iowa Democratic caucuses. Mr. Edwards's latest trip to Iowa offers evidence of the extent to which the rhythms of Iowa Democratic politics have shaped his decidedly populist pitch to the left this time around</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Teacher's Merit Pay Initiative  Minnesota's $86 million teacher professionalization and merit pay initiative has spread to dozens of the state's school districts, and it got a lift last week when teachers voted to expand it in Minneapolis. A major reason it is prospering, Gov. Tim Pawlenty said in an interview, is that union leaders helped develop it and sell it to teachers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-6</p>
        <p>Albany's Nightlife Suffers Under Tightened Rules  About 15 years ago, Albany was full of bars and restaurants that were a second home to the lawmakers during legislative sessions. But Albany's political nightlife has suffered under new rules on fraternization and lobbyist spending and since Gov. Eliot Spitzer took office. A1</p>
        <p>Coney Island Plan Revised  The developer who wants to remake Coney Island's amusement district has a new plan: A looming 40-story tower planned for the Boardwalk is gone, as are hundreds of rental apartments and luxury condominiums, replaced by hotels. The new proposal has more of the rides and attractions that America's first resort was once known for.  B1</p>
        <p>After-School Programs Cut  The after-school program at Lower East Side Preparatory High School, which provides students with extra hours of tutoring in any subject, is among 207 statewide that are about to run out of government support. Facing the financial crunch in New York City are 118 after-school programs serving almost 20,000 children. B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-12</p>
        <p>Old Banking Name Renewed  Taking advantage of its $3.3 billion purchase of U.S. Trust, Bank of America is expected to announce that the division serving its wealthiest customers will be called U.S. Trust, Bank of America Private Wealth Management.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Airbus Pins Hopes on A350  Production delays for the much-publicized A380 superjumbo has caused Airbus outsize woes. But it is another aircraft, the twin-engine A350, that Airbus hopes will grab the headlines at the Paris Air Show.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Table for Two With a Click  OpenTable is making it easier for restaurants to manage reservations and improve customer service online. Some 7,000 restaurants around the world now use it, and hundreds more are signing on every month.  C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Two cheers on global AIDS: muddy waters; the best judges business can buy: Francis X. Clines on a veteran patrolling the home front.</p>
        <p>Column: Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY D1-7</p>
        <p>Fight Over Big Ten Network  The Big Ten Athletic Conference and Comcast are headed for a clash over the cost of carrying the newly created Big Ten Network. The collegiate athletic conference vows the network will satiate its member universities' fans and alumni, but Comcast says the network is too expensive and too provincial to be broadly distributed. D5</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A17</p>
        <p>Gianfranco Ferré  An Italian fashion designer noted for his singular vision in his signature ready-to-wear collection and for opening the doors of French haute couture to foreign-born designers, he was 62.  A17</p>
        <p>Sir Wally Herbert  The first man to walk across the icebound Arctic Ocean and, some contend, the first to reach the North Pole on foot, a feat long credited to Rear Adm. Robert E. Peary, he was 72.  A17</p>
        <p>Robert Tracy  A prolific dance writer who wrote about dance, theater, music, art and film for newspapers and magazines including The New York Times, Vanity Fair, Dance, Elle and Vogue, he was 52.  A17</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E2  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E10  Weather D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
