<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Detroit Decides to Help Shape, Not Resist, Regulation of Emissions</title>
    <meta content="07emissions" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/business/07emissions.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York International Auto Show</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maynard, Micheline</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bunkley, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sturm, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Detroit Decides to Help Shape, Not Resist, Regulation of Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Detroit Decides to Help Shape, Not Resist, Regulation of Emissions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELINE MAYNARD and NICK BUNKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maynard, Micheline; Bunkley, Nick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carmakers at New York International Auto Show are contending with possibility that gas-guzzling vehicles may soon become harder to sell; Supreme Court has ruled that EPA has authority to regulate carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases from autos; carmakers and environmentalists say primary way that can be done is to increase automobile fuel efficiency; automakers say they want active role in movement to reduce damage vehicles do to environment; Toyota vice president Steve Sturm says one reason is public pressure; chart; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York International Auto Show, which opened to the public yesterday, is a picture of an industry with a cloud over its head.</p>
        <p>While the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center abounds with flashy new vehicles like the big Lexus LX 570, a sport utility vehicle equipped with 19 speakers and 10 air bags, and the high-powered Ford Mustang 500 GT KR, created by the longtime racing designer Carroll Shelby, the carmakers are also contending with the possibility that such gas-guzzling vehicles may soon become harder to sell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Automakers and their Washington trade group say they want an active role in the movement to reduce the damage vehicles do to the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York International Auto Show, which opened to the public yesterday, is a picture of an industry with a cloud over its head.</p>
        <p>While the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center abounds with flashy new vehicles like the big Lexus LX 570, a sport utility vehicle equipped with 19 speakers and 10 air bags, and the high-powered Ford Mustang 500 GT KR, created by the longtime racing designer Carroll Shelby, the carmakers are also contending with the possibility that such gas-guzzling vehicles may soon become harder to sell.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the Supreme Court ruled that the Environmental Protection Agency has the authority to regulate carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases from automobiles. The primary way that can be done, carmakers and environmentalists say, is to increase automobile fuel economy.</p>
        <p>In normal times, that would raise hackles from Detroit carmakers, which have a long history of fighting regulations covering both fuel economy and tailpipe emissions. But this week, company executives were saying something different.</p>
        <p>Rather than openly battle regulations that would force them to make vehicles more efficient, automakers and their Washington trade group are saying they want an active role in the movement to reduce the damage vehicles do to the environment.</p>
        <p>One reason is public pressure, said Steve Sturm, group vice president for Toyota in North America. ''Look at how many people went to see Al Gore's movie,'' Mr. Sturm said, referring to ''An Inconvenient Truth.''</p>
        <p>Environmental issues are ''in the news every week,'' Mr. Sturm added. ''It keeps getting major headlines.''</p>
        <p>Exhaust emissions from the tailpipes of cars and trucks account for about a fifth of the country's total emissions of heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>''People get it now,'' said David Doniger, a lawyer and climate center policy director of the Natural Resources Defense Council. ''They didn't pay much attention to global warming five years ago.''</p>
        <p>Another crucial factor is the move by both Congress and the Bush administration for action on fuel economy. Lawmakers have introduced bills calling for raising the fuel economy standard, called the corporate average fuel economy, to as high as 40 miles a gallon, compared with the current 27.5 miles a gallon for cars and 24 miles a gallon for light trucks.</p>
        <p>The administration's proposal, part of a collection of steps it wants to see taken on the environment, would call for more modest increases of about one mile a gallon per year over the next few years.</p>
        <p>No matter what is instituted, however, carmakers are getting the message that fuel economy is going to go up as part of the fight against global warming, even if government action is still several years away.</p>
        <p>Given that, carmakers said at the New York show that they want to be included in the dialogue, not shunted aside because of their past resistance.</p>
        <p>''We very much want to work with Congress,'' said Derrick M. Kuzak, group vice president for global product development at the Ford Motor Company, echoing the official stance of the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers, an industry trade group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuzak went on, ''We recognize that CO2 is an issue and we want to be part of the solution, but it has to be technology-based, and affordable.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doniger said, ''They're coming to the table so they can avoid being on the menu.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Kuzak said the worst thing Congress or the administration could do would be to make changes that would force consumers to change their buying habits and ''force us to include expensive technology'' that buyers are not willing to pay for. Even so, small cars outsold sport utility vehicles last year and analysts expect S.U.V. sales to continue to decline.</p>
        <p>The technology that would be required to fight automotive emissions could raise the cost of many vehicles by more than $5,000, said Robert A. Lutz, vice chairman at General Motors. Rebates and other incentives have made buyers resistant to price increases, so the struggling automakers would have to absorb the expense.</p>
        <p>''This technology does not come for free,'' he told reporters at the auto show. ''Anybody who thinks that the auto industry will invent some sort of device that will eliminate or absorb CO2 is dreaming.''</p>
        <p>Even so, for the last year G.M. has promoted the vehicles in its lineup that achieve 30 miles to the gallon. At the show this week, G.M. took that focus a step further. It showed off three tiny concept cars, the Trax, Beat and Groove, which could represent a future minicar to be sold by Chevrolet. The company is asking visitors to visit a Web site, www.vote4chevrolet.com, to choose their favorite among the three, which it could then put in production.</p>
        <p>Still, the carmakers are squaring off against states and environmentalists outside Washington. Eleven states have adopted the emissions regulations created by California, which are meant to cut emissions from cars and light trucks by 25 percent and from sport utility vehicles by 18 percent, beginning in 2009.</p>
        <p>Automakers have jointly filed suit against the regulations in California and will go to court in Vermont next week, in an effort to block the measures from being enacted there. The automakers say they would have to close dealerships and limit the number of big vehicles they sell in Vermont and elsewhere if the regulations take effect.</p>
        <p>Toyota, which has sold more than 500,000 hybrid-electric vehicles in the United States this decade, still has found itself a target of environmentalists because it has broadened its range to include big vehicles like the new version of the Tundra pickup.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, two protestors from the environmental group Freedom From Oil were arrested after they unfurled a 20-foot banner at the entrance to the Javits Center. Borrowing from Toyota's advertising slogan, the banner read, ''Toyota: The Truck That's Changing the Climate.''</p>
        <p>The protest took place a day after Toyota said that it sold a record number of Prius hybrid cars during March, thanks in part to an advertising campaign coupled with special lease deals.</p>
        <p>''Building Priuses does not give Toyota license to mass-produce the Tundra,'' said Sarah Connolly, the co-director of the Freedom From Oil campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sturm said he did not see any conflict between the vehicles. The Prius allows Toyota ''to be noticed as an environmentally sensitive company,'' he said, while Tundra puts Toyota in the big-truck market ''where everyone plays.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Kuzak at Ford agreed that it would be variety, not a single approach that is needed to address the fuel economy issue. He said Ford was looking at several strategies. .</p>
        <p>''It is not simply power train technology, it is not simply downsizing vehicles,'' said Mr. Kuzak, whose company showed off a new crossover vehicle called the Flex as well as a big Ford Expedition customized by the hip-hop disc jockey Funkmaster Flex.</p>
        <p>''All those technologies will get us to where we need to be as an industry,'' Mr. Kuzak said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
