<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Headline News</title>
    <meta content="Shacochis.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/18/books/review/Shacochis.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1833655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Raban, Jonathan</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Surveillance (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3D61231F93BA25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1254" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Headline News</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Headline News</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB SHACOCHIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shacochis, Bob</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SURVEILLANCE</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Raban.</p>
        <p>258 pp. Pantheon Books. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Jonathan Raban’s novel of the near future, paranoia infiltrateseveryday life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SURVEILLANCE</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Raban.</p>
        <p>258 pp. Pantheon Books. $24.</p>
        <p>To whom shall we entrust the rendering of this moment and its attendant verities -- the artist or the correspondent, the purveyors of fictions or the gatherers of facts? And who gets to play gatekeeper in this game? The question, both plot device and intellectual premise, animates ''Surveillance,'' the gripping new novel by Jonathan Raban, a British writer who for years has embedded himself in America, earning acclaim for his fresh-eyed travelogues and journalism.</p>
        <p>Once upon a time the question could be swatted away -- you're talking apples and oranges -- but not anymore. Boundaries have corroded, shapes blurred, genres intermarried. Fabrications are as efficacious as facts.</p>
        <p>When we read the Times Op-Ed columnist Bob Herbert on anger -- ''The anger quotient is much too low,'' he wrote recently, addressing the political mood in the country -- and then Raban's observations on the same subject, we find ourselves at the center of a murky debate about the current status of fiction versus nonfiction that occupies much of the thematic space in Raban's novel. ''Tad was angry,'' Raban writes. Tad Zachary is a 50ish, gay, H.I.V.-positive, professional actor in Seattle. ''He was angry with himself, angry with the presidency, angry with the nation, angry with the century. That much was rational, justifiable. ... Decent people now were angry people, and what America needed at this low moment in its history was more anger, not less.'' Tad, however, doesn't seek ''to rescue the administration from its folly: he wanted to see it blown to atomic dust or drowned in a sack.'' Here, at least, the anger quotient, considerably more heated than congressional oversight hearings on the Iraq war, is much too high. +</p>
        <p>At the place where Herbert and Raban intersect, do their words complement or cancel one another out, enhance or diminish the force of Herbert's analysis or Raban's make-believe? This is precisely the sort of human algebra that Raban bends his characters around throughout the book, to fascinating yet irresolute effect. Opinions appear to converge on a single truth, but each character has read the thermometer differently, the disparity in this case perhaps explained by the fact that ''Surveillance'' leans out from today's headlines to sniff at a horizon that is within walking distance, a Seattle that might not be 2007 yet edges no further into the calendar than 2008. An overly familiar America, accurately portrayed and perforce underimagined. What's new? One hardly needs a crystal ball: national identity cards, stone-faced soldiers manning checkpoints, an economy in the pits, intensified global warming. Bush still seems to be president, the nation remains divided, Iraq is Iraq. There have been no new terrorist attacks upon the homeland, although extravagant stagings of emergency and disaster drills, spiffed up with actors like Tad, are disruptively common.</p>
        <p>The drama at hand is mostly atmospheric, the texture of society itself, the quotidian pressures inflated by a ubiquitous sense of dread for what might one day wake us up -- not from the nightmare but into the nightmare. Yet the lives Raban zeroes in on are essentially stable, comfortable, urban middle-class or nouveau riche, their profiles instantly recognizable as our own in the cultural mirror.</p>
        <p>Tad, the eternally aggrieved leftist, cherishes the one good, sane thing in his life -- the postmodern family he has created with the tenants across the hall, Lucy Bengstrom and her 11-year-old daughter, Alida, in their slightly seedy downtown apartment building. Over the years he has become Alida's surrogate father and Lucy's platonic lover and domestic task-sharer. Lucy, an overweight, boomer-aged single mom and a ''model bourgeois liberal'' who believes in neither evil nor certitude, is a freelance writer for A-list magazines (Tina Brown kept her on a monthly retainer in the '90s) although the assignments have dwindled sufficiently of late for her to be grateful when she gets a timely call from GQ asking her to track down the reclusive literary sensation of the season, a retired history professor named August Vanags, who lives on an island in Puget Sound. Vanags, who claims to have been born in Latvia on the eve of World War II, has written a best-selling memoir (yes, Spielberg's making the movie) about his childhood, which included time in both Hitler's and Stalin's camps. He is one of two immigrants who bookend ''Surveillance'' -- the second is a ruthlessly ambitious Chinese landlord -- and their true identities remain uncertain throughout the narrative.</p>
        <p>What happens then among these five is a replay of the polarized polemics any sentient citizen has been exposed to throughout the past six years. Vanags, a former Kissinger aide during the Nixon administration, is a charming but unrepentant neocon who seems to be channeling Charles Krauthammer; Tad is to the diatribe born. The savantish 11-year-old interjects naïve, untested idealism; the landlord provides the rapacious entrepreneurial spirit that vacuums capitalism clean of conscience. Agnostic, skeptical Lucy listens and referees. She is a watcher who, like the author himself, has placed us all under benign surveillance and, given the conflicting evidence, is understandably reluctant to draw conclusions.</p>
        <p>Which returns us to the tricky question ''Surveillance'' forces upon its readers: In the courtroom of history, who gets to testify as a credible witness? Bush is the author of his own legacy, certainly, but how do we sort out his narrative from the one we ourselves create as a nation, especially in light of those among us who falsify, spin or otherwise revise to suit agendas that spawn parallel realities?</p>
        <p>There's plenty of talk in ''Surveillance'' about who reads what and why. Vanags distrusts The New York Times and favors The Wall Street Journal. Tad listens to Al-Jazeera and scours the European press for the ''real'' story. Alida hates fantasies but loves Agatha Christie. The Chinese landlord, contemptuous of novels, gulps down books about Sam Walton. For Lucy, the writer, the more alien the world she reads about, the happier she is.</p>
        <p>We might assume then that she'd be unhappy reading ''Surveillance,'' which is a bit like reality TV, both authentic and artificial. One begins to wonder, as I believe the author intends us to, if the contemporary moment is not ''better'' delivered by the news cycle and the unceasing slosh of cyberflotsam and citizen-journalists with videophones than by literature. The very relevance of ''Surveillance'' to the present moment, in a culture where nearly every surface is hyper-reflective, threatens to amplify the noise and weariness of the day and, paradoxically, actually drown the novel's own relevance out.</p>
        <p>To his credit, Raban seems to understand the gamble and make the most of it, though not without an occasional misstep -- most noticeably the tendency of characters to stagger beneath the metaphorical load. What the book offers in its auditing of the national dialogue contains no surprises. The talking heads talk. The characters also bloom into their bodies, lives and loves. The insufferable weather turns nostalgically clement. We look in the mirror -- here we are -- and look away, puzzled or embittered or cocksure.</p>
        <p>It's during the denouement of the deceptively modest plot that the big message is delivered, the long-awaited apocalyptic swipe brought to us by ... well, the Other Player in the mix. The novel unmasks itself as an elaborate, ingenious frame for a discourse on the nature of writing, and a platform from which to administer a strong kick of cosmic reality to the backside of mankind's roiling affairs. We're tossed onto the stage of a profound truth, where literature outperforms anything else.</p>
        <p>Good morning, Seattle. Welcome to New Orleans.</p>
        <p>Bob Shacochis' next novel, ''The Woman Who Lost Her Soul,'' will be published in 2008.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bob Shacochis' next novel, ''The Woman Who Lost Her Soul,'' will be published in 2008.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
