<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blotting Out the Big Sky</title>
    <meta content="29mcnamer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/opinion/29mcnamer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Montana</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFD7123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blotting Out the Big Sky</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blotting Out the Big Sky</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deirdre McNamer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcnamer, Deirdre</byline>
      <dateline>Missoula, Mont.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>APRIL is the month many Montanans start looking for dollar signs in the weather. Is the spring runoff from the mountains once again too early, too fast, too meager to mitigate the drought plaguing the farmers and ranchers who are the linchpins of the state's economy? Are river temperatures too high, too soon, for cold-water fish like trout that bring in thousands of tourists every summer? Will Glacier National Park's rapidly receding glaciers fail to bring in visitors this summer, or lure them for one last look? Will today's rain last more than a day? Will the forests wait until August to burn?</p>
        <p>When I was a child in the 1950s, much of Montana felt like a place that couldn't really be touched by the hand of man. Sometimes we threw our hamburger wrappers out the car window just to watch them land on the empty prairie and flutter like tiny flags planted on the moon. Then they blew away and out of sight and there was nothing to show that we'd ever passed through.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The weather that now bears very directly on the Montana economy is in crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>APRIL is the month many Montanans start looking for dollar signs in the weather. Is the spring runoff from the mountains once again too early, too fast, too meager to mitigate the drought plaguing the farmers and ranchers who are the linchpins of the state's economy? Are river temperatures too high, too soon, for cold-water fish like trout that bring in thousands of tourists every summer? Will Glacier National Park's rapidly receding glaciers fail to bring in visitors this summer, or lure them for one last look? Will today's rain last more than a day? Will the forests wait until August to burn?</p>
        <p>When I was a child in the 1950s, much of Montana felt like a place that couldn't really be touched by the hand of man. Sometimes we threw our hamburger wrappers out the car window just to watch them land on the empty prairie and flutter like tiny flags planted on the moon. Then they blew away and out of sight and there was nothing to show that we'd ever passed through.</p>
        <p>Even a decade later, brainwashed enough by the intervening litterbug campaign to keep our trash to ourselves, driving hundreds of miles in a gas-guzzling monster to a spring basketball tournament seemed all about freedom and celebration and the end of another scathing white winter. If someone had told us that we were altering the weather in the slightest respect, we would have laughed them into the next county.</p>
        <p>The weather that now bears very directly on the Montana economy has been, as one of our University of Montana climate scientists, Steve Running, puts it, ''a slow-motion crisis'' that began in the 1980s. That's the decade when ocean temperatures off Victoria, British Columbia, which determine downwind climates in Montana, began to turn upward. And it's the decade that saw the conflagrations in Yellowstone National Park transform into a pattern of ''monster wildfires'' every two to three years rather than every 20 or 30 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Running helped write the recent report from the International Panel on Climate Change on global warming trends, and he spoke at a library awards banquet I happened to attend a few weeks ago. Oddly, given the dire tone of the report, Mr. Running seems a rather buoyant, hopeful guy. In the 1980s, he pointed out, technological innovations like the cellphone, iPod and Internet-connected laptop were beyond our wildest imaginings. He said that a similar burst of technological innovation, already in progress, signals the possibility of flattening out carbon dioxide emissions over the next half-century.</p>
        <p>But even if technology comes through, humans might still insist on throwing their wrappers out the window, in a manner of speaking. Will we be willing to drive 65 miles per hour rather than 75? Cut our automobile miles in half? And, maybe most important, fly less?</p>
        <p>''I'm really worried about jet travel,'' Mr. Running said. And it doesn't take much poking around in the statistics to get worried too. While air travel generates only 3 percent of this country's annual carbon dioxide emissions, the pollution and clouds that jets produce increase that impact on the climate by two to four times.</p>
        <p>So here's the sort of situation you've got in Montana on the brink of tourist season. The state's major economic assets include the fish that people want to catch, the birds they want to shoot, the vistas they want to contemplate, the unspoiled terrain they want to experience. And a large percentage of the tourists who come to do those things will not think twice about arriving in a car or a jet, although these emissions negate a lot of the Prius driving, fluorescent light bulb using, Energy Star appliance buying and local-food eating that the tourist might practice at home. And each trip makes it at least incrementally less likely that the fish and wildlife and terrain they come to see will be intact the next time they arrive.</p>
        <p>There is a window of economic opportunity for Montanans between April and September, when about 70 percent of the 10 million who visit the state each year show up and spend their money. We aren't going to tell anybody to stay away. Know, though, that the way you get here affects what we may have to offer you in the future. And think about taking the train.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Deirdre McNamer is the author of the forthcoming novel ''Red Rover.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Deirdre McNamer is the author of the forthcoming novel ''Red Rover.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
