<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GQ Hopes to Make the 'G' Stand for Generosity</title>
    <meta content="23adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/23/business/media/23adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1828200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E5DD103EF930A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GQ Hopes to Make the 'G' Stand for Generosity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">GQ Hopes to Make the ‘G’ Stand for Generosity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE term ''very GQ'' entered the vernacular long ago, evoking sartorial splendor or stylish behavior. Now, the magazine that inspired the phrase is hoping to redefine it by declaring that you are never fully dressed without a social conscience.</p>
        <p>To help commemorate its 50th anniversary this year, GQ magazine is starting a charitable project called the Gentlemen's Fund. The initiative is centered on a Web site that is planned to go live today, thegentlemensfund.com. It will also involve the GQ Mobile text-messaging service and events at stores like Saks Fifth Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Burnishing the image of a brand or company by forging ties with a philanthropy or charity is becoming increasingly popular on Madison Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE term ''very GQ'' entered the vernacular long ago, evoking sartorial splendor or stylish behavior. Now, the magazine that inspired the phrase is hoping to redefine it by declaring that you are never fully dressed without a social conscience.</p>
        <p>To help commemorate its 50th anniversary this year, GQ magazine is starting a charitable project called the Gentlemen's Fund. The initiative is centered on a Web site that is planned to go live today, thegentlemensfund.com. It will also involve the GQ Mobile text-messaging service and events at stores like Saks Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>The singer John Legend, who is the spokesman for the fund, will encourage visitors to the Web site to make donations, to buy merchandise from marketers like Nautica and to take part in eBay auctions. All proceeds are to benefit five organizations in areas like education, men's health and the environment.</p>
        <p>''When we were kids, if someone dressed nicely, we said they were GQ,'' Mr. Legend said in a telephone interview yesterday.</p>
        <p>''It's cool using the name for more than looking good,'' he added. ''If you want to be a GQ man, you should give.'' Mr. Legend said he would represent the fund without charge.</p>
        <p>The project will be promoted in a print and online campaign that carries the theme ''Better men. Better world.'' The fund begins with $325,000 and has a goal of raising $2 million, said Peter King Hunsinger, vice president and publisher at GQ, part of the Condé Nast Publications unit of Advance Publications.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunsinger said the seed donations came from 55 contributors, including Bloomingdale's, a division of Federated Department Stores; the Carat North America media agency, part of the Aegis Group; the Gucci Group; Moët &amp; Chandon, owned by LVMH Moët Hennessy Louis Vuitton; and the YouTube unit of Google.</p>
        <p>The project is an example of cause-related marketing or cause marketing, which is becoming increasingly popular on Madison Avenue. The idea is to burnish the image of a brand or company by forging ties with a philanthropy or charity.</p>
        <p>Cause marketing has been around for more than two decades, but recently seems to be gathering steam. One reason is the ardent interest in causes among younger Americans, according to Carol Cone, the chairwoman at Cone Inc. in Boston, an agency owned by the Omnicom Group that specializes in the practice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunsinger said the idea for the fund stemmed from the response to an article that ran in the December issue of GQ, ''The New Rules of Charity,'' which suggested ''that this new generation of guys wants to be involved and find a way to make a difference.''</p>
        <p>Another reason for the growth of cause-related marketing is its integration with the consumer culture, particularly when people are told that purchasing products they may already intend to buy will generate revenue for charities.</p>
        <p>Current examples include the (Product) Red campaign, supported by marketers like Apple, Gap and Motorola, which raises money for programs to prevent and treat AIDS. Some trace this aspect of the trend to entreaties from elected officials after 9/11, asserting that Americans could fight terrorism by stimulating the American economy -- shopping, in other words.</p>
        <p>''We have customers who feel they are in a position to help other people,'' said Michael Macko, vice president and men's fashion director at Saks Fifth Avenue, part of Saks Inc. ''When you can tie it into the shopping experience, our customers like that very much.''</p>
        <p>Saks, the national retail partner for the fund, will sponsor an eight-page section in the anniversary issue of GQ, scheduled for October, and will play host to events at stores in New York, San Francisco and the Washington area. It will also promote the fund in its fall men's catalog and devote displays in six windows in October at its flagship Midtown Manhattan store to the fund and GQ.</p>
        <p>''We're approached all the time to partner on things like this,'' Mr. Macko said. ''This really stood out and captured our attention, especially when you can partner with someone you have a longstanding history with.''</p>
        <p>His reference was to the fact that the first issue of GQ carried an ad from Saks. It was, according to Mr. Macko's files, for a black Italian suit that cost $200.</p>
        <p>''It's not that dissimilar from a suit we still sell,'' Mr. Macko said, adding dryly, ''The price has changed a bit.'' One of the six window displays in October will recreate the ad.</p>
        <p>Shoppers on the fund's Web site will be offered a customized version of a new product, the deck shirt, from the Nautica clothing line sold by the VF Corporation. It will bear the fund's logo of a standing man along with the Nautica brand logo of a J-class sailboat.</p>
        <p>The customized shirts will also be sold on the Nautica Web site (www.nautica.com ). All proceeds from the sales of the shirts, costing $49.50 each, will be donated to the fund.</p>
        <p>''People want to give back,'' said Denise V. Seegal, president and chief executive at the VF sportswear coalition unit of VF, ''and we're happy to support causes that highlight important men's issues.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunsinger of GQ described the five organizations that would benefit from the fund as ''great, midsized charities that could use our help to get support and awareness.''</p>
        <p>The charities are A Better Chance, which helps academically talented minority youngsters to attend college-preparatory schools; Career Gear, which provides training, counseling and even interview clothes for men re-entering the work force; the Design Industries Foundation Fighting AIDS, known as Diffa; Global Green USA, which is devoted to issues like climate change and safe drinking water; and Justice for Children International, which battles child exploitation and sex-trafficking.</p>
        <p>''People are going to find out about us who would not otherwise,'' said John Sanful, managing director at Career Gear.</p>
        <p>''And working with GQ could lead to more corporate partnerships down the line,'' he added, ''which could help us serve more men.''</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
