<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Intellectual Property Is on the Block at a German Auctioneer</title>
    <meta content="15auction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/15/business/worldbusiness/15auction.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">IP Auctions</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Brien, Kevin J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0D61231F936A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Intellectual Property Is on the Block at a German Auctioneer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Intellectual Property Is on the Block at a German Auctioneer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN J. O'BRIEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Brien, Kevin J</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, May 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Intellectual property rights will be auctioned by IP Auctions in Germany; event is first auction of such property in Europe, and its organizers hope it will open new sales channel to speed transfer of intellectual property in cheaper, more open marketplace; global sales of intellectual property surged with rise of digital economy, with annual transactions rising to $200 billion this year, from $10 billion in 1990; 84 sellers will offer licenses and patents for technologies ranging from industrial coating machinery to treatments for skin cancer; minimum value of intellectual property being auctioned in Munich is more than 5 million euros ($6.7 million) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Webasto, an auto parts maker based in a Munich suburb, has spent millions over the last decade negotiating licenses for its products to automakers like Mercedes-Benz, Volvo, Opel, Volkswagen and Audi.</p>
        <p>But on Tuesday, it plans to auction the rights to one of its best-selling products -- a rooftop solar panel -- to the highest bidder at a public auction. The event is the first auction of intellectual property in Europe, and its organizers hope it will open a new sales channel to speed the transfer of intellectual property in a cheaper, more open marketplace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Webasto plans to auction the rights to one of its best-selling products to the highest bidder at a public auction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Webasto, an auto parts maker based in a Munich suburb, has spent millions over the last decade negotiating licenses for its products to automakers like Mercedes-Benz, Volvo, Opel, Volkswagen and Audi.</p>
        <p>But on Tuesday, it plans to auction the rights to one of its best-selling products -- a rooftop solar panel -- to the highest bidder at a public auction. The event is the first auction of intellectual property in Europe, and its organizers hope it will open a new sales channel to speed the transfer of intellectual property in a cheaper, more open marketplace.</p>
        <p>''The knowledge society is becoming more and more important,'' said Manfred Petri of IP Auctions, a Hamburg company that is organizing the event. ''The values being created by intellectual property are becoming too large to trade in a clandestine market.''</p>
        <p>Global sales of intellectual property surged with the rise of the digital economy, with annual transactions rising to $200 billion this year, from $10 billion in 1990, according to Mr. Petri.</p>
        <p>At Tuesday's auction, 84 sellers will offer licenses and patents for technologies ranging from industrial coating machinery to treatments for skin cancer.</p>
        <p>The minimum value of the intellectual property being auctioned in Munich is more than 5 million euros ($6.7 million), according to the organizers. The event has attracted large companies like Bayer, Rolls-Royce Deutschland and ABB, as well as universities, research institutes and individuals.</p>
        <p>Many sellers are hoping for a new sales channel for intellectual property, which is costly to market through the traditional method of hiring patent lawyers to negotiate with potential buyers. Webasto, for example, is hoping to get a seven-digit sum for the license to its sunroof solar panel, which generates electricity to ventilate parked cars on hot summer days.</p>
        <p>''Climate change is a very big topic right now and we are approaching this auction with that in mind,'' said Markus Bedenbecker, Webasto's director of intellectual property services. ''The normal way we sell I.P. is to study the market and make contacts, but that is immensely labor-intensive.''</p>
        <p>Smaller sellers, who often lack the power to obtain large royalty fees in negotiations with corporations, are also hoping for better profits. That includes Ipal, an organization that markets patents developed by researchers at universities and teaching hospitals in Berlin. In Munich, Ipal is auctioning rights to inositolized phospholipids, a substance developed by researchers at Charité Hospital that has shown promise in treating skin ailments.</p>
        <p>An intellectual property auction held in April by Ocean Tomo Auctions, a Chicago company, netted $11.4 million for sellers, including the largest single fee paid, $3 million. Ocean Tomo plans to hold its first European auction in London on June 1.</p>
        <p>''The auction is a unique platform. It creates a sense of urgency,'' said Andrew T. Ramer, president of Ocean Tomo Auctions. ''It is appropriate not just for patents and licenses, but for brands and catalogs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramer said the auction format was suited to all types of intellectual property except complex pharmaceutical patents, where the density of information is too great for the compressed negotiating atmosphere of an auction.</p>
        <p>But Lothar Steiling, chief patent counsel at Bayer, who is also president of the German Association of Intellectual Property Experts, said auctions would probably fill a niche only for smaller intellectual property sales, with larger sales remaining subject to protracted one-on-one negotiations.</p>
        <p>Still, even Bayer is willing to experiment. On Tuesday, it will auction a license for electrochromic systems, a nanotechnology used to tint windows and enable car mirrors to be used as digital displays. In addition to gaining royalties, Mr. Steiling said Bayer wanted to cut the cost of maintaining 80,000 patents.</p>
        <p>''If this auction is successful,'' he said, ''we will be back.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
