<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Best After-Party? Sorry, There's No Competition</title>
    <meta content="27part" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/27/movies/27part.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070301T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards/Academy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Vanity Fair</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Morton's</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Scorsese, Martin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">DeGeneres, Ellen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cruise, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitaker, Forest</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mirren, Helen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EEDC1E3EF934A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Best After-Party? Sorry, There's No Competition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Best After-Party? Sorry, There’s No Competition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHARON WAXMAN and ERIC WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waxman, Sharon; Wilson, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif., Feb. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long past midnight, Martin Scorsese stood in the center of the celebrity scrum at the Vanity Fair party here.</p>
        <p>''The most surprising thing was best picture,'' he said, holding his Oscar tightly about the neck, pausing for a moment so the director John Singleton could snap a picture of him with his longtime editor and fellow winner, Thelma Schoonmaker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was joy in the room at the Vanity Fair party at Morton’s, by now an Oscar night tradition that has cowed the competition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long past midnight, Martin Scorsese stood in the center of the celebrity scrum at the Vanity Fair party here.</p>
        <p>''The most surprising thing was best picture,'' he said, holding his Oscar tightly about the neck, pausing for a moment so the director John Singleton could snap a picture of him with his longtime editor and fellow winner, Thelma Schoonmaker.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think it was the kind of film that they would choose,'' Mr. Scorsese said of ''The Departed.'' But they did, for two of the biggest awards: best picture, best director. Hollywood, all is forgiven. ''For me, it's good that it came now,'' said Mr. Scorsese, referring to his seven previous nominations, and snubs. ''Now I'm concentrating on the work.''</p>
        <p>There was joy in the room at the Vanity Fair party at Morton's, by now an Oscar night tradition that has cowed the competition. The restaurant filled on Sunday night with the likes of Helen Mirren, Forest Whitaker, Jennifer Hudson and Peter O'Toole (who was perched merrily on a banquette most of the night). It was as if the industry breathed a collective sigh of relief that the Martin Scorsese Story now had a beginning, a middle and a happy end: spurned for his most brilliant, early work (''Taxi Driver,'' ''Raging Bull''), left to wander in the cinematic wilderness -- or, at least, New York -- for decades, and now, finally, the prize for ''The Departed,'' a return to his gangster roots.</p>
        <p>And that's a strange thing about Hollywood. It operates very much like an exotic tribe, with its own social code and pecking order. Within the tribe, there was widespread accord that the director had been overlooked for too long. It was time to right the wrong; this was the topic on everyone's lips at the parties, post-Oscar.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't surprised'' to see the Scorsese win, said Mr. Singleton, who is also a producer (of ''Hustle &amp; Flow,'' among other films). ''I was very happy,'' he added. ''It's ironic to give Marty the Oscar for what, essentially, is a cowboy movie. This one is foulmouthed, but they accepted it. It's funny.''</p>
        <p>Graham King, a producer of ''The Departed,'' stood clutching his statue, looking not a little bit shell-shocked. ''The funny thing is, we never talked about it during the making of the film,'' he said. (''It,'' of course, being Oscar.) ''We did during 'Gangs of New York.' And 'The Aviator.' But not during 'The Departed.' And here we are.''</p>
        <p>On this night, Hollywood gathers at the Vanity Fair party, which ranges through Morton's restaurant and into a massive white tent, a sprawling space crackling with the electric energy of dozens of movie stars left to roam without agents, publicists and security guards. Rich folks don't rate much: Paul Allen, the Microsoft billionaire and an original backer of DreamWorks, wandered around, barely noticed. Jeff Skoll, the eBay billionaire, was having more luck, but that's because he financed ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' the global- warming film that won best documentary.</p>
        <p>Strange pairings are the order of the evening: Sean Penn talking to Naomi Campbell, for instance (neither angrily), or the Nascar driver Jeff Gordon listening to the actor Aaron Eckhart. ''Twenty-four is my favorite number,'' Mr. Eckhart said, referring to the figure emblazoned on Mr. Gordon's car.</p>
        <p>There may be fancier parties, but Vanity Fair's has become the sine qua non of Oscar night. Even Elton John trimmed back his charity fundraiser for AIDS, the one major remaining rival to the annual juggernaut of Vanity Fair's editor, Graydon Carter.</p>
        <p>''Last year there were too many people coming in'' at his after-party, said Elton John, wearing shiny Yohji Yamamoto pants with a stripe down the side. ''We weren't making any extra money,'' he added, ''and it was a lot more hard work for the people involved.'' (Tickets for his after-party cost less than the dinner.)</p>
        <p>Instead, this year he held a dinner during the awards and a post-Oscars performance with the British crooner James Blunt, and, by midnight, here he was at Mr. Carter's do. Like Mr. Scorsese, Ellen DeGeneres was breathing her own sigh of relief, but for different reasons. Her first gig as Oscar host was over, and she had survived. ''For about three hours I couldn't breathe,'' she said, as Sacha Baron Cohen listened with interest.</p>
        <p>''It was completely an out-of-body experience,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Around the room, plenty of people were giving her high marks. James Taylor was one of them. ''You know, no home runs, but she had some good, solid moments. They would do well to have her back again.''</p>
        <p>In the back of the room, a power huddle had gathered around an L-shape couch. Once upon a time this would have been the spot for Tom Cruise and Nicole Kidman, with the publicist Pat Kingsley protectively perched on the edge. This time the reigning queen bee was Oprah Winfrey, surrounded by Oprahphiles, including John Travolta and Kelly Preston.</p>
        <p>But in a celebrity-besotted culture like this one, some of the most amazing moments happen when the famous are unexpectedly approached by the plebian. At the annual pre-Oscars luncheon thrown on Saturday by Diane von Furstenberg and Barry Diller on their lawn, a fashion executive could not resist the opportunity to talk to Shirley MacLaine, sitting at a picnic table in a big leather jacket while her brother, Warren Beatty, made the rounds.</p>
        <p>''I think you're great,'' the executive said.</p>
        <p>''You have good taste,'' Ms. MacLaine replied. ''Can you get me some dessert?''</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 1, 2007, Thursday  Because of an editing error, an article in The Arts on Tuesday about the Vanity Fair party after the Academy Awards ceremony carried an erroneous dateline and misidentified the site of Morton's restaurant, where the party was held. The article was reported from West Hollywood, where Morton's is located -- not from Beverly Hills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 1, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in The Arts on Tuesday about the Vanity Fair party after the Academy Awards ceremony carried an erroneous dateline and misidentified the site of Morton's restaurant, where the party was held. The article was reported from West Hollywood, where Morton's is located -- not from Beverly Hills.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
