<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe Sets Ambitious Limits on Greenhouse Gases, and Challenges Others to Match It</title>
    <meta content="10europe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/10/world/europe/10europe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1831789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bilefsky, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkel, Angela (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DB1331F933A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe Sets Ambitious Limits on Greenhouse Gases, and Challenges Others to Match It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europe Sets Ambitious Limits on Greenhouse Gases</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BILEFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bilefsky, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, March 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union approves compromise agreement that would make Europe world's leader in fight against climate change but would also allow some of Europe's most polluting countries to limit their environmental goals; Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany calls on US, China and India to follow European Union's commitment to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 20 percent from 1990 levels by year 2020; says bloc's 27 members would commit to 30 percent reduction if other nations followed suit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Union approved a compromise agreement on Friday that would make Europe the world's leader in the fight against climate change but would also allow some of Europe's most polluting countries to limit their environmental goals.</p>
        <p>Issuing a challenge to the United States, China and India to match European ambitions in the battle against global warming, Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany called on the world to follow the European Union's commitment to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 20 percent from 1990 levels by the year 2020. She said the bloc's 27 members would commit to a 30 percent reduction if other nations followed suit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Union approved a compromise agreement on Friday that would make Europe the world leader in the fight against climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European Union approved a compromise agreement on Friday that would make Europe the world's leader in the fight against climate change but would also allow some of Europe's most polluting countries to limit their environmental goals.</p>
        <p>Issuing a challenge to the United States, China and India to match European ambitions in the battle against global warming, Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany called on the world to follow the European Union's commitment to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 20 percent from 1990 levels by the year 2020. She said the bloc's 27 members would commit to a 30 percent reduction if other nations followed suit.</p>
        <p>The plan goes beyond the 35-nation Kyoto Protocol, which requires industrial nations to reduce the emission of global-warming gases by an average of 5 percent below 1990 levels by 2012. Major European Union economies had already committed to do better than that, promising to decrease greenhouse gases by 8 percent in that time.</p>
        <p>The accord by the European Union -- unveiled after two days of heated negotiations and hailed by President Jacques Chirac of France as ''a great moment in European history'' -- will require the bloc to derive a fifth of its energy from renewable sources like wind and solar power by 2020. Renewables account for less than 7 percent of the energy mix used by the Europeans.</p>
        <p>The bloc will also be required to fuel 10 percent of its cars and trucks on biofuels made from plants by 2020.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Merkel said the agreement would help the European Union become a model for the rest of the world. ''This text really gives European Union policies a new quality and will establish us as a world pioneer,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She plans to press the issue at a June summit meeting in Germany of the Group of 8 leading industrial nations, to try to push the world's biggest polluters, including the United States, China and India, to tackle climate change.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain, who has struggled to use his influence in Washington to press the Bush administration to be more diligent in fighting global warming, called it a ''groundbreaking'' deal. ''It gives Europe a clear leadership position on this crucial issue facing the world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, the agreement faces daunting challenges to transform lofty ambitions into reality, environment analysts warned. Under pressure from several countries of the former Soviet bloc, which rely heavily on cheap coal and oil for their energy and are reluctant to switch to more costly, environmentally friendly alternatives, the European Union agreed that individual targets would be allowed for each of the 27 members to meet the renewable energy goal.</p>
        <p>That means that some of the worst polluters in the fast-growing economies of East Europe will face less stringent targets than their Western European counterparts.</p>
        <p>Many of the eight former Communist nations that joined the European Union in May 2004 are far behind the rest of the union in developing renewable energy. Poland, for example, obtains more than 90 percent of its energy for heating from coal.</p>
        <p>The European Commission, which drafts legislation for the European Union, will be charged with coming up with individual countries' targets in coordination with those nations.</p>
        <p>José Manuel Barroso, the European Commission president, and Mrs. Merkel acknowledged that there would be difficult political and legal wrangling ahead, given that countries would have to approve binding renewable targets set for them by the European Commission.</p>
        <p>European Union lawyers still have to draw up the detailed rules specifying how the agreement will be enforced, but the bloc's officials said the ultimate sanction for countries that violated the targets would be prosecution at the European Court of Justice and the imposition of heavy fines.</p>
        <p>In a nod to Mr. Chirac, who lobbied hard for the European Union to include nuclear power as a noncarbon energy alternative, the agreement acknowledges the role of nuclear power, saying it will be taken into account when the European Commission determines national renewable energy targets.</p>
        <p>That will help France meet its renewable energy goals. The inclusion of nuclear energy as an energy alternative met stiff resistance from Austria, Denmark and Ireland, where nuclear energy is regarded with deep suspicion.</p>
        <p>Some European business leaders fear overly ambitious environmental goals could harm European industry.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups generally welcomed the deal. But Friends of the Earth, the Brussels- based lobbying group, called the agreement ''timid and tentative.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
