<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Regulatory Commission Downgrades Indian Point Reactor After Fire and Another Shutdown</title>
    <meta content="07power" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/nyregion/07power.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070407T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buchanan (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Entergy Nuclear Northeast</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Andrew J (County Exec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Entergy Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0D8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Regulatory Commission Downgrades Indian Point Reactor After Fire and Another Shutdown</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Regulatory Commission Downgrades Indian Point Reactor After Fire and Another Shutdown</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD; Juli S. Charkes contributed reporting from Hawthorne, N.Y.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nuclear Regulatory Commission downgrades its safety assessment of Indian Point No 3 nuclear reactor in Buchanan, NY, after transformer fire forces plant's second shutdown in a week and its fourth in last 12 months; cause of fire is not clear; no radiation was released; commission's downgrade means additional inspectors will be sent to look into cause of current shutdown and of last three; Entergy, owner of plant, is seeking to extend 40-year licenses on two operating reactors by 20 years over objections of County Exec Andrew J Spano; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission downgraded its safety assessment of the Indian Point No. 3 nuclear reactor on Friday, hours after a transformer fire forced the plant's second shutdown in a week and the fourth in the last 12 months. The commission said it would conduct extra inspections.</p>
        <p>The cause of the fire, which occurred shortly after 11 a.m. at the plant in Buchanan, N.Y., was not clear. The fire was extinguished by an automatic system and by the plant's fire brigade, which sprayed foam. No radiation was released, but people in northern Rockland County, on the other side of the Hudson River, reported smoke and ''booms.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>No radiation was released during the fire, but people in northern Rockland County, on the other side of the Hudson River, reported smoke and “booms.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission downgraded its safety assessment of the Indian Point No. 3 nuclear reactor on Friday, hours after a transformer fire forced the plant's second shutdown in a week and the fourth in the last 12 months. The commission said it would conduct extra inspections.</p>
        <p>The cause of the fire, which occurred shortly after 11 a.m. at the plant in Buchanan, N.Y., was not clear. The fire was extinguished by an automatic system and by the plant's fire brigade, which sprayed foam. No radiation was released, but people in northern Rockland County, on the other side of the Hudson River, reported smoke and ''booms.''</p>
        <p>Jim Steets, a spokesman for Entergy, which owns the plant, said that operators were unsure if there had been an explosion. The booms might have been from an automatic dumping of excess steam, he said.</p>
        <p>The commission's downgraded assessment means that additional inspectors will be sent to look into the cause of the current shutdown and of the last three.</p>
        <p>Indian Point is on the east bank of the Hudson, 24 miles north of the Bronx. Reactor 1 has been decommissioned; Nos. 2 and 3 produce about 10 percent of the state's electricity.</p>
        <p>The fire comes at a sensitive time for the plant. The owners are seeking to extend the 40-year licenses on the two operating reactors by 20 years, over the opposition of the Westchester County executive, Andrew J. Spano. They are also seeking to find and stop at least two leaks from spent fuel pools, which are allowing radioactive water to seep into the soil and, presumably, into the Hudson River. The plant is already subject to extra inspections because of the groundwater pollution.</p>
        <p>The commission acted on Friday because it was the plant's fourth shutdown since last July 1. The national average is fewer than one unplanned shutdown per reactor per year. ''We're going to get rigorously attacked by our opponents,'' Mr. Steets said.</p>
        <p>In fact, Susan Tolchin, Mr. Spano's chief adviser, said that while the fire did not pose an immediate threat, in light of the plant's recent operating history, ''this is a cause for concern for us.'' At a news conference, she also referred to the failure of the alarm sirens to work in a recent test. (The event on Friday was not serious enough to merit their use.) She said that the shutdowns, the sirens and the age of the plants, both of which entered service in the 1970s, ''are all reasons why County Executive Spano wants to see the plant shut down.''</p>
        <p>Studies have shown, though, that building a replacement plant and reducing demand through efficiency would be difficult and costly. In addition, New York State has joined a pact with neighboring states to reduce global warming gases from power generation, which would be much more difficult if the reactors were shut.</p>
        <p>The other operable reactor, Indian Point 2, has had three unplanned shutdowns in the last 12 months.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission ranks reactors according to 16 ''performance indicators,'' and both Indian Point plants had been ''green,'' the highest grade, in all of them, until the fire. But in the category of unplanned shutdowns per 7,000 hours of operation, Indian Point 3's grade is now ''white,'' the second-highest. The other categories are yellow and red.</p>
        <p>Seven thousand is the approximate number of hours that a well-run reactor will operate in a year. As the federal regulators have demanded improved performance, the threshold for sending in extra inspectors has declined, so that a single ''indicator'' below the top grade is now sufficient to do so.</p>
        <p>To maximize the number of hours it runs, the owners have switched Indian Point 3 to an every-other-year refueling system, and finished a refueling shutdown in record time, 24 days, on March 31. But it shut down again on April 3, before it could reach full power. In the predawn hours, it developed a problem in a pump that delivers clean, nonradioactive water to its steam generators, for heating into steam.</p>
        <p>On Friday it was still ramping up to full power when the fire hit. The company declared an ''unusual event,'' the lowest category in a four-level ranking of emergencies, at 11:43 a.m. The event was declared over about an hour later, but the fire was out before the event declaration; Mr. Steets said the operators took a few minutes to decide whether there had been an explosion, which would have moved the incident into the category of unusual event. Being unable to make a conclusive determination, they went ahead and declared the event.</p>
        <p>In Rockland County, C. J. Miller, a spokeswoman for the county executive, said that residents of Stony Point had called their local police to report smoke at 11:09 a.m., but that the county did not have any information from Entergy until an e-mail message at 11:36, and then a phone call 20 minutes after that. ''There is a repeated lag,'' she said, in what information is disseminated ''and when and to whom. If something happens, we need to act quickly.''</p>
        <p>Last July, an electrical flaw in the generator caused the plant to shut down. Then workers put metal scaffolding too close to electrical equipment and observed electric arcing, so the plant was shut. A focus of the enhanced inspection will be to see if there are any physical issues or management issues that link the shutdowns.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 7, 2007, Saturday  A brief article in the Westchester section this weekend about the shutdown of the Indian Point 3 reactor on Tuesday was printed before a fire yesterday forced the plant to close again. An article on B3 today reports on the latest developments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 7, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A brief article in the Westchester section this weekend about the shutdown of the Indian Point 3 reactor on Tuesday was printed before a fire yesterday forced the plant to close again. An article on B3 today reports on the latest developments.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
