<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Studies of 2 Alien Planets Show No Evidence of Water</title>
    <meta content="22planets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1827944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spitzer Space Telescope</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Overbye, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1DD133EF931A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Studies of 2 Alien Planets Show No Evidence of Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS OVERBYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Overbye, Dennis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Astronomers say most extensive examinations yet of atmospheres of planets orbiting other stars did not detect water; two planets were observed with Spitzer Space Telescope; results of studies are being published in Nature (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>And now the alien planet weather report: scorching, dry, dark and windy.</p>
        <p>Astronomers said yesterday that the most extensive examinations yet of the atmospheres of planets orbiting other stars was most noteworthy for what they did not see: namely water, a substance predicted by virtually all theories of planet formation, not to mention the essential ingredient for life as we know it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>And now the alien planet weather report: scorching, dry, dark and windy.</p>
        <p>Astronomers said yesterday that the most extensive examinations yet of the atmospheres of planets orbiting other stars was most noteworthy for what they did not see: namely water, a substance predicted by virtually all theories of planet formation, not to mention the essential ingredient for life as we know it.</p>
        <p>''The steam that was predicted to be there was nowhere to be found,'' said L. Jeremy Richardson of NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richardson led one of three teams that reported the results of observations of two planets with the Spitzer Space Telescope in a telephone news conference yesterday.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richardson's results are being published in Nature today. His data suggest that at least one of the planets is swaddled in high-level clouds of dark dust. ''The water could still be there,'' he said. ''We just can't see it.''</p>
        <p>Astronomers said the work was another steppingstone in the search for life elsewhere in the universe. Mark Swain at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, the leader of a second team, called it ''a dress rehearsal.''</p>
        <p>The discovery was also in keeping with the history of planets orbiting other stars, or extrasolar planets, which has been nothing but a series of surprises over the last 10 years as planetary systems out there have so far looked nothing like our own. Alan Boss, a theorist at the Carnegie Institution who was not involved in the work, said: ''This is a field where observers are leading the way. The scorecard should read, 'Observers 200, Theorists 0.' ''</p>
        <p>David Charbonneau of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, who was a member of a third group, led by Carl J. Grillmair of NASA's Spitzer Science Center at the California Institute of Technology, described the extrasolar bodies as ''blacker than any planet in the solar system.''</p>
        <p>''In a sense,'' Dr. Charbonneau said, ''we're getting our first sniffs of air from an alien world.''</p>
        <p>Both of the planets studied are so-called hot Jupiters, gas giants that circle their home stars in tight hot life-defying orbits. And both pass directly in front of their stars and then behind them, as seen from Earth. One, known as HD 209458b, with a surface temperature of about 1,500 degrees Fahrenheit, circles a Sun-like star about 150 light-years away in Pegasus at a distance of about 5 million miles every 3.6 days. (Mercury, the closest planet to our Sun, is 36 million miles from it.) Five years ago, a group led by Dr. Charbonneau using the Hubble Space Telescope detected traces of sodium in the planet's atmosphere as it was backlighted by its home star.</p>
        <p>The other planet, known equally charmingly as HD 189733b, is 62 light-years away in Vulpecula, circling a reddish star slightly smaller than the Sun every 2.2 days.</p>
        <p>The groups analyzed the planets' atmospheres by using the Spitzer Space Telescope to record their spectrum of infrared, or heat, radiation. The planets are too overwhelmed by their stars' glare to be imaged directly. But by subtracting Spitzer observations of the star when the planet was behind it from observations when the planet and star were both visible, the astronomers could obtain the spectrum of the planet itself.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richardson's group first did this for the Pegasus planet in July 2005, but analyzing the data took longer than it expected. All Spitzer data become public after a year, so Dr. Swain's group took up the analysis as well.</p>
        <p>According to theoretical models, molecules like water and carbon dioxide should have produced bumps and wiggles at characteristic wavelengths in the planets' spectrums. Instead, the spectrums were virtually flat.</p>
        <p>Sara Seager, a planetary theorist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology who was a member of Dr. Richardson's team, said the lack of such features was ''truly exciting.'' Dr. Seager explained that in so-called brown dwarfs, failed stars that are the closest thing to the hot Jupiters, water vapor dominates the spectrum.</p>
        <p>There are many ways, she said, that the water could be there but hidden from our view.</p>
        <p>One idea, which has gained some support from Dr. Richardson's analysis, is that high clouds could mask the atmosphere. Dr. Richardson's spectrum has a broad bump at a wavelength of 9.6 microns, which he says is consistent with emission from heated dust grains.</p>
        <p>Dr. Swain said he did not claim to have detected the dust feature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
