<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Something's Up With the Violets</title>
    <meta content="06wild" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/nyregion/thecity/06wild.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CENTRAL PARK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brill, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giddens, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Central Park (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7D9113EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Something's Up With the Violets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Something’s Up With the Violets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH GIDDENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Giddens, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Steve Brill, known as Wildman, who for 25 years has feasted on wild edibles and led foraging tours of New York City parks; Brill expresses alarm at unseasonably warm April weather and has increasingly peppered his tours with references to global warming; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR many New Yorkers, familiarity with nature comes mainly in the form of extravagant salads, but for Steve Brill, extravagant salads come from his familiarity with nature. He has been living off the bounty of the city's parks for 25 years, feasting on wild edibles and leading foraging tours twice a week.</p>
        <p>In Central Park alone, he has introduced more than 25,000 people to some of the 200 edible species that grow there. With his nose so close to the ground, Mr. Brill has noticed a number of drastic changes in the local flora that he contends have been wrought by climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR many New Yorkers, familiarity with nature comes mainly in the form of extravagant salads, but for Steve Brill, extravagant salads come from his familiarity with nature. He has been living off the bounty of the city’s parks for 25 years, feasting on wild edibles and leading foraging tours twice a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR many New Yorkers, familiarity with nature comes mainly in the form of extravagant salads, but for Steve Brill, extravagant salads come from his familiarity with nature. He has been living off the bounty of the city's parks for 25 years, feasting on wild edibles and leading foraging tours twice a week.</p>
        <p>In Central Park alone, he has introduced more than 25,000 people to some of the 200 edible species that grow there. With his nose so close to the ground, Mr. Brill has noticed a number of drastic changes in the local flora that he contends have been wrought by climate change.</p>
        <p>''The park,'' he said, ''is a window onto global warming.''</p>
        <p>To Mr. Brill, widely known as the Wildman, the brilliant spring sunshine is a sign of dark times. On an unseasonably warm day in early April, as he led a troop of eager home-schooled children on a tour, Mr. Brill found the premature blooming of Central Park's flowers a cause for alarm.</p>
        <p>''The violets have been coming up early,'' he said, charging through the park's back alleys and byways. ''The wild raisins are already budding. And the dandelions were flowering in February. They wouldn't have dared to do that back in the '70s.''</p>
        <p>Bald, bespectacled, bearded and pale, and decked out this day in cargo pants, sneakers and a pith helmet, Mr. Brill is as quick and spry as a bird, hopping about, diving into underbrush, tugging roots and nibbling leaves.</p>
        <p>The children followed Mr. Brill's brisk Willy Wonka-style lead, eager to touch, smell and taste every nut, root and leaf that he presented, looking on with wonder as he instructed them in the fine art of making spicebush tea and chickweed poultices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brill has always tutored his charges in the culinary and medicinal potential of the park. But in the past few years, he has increasingly peppered his tours with references to global warming.</p>
        <p>''The Pennsylvania bittercress has finished flowering, and it's usually much later,'' he said this day. ''The knotweed is up early -- thanks to global warming.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brill explained: ''It's very emotionally upsetting to me, so I do talk about it. But I want people to have a positive experience with nature that will make them take better care of the ecosystem. So I try not to nag.''</p>
        <p>The children are all too familiar with the apocalyptic warnings of climate change. ''A lot of people are going to die'' from global warming, a 9-year-old girl from Harlem announced at one point. And a 7-year-old boy from Park Slope said with a quiet lisp, ''When you use too much electricity, it kills animals.''</p>
        <p>Scientists do not believe that Central Park will be flooded by rising sea levels, or that will it be transformed into desert. But a recent report by the Union of Concerned Scientists predicts that in the absence of sharp reductions in carbon dioxide emissions, the number of 90-degree days in the city will increase to more than 70 a year from 15 by the end of this century. That's excellent news for the mosquito and, as it happens, for poison ivy.</p>
        <p>''In response to increased carbon dioxide, poison ivy grows faster, gets bigger and contains more toxins,'' Mr. Brill said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brill has been tracking these changes for some time. When he wrote a guide to identifying wild edibles in 1994, he omitted precise blooming schedules because he knew they would become obsolete.</p>
        <p>But, he added, the implications for the park's ecosystem are far more profound than a simple shift in blooming schedules.</p>
        <p>''Some species, for their fruiting or flowering or migrating, respond to temperature and some to length of daylight -- so some will shift and others won't, which messes up the synchronized predator-prey relationship, or the herbivore-fruit relationship,'' he said. ''One is ready to eat, and the other has already gone through the cycle that the first depends on.''</p>
        <p>Though mosquitoes and poison ivy may someday overrun his workplace, Mr. Brill is not among the herbivores whose diets would suffer as a result of climate change. The dandelions, for instance, which are among his favorite foods, are flourishing.</p>
        <p>''Now that the ground isn't frozen in December, the dandelions' second season is immense,'' Mr. Brill said. ''And the few minor frosts that remain just make them sweeter.''</p>
        <p>That bodes well for some of his signature dishes -- curried dandelion, dandelion fried rice -- but the boon extends beyond his kitchen. As recently as the '80s, his January tours were typically romps through heavy snow, attended by a dedicated and hardy few, but thanks to milder weather, these events are thronged with an array of curious types.</p>
        <p>''It's very good for business,'' Mr. Brill acknowledged, ''but we need a planet to live on.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CENTRAL PARK Elizabeth Giddens is a former senior editor of Harper's Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Giddens is a former senior editor of Harper's Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
