<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Uninviting Invitations</title>
    <meta content="11age" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/11/fashion/11age.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1825454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE AGE OF DISSONANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birthdays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birthdays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5DC1E3FF932A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Uninviting Invitations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Uninviting Invitations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Morris Age of Dissonance column on recent deluge of save-the-date invitations; asks if it is necessary or reasonable to expect people to reserve party date six months in advance; notes that most etiquette guides recommend six weeks; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There it is. Addressed personally to you, but not quite glamorous looking enough to be a formal invitation. What could it be? Tada! It's a ''Save the Date'' notice.</p>
        <p>For many people, those three words inspire a gnashing of teeth and soul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometime next summer, I’d like to see you. Hold that date.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There it is. Addressed personally to you, but not quite glamorous looking enough to be a formal invitation. What could it be? Tada! It's a ''Save the Date'' notice.</p>
        <p>For many people, those three words inspire a gnashing of teeth and soul.</p>
        <p>My cousin Robert is a pretty relaxed lawyer who has a great sense of humor and lives in central Vermont. But when a ''save the date'' notice arrived in his mailbox last month for a party in honor of friends this June, he became incensed. All winter he waits for summer to come so he can spend weekends on his sailboat on Lake Champlain or the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Then this piece of mail arrives.</p>
        <p>''It's invitation by intimidation,'' he said. ''Instead of notifying you about an event the normal six weeks in advance, these save-the-date people feel compelled to impose on you six months in advance. Why do they do that?''</p>
        <p>Good question. Is it a lack of confidence that one invitation isn't enough and that you need to be held down by a head's up twice? Is it the sheer amount of events in this over-programmed and overly ambitious world, all vying for the precious time of every guest? Certainly anyone on the benefit-party hit list has seen as many save-the-date notices lately as credit card bills, often with checks to be written that are just as big.</p>
        <p>At least that's for the serious purpose of raising money for good causes.</p>
        <p>But does every wedding hold as much urgency for every single guest? What about 25th anniversary parties? Fortieth birthdays? Retirements? Showers? Is every celebration now due cause for declaring by early edict that a summer weekend must be given away in addition to a gift?</p>
        <p>''I just got one for a wedding in London in June,'' said Jamee Gregory, an author, columnist and popular figure on the New York social scene. ''I already feel traumatized because I don't like to leave my garden on Long Island in June. When someone invites you that early, you can't just say you've already made plans to be in Capri at a friend's villa. It's too early for that, so it actually stops you from lying.''</p>
        <p>So how did we get into this save-the-date overdrive anyway, when the latest editions of ''Emily Post's Etiquette'' and ''Amy Vanderbilt's Complete Book of Etiquette'' still advise that even the most formal of invitations go out only six weeks in advance?</p>
        <p>Marcy Blum, a New York party planner who wrote ''Weddings for Dummies'' with Laura Fisher Kaiser, has watched these save-the-date mailings go from rare to standard in just three years. Ms. Blum thinks it's because weddings that used to take place in one afternoon or evening have expanded into full weekends, often in destinations that require advance travel booking.</p>
        <p>''If you're having a party where most of your friends and family are nearby, sending a save-the-date is preposterous,'' she said. ''On the other hand, now that people think their parties are the be all and end all of everything, what else can you expect?''</p>
        <p>Of course, there are plenty of occasions when you wouldn't want to miss an event. And there are times when getting some notice well in advance is helpful.</p>
        <p>The other day my sister-in-law, Janet, informed me that I should save a date in April 2008 for my nephew's bar mitzvah and lunch to follow at the Central Park Boathouse. I'm delighted to know about it. But where do I write it down? My diary only runs through next January. And here is another question: Given the recent global warming reports, might it be a little early to assume the facility will still be above ground at that time?</p>
        <p>''So you'll wear hip boots like they do in Venice,'' said Janet, who, by the way, once received a save-the-date for a birthday party nine months in advance.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was bizarre,'' she said. ''But hey, whatever floats your boat.''</p>
        <p>Which brings us back to my cousin Robert and his beloved sailboat. What is he going to do about the save-the-date he received for that party six months away?</p>
        <p>''My wife doesn't want to be unpleasant, so I'm going to have to go,'' he said. ''But at least now I'll have the pleasure of going with a reason to be unhappy.''</p>
        <p>Nothing like some bubbling resentment to go with your choice of salmon or chicken.</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF DISSONANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
