<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now Playing: Inconvenient Truths</title>
    <meta content="23docs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/23/movies/awardsseason/23docs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070302T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1828125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards/Academy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5D6133EF930A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now Playing: Inconvenient Truths</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Now Playing: Inconvenient Truths</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A.O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''An Inconvenient Truth'' is the name of the film favored to win the Academy Award in the documentary feature category on Sunday night. Directed by Davis Guggenheim and mainly consisting of a lecture about climate change given by Al Gore, the movie has had the highest profile and the largest box office of the five nominees, but its title could, without too much distortion, apply to any of them. For the moment, at least, one of the jobs of nonfiction filmmaking, perhaps its major responsibility, is to deliver uncomfortable news to a reluctant audience. While other documentary modes continue to flourish and cross-pollinate -- biographies of the famous and notorious; wrenching tales of individual misery; uplifting stories of success against the odds; archival excavations of history -- the Academy seems at the moment especially focused on larger problems, on public issues that won't go away no matter how fervently we might wish they would.</p>
        <p>Global warming may be the most urgent and all-encompassing of these. When Mr. Gore displays maps and graphics projecting vanished coastlines and violent weather, the scale of the catastrophe makes everything else look trivial. But if the prospect of inundated cities and melted ice caps is not your worry of choice, there is plenty of bad news from other quarters. Iraq is falling apart. America is riven by religious and cultural divisions. The Roman Catholic Church has failed to protect children from molestation by priests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“An Inconvenient Truth” is the name of the film favored to win the documentary feature Oscar on Sunday. But its name could apply to any of the nominated documentaries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''An Inconvenient Truth'' is the name of the film favored to win the Academy Award in the documentary feature category on Sunday night. Directed by Davis Guggenheim and mainly consisting of a lecture about climate change given by Al Gore, the movie has had the highest profile and the largest box office of the five nominees, but its title could, without too much distortion, apply to any of them. For the moment, at least, one of the jobs of nonfiction filmmaking, perhaps its major responsibility, is to deliver uncomfortable news to a reluctant audience. While other documentary modes continue to flourish and cross-pollinate -- biographies of the famous and notorious; wrenching tales of individual misery; uplifting stories of success against the odds; archival excavations of history -- the Academy seems at the moment especially focused on larger problems, on public issues that won't go away no matter how fervently we might wish they would.</p>
        <p>Global warming may be the most urgent and all-encompassing of these. When Mr. Gore displays maps and graphics projecting vanished coastlines and violent weather, the scale of the catastrophe makes everything else look trivial. But if the prospect of inundated cities and melted ice caps is not your worry of choice, there is plenty of bad news from other quarters. Iraq is falling apart. America is riven by religious and cultural divisions. The Roman Catholic Church has failed to protect children from molestation by priests.</p>
        <p>The Iraq situation is observed in Laura Poitras's ''My Country, My Country'' and James Longley's ''Iraq in Fragments.'' Amy Berg's ''Deliver Us From Evil'' focuses on the case of an especially repellent pedophile priest. And ''Jesus Camp,'' directed by Heidi Ewing and Rachel Grady, looks with fascination (and alarm) at a politically charged, militant strain of American evangelical Christianity.</p>
        <p>None of the stories these films tell are, strictly speaking, news. Movies, which take a long time to make and reach their audience over a period of weeks and months rather than hours or days, do not score many scoops. And it does not take any great sociological expertise to suppose that much of the audience for the five nominated documentaries will have at least some knowledge of their subjects going in. The fissures dividing Sunni, Shiites and Kurds in Iraq -- and their violent intensification since the United States invasion four years ago -- are by now familiar to American newspaper readers, as are the sex scandals in the Roman Catholic church, the rise of religious conservatism and the long-term danger posed by carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, the audience for these movies is likely to have opinions on such matters more or less congruent with the point of view -- implicit or overt -- of the filmmakers. And there probably aren't too many conservatives among Academy voters. Liberal bias? Preaching to the choir? Maybe so. It is a fact of our cultural life -- noted with all due qualifications and exceptions -- that documentary filmmaking tilts leftward, much as cable news and AM talk radio skew right. But to take this statement of the obvious as a reason to dismiss or discount the work of committed and serious filmmakers is not only to miss the complexities of that work, but also to refuse the possibility of serious conversation.</p>
        <p>As a form of visual journalism, documentary filmmaking has more often, especially in recent years, inclined toward advocacy and argument rather than neutrality. The apparent objectivity of the filmed image -- the deeply ingrained assumption that the camera does not lie -- is both a powerful polemical weapon and a source of internal tension. Sometimes, that is, the pictures will be selected and arranged in support of the argument. But at other times, the particularity of what we see on screen -- the unrehearsed, captured moments of other lives -- will bring us face to face with a reality deeper than politics or ideology.</p>
        <p>Maybe because public discussion of the Iraq war has been, since before it began, so thoroughly politicized, the conflict has inspired an unusual number of films that pointedly refrain from overt position taking. Over here, opinions -- steadfast or changeable, coherent or self-contradictory -- proliferate like weeds. But an intimate acquaintance with the facts of daily life in Iraq, of the kind offered in ''Iraq in Fragments'' and ''My Country, My Country,'' is more likely to increase confusion than to bring decisive clarity. And that is very much the point of these films and others like them, including Michael Tucker and Petra Epperlein's ''Gunner Palace'' (2005) and ''The War Tapes,'' directed by Deborah Scranton and released last year.</p>
        <p>''Iraq in Fragments'' and ''My Country, My Country'' both adapt the impersonal, fly-on-the-wall techniques of cinéma vérité to focus attention on the lives of individual Iraqis. ''My Country, My Country'' concentrates on the experiences of a Sunni doctor in the months leading up to the January 2005 elections. His daily struggle to retain a shred of optimism in the face of proliferating frustration becomes a microcosm of Iraq's political and moral crisis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Longley's ''Iraq in Fragments'' ranges more widely -- its three sections take us from Sunni to Shia to Kurdish perspectives -- but it is similarly committed to examining the texture of daily life rather than the abstractions of ideology. It is also entrancingly, almost disturbingly beautiful, as Mr. Longley uses the grainy, smeary palette of digital video to create vivid, haunting tableaus of urban and rural Iraq.</p>
        <p>''The War Tapes,'' overlooked by the Academy (which could easily have filled out its roster of documentary feature nominees with Iraq movies alone), was one of the most formally radical films of 2006, even as Ms. Scranton's method seems, in retrospect, head-smackingly obvious. She provided members of a National Guard unit with digital cameras and edited the video they shot into a film that is raw, honest and moving. It also, fittingly enough in the age of YouTube, collapses the traditional distance between director and subject.</p>
        <p>The same might be said about Mr. Guggenheim's film, which is more commonly referred to as ''The Al Gore movie.'' Because Mr. Gore is so central to the film, and because it is not really about him, it is easy to forget, or to underestimate, the filmmaker's role. But turning the spectacle of a man talking onstage into cinema -- even a man making use of high-tech props and gadgets -- is no easy feat, and turning data into drama is Mr. Guggenheim's accomplishment as much as it is Mr. Gore's.</p>
        <p>But ''An Inconvenient Truth'' is, in the end, a case in which the message is the message. If Mr. Longley takes documentary technique to the edge of poetry, using a logic of associations and impressions rather than of argument or narrative, Mr. Guggenheim and Mr. Gore work in a more essayistic, op-ed vein. Most documentaries these days operate between these two poles, trying to balance thought and emotion, immediacy and analysis, the rational and the uncanny.</p>
        <p>''Deliver Us From Evil'' and ''Jesus Camp'' both occupy this middle ground. Ms. Berg's ''Deliver Us From Evil'' is a passionate piece of advocacy on behalf of the victims of Oliver O'Grady, who molested dozens of children in several California parishes before he was defrocked, imprisoned and deported to Ireland. But the molten core of the movie -- what makes it gripping and horrifying and queasily fascinating to watch -- lies in the extended interviews with Mr. O'Grady himself. He is a genial, almost twinkly figure, whose expressions of regret do not seem to emerge from any deep sense of remorse, and Ms. Berg, somewhat in the manner of Errol Morris, allows him to talk on camera until the truth of his character begins to emerge.</p>
        <p>And it is not a truth that is easily summarized or explained. The power of documentary depends on the fiction that the world will reveal itself to the camera in all its rough, obdurate actuality, and the practice of documentary often consists of trying to control or curtail this power, to maintain a safe distance. ''Jesus Camp,'' which travels deep into the world of a Pentecostalist retreat where children are trained to be culture warriors, includes lengthy speeches by a liberal talk show host warning of the dangers these Christians pose to democracy. Within the film, his arguments provide a kind of ideological prophylaxis, a protection against the charm, sincerity and seriousness of purpose that the children manifest, a reminder that we should find them scary rather than appealing.</p>
        <p>And maybe we should. But the real achievement of ''Jesus Camp'' is to make them, well, real. It may be strange that reminders of this kind -- that Iraqis are real; that the violation of children is real; that global warming is real -- should seem so necessary. But then again, documentary film has always held out the promise of being stranger than fiction.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 2, 2007, Friday  A picture caption in Weekend last Friday with an article about the films that won Oscar nominations for best documentary feature carried an incomplete credit. The photograph, showing a scene from one of the films, ''Iraq in Fragments,'' was also from HBO Documentary, not just from Typecast Releasing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 2, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in Weekend last Friday with an article about the films that won Oscar nominations for best documentary feature carried an incomplete credit. The photograph, showing a scene from one of the films, ''Iraq in Fragments,'' was also from HBO Documentary, not just from Typecast Releasing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
