1	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
2	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	and	CC		cc	O	
4	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
5	Koizumi	NNP	PERSON	conj	O	
6	were	VBD		ROOT	O	
7	also	RB		advmod	O	
8	to	TO		aux	O	
9	discuss	VB		xcomp	O	
10	global	JJ		amod	O	
11	warming	NN		dobj	O	
12	.	.		punct	O	
13	 	_SP			O	
1	While	IN		mark	O	
2	the	DT		det	B-ACT		1991/12/03/0491259
3	Japanese	NNPS	NORP	nsubj	I-ACT	
4	have	VBP		aux	O	
5	politely	RB		advmod	O	
6	praised	VBN		advcl	O	
7	Mr.	NNP		compound	B-CLAIM	+
8	Bush	NNP	PERSON	poss	I-CLAIM	+
9	's	POS		case	I-CLAIM	+
10	recent	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
11	plan	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
12	to	TO		aux	I-CLAIM	+
13	control	VB		acl	I-CLAIM	+
14	greenhouse	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
15	gases	NNS		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
16	as	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
17	evidence	NN		pobj	O	
18	that	IN		mark	O	
19	America	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
20	is	VBZ		acl	O	
21	committed	VBN		acomp	O	
22	to	IN		prep	O	
23	the	DT		det	O	
24	issue	NN		pobj	O	
25	,	,		punct	O	
26	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
27	have	VBP		aux	O	
28	also	RB		advmod	O	
29	made	VBN		ROOT	O	
30	clear	JJ		ccomp	O	
31	their	PRP$		poss	O	
32	hope	NN		nsubj	O	
33	that	IN		mark	O	
34	the	DT	GPE	det	O	
35	United	NNP	GPE	compound	B-CLAIM	+
36	States	NNP	GPE	nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
37	will	MD		aux	I-CLAIM	+
38	return	VB		acl	I-CLAIM	+
39	to	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
40	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
41	treaty	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
42	,	,		punct	O	
43	negotiated	VBN		acl	I-CLAIM	+
44	in	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
45	Kyoto	NNP	GPE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
46	,	,		punct	O	
47	with	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
48	other	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
49	industrialized	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
50	nations	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
51	.	.		punct	O	
1	A	DT		det	O	
2	group	NN		nsubj	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	of	IN		prep	O	
4	about	RB	CARDINAL	advmod	O	
5	50	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	B-ACT	
6	Japanese	JJ	NORP	amod	I-ACT	
7	and	CC		cc	I-ACT	
8	American	JJ	NORP	conj	I-ACT	
9	demonstrators	NNS		pobj	I-ACT	
10	protested	VBD		ROOT	O	
11	Mr.	NNP		compound	B-CLAIM	-
12	Bush	NNP	PERSON	poss	I-CLAIM	-
13	's	POS		case	I-CLAIM	-
14	environmental	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	-
15	policies	NNS		dobj	I-CLAIM	-
16	near	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	-
17	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
18	American	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
19	Embassy	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
20	in	IN		prep	O	
21	Tokyo	NNP	GPE	pobj	O	
22	on	IN		prep	O	
23	Sunday	NNP	DATE	pobj	O	
24	,	,		punct	O	
25	shortly	RB		advmod	O	
26	before	IN		mark	O	
27	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
28	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
29	arrived	VBD		advcl	O	
30	.	.		punct	O	
1	This	DT	TIME	det	O	
2	morning	NN	TIME	npadvmod	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	a	DT		det	O	
5	robust	RB		advmod	O	
6	-	HYPH		punct	O	
7	looking	VBG		amod	O	
8	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
9	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
10	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
11	that	IN		mark	O	
12	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
13	felt	VBD		ccomp	O	
14	'	``		punct	O	
15	'	``		punct	O	
16	great	JJ		acomp	O	
17	'	''		punct	O	
18	'	''		punct	O	
19	as	IN		mark	O	
20	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
21	began	VBD		advcl	O	
22	his	PRP$	DATE	poss	O	
23	day	NN	DATE	dobj	O	
24	with	IN		prep	O	
25	a	DT		det	O	
26	trip	NN		pobj	O	
27	to	IN		prep	O	
28	Meiji	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
29	Jingu	NNP	PERSON	pobj	O	
30	,	,		punct	O	
31	a	DT		det	O	
32	Shinto	NNP	GPE	compound	O	
33	shrine	NN		appos	O	
34	.	.		punct	O	
1	He	PRP		nsubjpass	O	
2	and	CC		cc	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	Laura	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
4	Bush	NNP	PERSON	conj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	who	WP		nsubj	O	
7	held	VBD		relcl	O	
8	hands	NNS		dobj	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	were	VBD		auxpass	O	
11	accompanied	VBN		ROOT	O	
12	by	IN		agent	O	
13	a	DT		det	O	
14	chief	JJ		amod	O	
15	priest	NN		pobj	O	
16	of	IN		prep	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	shrine	NN		pobj	O	
19	,	,		punct	O	
20	dressed	VBN		acl	O	
21	in	IN		prep	O	
22	full	JJ		amod	O	
23	-	HYPH		punct	O	
24	length	NN		compound	O	
25	cream	NN		nmod	O	
26	-	HYPH		punct	O	
27	colored	VBN		amod	O	
28	silk	NN		pobj	O	
29	.	.		punct	O	
1	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
2	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	spent	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	about	RB	TIME	advmod	O	
5	10	CD	TIME	nummod	O	
6	minutes	NNS	TIME	dobj	O	
7	inside	IN		prep	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	shrine	NN		pobj	O	
10	,	,		punct	O	
11	then	RB		advmod	O	
12	signed	VBD		dep	O	
13	a	DT		det	O	
14	guest	NN		compound	O	
15	book	NN		dobj	O	
16	.	.		punct	O	
1	From	IN		prep	O	
2	there	RB		pcomp	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
4	left	VBD		ROOT	O	
5	for	IN		prep	O	
6	a	DT		det	O	
7	display	NN		pobj	O	
8	of	IN		prep	O	
9	yabusame	NN		pobj	O	
10	,	,		punct	O	
11	or	CC		cc	O	
12	archery	NN		conj	O	
13	from	IN		prep	O	
14	horses	NNS		pobj	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	an	DT		det	O	
17	ancient	JJ		amod	O	
18	Japanese	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
19	religious	JJ		amod	O	
20	practice	NN		appos	O	
21	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	a	DT		det	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	large	JJ		amod	O	
4	field	NN		pobj	O	
5	near	IN		prep	O	
6	the	DT		det	O	
7	shrine	NN		pobj	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
10	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
11	sat	VBD		ROOT	O	
12	next	RB		advmod	O	
13	to	IN		prep	O	
14	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
15	Koizumi	NNP	PERSON	pobj	O	
16	and	CC		cc	O	
17	watched	VBD		conj	O	
18	as	IN		mark	O	
19	horsemen	NNS		nsubj	O	
20	rode	VBD		advcl	O	
21	by	IN		prep	O	
22	at	IN		prep	O	
23	a	DT		det	O	
24	breakneck	NN		compound	O	
25	gallop	NN		pobj	O	
26	and	CC		cc	O	
27	shot	NN		conj	O	
28	arrows	NNS		dobj	O	
29	into	IN		prep	O	
30	a	DT		det	O	
31	small	JJ		amod	O	
32	clay	NN		compound	O	
33	target	NN		pobj	O	
34	.	.		punct	O	
35	''	''		punct	O	
1	Oh	UH		intj	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	yeah	UH		ROOT	O	
4	!	.		punct	O	
5	'	''		punct	O	
6	'	''		punct	O	
1	the	DT		det	O	
2	president	NNP		nsubj	O		1991/12/03/0491259
3	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	when	WRB		advmod	O	
5	one	CD		nummod	O	
6	horseman	NN		nsubj	O	
7	hit	VBD		advcl	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	target	NN		dobj	O	
10	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	White	NNP	ORG	compound	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	House	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
4	statement	NN		nsubj	O	
5	on	IN		prep	O	
6	climate	NN		compound	O	
7	change	NN		pobj	O	
8	read	VBD		ROOT	O	
9	:	:		punct	O	
10	''	''		punct	O	
1	President	NNP		compound	O	
2	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	announced	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	today	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
5	that	IN		mark	O	
6	the	DT	GPE	det	B-ACT	
7	United	NNP	GPE	compound	I-ACT	
8	States	NNP	GPE	nsubj	I-ACT	
9	has	VBZ		aux	O	
10	agreed	VBN		ccomp	O	
11	with	IN		prep	O	
12	other	JJ		amod	O	
13	industrialized	VBN		amod	O	
14	nations	NNS		pobj	O	
15	that	IN		mark	O	
16	stabilization	NN		nsubjpass	B-CLAIM	+
17	of	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
18	carbon	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
19	dioxide	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
20	emissions	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
21	should	MD		aux	I-CLAIM	+
22	be	VB		auxpass	I-CLAIM	+
23	achieved	VBN		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
24	as	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
25	soon	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
26	as	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
27	possible	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
28	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT	GPE	det	O	
2	United	NNP	GPE	compound	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	States	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
4	also	RB		advmod	O	
5	agreed	VBD		ROOT	O	
6	that	IN		mark	O	
7	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
8	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
9	timely	JJ		acomp	O	
10	to	TO		aux	O	
11	investigate	VB		xcomp	O	
12	quantitative	JJ		amod	O	
13	targets	NNS		dobj	O	
14	to	TO		aux	O	
15	limit	VB		advcl	O	
16	or	CC		cc	O	
17	reduce	VB		conj	O	
18	carbon	NN		compound	O	
19	dioxide	NN		compound	O	
20	emissions	NNS		dobj	O	
21	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	That	DT		nsubj	O	
4	was	VBD		ROOT	O	
5	Nov.	NNP	DATE	attr	O	
6	7	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
7	,	,	DATE	punct	O	
8	1989	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	one	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
11	year	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
12	after	IN		mark	O	
13	a	DT		det	O	
14	global	JJ		amod	O	
15	heat	NN		compound	O	
16	wave	NN		nsubj	O	
17	made	VBD		advcl	O	
18	the	DT		det	O	
19	environment	NN		nsubj	O	
20	a	DT		det	O	
21	top	JJ		amod	O	
22	political	JJ		amod	O	
23	issue	NN		ccomp	O	
24	and	CC		cc	O	
25	raised	VBD		conj	O	
26	the	DT		det	O	
27	prospect	NN		dobj	O	
28	that	IN		mark	O	
29	people	NNS		nsubj	O	
30	might	MD		aux	O	
31	be	VB		aux	O	
32	affecting	VBG		acl	O	
33	the	DT		det	O	
34	climate	NN		dobj	O	
35	by	IN		prep	O	
36	adding	VBG		pcomp	O	
37	carbon	NN		compound	O	
38	dioxide	NN		dobj	O	
39	and	CC		cc	O	
40	other	JJ		amod	O	
41	heat	NN		npadvmod	O	
42	-	HYPH		punct	O	
43	trapping	VBG		amod	O	
44	gases	NNS		conj	O	
45	to	IN		prep	O	
46	the	DT		det	O	
47	air	NN		pobj	O	
48	,	,		punct	O	
49	warming	VBG		conj	O	
50	the	DT		det	O	
51	planet	NN		dobj	O	
52	as	IN		mark	O	
53	if	IN		mark	O	
54	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
55	were	VBD		advcl	O	
56	inside	IN		prep	O	
57	a	DT		det	O	
58	greenhouse	NN		pobj	O	
59	.	.		punct	O	
1	Twelve	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
2	years	NNS	DATE	npadvmod	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	later	RB	DATE	advmod	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	under	IN		prep	O	
6	a	DT		det	O	
7	new	JJ		amod	O	
8	President	NNP		compound	B-ACT	
9	Bush	NNP	PERSON	pobj	I-ACT	
10	,	,		punct	O	
11	the	DT		det	O	
12	urgency	NN		nsubj	B-CLAIM	-
13	has	VBZ		aux	O	
14	evaporated	VBN		ROOT	O	
15	.	.		punct	O	
1	On	IN		prep	O	
2	Feb.	NNP	DATE	pobj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	14	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	president	NN		nsubj	O	
6	articulated	VBD		ROOT	O	
7	a	DT		det	O	
8	new	JJ		amod	O	
9	approach	NN		dobj	O	
10	to	IN		prep	O	
11	what	WP		nsubj	O	
12	has	VBZ		aux	O	
13	become	VBN		pcomp	O	
14	a	DT		det	O	
15	lingering	NN		amod	O	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	complicated	JJ		amod	O	
18	,	,		punct	O	
19	politically	RB		advmod	O	
20	charged	VBN		amod	O	
21	scientific	JJ		amod	O	
22	issue	NN		attr	O	
23	.	.		punct	O	
1	It	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	relies	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	on	IN		prep	O	
4	voluntary	JJ		amod	O	
5	efforts	NNS		pobj	O	
6	to	TO		aux	O	
7	slow	VB		acl	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	but	CC		cc	O	
10	not	RB		neg	O	
11	halt	VB		conj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	the	DT		det	O	
14	growth	NN		npadvmod	O	
15	in	IN		prep	O	
16	emissions	NNS		pobj	O	
17	of	IN		prep	O	
18	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
19	gases	NNS		pobj	O	
20	.	.		punct	O	
1	Progress	NN		nsubj	O	
2	is	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	to	TO		aux	O	
4	be	VB		auxpass	O	
5	measured	VBN		xcomp	O	
6	by	IN		agent	O	
7	tracking	VBG		pcomp	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	growth	NN		dobj	O	
10	of	IN		prep	O	
11	emissions	NNS		pobj	O	
12	relative	JJ		advmod	O	
13	to	IN		prep	O	
14	the	DT		det	O	
15	growth	NN		pobj	O	
16	of	IN		prep	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	economy	NN		pobj	O	
19	.	.		punct	O	
1	For	IN		prep	O	
2	nearly	RB	DATE	advmod	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	a	DT	DATE	nummod	O	
4	year	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	the	DT		det	O	
7	president	NN		nsubj	O	
8	has	VBZ		aux	O	
9	been	VBN		aux	O	
10	saying	VBG		ROOT	O	
11	there	EX		expl	O	
12	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
13	no	DT		det	O	
14	scientific	JJ		amod	O	
15	justification	NN		attr	O	
16	for	IN		prep	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	specific	JJ		amod	O	
19	emissions	NNS		compound	O	
20	targets	NNS		pobj	O	
21	set	VBN		acl	O	
22	forth	RP		prt	O	
23	in	IN		prep	O	
24	the	DT	LAW	det	O	
25	Kyoto	NNP	LAW	compound	O	
26	Protocol	NNP	LAW	pobj	O	
27	,	,		punct	O	
28	the	DT		det	O	
29	climate	NN		compound	O	
30	treaty	NN		attr	O	
31	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
32	would	MD		aux	O	
33	require	VB		relcl	O	
34	participating	VBG		xcomp	O	
35	industrialized	VBN		amod	O	
36	countries	NNS		dobj	O	
37	to	TO		aux	O	
38	cut	VB		xcomp	O	
39	emissions	NNS		dobj	O	
40	by	IN		prep	O	
41	2012	CD	DATE	pobj	O	
42	below	IN		prep	O	
43	their	PRP$		poss	O	
44	level	NN		pobj	O	
45	of	IN		prep	O	
46	1990	CD	DATE	pobj	O	
47	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	administration	NN		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	says	VBZ		ROOT	O	
4	that	IN		mark	O	
5	when	WRB		advmod	O	
6	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
7	comes	VBZ		advcl	O	
8	to	IN		prep	O	
9	carbon	NN		compound	O	
10	dioxide	NN		pobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	the	DT		det	O	
13	main	JJ		amod	O	
14	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
15	gas	NN		nsubj	O	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	no	DT		det	O	
18	one	NN		nsubj	O	
19	has	VBZ		aux	O	
20	yet	RB		advmod	O	
21	determined	VBN		ccomp	O	
22	how	WRB		advmod	O	
23	much	JJ		nsubj	O	
24	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
25	too	RB		advmod	O	
26	much	JJ		acomp	O	
27	.	.		punct	O	
1	But	CC		cc	O	
2	after	IN		prep	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	analyzing	VBG		pcomp	O	
4	details	NNS		dobj	O	
5	of	IN		prep	O	
6	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
7	Bush	NNP	PERSON	poss	O	
8	's	POS		case	O	
9	new	JJ		amod	O	
10	plan	NN		pobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	many	JJ		amod	O	
13	scientists	NNS		nsubj	B-ACT	
14	and	CC		cc	I-ACT	
15	economists	NNS		conj	I-ACT	
16	who	WP		nsubj	I-ACT	
17	study	VBP		relcl	O	
18	climate	NN		compound	O	
19	data	NNS		dobj	O	
20	and	CC		cc	O	
21	policy	NN		conj	O	
22	say	VBP		ROOT	O	
23	the	DT		det	O	
24	scientific	JJ		amod	B-CLAIM	+
25	ambiguity	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
26	that	IN		mark	I-CLAIM	+
27	the	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
28	administration	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
29	used	VBD		acl	I-CLAIM	+
30	to	TO		aux	I-CLAIM	+
31	justify	VB		xcomp	I-CLAIM	+
32	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
33	limited	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
34	response	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
35	certainly	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
36	exists	VBZ		acl	I-CLAIM	+
37	,	,		punct	O	
38	but	CC		cc	I-CLAIM	+
39	cuts	VBZ		conj	O	
40	both	DT		det	O	
41	ways	NNS		npadvmod	O	
42	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	``		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	What	WP		dobj	O	
4	people	NNS		nsubj	O	
5	sometimes	RB		advmod	O	
6	forget	VBP		csubj	O	
7	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
8	that	IN		mark	O	
9	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	+
10	uncertainty	NN		nsubjpass	I-CLAIM	+
11	in	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
12	the	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
13	science	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
14	is	VBZ		auxpass	I-CLAIM	+
15	double	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
16	-	HYPH		punct	I-CLAIM	+
17	edged	JJ		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
18	,	,		punct	O	
19	'	''		punct	O	
20	'	''		punct	O	
21	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
22	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
23	Ronald	NNP	PERSON	compound	B-ACT	
24	G.	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-ACT	
25	Prinn	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	I-ACT	
26	,	,		punct	O	
27	the	DT		det	O	
28	director	NN		appos	O	
29	of	IN		prep	O	
30	the	DT		det	O	
31	department	NNP		pobj	O	
32	of	IN		prep	O	
33	earth	NNP		pobj	O	
34	,	,		punct	O	
35	atmospheric	JJ		amod	O	
36	and	CC		cc	O	
37	planetary	JJ		conj	O	
38	sciences	NNS		appos	O	
39	at	IN		prep	O	
40	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
41	Massachusetts	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
42	Institute	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
43	of	IN	ORG	prep	O	
44	Technology	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
45	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	``		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	In	IN		prep	O	
4	our	PRP$		poss	O	
5	own	JJ		amod	O	
6	studies	NNS		pobj	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
9	estimate	VBP		ccomp	O	
10	about	IN		prep	O	
11	a	DT		det	O	
12	chance	NN		pobj	O	
13	in	IN		prep	O	
14	20	CD	CARDINAL	pobj	O	
15	that	IN		mark	O	
16	the	DT		det	O	
17	warming	NN		nsubj	O	
18	in	IN		prep	O	
19	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
20	next	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
21	100	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
22	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
23	will	MD		aux	O	
24	exceed	VB		acl	O	
25	eight	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
26	degrees	NNS		dobj	O	
27	Fahrenheit	JJ	GPE	appos	O	
28	,	,		punct	O	
29	'	''		punct	O	
30	'	''		punct	O	
31	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
32	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
33	.	.		punct	O	
34	''	''		punct	O	
1	There	EX		expl	O	
2	's	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	no	DT		det	O	
4	doubt	NN		attr	O	
5	in	IN		prep	O	
6	my	PRP$		poss	O	
7	mind	NN		pobj	O	
8	that	IN		mark	O	
9	eight	CD	QUANTITY	nummod	O	
10	degrees	NNS	QUANTITY	nsubj	O	
11	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
12	something	NN		attr	O	
13	to	TO		aux	O	
14	deeply	RB		advmod	O	
15	worry	VB		relcl	O	
16	about	IN		prep	O	
17	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	target	NN		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	set	VBN		acl	O	
4	by	IN		agent	O	
5	the	DT		det	O	
6	president	NN		poss	O	
7	's	POS		case	O	
8	policy	NN		pobj	O	
9	to	IN		prep	O	
10	me	PRP		pobj	O	
11	looks	VBZ		ROOT	O	
12	inadequate	JJ		acomp	O	
13	in	IN		prep	O	
14	the	DT		det	O	
15	face	NN		pobj	O	
16	of	IN		prep	O	
17	that	DT		det	O	
18	risk	NN		pobj	O	
19	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	Under	IN		ROOT	O	
1	the	DT		det	O	
2	administration	NN		poss	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	's	POS		case	O	
4	plan	NN		nsubj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	carbon	NN		compound	O	
7	dioxide	NN		compound	O	
8	emissions	NNS		nsubj	O	
9	would	MD		aux	O	
10	rise	VB		ROOT	O	
11	about	RB	PERCENT	advmod	O	
12	14	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
13	percent	NN	PERCENT	npadvmod	O	
14	over	IN		prep	O	
15	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
16	next	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
17	decade	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
18	--	:		punct	O	
19	the	DT		det	O	
20	same	JJ		amod	O	
21	increase	NN		npadvmod	O	
22	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
23	took	VBD		relcl	O	
24	place	NN		dobj	O	
25	over	IN		prep	O	
26	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
27	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
28	decade	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
29	.	.		punct	O	
30	''	''		punct	O	
1	Ca	MD		aux	O	
2	n't	RB		neg	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
4	do	VB		ROOT	O	
5	maybe	RB		advmod	O	
6	twice	RB		advmod	O	
7	what	WP		dobj	O	
8	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
9	did	VBD		advcl	O	
10	in	IN		prep	O	
11	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
12	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
13	10	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
14	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
15	?	.		punct	O	
16	'	''		punct	O	
17	'	''		punct	O	
1	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
2	Prinn	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	B-ACT		1995/01/17/0737418
3	asked	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	suggesting	VBG		advcl	O	
6	that	IN		mark	O	
7	the	DT	ORG	det	B-CLAIM	+
8	White	NNP	ORG	compound	I-CLAIM	+
9	House	NNP	ORG	nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
10	should	MD		aux	I-CLAIM	+
11	move	VB		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
12	more	RBR		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
13	aggressively	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
14	against	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
15	emissions	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
16	.	.		punct	O	
17	''	''		punct	O	
1	Then	RB		advmod	O	
2	you	PRP		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	'd	MD		aux	O	
4	have	VB		ROOT	O	
5	much	RB		advmod	O	
6	more	JJR		dobj	O	
7	of	IN		prep	O	
8	a	DT		det	O	
9	chance	NN		pobj	O	
10	of	IN		prep	O	
11	real	JJ		amod	O	
12	reductions	NNS		pobj	O	
13	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	Moreover	RB		advmod	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	many	JJ		amod	O	
6	climate	NN		compound	O	
7	experts	NNS		nsubj	O	
8	said	VBD		parataxis	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	rising	VBG		csubj	B-CLAIM	+
11	productivity	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
12	and	CC		cc	I-CLAIM	+
13	energy	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
14	efficiency	NN		conj	I-CLAIM	+
15	have	VBP		aux	I-CLAIM	+
16	been	VBN		aux	I-CLAIM	+
17	slowing	VBG		ROOT	I-CLAIM	+
18	the	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
19	growth	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
20	of	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
21	emissions	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
22	compared	VBN		prep	O	
23	with	IN		prep	O	
24	economic	JJ		amod	O	
25	growth	NN		pobj	O	
26	for	IN		prep	O	
27	more	JJR	DATE	amod	O	
28	than	IN	DATE	quantmod	O	
29	a	DT	DATE	nummod	O	
30	decade	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
31	--	:		punct	O	
32	at	IN		prep	O	
33	the	DT		det	O	
34	same	JJ		amod	O	
35	pace	NN		pobj	O	
36	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
37	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
38	is	VBZ		aux	B-ACT	
39	proposing	VBG		relcl	O	
40	.	.		punct	O	
1	Simply	RB		advmod	O	
2	continuing	VBG		csubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	this	DT		det	O	
4	course	NN		dobj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	many	JJ		nsubj	O	
7	said	VBD		parataxis	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	is	VBZ		ROOT	O	
10	inadequate	JJ		acomp	O	
11	to	TO		aux	O	
12	promote	VB		xcomp	O	
13	the	DT		det	O	
14	changes	NNS		dobj	O	
15	needed	VBN		acl	O	
16	to	TO		aux	O	
17	flatten	VB		advcl	O	
18	the	DT		det	O	
19	curve	NN		dobj	O	
20	of	IN		prep	O	
21	growth	NN		pobj	O	
22	--	:		punct	O	
23	and	CC		cc	O	
24	eventually	RB		advmod	O	
25	turn	VB		conj	O	
26	it	PRP		dobj	O	
27	downward	RB		advmod	O	
28	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	debate	NN		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	over	IN		prep	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	new	JJ		amod	O	
6	plan	NN		pobj	O	
7	should	MD		aux	O	
8	reach	VB		ROOT	O	
9	Capitol	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
10	Hill	NNP	ORG	dobj	O	
11	this	DT	DATE	det	O	
12	week	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
13	,	,		punct	O	
14	when	WRB		advmod	O	
15	the	DT		det	O	
16	Senate	NNP	ORG	nsubjpass	O	
17	is	VBZ		auxpass	O	
18	expected	VBN		relcl	O	
19	to	TO		aux	O	
20	consider	VB		xcomp	O	
21	an	DT		det	O	
22	energy	NN		compound	O	
23	bill	NN		dobj	O	
24	with	IN		prep	O	
25	contentious	JJ		amod	O	
26	provisions	NNS		pobj	O	
27	on	IN		prep	O	
28	oil	NN		compound	O	
29	drilling	NN		pobj	O	
30	,	,		punct	O	
31	gas	NN		compound	O	
32	-	HYPH		punct	O	
33	mileage	NN		compound	O	
34	standards	NNS		conj	O	
35	and	CC		cc	O	
36	other	JJ		amod	O	
37	policies	NNS		conj	O	
38	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
39	may	MD		aux	O	
40	affect	VB		relcl	O	
41	emissions	NNS		compound	O	
42	rates	NNS		dobj	O	
43	.	.		punct	O	
1	Critics	NNS		nsubj	O	
2	of	IN		prep	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	-
4	Bush	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-CLAIM	-
5	approach	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	-
6	include	VBP		ROOT	O	
7	several	JJ		amod	O	
8	members	NNS		dobj	B-ACT	
9	of	IN		prep	I-ACT	
10	a	DT		det	I-ACT	
11	scientific	JJ		amod	I-ACT	
12	committee	NN		pobj	I-ACT	
13	assembled	VBN		acl	I-ACT	
14	last	JJ	DATE	amod	I-ACT	
15	year	NN	DATE	npadvmod	I-ACT	
16	at	IN		prep	I-ACT	
17	the	DT		det	I-ACT	
18	behest	NN		pobj	I-ACT	
19	of	IN		prep	I-ACT	
20	the	DT	ORG	det	I-ACT	
21	White	NNP	ORG	compound	I-ACT	
22	House	NNP	ORG	pobj	I-ACT	
23	by	IN		prep	I-ACT	
24	the	DT	ORG	det	I-ACT	
25	National	NNP	ORG	compound	I-ACT	
26	Academy	NNP	ORG	pobj	I-ACT	
27	of	IN	ORG	prep	I-ACT	
28	Sciences	NNPS	ORG	pobj	I-ACT	
29	to	TO		aux	O	
30	assess	VB		advcl	O	
31	questions	NNS		dobj	O	
32	about	IN		prep	O	
33	climate	NN		compound	O	
34	change	NN		pobj	O	
35	.	.		punct	O	
1	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
2	Ralph	NNP	PERSON	compound	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	J.	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
4	Cicerone	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	chairman	NN		appos	O	
7	of	IN		prep	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	academy	NN		compound	O	
10	panel	NN		pobj	O	
11	and	CC		cc	O	
12	chancellor	NNP		conj	O	
13	of	IN		prep	O	
14	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
15	University	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
16	of	IN	ORG	prep	O	
17	California	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
18	at	IN	ORG	prep	O	
19	Irvine	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
22	the	DT		det	B-ACT	
23	Bush	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-ACT	
24	administration	NN		nsubj	I-ACT	
25	was	VBD		ccomp	O	
26	mistaken	VBN		acomp	O	
27	to	TO		aux	O	
28	view	VB		advcl	O	
29	uncertainty	NN		dobj	B-CLAIM	+
30	as	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
31	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
32	cause	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
33	for	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
34	comfort	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
35	.	.		punct	O	
1	He	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	said	VBD		ROOT	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	there	EX		expl	O	
4	was	VBD		ccomp	O	
5	no	RB		neg	O	
6	longer	RBR		advmod	O	
7	any	DT		det	O	
8	ambiguity	NN		attr	O	
9	about	IN		prep	O	
10	whether	IN		mark	O	
11	humans	NNS		nsubj	O	
12	were	VBD		pcomp	O	
13	significant	JJ		amod	O	
14	contributors	NNS		attr	O	
15	to	IN		prep	O	
16	global	JJ		amod	O	
17	warming	NN		pobj	O	
18	,	,		punct	O	
19	and	CC		cc	O	
20	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
21	noted	VBD		conj	O	
22	that	IN		mark	O	
23	in	IN		prep	O	
24	the	DT		det	O	
25	opening	NN		amod	O	
26	line	NN		pobj	O	
27	of	IN		prep	O	
28	its	PRP$		poss	O	
29	report	NN		pobj	O	
30	to	IN		prep	O	
31	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
32	White	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
33	House	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
34	,	,		punct	O	
35	the	DT		det	B-ACT	
36	panel	NN		nsubj	I-ACT	
37	stated	VBD		ccomp	O	
38	plainly	RB		advmod	O	
39	that	IN		mark	O	
40	'	``		punct	O	
41	'	``		punct	O	
42	greenhouse	NN		compound	B-CLAIM	+
43	gases	NNS		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
44	are	VBP		aux	I-CLAIM	+
45	accumulating	VBG		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
46	in	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
47	Earth	NNP	LOC	poss	I-CLAIM	+
48	's	POS		case	I-CLAIM	+
49	atmosphere	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
50	as	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
51	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
52	result	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
53	of	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
54	human	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
55	activities	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
56	,	,		punct	O	
57	causing	VBG		advcl	I-CLAIM	+
58	surface	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
59	air	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
60	temperatures	NNS		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
61	and	CC		cc	I-CLAIM	+
62	subsurface	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
63	ocean	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
64	temperatures	NNS		conj	I-CLAIM	+
65	to	TO		aux	I-CLAIM	+
66	rise	VB		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
67	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	Last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
4	week	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
7	Cicerone	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	B-ACT	
8	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
9	continued	JJ		amod	B-CLAIM	+
10	growth	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
11	in	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
12	emissions	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
13	would	MD		aux	I-CLAIM	+
14	make	VB		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
15	things	NNS		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
16	worse	JJR		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
17	.	.		punct	O	
18	''	''		punct	O	
1	This	DT		det	B-CLAIM	-
2	situation	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	-	1995/01/17/0737418
3	is	VBZ		ccomp	I-CLAIM	-
4	not	RB		neg	I-CLAIM	-
5	sustainable	JJ		acomp	I-CLAIM	-
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	and	CC		cc	O	
8	its	PRP$		poss	O	
9	trajectory	NN		nsubj	O	
10	is	VBZ		conj	O	
11	toward	IN		prep	O	
12	dangers	NNS		pobj	O	
13	,	,		punct	O	
14	'	''		punct	O	
15	'	''		punct	O	
16	he	PRP		nsubj	B-ACT	
17	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
18	,	,		punct	O	
19	adding	VBG		advcl	O	
20	that	IN		mark	O	
21	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	-
22	White	NNP	ORG	compound	I-CLAIM	-
23	House	NNP	ORG	compound	I-CLAIM	-
24	proposal	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	-
25	'	''		punct	O	
26	'	''		punct	O	
27	lacks	VBZ		ccomp	O	
28	ambition	NN		dobj	O	
29	and	CC		cc	O	
30	foresight	NN		conj	O	
31	'	''		punct	O	
32	'	''		punct	O	
1	and	CC		cc	O	
2	'	``		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	'	``		punct	O	
4	sets	VBZ		ROOT	O	
5	goals	NNS		dobj	O	
6	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
7	are	VBP		relcl	O	
8	too	RB		advmod	O	
9	timid	JJ		acomp	O	
10	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	The	DT		det	O	
4	goals	NNS		nsubj	O	
5	were	VBD		ROOT	O	
6	far	RB		advmod	O	
7	from	IN		prep	O	
8	modest	JJ		amod	O	
9	when	WRB		advmod	O	
10	Mr.	NNP		compound	B-ACT	
11	Bush	NNP	PERSON	poss	I-ACT	
12	's	POS		case	I-ACT	
13	father	NN		nsubj	I-ACT	
14	signed	VBD		advcl	I-ACT	
15	the	DT		det	O	
16	first	JJ		amod	B-CLAIM	+
17	climate	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
18	treaty	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
19	,	,		punct	O	
20	in	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
21	1992	CD	DATE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
22	.	.		punct	O	
1	Under	IN		prep	O	
2	that	DT		det	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	treaty	NN		pobj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	industrialized	JJ		amod	O	
6	nations	NNS		nsubj	O	
7	agreed	VBD		ROOT	O	
8	to	TO		aux	O	
9	strive	VB		xcomp	O	
10	to	TO		aux	O	
11	reduce	VB		xcomp	O	
12	their	PRP$		poss	O	
13	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
14	emissions	NNS		dobj	O	
15	to	IN		prep	O	
16	1990	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
17	levels	NNS		pobj	O	
18	by	IN		prep	O	
19	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
20	year	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
21	2000	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
22	.	.		punct	O	
1	Instead	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	however	RB		advmod	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	global	JJ		amod	O	
6	emissions	NNS		nsubj	O	
7	continued	VBD		ROOT	O	
8	to	TO		aux	O	
9	rise	VB		xcomp	O	
10	.	.		punct	O	
1	American	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
2	releases	NNS		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	of	IN		prep	O	
4	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
5	gases	NNS		pobj	O	
6	rose	VBD		ROOT	O	
7	more	JJR	PERCENT	amod	O	
8	than	IN	PERCENT	quantmod	O	
9	12	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
10	percent	NN	PERCENT	npadvmod	O	
11	in	IN		prep	O	
12	that	DT		det	O	
13	period	NN		pobj	O	
14	.	.		punct	O	
1	Last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
2	fall	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	most	RBS		advmod	O	
5	industrialized	JJ		amod	O	
6	nations	NNS		nsubj	O	
7	rallied	VBD		ROOT	O	
8	around	IN		prep	O	
9	a	DT		det	O	
10	new	JJ		amod	O	
11	treaty	NN		pobj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	the	DT		det	O	
14	1997	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
15	Kyoto	NNP	LAW	compound	O	
16	Protocol	NNP	LAW	appos	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	though	IN		mark	O	
19	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
20	have	VBP		advcl	O	
21	yet	RB		advmod	O	
22	to	TO		aux	O	
23	ratify	VB		xcomp	O	
24	it	PRP		dobj	O	
25	.	.		punct	O	
1	That	DT		det	O	
2	treaty	NN		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	which	WDT		dobj	O	
5	the	DT		det	B-ACT	
6	Clinton	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-ACT	
7	administration	NN		nsubj	I-ACT	
8	had	VBD		aux	O	
9	signed	VBN		relcl	O	
10	,	,		punct	O	
11	would	MD		aux	O	
12	require	VB		ROOT	B-CLAIM	+
13	participating	VBG		xcomp	I-CLAIM	+
14	industrialized	VBN		amod	I-CLAIM	+
15	countries	NNS		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
16	to	TO		aux	I-CLAIM	+
17	cut	VB		xcomp	I-CLAIM	+
18	emissions	NNS		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
19	by	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
20	2012	CD	DATE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
21	below	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
22	where	WRB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
23	they	PRP		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
24	stood	VBD		pcomp	I-CLAIM	+
25	in	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
26	1990	CD	DATE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
27	.	.		punct	O	
1	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
2	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	B-ACT		1995/01/17/0737418
3	rejected	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	-
5	Kyoto	NNP	GPE	compound	I-CLAIM	-
6	treaty	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	-
7	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
8	year	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	saying	VBG		advcl	O	
11	the	DT		det	O	
12	emissions	NNS		compound	O	
13	targets	NNS		nsubj	O	
14	were	VBD		ccomp	O	
15	not	RB		neg	O	
16	scientifically	RB		advmod	O	
17	justified	VBN		acomp	O	
18	.	.		punct	O	
1	He	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	said	VBD		ROOT	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	that	IN		mark	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	treaty	NN		nsubj	O	
6	unfairly	RB		advmod	O	
7	required	VBD		ccomp	O	
8	no	DT		det	O	
9	emissions	NNS		compound	O	
10	cuts	NNS		dobj	O	
11	of	IN		prep	O	
12	fast	RB		advmod	O	
13	-	HYPH		punct	O	
14	growing	VBG		amod	O	
15	countries	NNS		pobj	O	
16	like	IN		prep	O	
17	China	NNP	GPE	pobj	O	
18	and	CC		cc	O	
19	that	IN		mark	O	
20	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
21	would	MD		aux	O	
22	harm	VB		conj	O	
23	the	DT		det	O	
24	American	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
25	economy	NN		dobj	O	
26	.	.		punct	O	
1	Last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
2	week	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
5	Conrad	NNP	PERSON	compound	B-ACT	
6	C.	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-ACT	
7	Lautenbacher	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-ACT	
8	Jr.	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	I-ACT	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	a	DT		det	O	
11	mathematician	JJ		appos	O	
12	and	CC		cc	O	
13	retired	VBN		amod	O	
14	Navy	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
15	vice	NN		compound	O	
16	admiral	NN		conj	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	who	WP		nsubj	O	
19	is	VBZ		relcl	O	
20	the	DT		det	O	
21	under	JJ		amod	O	
22	secretary	NN		attr	O	
23	of	IN		prep	O	
24	commerce	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
25	for	IN		prep	O	
26	oceans	NNPS		pobj	O	
27	and	CC		cc	O	
28	atmosphere	NN		conj	O	
29	,	,		punct	O	
30	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
31	Mr.	NNP		compound	B-CLAIM	+
32	Bush	NNP	PERSON	poss	I-CLAIM	+
33	's	POS		case	I-CLAIM	+
34	new	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
35	plan	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
36	struck	VBD		ccomp	O	
37	a	DT		det	O	
38	reasonable	JJ		amod	O	
39	balance	NN		dobj	O	
40	between	IN		prep	O	
41	economic	JJ		amod	O	
42	and	CC		cc	O	
43	environmental	JJ		conj	O	
44	concerns	NNS		pobj	O	
45	.	.		punct	O	
46	''	''		punct	O	
1	You	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	're	VBP		aux	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	playing	VBG		ccomp	O	
4	with	IN		prep	O	
5	a	DT		det	O	
6	$	$	MONEY	quantmod	O	
7	12	CD	MONEY	compound	O	
8	trillion	CD	MONEY	nummod	O	
9	economy	NN		pobj	O	
10	here	RB		advmod	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	'	''		punct	O	
13	'	''		punct	O	
14	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
15	Lautenbacher	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
16	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
17	.	.		punct	O	
18	''	''		punct	O	
1	There	EX		expl	O	
2	's	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	such	PDT		predet	O	
4	a	DT		det	O	
5	large	JJ		amod	O	
6	connection	NN		attr	O	
7	with	IN		prep	O	
8	our	PRP$		poss	O	
9	economy	NN		pobj	O	
10	based	VBN		acl	O	
11	on	IN		prep	O	
12	what	WP		dobj	O	
13	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
14	do	VBP		pcomp	O	
15	and	CC		cc	O	
16	to	TO		prep	O	
17	what	WDT		det	O	
18	degree	NN		pcomp	O	
19	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
20	do	VBP		pcomp	O	
21	it	PRP		dobj	O	
22	that	IN		mark	O	
23	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
24	'd	MD		aux	O	
25	be	VB		ccomp	O	
26	foolish	JJ		acomp	O	
27	not	RB		neg	O	
28	to	TO		aux	O	
29	try	VB		xcomp	O	
30	to	TO		aux	O	
31	understand	VB		xcomp	O	
32	the	DT		det	O	
33	basic	JJ		amod	O	
34	processes	NNS		dobj	O	
35	better	RBR		advmod	O	
36	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	The	DT		det	O	
4	new	JJ		amod	O	
5	policy	NN		nsubj	O	
6	is	VBZ		aux	O	
7	also	RB		advmod	O	
8	attracting	VBG		ROOT	O	
9	support	NN		dobj	O	
10	from	IN		prep	O	
11	scientists	NNS		pobj	O	
12	who	WP		nsubj	O	
13	are	VBP		relcl	O	
14	skeptical	JJ		acomp	O	
15	that	IN		mark	O	
16	global	JJ		amod	O	
17	warming	NN		nsubj	O	
18	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
19	a	DT		det	O	
20	serious	JJ		amod	O	
21	long	JJ		amod	O	
22	-	HYPH		punct	O	
23	term	NN		compound	O	
24	threat	NN		attr	O	
25	.	.		punct	O	
1	More	RBR		advmod	O	
2	aggressive	JJ		amod	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	moves	NNS		nsubj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
6	say	VBP		parataxis	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	would	MD		aux	O	
9	harm	VB		ROOT	O	
10	the	DT		det	O	
11	economy	NN		nmod	O	
12	and	CC		cc	O	
13	waste	NN		conj	O	
14	resources	NNS		dobj	O	
15	that	WDT		nsubjpass	O	
16	could	MD		aux	O	
17	be	VB		auxpass	O	
18	used	VBN		relcl	O	
19	to	TO		aux	O	
20	solve	VB		xcomp	O	
21	other	JJ		amod	O	
22	problems	NNS		dobj	O	
23	.	.		punct	O	
1	Indeed	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	some	DT		det	O	
4	skeptics	NNS		nsubj	O	
5	say	VBP		ROOT	O	
6	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
7	Bush	NNP	PERSON	poss	B-ACT	
8	's	POS		case	B-ACT	
9	policy	NN		nsubj	O	
10	concedes	VBZ		ccomp	O	
11	too	RB		advmod	O	
12	much	JJ		advmod	O	
13	by	IN		prep	O	
14	even	RB		advmod	O	
15	acknowledging	VBG		pcomp	O	
16	that	IN		mark	O	
17	voluntary	JJ		amod	O	
18	changes	NNS		nsubjpass	B-CLAIM	+
19	are	VBP		auxpass	I-CLAIM	+
20	needed	VBN		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
21	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	Voluntary	JJ		ROOT	O	
1	has	VBZ		ccomp	O	
2	a	DT		det	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	nasty	JJ		amod	O	
4	habit	NN		dobj	O	
5	of	IN		prep	O	
6	turning	VBG		pcomp	O	
7	mandatory	JJ		advmod	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	'	''		punct	O	
10	'	''		punct	O	
11	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
12	S.	NNP	PERSON	compound	B-ACT	
13	Fred	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-ACT	
14	Singer	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	I-ACT	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	a	DT		det	O	
17	climatologist	NN		appos	O	
18	,	,		punct	O	
19	who	WP		nsubj	O	
20	has	VBZ		aux	O	
21	long	RB		advmod	O	
22	criticized	VBN		relcl	O	
23	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	-
24	consensus	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	-
25	view	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	-
26	on	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	-
27	warming	VBG		pobj	I-CLAIM	-
28	and	CC		cc	O	
29	who	WP		nsubj	O	
30	heads	VBZ		conj	O	
31	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
32	Science	NNP	ORG	nmod	O	
33	and	CC	ORG	cc	O	
34	Environmental	NNP	ORG	conj	O	
35	Policy	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
36	Project	NNP	ORG	dobj	O	
37	,	,		punct	O	
38	a	DT		det	O	
39	research	NN		nmod	O	
40	and	CC		cc	O	
41	advocacy	NN		conj	O	
42	group	NN		appos	O	
43	financed	VBN		acl	O	
44	by	IN		agent	O	
45	private	JJ		amod	O	
46	contributions	NNS		pobj	O	
47	.	.		punct	O	
1	Dr.	NNP		compound	B-ACT	
2	Singer	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	I-ACT		1995/01/17/0737418
3	says	VBZ		ROOT	O	
4	recent	JJ		amod	O	
5	studies	NNS		nsubj	O	
6	have	VBP		aux	O	
7	steadily	RB		advmod	O	
8	whittled	VBN		ccomp	O	
9	away	RB		advmod	O	
10	at	IN		prep	O	
11	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	-
12	direst	JJS		amod	I-CLAIM	-
13	predictions	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	-
14	for	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	-
15	warming	VBG		pobj	I-CLAIM	-
16	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	``		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	Every	DT		det	O	
4	bit	NN		nsubj	O	
5	of	IN		prep	O	
6	data	NNS		pobj	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	'	''		punct	O	
9	'	''		punct	O	
10	he	PRP		nsubj	B-ACT	
11	said	VBD		parataxis	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	'	''		punct	O	
14	'	``		punct	O	
15	seems	VBZ		ROOT	O	
16	to	TO		aux	O	
17	confirm	VB		xcomp	O	
18	that	IN		mark	O	
19	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	+
20	climate	NN		compound	I-CLAIM	+
21	sensitivity	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
22	is	VBZ		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
23	well	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
24	below	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
25	even	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
26	the	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
27	lowest	JJS		amod	I-CLAIM	+
28	value	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
29	given	VBN		acl	I-CLAIM	+
30	'	''		punct	O	
31	'	''		punct	O	
32	by	IN		agent	O	
33	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
34	Intergovernmental	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
35	Panel	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
36	on	IN	ORG	prep	O	
37	Climate	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
38	Change	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
39	,	,		punct	O	
40	an	DT		det	O	
41	international	JJ		amod	O	
42	scientific	JJ		amod	O	
43	group	NN		appos	O	
44	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
45	has	VBZ		aux	O	
46	issued	VBN		relcl	O	
47	three	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
48	assessments	NNS		dobj	O	
49	of	IN		prep	O	
50	climate	NN		compound	O	
51	science	NN		pobj	O	
52	over	IN		prep	O	
53	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
54	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
55	10	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
56	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
57	.	.		punct	O	
1	But	CC		cc	O	
2	the	DT		det	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	lead	JJ		amod	O	
4	author	NN		nsubj	O	
5	of	IN		prep	O	
6	one	CD	CARDINAL	pobj	O	
7	of	IN		prep	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	new	JJ		amod	O	
10	studies	NNS		pobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
13	James	NNP	PERSON	compound	B-ACT	
14	E.	NNP	PERSON	compound	I-ACT	
15	Hansen	NNP	PERSON	appos	I-ACT	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	director	NN		appos	O	
19	of	IN		prep	O	
20	NASA	NNP	ORG	poss	O	
21	's	POS		case	O	
22	Goddard	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
23	Institute	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
24	for	IN	ORG	prep	O	
25	Space	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
26	Studies	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
27	,	,		punct	O	
28	says	VBZ		ROOT	O	
29	there	EX		expl	O	
30	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
31	a	DT		det	O	
32	difference	NN		attr	O	
33	between	IN		prep	O	
34	refining	NN		compound	O	
35	projections	NNS		pobj	O	
36	of	IN		prep	O	
37	change	NN		pobj	O	
38	and	CC		cc	O	
39	saying	VBG		conj	B-CLAIM	-
40	global	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	-
41	warming	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	-
42	is	VBZ		ccomp	I-CLAIM	-
43	not	RB		neg	I-CLAIM	-
44	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	-
45	serious	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	-
46	problem	NN		attr	I-CLAIM	-
47	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	a	DT		det	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	paper	NN		pobj	O	
4	in	IN		prep	O	
5	a	DT		det	O	
6	recent	JJ		amod	O	
7	issue	NN		pobj	O	
8	of	IN		prep	O	
9	The	DT	ORG	det	O	
10	Proceedings	NNPS	ORG	pobj	O	
11	of	IN	ORG	prep	O	
12	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
13	National	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
14	Academy	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
15	of	IN	ORG	prep	O	
16	Sciences	NNPS	ORG	pobj	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
19	Hansen	NNP	PERSON	conj	B-ACT	
20	and	CC		cc	O	
21	a	DT		det	O	
22	Goddard	NNP	PERSON	amod	O	
23	colleague	NN		conj	O	
24	,	,		punct	O	
25	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
26	Makiko	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
27	Sato	NNP	PERSON	conj	O	
28	,	,		punct	O	
29	plotted	VBD		ROOT	O	
30	the	DT		det	O	
31	changing	VBG		amod	O	
32	concentrations	NNS		dobj	O	
33	of	IN		prep	O	
34	various	JJ		amod	O	
35	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
36	gases	NNS		pobj	O	
37	and	CC		cc	O	
38	predicted	VBD		conj	O	
39	that	IN		mark	O	
40	the	DT		det	B-CLAIM	+
41	average	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
42	global	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
43	temperature	NN		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
44	would	MD		aux	I-CLAIM	+
45	rise	VB		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
46	1.3	CD	QUANTITY	nummod	I-CLAIM	+
47	degrees	NNS	QUANTITY	dobj	I-CLAIM	+
48	over	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
49	the	DT	DATE	det	I-CLAIM	+
50	next	JJ	DATE	amod	I-CLAIM	+
51	50	CD	DATE	nummod	I-CLAIM	+
52	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
53	.	.		punct	O	
1	That	DT		nsubj	O	
2	is	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	at	IN		prep	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	low	JJ		amod	O	
6	end	NN		pobj	O	
7	of	IN		prep	O	
8	predictions	NNS		pobj	O	
9	for	IN		prep	O	
10	warming	VBG		pobj	O	
11	generated	VBN		acl	O	
12	by	IN		agent	O	
13	most	JJS		amod	O	
14	computer	NN		compound	O	
15	models	NNS		pobj	O	
16	of	IN		prep	O	
17	climate	NN		pobj	O	
18	,	,		punct	O	
19	but	CC		cc	O	
20	more	JJR		advmod	O	
21	than	IN		mark	O	
22	temperatures	NNS		nsubj	O	
23	rose	VBD		conj	O	
24	over	IN		prep	O	
25	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
26	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
27	100	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
28	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
29	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	paper	NN		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	concluded	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	that	IN		mark	O	
5	the	DT		det	O	
6	warming	VBG		compound	O	
7	trend	NN		nsubj	O	
8	was	VBD		ccomp	O	
9	likely	JJ		acomp	O	
10	to	TO		aux	O	
11	be	VB		xcomp	O	
12	substantially	RB		advmod	O	
13	slower	JJR		acomp	O	
14	than	IN		mark	O	
15	previously	RB		advmod	O	
16	thought	VBN		advcl	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	given	VBN		prep	O	
19	the	DT		det	O	
20	slowing	VBG		amod	O	
21	buildup	NN		pobj	O	
22	of	IN		prep	O	
23	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
24	gases	NNS		pobj	O	
25	other	JJ		amod	O	
26	than	IN		prep	O	
27	carbon	NN		compound	O	
28	dioxide	NN		pobj	O	
29	.	.		punct	O	
1	For	IN		prep	O	
2	example	NN		pobj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
5	Hansen	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
6	said	VBD		parataxis	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	methane	NN		nsubj	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	a	DT		det	O	
11	potent	JJ		amod	O	
12	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
13	gas	NN		appos	O	
14	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
15	was	VBD		aux	O	
16	once	RB		advmod	O	
17	rapidly	RB		advmod	O	
18	building	VBG		relcl	O	
19	in	IN		prep	O	
20	the	DT		det	O	
21	atmosphere	NN		pobj	O	
22	,	,		punct	O	
23	has	VBZ		aux	O	
24	shown	VBN		ccomp	O	
25	a	DT		det	O	
26	sharp	JJ		amod	O	
27	decline	NN		dobj	O	
28	in	IN		prep	O	
29	its	PRP$		poss	O	
30	growth	NN		compound	O	
31	rate	NN		pobj	O	
32	since	IN		prep	O	
33	1980	CD	DATE	pobj	O	
34	,	,		punct	O	
35	for	IN		prep	O	
36	reasons	NNS		pobj	O	
37	scientists	NNS		nsubj	O	
38	can	MD		aux	O	
39	not	RB		neg	O	
40	explain	VB		ROOT	O	
41	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	scientists	NNS		nsubj	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	also	RB		advmod	O	
4	calculated	VBD		ROOT	O	
5	that	IN		mark	O	
6	a	DT		det	O	
7	concerted	JJ		amod	O	
8	effort	NN		nsubj	O	
9	to	TO		aux	O	
10	raise	VB		acl	O	
11	fuel	NN		compound	O	
12	efficiency	NN		dobj	O	
13	and	CC		cc	O	
14	find	VB		conj	O	
15	ways	NNS		dobj	O	
16	to	TO		aux	O	
17	remove	VB		relcl	O	
18	carbon	NN		compound	O	
19	dioxide	NN		dobj	O	
20	from	IN		prep	O	
21	the	DT		det	O	
22	air	NN		pobj	O	
23	could	MD		aux	O	
24	well	RB		advmod	O	
25	cause	VB		ccomp	O	
26	emissions	NNS		nsubj	O	
27	to	TO		aux	O	
28	stop	VB		ccomp	O	
29	growing	VBG		xcomp	O	
30	altogether	RB		advmod	O	
31	later	RB	DATE	advmod	O	
32	in	IN	DATE	prep	O	
33	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
34	century	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
35	and	CC		cc	O	
36	,	,		punct	O	
37	eventually	RB		advmod	O	
38	,	,		punct	O	
39	to	TO		aux	O	
40	decline	VB		conj	O	
41	.	.		punct	O	
1	But	CC		cc	O	
2	over	IN		prep	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	all	DT		pobj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
6	Hansen	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	B-ACT	
7	said	VBD		parataxis	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	the	DT		det	O	
10	Goddard	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
11	analysis	NN		nsubj	O	
12	still	RB		advmod	O	
13	means	VBZ		ROOT	O	
14	that	IN		mark	O	
15	temperatures	NNS		nsubj	B-CLAIM	+
16	by	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
17	2050	CD	DATE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
18	will	MD		aux	I-CLAIM	+
19	be	VB		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
20	more	JJR	QUANTITY	amod	I-CLAIM	+
21	than	IN	QUANTITY	quantmod	I-CLAIM	+
22	two	CD	QUANTITY	nummod	I-CLAIM	+
23	degrees	NNS	QUANTITY	npadvmod	I-CLAIM	+
24	warmer	JJR		acomp	I-CLAIM	+
25	than	IN		mark	I-CLAIM	+
26	they	PRP		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
27	were	VBD		advcl	I-CLAIM	+
28	at	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
29	the	DT	DATE	det	I-CLAIM	+
30	beginning	NN	DATE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
31	of	IN	DATE	prep	I-CLAIM	+
32	the	DT	DATE	det	I-CLAIM	+
33	20th	JJ	DATE	amod	I-CLAIM	+
34	century	NN	DATE	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
35	,	,		punct	O	
36	when	WRB		advmod	O	
37	the	DT		det	O	
38	accelerating	VBG		amod	O	
39	Industrial	NNP	EVENT	compound	O	
40	Revolution	NNP	EVENT	nsubj	O	
41	began	VBD		relcl	O	
42	transforming	VBG		xcomp	O	
43	vast	JJ		amod	O	
44	stores	NNS		dobj	O	
45	of	IN		prep	O	
46	coal	NN		pobj	O	
47	and	CC		cc	O	
48	oil	NN		conj	O	
49	into	IN		prep	O	
50	carbon	NN		compound	O	
51	dioxide	NN		pobj	O	
52	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	I	PRP		nsubj	O	
4	could	MD		aux	O	
5	see	VB		ccomp	O	
6	keeping	VBG		xcomp	O	
7	the	DT		det	O	
8	warming	NN		dobj	O	
9	relatively	RB		advmod	O	
10	moderate	JJ		oprd	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	but	CC		cc	O	
13	I	PRP		nsubj	O	
14	point	VBP		conj	O	
15	out	RP		prt	O	
16	that	IN		mark	O	
17	even	RB		advmod	O	
18	a	DT		det	O	
19	two	CD		nummod	O	
20	-	HYPH		punct	O	
21	degree	NN		compound	O	
22	warming	NN		nsubj	O	
23	is	VBZ		aux	O	
24	going	VBG		ccomp	O	
25	to	TO		aux	O	
26	make	VB		xcomp	O	
27	the	DT		det	O	
28	earth	NN	LOC	nsubj	O	
29	very	RB		advmod	O	
30	warm	JJ		ccomp	O	
31	compared	VBN		prep	O	
32	to	IN		prep	O	
33	the	DT		det	O	
34	history	NN		pobj	O	
35	of	IN		prep	O	
36	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
37	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
38	millions	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
39	of	IN	DATE	prep	O	
40	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
41	,	,		punct	O	
42	'	''		punct	O	
43	'	''		punct	O	
44	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
45	Hansen	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
46	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
47	.	.		punct	O	
1	And	CC		cc	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	he	PRP		nsubj	B-ACT	
4	noted	VBD		ROOT	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	if	IN		mark	O	
7	emissions	NNS		nsubj	B-CLAIM	-
8	continue	VBP		advcl	I-CLAIM	-
9	to	TO		aux	I-CLAIM	-
10	rise	VB		xcomp	I-CLAIM	-
11	just	RB	PERCENT	advmod	I-CLAIM	-
12	1	CD	PERCENT	nummod	I-CLAIM	-
13	percent	NN	PERCENT	dobj	I-CLAIM	-
14	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	-
15	year	NN		npadvmod	I-CLAIM	-
16	--	:		punct	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	current	JJ		amod	O	
19	rate	NN		npadvmod	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	and	CC		cc	O	
22	the	DT		det	O	
23	rate	NN		conj	O	
24	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
25	would	MD		aux	O	
26	result	VB		relcl	O	
27	under	IN		prep	O	
28	the	DT		det	O	
29	policies	NNS		pobj	O	
30	proposed	VBN		acl	O	
31	by	IN		agent	O	
32	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
33	Bush	NNP	PERSON	pobj	O	
34	--	:		punct	O	
35	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
36	adds	VBZ		relcl	O	
37	up	RP		prt	O	
38	to	IN		prep	O	
39	a	DT		det	O	
40	lot	NN		pobj	O	
41	of	IN		prep	O	
42	greenhouse	NN		compound	O	
43	gases	NNS		pobj	O	
44	by	IN		prep	O	
45	later	RB	DATE	pcomp	O	
46	in	IN	DATE	prep	O	
47	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
48	century	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
49	.	.		punct	O	
1	Still	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
4	Hansen	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	B-ACT	
5	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
6	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
7	remained	VBD		ccomp	O	
8	optimistic	JJ		acomp	O	
9	that	IN		mark	O	
10	societies	NNS		nsubj	O	
11	would	MD		aux	O	
12	rise	VB		ccomp	O	
13	to	IN		prep	O	
14	the	DT		det	O	
15	challenge	NN		pobj	O	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	adding	VBG		advcl	O	
18	that	DT		mark	O	
19	natural	JJ		amod	O	
20	evidence	NN		nsubj	O	
21	of	IN		prep	O	
22	a	DT		det	O	
23	strong	JJ		amod	O	
24	human	JJ		amod	O	
25	contribution	NN		pobj	O	
26	to	IN		prep	O	
27	global	JJ		amod	O	
28	warming	NN		pobj	O	
29	was	VBD		ccomp	O	
30	likely	JJ		acomp	O	
31	to	TO		aux	O	
32	pile	VB		xcomp	O	
33	up	RP		prt	O	
34	in	IN		prep	O	
35	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
36	next	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
37	few	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
38	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
39	--	:		punct	O	
40	along	IN		prep	O	
41	with	IN		prep	O	
42	a	DT		det	O	
43	consensus	NN		pobj	B-CLAIM	+
44	for	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
45	more	JJR		amod	I-CLAIM	+
46	action	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
47	to	TO		aux	I-CLAIM	+
48	counter	VB		acl	I-CLAIM	+
49	it	PRP		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
50	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	``		punct	O		1995/01/17/0737418
3	We	PRP		nsubj	O	
4	'll	MD		aux	O	
5	be	VB		aux	O	
6	seeing	VBG		ccomp	O	
7	how	WRB		advmod	O	
8	things	NNS		nsubj	O	
9	are	VBP		aux	O	
10	going	VBG		csubj	O	
11	well	RB		advmod	O	
12	before	IN		prep	O	
13	10	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
14	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
15	are	VBP		ccomp	O	
16	out	RB		advmod	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	'	''		punct	O	
19	'	''		punct	O	
20	Dr.	NNP		compound	O	
21	Hansen	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
22	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
23	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	last	JJ		amod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	time	NN		npadvmod	O	
4	America	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
5	dominated	VBD		ROOT	O	
6	the	DT		det	O	
7	world	NN		dobj	O	
8	as	RB		advmod	O	
9	overwhelmingly	RB		advmod	O	
10	as	IN		mark	O	
11	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
12	does	VBZ		advcl	O	
13	today	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
14	was	VBD		conj	O	
15	in	IN		prep	O	
16	the	DT		det	O	
17	wake	NN		pobj	O	
18	of	IN		prep	O	
19	World	NNP	EVENT	compound	O	
20	War	NNP	EVENT	compound	O	
21	II	NNP	EVENT	pobj	O	
22	.	.		punct	O	
1	So	RB		advmod	O	
2	why	WRB		advmod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	did	VBD		aux	O	
4	that	IN		mark	O	
5	America	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
6	not	RB		neg	O	
7	inspire	VBP		ROOT	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	sort	NN		dobj	O	
10	of	IN		prep	O	
11	global	JJ		amod	O	
12	anger	NN		pobj	O	
13	that	IN		dobj	O	
14	today	NN	DATE	poss	O	
15	's	POS		case	O	
16	America	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
17	does	VBZ		relcl	O	
18	?	.		punct	O	
1	Partly	RB		advmod	O	
2	it	PRP		nsubj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	's	VBZ		ROOT	O	
4	because	IN		mark	O	
5	the	DT		det	O	
6	rest	NN		nsubj	O	
7	of	IN		prep	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	world	NN		pobj	O	
10	was	VBD		advcl	O	
11	flat	JJ		acomp	O	
12	on	IN		prep	O	
13	its	PRP$		poss	O	
14	back	NN		pobj	O	
15	then	RB		advmod	O	
16	.	.		punct	O	
1	But	CC		cc	O	
2	more	RBR		advmod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	important	JJ		acomp	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
6	's	VBZ		ROOT	O	
7	because	IN		mark	O	
8	America	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
9	after	IN		mark	O	
10	World	NNP	EVENT	compound	O	
11	War	NNP	EVENT	compound	O	
12	II	NNP	EVENT	nsubj	O	
13	took	VBD		advcl	O	
14	responsibility	NN		dobj	O	
15	for	IN		prep	O	
16	making	VBG		pcomp	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	world	NN		dobj	O	
19	both	CC		preconj	O	
20	a	DT		det	O	
21	more	RBR		advmod	O	
22	secure	JJ		amod	O	
23	place	NN		ccomp	O	
24	to	TO		aux	O	
25	live	VB		relcl	O	
26	and	CC		cc	O	
27	a	DT		det	O	
28	better	JJR		amod	O	
29	place	NN		conj	O	
30	to	TO		aux	O	
31	live	VB		relcl	O	
32	.	.		punct	O	
1	And	CC		cc	O	
2	it	PRP		nsubj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	expended	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	a	DT		det	O	
5	lot	NN		dobj	O	
6	of	IN		prep	O	
7	resources	NNS		pobj	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	as	IN		prep	O	
10	in	IN		prep	O	
11	the	DT	LAW	det	O	
12	Marshall	NNP	LAW	compound	O	
13	Plan	NNP	LAW	pobj	O	
14	,	,		punct	O	
15	to	TO		aux	O	
16	do	VB		advcl	O	
17	both	DT		dobj	O	
18	.	.		punct	O	
1	Since	IN		prep	O	
2	Sept.	NNP	DATE	pobj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	11	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	the	DT		det	O	
6	Bush	NNP	PERSON	compound	B-ACT	
7	team	NN		nsubj	O	
8	has	VBZ		aux	O	
9	focused	VBN		ROOT	O	
10	on	IN		prep	O	
11	making	VBG		pcomp	O	
12	the	DT		det	O	
13	world	NN		nsubj	O	
14	safer	JJR		ccomp	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	but	CC		cc	O	
17	has	VBZ		aux	O	
18	shown	VBN		conj	O	
19	little	JJ		amod	O	
20	interest	NN		dobj	O	
21	in	IN		prep	O	
22	making	VBG		pcomp	B-CLAIM	-
23	it	PRP		nsubj	I-CLAIM	-
24	more	RBR		advmod	I-CLAIM	-
25	healthy	JJ		ccomp	I-CLAIM	-
26	,	,		punct	O	
27	less	RBR		advmod	I-CLAIM	-
28	poor	JJ		conj	I-CLAIM	-
29	and	CC		cc	I-CLAIM	-
30	more	RBR		advmod	I-CLAIM	-
31	environmentally	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	-
32	sound	JJ		conj	I-CLAIM	-
33	.	.		punct	O	
1	As	IN		prep	O	
2	a	DT		det	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	result	NN		pobj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	there	EX		expl	O	
6	has	VBZ		aux	O	
7	been	VBN		ROOT	O	
8	little	JJ		amod	O	
9	chance	NN		attr	O	
10	that	IN		mark	O	
11	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
12	was	VBD		aux	O	
13	going	VBG		acl	O	
14	to	TO		aux	O	
15	end	VB		xcomp	O	
16	up	RP		prt	O	
17	safer	JJR		advmod	O	
18	for	IN		prep	O	
19	Americans	NNPS	NORP	pobj	O	
20	.	.		punct	O	
1	Therefore	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	President	NNP		compound	O	
4	Bush	NNP	PERSON	poss	B-ACT	
5	's	POS		case	B-ACT	
6	speech	NN		nsubj	O	
7	on	IN		prep	O	
8	Thursday	NNP	DATE	pobj	O	
9	announcing	VBG		csubj	O	
10	a	DT		det	O	
11	$	$	MONEY	quantmod	B-CLAIM	+
12	5	CD	MONEY	compound	I-CLAIM	+
13	billion	CD	MONEY	nummod	I-CLAIM	+
14	increase	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
15	in	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
16	foreign	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
17	aid	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
18	for	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
19	poor	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
20	countries	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
21	is	VBZ		ROOT	O	
22	important	JJ		acomp	O	
23	--	:		punct	O	
24	not	RB		preconj	O	
25	only	RB		advmod	O	
26	as	IN		prep	O	
27	a	DT		det	O	
28	substantive	JJ		amod	O	
29	breakthrough	NN		pobj	O	
30	for	IN		prep	O	
31	this	DT		det	O	
32	administration	NN		pobj	O	
33	,	,		punct	O	
34	but	CC		cc	O	
35	also	RB		advmod	O	
36	,	,		punct	O	
37	one	CD		nummod	O	
38	hopes	VBZ		pobj	O	
39	,	,		punct	O	
40	as	IN		prep	O	
41	a	DT		det	O	
42	psychological	JJ		amod	O	
43	one	NN		pobj	O	
44	.	.		punct	O	
1	Since	IN		prep	O	
2	Sept.	NNP	DATE	pobj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	11	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	President	NNP		compound	O	
6	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
7	has	VBZ		aux	O	
8	often	RB		advmod	O	
9	noted	VBN		ROOT	O	
10	that	IN		mark	O	
11	the	DT		det	O	
12	world	NN		nsubj	O	
13	has	VBZ		aux	O	
14	fundamentally	RB		advmod	O	
15	changed	VBN		ccomp	O	
16	.	.		punct	O	
1	Yet	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	time	NN		npadvmod	O	
4	after	IN		prep	O	
5	time	NN		pobj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
8	has	VBZ		aux	O	
9	exploited	VBN		ROOT	O	
10	the	DT		det	O	
11	shock	NN		dobj	O	
12	of	IN		prep	O	
13	Sept.	NNP	DATE	pobj	O	
14	11	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
15	to	TO		aux	O	
16	argue	VB		advcl	O	
17	why	WRB		advmod	O	
18	his	PRP$		poss	O	
19	same	JJ		amod	O	
20	old	JJ		amod	O	
21	,	,		punct	O	
22	pre	JJ	DATE	dep	O	
23	-	JJ	DATE	dep	O	
24	Sept	JJ	DATE	dep	O	
25	.	NNP	DATE	npadvmod	O	
26	11	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
27	policies	NNS		nsubj	O	
28	were	VBD		ccomp	O	
29	still	RB		advmod	O	
30	the	DT		det	O	
31	only	JJ		amod	O	
32	way	NN		attr	O	
33	to	TO		aux	O	
34	proceed	VB		relcl	O	
35	--	:		punct	O	
36	only	RB		advmod	O	
37	more	RBR		advmod	O	
38	so	RB		advmod	O	
39	.	.		punct	O	
1	Because	IN		prep	O	
2	of	IN		pcomp	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	Sept.	NNP	DATE	pobj	O	
4	11	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
7	has	VBZ		aux	O	
8	argued	VBN		parataxis	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
11	need	VBP		ROOT	O	
12	even	RB		advmod	O	
13	deeper	JJR		amod	O	
14	tax	NN		compound	O	
15	cuts	NNS		dobj	O	
16	for	IN		prep	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	wealthy	JJ		amod	O	
19	,	,		punct	O	
20	even	RB		advmod	O	
21	more	JJR		amod	O	
22	money	NN		pobj	O	
23	for	IN		prep	O	
24	a	DT		det	O	
25	pie	NN		nmod	O	
26	-	HYPH		punct	O	
27	in	IN		prep	O	
28	-	HYPH		punct	O	
29	the	DT		det	O	
30	-	HYPH		punct	O	
31	sky	NN		pobj	O	
32	missile	NN		compound	O	
33	defense	NN		pobj	O	
34	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
35	would	MD		aux	O	
36	have	VB		aux	O	
37	been	VBN		relcl	O	
38	no	DT		det	O	
39	use	NN		attr	O	
40	on	IN		prep	O	
41	Sept.	NNP	DATE	pobj	O	
42	11	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
43	,	,		punct	O	
44	an	DT		det	O	
45	even	RB		advmod	O	
46	bigger	JJR		amod	O	
47	defense	NN		compound	O	
48	budget	NN		appos	O	
49	and	CC		cc	O	
50	even	RB		advmod	O	
51	more	JJR		amod	O	
52	drilling	NN		conj	O	
53	for	IN		prep	O	
54	oil	NN		pobj	O	
55	in	IN		prep	O	
56	wilderness	NN		compound	O	
57	areas	NNS		pobj	O	
58	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	most	RBS		advmod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	obvious	JJ		amod	O	
4	conclusion	NN		nsubj	O	
5	from	IN		prep	O	
6	Sept.	NNP	DATE	pobj	O	
7	11	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
8	--	:		punct	O	
9	that	IN		mark	O	
10	fighting	VBG		csubj	O	
11	terrorism	NN		dobj	B-CLAIM	-
12	around	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	-
13	the	DT		det	I-CLAIM	-
14	globe	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	-
15	will	MD		aux	I-CLAIM	-
16	require	VB		acl	I-CLAIM	-
17	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	-
18	new	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	-
19	,	,		punct	O	
20	multidimensional	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	-
21	strategy	NN		dobj	I-CLAIM	-
22	,	,		punct	O	
23	not	RB		neg	I-CLAIM	-
24	just	RB		advmod	O	
25	a	DT		det	O	
26	defense	NN		compound	O	
27	strategy	NN		appos	O	
28	--	:		punct	O	
29	was	VBD		ROOT	O	
30	the	DT		det	O	
31	one	CD	CARDINAL	attr	O	
32	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
33	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
34	seemed	VBD		relcl	O	
35	least	RBS		advmod	B-ACT	
36	inclined	JJ		oprd	O	
37	to	TO		aux	O	
38	draw	VB		xcomp	O	
39	,	,		punct	O	
40	and	CC		cc	O	
41	that	DT		nsubj	O	
42	's	VBZ		conj	O	
43	why	WRB		advmod	O	
44	his	PRP$		poss	O	
45	speech	NN		nsubjpass	O	
46	should	MD		aux	O	
47	be	VB		auxpass	O	
48	welcomed	VBN		ccomp	O	
49	.	.		punct	O	
1	It	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	will	MD		aux	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	be	VB		ROOT	O	
4	relevant	JJ		acomp	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	though	RB		advmod	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	only	RB		advmod	O	
9	if	IN		mark	O	
10	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
11	really	RB		advmod	O	
12	signals	VBZ		advcl	O	
13	an	DT		det	O	
14	understanding	NN		dobj	O	
15	by	IN		prep	O	
16	the	DT		det	O	
17	Bush	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
18	team	NN		pobj	O	
19	that	IN		mark	O	
20	there	EX		expl	O	
21	are	VBP		acl	O	
22	no	DT		det	O	
23	walls	NNS		attr	O	
24	for	IN		mark	O	
25	us	PRP		nsubj	O	
26	to	TO		aux	O	
27	hide	VB		relcl	O	
28	behind	RB		prt	O	
29	anymore	RB		advmod	O	
30	,	,		punct	O	
31	that	IN		mark	O	
32	everything	NN		nsubjpass	O	
33	is	VBZ		auxpass	O	
34	connected	VBN		ccomp	O	
35	to	IN		prep	O	
36	everything	NN		pobj	O	
37	else	RB		advmod	O	
38	and	CC		cc	O	
39	that	IN		mark	O	
40	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
41	can	MD		aux	O	
42	not	RB		neg	O	
43	win	VB		conj	O	
44	a	DT		det	O	
45	global	JJ		amod	O	
46	war	NN		dobj	O	
47	against	IN		prep	O	
48	terrorism	NN		pobj	O	
49	without	IN		prep	O	
50	global	JJ		amod	O	
51	allies	NNS		pobj	O	
52	,	,		punct	O	
53	but	CC		cc	O	
54	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
55	will	MD		aux	O	
56	have	VB		conj	O	
57	those	DT		det	O	
58	allies	NNS		dobj	O	
59	only	RB		advmod	O	
60	if	IN		mark	O	
61	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
62	practice	VBP		advcl	O	
63	what	WP		dobj	O	
64	the	DT		det	O	
65	architects	NNS		nsubj	O	
66	of	IN		prep	O	
67	the	DT	LAW	det	O	
68	Marshall	NNP	LAW	compound	O	
69	Plan	NNP	LAW	pobj	O	
70	practiced	VBD		ccomp	O	
71	:	:		punct	O	
72	enlightened	VBN		amod	O	
73	self	NN		compound	O	
74	-	HYPH		punct	O	
75	interest	NN		appos	O	
76	,	,		punct	O	
77	not	RB		neg	O	
78	just	RB		advmod	O	
79	self	NN		compound	O	
80	-	HYPH		punct	O	
81	interest	NN		conj	O	
82	.	.		punct	O	
1	Those	DT		det	O	
2	postwar	JJ		amod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	wise	JJ		amod	O	
4	men	NNS		nsubj	O	
5	persuaded	VBD		ROOT	O	
6	others	NNS		dobj	O	
7	to	TO		aux	O	
8	follow	VB		xcomp	O	
9	us	PRP		dobj	O	
10	because	IN		mark	O	
11	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
12	not	RB		preconj	O	
13	only	RB		advmod	O	
14	respected	VBD		advcl	O	
15	our	PRP$		poss	O	
16	power	NN		dobj	O	
17	but	CC		cc	O	
18	also	RB		advmod	O	
19	our	PRP$		poss	O	
20	wisdom	NN		conj	O	
21	and	CC		cc	O	
22	moral	JJ		amod	O	
23	example	NN		conj	O	
24	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	9/11	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	terrorists	NNS		nsubj	O	
4	did	VBD		aux	O	
5	not	RB		neg	O	
6	hit	VB		ROOT	O	
7	us	PRP		dobj	O	
8	because	IN		mark	O	
9	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
10	were	VBD		advcl	O	
11	poor	JJ		acomp	O	
12	.	.		punct	O	
1	But	CC		cc	O	
2	millions	NNS	CARDINAL	nsubj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	of	IN		prep	O	
4	poor	JJ		amod	O	
5	people	NNS		pobj	O	
6	gave	VBD		ROOT	O	
7	passive	JJ		amod	O	
8	support	NN		dobj	O	
9	to	IN		dative	O	
10	those	DT		det	O	
11	terrorists	NNS		pobj	O	
12	because	IN		mark	O	
13	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
14	resented	VBD		advcl	O	
15	our	PRP$		poss	O	
16	greed	NN		dobj	O	
17	or	CC		cc	O	
18	our	PRP$		poss	O	
19	support	NN		conj	O	
20	for	IN		prep	O	
21	their	PRP$		poss	O	
22	bad	JJ		amod	O	
23	regimes	NNS		pobj	O	
24	.	.		punct	O	
1	That	DT		nsubj	O	
2	's	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	why	WRB		advmod	O	
4	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
5	was	VBD		ccomp	O	
6	important	JJ		acomp	O	
7	that	IN		mark	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	president	NN		nsubj	O	
10	said	VBD		ccomp	O	
11	our	PRP$		poss	O	
12	increased	VBN		amod	O	
13	foreign	JJ		amod	O	
14	aid	NN		nsubjpass	O	
15	must	MD		aux	O	
16	be	VB		auxpass	O	
17	conditioned	VBN		ccomp	O	
18	on	IN		prep	O	
19	countries	NNS		nsubj	O	
20	'	POS		case	O	
21	improving	VBG		pcomp	O	
22	their	PRP$		poss	O	
23	governance	NN		dobj	O	
24	,	,		punct	O	
25	rule	NN		appos	O	
26	of	IN		prep	O	
27	law	NN		pobj	O	
28	,	,		punct	O	
29	social	JJ		amod	O	
30	safety	NN		compound	O	
31	nets	NNS		conj	O	
32	,	,		punct	O	
33	investment	NN		compound	O	
34	climates	NNS		conj	O	
35	and	CC		cc	O	
36	anticorruption	NN		compound	O	
37	practices	NNS		conj	O	
38	.	.		punct	O	
1	We	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	ca	MD		aux	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	n't	RB		neg	O	
4	force	VB		ROOT	O	
5	elections	NNS		dobj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	but	CC		cc	O	
8	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
9	can	MD		aux	O	
10	use	VB		conj	O	
11	our	PRP$		poss	O	
12	aid	NN		dobj	O	
13	to	IN		aux	O	
14	pressure	NN		xcomp	O	
15	developing	VBG		amod	O	
16	countries	NNS		dobj	O	
17	to	TO		aux	O	
18	give	VB		xcomp	O	
19	their	PRP$		poss	O	
20	people	NNS		dative	O	
21	more	JJR		amod	O	
22	voice	NN		dobj	O	
23	,	,		punct	O	
24	more	JJR		amod	O	
25	rule	NN		conj	O	
26	of	IN		prep	O	
27	law	NN		pobj	O	
28	and	CC		cc	O	
29	a	DT		det	O	
30	fairer	JJR		amod	O	
31	slice	NN		conj	O	
32	of	IN		prep	O	
33	the	DT		det	O	
34	pie	NN		pobj	O	
35	,	,		punct	O	
36	which	WDT		nsubj	O	
37	are	VBP		relcl	O	
38	their	PRP$		poss	O	
39	people	NNS		poss	O	
40	's	POS		case	O	
41	real	JJ		amod	O	
42	priorities	NNS		attr	O	
43	.	.		punct	O	
1	Here	RB		advmod	O	
2	's	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	a	DT		det	O	
4	tip	NN		nsubj	O	
5	:	:		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	reason	NN		nsubj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	Islam	NNP	ORG	nsubj	O	
4	seems	VBZ		relcl	O	
5	like	IN		prep	O	
6	such	PDT		predet	O	
7	an	DT		det	O	
8	angry	JJ		amod	O	
9	religion	NN		pobj	O	
10	today	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
11	is	VBZ		ROOT	O	
12	because	IN		mark	O	
13	so	RB		advmod	O	
14	many	JJ		amod	O	
15	Muslims	NNPS	NORP	nsubj	O	
16	are	VBP		advcl	O	
17	angry	JJ		acomp	O	
18	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	reason	NN		nsubj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	so	RB		advmod	O	
4	many	JJ		amod	O	
5	Muslims	NNPS	NORP	nsubj	O	
6	are	VBP		csubj	O	
7	angry	JJ		acomp	O	
8	is	VBZ		ROOT	O	
9	because	IN		mark	O	
10	most	JJS		nsubj	O	
11	of	IN		prep	O	
12	them	PRP		pobj	O	
13	live	VBP		advcl	O	
14	under	IN		prep	O	
15	antidemocratic	JJ		amod	O	
16	regimes	NNS		pobj	O	
17	backed	VBN		acl	O	
18	by	IN		agent	O	
19	America	NNP	GPE	pobj	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	with	IN		prep	O	
22	lagging	JJ		amod	O	
23	economies	NNS		pobj	O	
24	and	CC		cc	O	
25	shrinking	VBG		amod	O	
26	opportunities	NNS		conj	O	
27	for	IN		prep	O	
28	young	JJ		amod	O	
29	people	NNS		pobj	O	
30	.	.		punct	O	
1	Beyond	IN		prep	O	
2	just	JJ		advmod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	aid	NN		pobj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	though	RB		advmod	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
8	should	MD		aux	O	
9	also	RB		advmod	O	
10	be	VB		aux	O	
11	forging	VBG		ROOT	O	
12	free	JJ		amod	O	
13	trade	NN		compound	O	
14	accords	NNS		dobj	O	
15	with	IN		prep	O	
16	as	RB		advmod	O	
17	many	JJ		amod	O	
18	Muslim	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
19	nations	NNS		pobj	O	
20	as	IN		prep	O	
21	possible	JJ		amod	O	
22	(	-LRB-		punct	O	
23	instead	RB		advmod	O	
24	of	IN		cc	O	
25	throwing	VBG		pcomp	O	
26	up	RP		prt	O	
27	insane	JJ		amod	O	
28	protectionist	JJ		compound	O	
29	walls	NNS		dobj	O	
30	around	IN		prep	O	
31	our	PRP$		poss	O	
32	steel	NN		compound	O	
33	industry	NN		pobj	O	
34	)	-RRB-		punct	O	
35	.	.		punct	O	
1	At	IN		prep	O	
2	the	DT		det	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	Davos	NNP	ORG	nmod	O	
4	economic	JJ		amod	O	
5	forum	NN		pobj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	one	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
8	expert	NN		nsubj	O	
9	noted	VBD		ROOT	O	
10	that	IN		mark	O	
11	Muslim	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
12	countries	NNS		nsubj	O	
13	made	VBD		ccomp	O	
14	up	RP		prt	O	
15	20	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
16	percent	NN	PERCENT	dobj	O	
17	of	IN		prep	O	
18	the	DT		det	O	
19	world	NN		poss	O	
20	's	POS		case	O	
21	population	NN		pobj	O	
22	,	,		punct	O	
23	yet	CC		advmod	O	
24	only	RB	PERCENT	advmod	O	
25	4	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
26	percent	NN	PERCENT	conj	O	
27	of	IN		prep	O	
28	the	DT		det	O	
29	world	NN		poss	O	
30	's	POS		case	O	
31	trade	NN		pobj	O	
32	.	.		punct	O	
1	Trade	NN		nsubj	O	
2	in	IN		prep	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	goods	NNS		pobj	O	
4	brings	VBZ		ROOT	O	
5	trade	NN		dobj	O	
6	in	IN		prep	O	
7	ideas	NNS		pobj	O	
8	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	most	RBS		advmod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	open	JJ		amod	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	tolerant	JJ		amod	O	
6	places	NNS		nsubj	O	
7	in	IN		prep	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	Muslim	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
10	world	NN		pobj	O	
11	today	NN		npadvmod	O	
12	are	VBP		ROOT	O	
13	all	DT		dep	O	
14	trading	NN		compound	O	
15	centers	NNS		attr	O	
16	:	:		punct	O	
1	Dubai	NNP	GPE	ROOT	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	Istanbul	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	Bahrain	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	Amman	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	Beirut	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
10	,	,		punct	O	
11	Jakarta	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	coastal	JJ		amod	O	
14	India	NNP	GPE	appos	O	
15	.	.		punct	O	
1	But	CC		cc	O	
2	enlightened	VBN		amod	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	self	NN		compound	O	
4	-	HYPH		punct	O	
5	interest	NN		nsubj	O	
6	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
7	not	RB		neg	O	
8	just	RB		advmod	O	
9	about	IN		prep	O	
10	generosity	NN		pobj	O	
11	;	:		punct	O	
12	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
13	's	VBZ		ROOT	O	
14	also	RB		advmod	O	
15	about	IN		prep	O	
16	self	NN		compound	O	
17	-	HYPH		punct	O	
18	restraint	NN		pobj	O	
19	.	.		punct	O	
1	We	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	need	VBP		ROOT	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	to	TO		aux	O	
4	find	VB		xcomp	O	
5	a	DT		det	O	
6	way	NN		dobj	O	
7	to	TO		aux	O	
8	ratify	VB		relcl	O	
9	the	DT		det	O	
10	Kyoto	NNP	GPE	compound	O	
11	climate	NN		compound	O	
12	change	NN		compound	O	
13	treaty	NN		dobj	O	
14	.	.		punct	O	
1	It	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	's	VBZ		ROOT	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	not	RB		neg	O	
4	only	RB		advmod	O	
5	the	DT		det	O	
6	right	JJ		amod	O	
7	thing	NN		attr	O	
8	to	TO		aux	O	
9	do	VB		relcl	O	
10	,	,		punct	O	
11	but	CC		cc	O	
12	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
13	would	MD		aux	O	
14	also	RB		advmod	O	
15	send	VB		conj	O	
16	a	DT		det	O	
17	hugely	RB		advmod	O	
18	positive	JJ		amod	O	
19	signal	NN		dobj	O	
20	to	IN		dative	O	
21	the	DT		det	O	
22	world	NN		pobj	O	
23	--	:		punct	O	
24	that	IN		mark	O	
25	America	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
26	understands	VBZ		conj	O	
27	that	IN		mark	O	
28	if	IN		mark	O	
29	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
30	's	VBZ		aux	O	
31	going	VBG		advcl	O	
32	to	TO		aux	O	
33	have	VB		xcomp	O	
34	lasting	JJ		amod	O	
35	allies	NNS		dobj	O	
36	in	IN		prep	O	
37	a	DT		det	O	
38	global	JJ		amod	O	
39	war	NN		pobj	O	
40	on	IN		prep	O	
41	terrorism	NN		pobj	O	
42	,	,		punct	O	
43	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
44	has	VBZ		ccomp	O	
45	to	TO		aux	O	
46	be	VB		xcomp	O	
47	the	DT		det	O	
48	best	RBS		amod	O	
49	global	JJ		amod	O	
50	citizen	NN		attr	O	
51	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
52	can	MD		aux	O	
53	be	VB		relcl	O	
54	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	attitude	NN		nsubj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	that	IN		mark	O	
4	we	PRP		nsubjpass	O	
5	are	VBP		auxpass	O	
6	entitled	VBN		relcl	O	
7	to	TO		aux	O	
8	consume	VB		xcomp	O	
9	25	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
10	percent	NN	PERCENT	dobj	O	
11	of	IN		prep	O	
12	the	DT		det	O	
13	world	NN		poss	O	
14	's	POS		case	O	
15	energy	NN		pobj	O	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	while	IN		mark	O	
18	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
19	're	VBP		advcl	O	
20	only	RB	PERCENT	advmod	O	
21	4	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
22	percent	NN	PERCENT	attr	O	
23	of	IN		prep	O	
24	the	DT		det	O	
25	world	NN		poss	O	
26	's	POS		case	O	
27	population	NN		pobj	O	
28	,	,		punct	O	
29	is	VBZ		ROOT	O	
30	obnoxious	JJ		acomp	O	
31	.	.		punct	O	
1	Selfishness	NNP		nsubj	O	
2	and	CC		cc	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	hubris	NNP		conj	O	
4	are	VBP		ROOT	O	
5	a	DT		det	O	
6	terrible	JJ		amod	O	
7	combination	NN		attr	O	
8	.	.		punct	O	
1	Mr.	NNP		compound	O	
2	Bush	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	has	VBZ		aux	O	
4	repeatedly	RB		advmod	O	
5	told	VBN		ROOT	O	
6	the	DT		det	O	
7	world	NN		dobj	O	
8	:	:		punct	O	
9	If	IN		mark	O	
10	you	PRP		nsubj	O	
11	're	VBP		advcl	O	
12	not	RB		neg	O	
13	with	IN		prep	O	
14	us	PRP		pobj	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	you	PRP		nsubj	O	
17	're	VBP		ccomp	O	
18	against	IN		prep	O	
19	us	PRP		pobj	O	
20	.	.		punct	O	
1	He	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	needs	VBZ		ccomp	O		1995/02/24/0745137
3	to	TO		aux	O	
4	remember	VB		xcomp	O	
5	this	DT		dobj	O	
6	:	:		punct	O	
7	The	DT		det	O	
8	rest	NN		nsubj	O	
9	of	IN		prep	O	
10	the	DT		det	O	
11	world	NN		pobj	O	
12	is	VBZ		aux	O	
13	saying	VBG		ROOT	O	
14	the	DT		det	O	
15	same	JJ		amod	O	
16	thing	NN		dobj	O	
17	to	IN		prep	O	
18	us	PRP		pobj	O	
19	.	.		punct	O	
1	To	IN		prep	O	
2	the	DT		det	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	Editor	NNP		pobj	O	
4	:	:		punct	O	
5	Re	IN		intj	O	
6	'	``		punct	O	
7	'	''		punct	O	
8	Large	JJ		amod	O	
9	Ice	NNP		compound	O	
10	Shelf	NNP		dobj	O	
11	in	IN		prep	O	
12	Antarctica	NNP		compound	O	
13	Disintegrates	NNP		pobj	O	
14	at	IN		prep	O	
15	Great	NNP		compound	O	
16	Speed	NN		pobj	O	
17	'	''		punct	O	
18	'	''		punct	O	
19	(	-LRB-		punct	O	
20	news	NN		compound	O	
21	article	NN		parataxis	O	
22	,	,		punct	O	
23	March	NNP	DATE	npadvmod	O	
24	20	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
25	)	-RRB-		punct	O	
26	:	:		punct	O	
27	The	DT		det	O	
28	dramatic	JJ		amod	O	
29	satellite	NN		compound	O	
30	images	NNS		nsubj	O	
31	documenting	VBG		acl	O	
32	the	DT		det	O	
33	breakup	NN		dobj	O	
34	of	IN		prep	O	
35	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
36	Larson	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
37	B	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
38	ice	NN	ORG	compound	O	
39	shelf	NN		pobj	O	
40	in	IN		prep	O	
41	Antarctica	NNP	LOC	pobj	O	
42	are	VBP		ROOT	O	
43	a	DT		det	O	
44	sharp	JJ		amod	O	
45	reminder	NN		attr	O	
46	of	IN		prep	O	
47	how	WRB		advmod	O	
48	global	JJ		amod	O	
49	warming	NN		nsubj	O	
50	can	MD		aux	O	
51	cause	VB		pcomp	O	
52	rapid	JJ		amod	O	
53	,	,		punct	O	
54	large	JJ		amod	O	
55	-	HYPH		punct	O	
56	scale	NN		compound	O	
57	change	NN		dobj	O	
58	.	.		punct	O	
1	Critics	NNS		nsubj	O	
2	of	IN		prep	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	the	DT		det	O	
4	Kyoto	NNP	GPE	compound	O	
5	climate	NN		compound	O	
6	treaty	NN		pobj	O	
7	point	VBP		ROOT	O	
8	out	RP		prt	O	
9	that	IN		mark	O	
10	the	DT		det	O	
11	global	JJ		amod	O	
12	system	NN		nsubj	O	
13	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
14	extremely	RB		advmod	O	
15	complicated	JJ		acomp	O	
16	and	CC		cc	O	
17	any	DT		det	O	
18	predictions	NNS		nsubj	O	
19	are	VBP		conj	O	
20	fraught	JJ		acomp	O	
21	with	IN		prep	O	
22	potential	JJ		amod	O	
23	error	NN		pobj	O	
24	.	.		punct	O	
1	This	DT		nsubj	O	
2	is	VBZ		ccomp	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	undoubtedly	RB		advmod	O	
4	true	JJ		acomp	O	
5	;	:		punct	O	
6	catastrophe	NN		nsubj	O	
7	need	VBP		aux	O	
8	not	RB		neg	O	
9	accompany	VB		ROOT	O	
10	global	JJ		amod	O	
11	warming	NN		dobj	O	
12	.	.		punct	O	
1	However	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	the	DT		det	O	
4	sudden	JJ		amod	O	
5	collapse	NN		nsubj	O	
6	of	IN		prep	O	
7	a	DT		det	O	
8	12,000-year	CD	DATE	advmod	O	
9	-	HYPH	DATE	punct	O	
10	old	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
11	ice	NN		compound	O	
12	shelf	NN		pobj	O	
13	the	DT		det	O	
14	size	NN		nsubj	O	
15	of	IN		prep	O	
16	Rhode	NNP	GPE	compound	O	
17	Island	NNP	GPE	pobj	O	
18	indicates	VBZ		ROOT	O	
19	that	IN		mark	O	
20	the	DT		det	O	
21	risk	NN		nsubj	O	
22	of	IN		prep	O	
23	fossil	JJ		amod	O	
24	fuel	NN		compound	O	
25	dependence	NN		pobj	O	
26	may	MD		aux	O	
27	be	VB		ccomp	O	
28	far	RB		advmod	O	
29	too	RB		advmod	O	
30	high	JJ		acomp	O	
31	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	technology	NN		nsubj	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	exists	VBZ		ROOT	O	
4	to	TO		aux	O	
5	greatly	RB		advmod	O	
6	increase	VB		xcomp	O	
7	our	PRP$		poss	O	
8	use	NN		dobj	O	
9	of	IN		prep	O	
10	renewable	JJ		amod	O	
11	energy	NN		compound	O	
12	resources	NNS		pobj	O	
13	.	.		punct	O	
1	Failure	NN		nsubj	O	
2	to	TO		aux	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	act	VB		acl	O	
4	ensures	VBZ		ROOT	O	
5	several	JJ		amod	O	
6	things	NNS		dobj	O	
7	:	:		punct	O	
8	more	JJR		amod	O	
9	oil	NN		compound	O	
10	spills	NNS		appos	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	more	JJR		amod	O	
13	pollution	NN		conj	O	
14	in	IN		prep	O	
15	the	DT		det	O	
16	lungs	NNS		pobj	O	
17	of	IN		prep	O	
18	city	NN		compound	O	
19	dwellers	NNS		pobj	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	more	JJR		amod	O	
22	terrorists	NNS		conj	O	
23	,	,		punct	O	
24	more	JJR		amod	O	
25	alliances	NNS		conj	O	
26	with	IN		prep	O	
27	inhumane	JJ		amod	O	
28	regimes	NNS		pobj	O	
29	.	.		punct	O	
1	Not	RB		neg	O	
2	to	TO		aux	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	mention	VB		ROOT	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	unlikely	JJ		amod	O	
6	but	CC		cc	O	
7	horrible	JJ		conj	O	
8	possibility	NN		dobj	O	
9	of	IN		prep	O	
10	a	DT		det	O	
11	global	JJ		amod	O	
12	climate	NN		pobj	O	
13	so	RB		advmod	O	
14	altered	VBD		acl	O	
15	as	IN		mark	O	
16	to	TO		aux	O	
17	cause	VB		advcl	O	
18	environmental	JJ		amod	O	
19	damage	NN		dobj	O	
20	and	CC		cc	O	
21	human	JJ		amod	O	
22	suffering	NN		conj	O	
23	more	RBR		advmod	O	
24	vast	JJ		amod	O	
25	than	IN		prep	O	
26	any	DT		det	O	
27	war	NN		pobj	O	
28	.	.		punct	O	
1	STEPHEN	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
2	GRANT	NNP		ROOT	O		1997/01/13/0901580
3	 	_SP			O	
4	West	NNP	GPE	compound	O	
5	Newton	NNP	GPE	appos	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	Mass.	NNP	GPE	appos	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	March	NNP	DATE	appos	O	
10	21	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
11	,	,	DATE	punct	O	
12	2002	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
1	THE	DT		det	O	
2	Enron	NNP	ORG	compound	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	-	HYPH	ORG	punct	O	
4	Andersen	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
5	debacle	NN		nsubj	O	
6	has	VBZ		aux	O	
7	cast	VBN		ROOT	O	
8	an	DT		det	O	
9	unforgiving	VBG		amod	O	
10	light	NN		dobj	O	
11	on	IN		prep	O	
12	corporate	JJ		amod	O	
13	bookkeeping	NN		pobj	O	
14	,	,		punct	O	
15	but	CC		cc	O	
16	the	DT		det	O	
17	growing	VBG		amod	O	
18	demand	NN		nsubj	O	
19	for	IN		prep	O	
20	accountability	NN		pobj	O	
21	could	MD		aux	O	
22	extend	VB		conj	O	
23	far	RB		advmod	O	
24	beyond	IN		prep	O	
25	financial	JJ		amod	O	
26	statements	NNS		pobj	O	
27	.	.		punct	O	
1	Pressure	NN		nsubj	O	
2	from	IN		prep	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	investors	NNS		pobj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	customers	NNS		conj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	consumer	NN		compound	O	
8	activists	NNS		conj	O	
9	and	CC		cc	O	
10	even	RB		advmod	O	
11	some	DT		det	O	
12	governments	NNS		conj	O	
13	is	VBZ		aux	O	
14	pushing	VBG		ROOT	O	
15	more	JJR		amod	O	
16	companies	NNS		dobj	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	particularly	RB		advmod	O	
19	multinational	JJ		amod	O	
20	ones	NNS		appos	O	
21	,	,		punct	O	
22	to	TO		aux	O	
23	report	VB		xcomp	O	
24	their	PRP$		poss	O	
25	nonfinancial	JJ		amod	O	
26	performance	NN		dobj	O	
27	,	,		punct	O	
28	detailing	VBG		conj	O	
29	the	DT		det	O	
30	impact	NN		dobj	O	
31	of	IN		prep	O	
32	their	PRP$		poss	O	
33	businesses	NNS		pobj	O	
34	on	IN		prep	O	
35	the	DT		det	O	
36	environment	NN		pobj	O	
37	and	CC		cc	O	
38	human	JJ		amod	O	
39	rights	NNS		conj	O	
40	.	.		punct	O	
1	This	DT		det	O	
2	so	RB		advmod	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	-	HYPH		punct	O	
4	called	VBN		amod	O	
5	social	JJ		amod	O	
6	reporting	NN		nsubj	O	
7	has	VBZ		aux	O	
8	been	VBN		ROOT	O	
9	under	IN		prep	O	
10	way	NN		pobj	O	
11	since	IN		prep	O	
12	the	DT		det	O	
13	late	JJ		amod	O	
14	1980	CD	DATE	pobj	O	
15	's	POS		case	O	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	when	WRB		advmod	O	
18	corporations	NNS		nsubj	O	
19	,	,		punct	O	
20	reacting	VBG		advcl	O	
21	to	IN		prep	O	
22	the	DT		det	O	
23	growing	VBG		amod	O	
24	environmental	JJ		amod	O	
25	movement	NN		pobj	O	
26	,	,		punct	O	
27	began	VBD		relcl	O	
28	publishing	VBG		xcomp	O	
29	brochures	NNS		dobj	O	
30	about	IN		prep	O	
31	reducing	VBG		pcomp	O	
32	pollution	NN		dobj	O	
33	.	.		punct	O	
1	But	CC		cc	O	
2	many	JJ		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	of	IN		prep	O	
4	those	DT		det	O	
5	early	JJ		amod	O	
6	efforts	NNS		pobj	O	
7	produced	VBD		ROOT	O	
8	little	JJ		advmod	O	
9	more	JJR		advmod	O	
10	than	IN		prep	O	
11	glossy	JJ		amod	O	
12	propaganda	NN		pobj	O	
13	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	the	DT	DATE	det	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
4	few	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
5	years	NNS	DATE	pobj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	the	DT		det	O	
8	forces	NNS		nsubj	O	
9	of	IN		prep	O	
10	globalization	NN		pobj	O	
11	and	CC		cc	O	
12	increased	VBN		amod	O	
13	access	NN		conj	O	
14	to	IN		prep	O	
15	information	NN		pobj	O	
16	via	IN		prep	O	
17	the	DT		det	O	
18	Internet	NN		pobj	O	
19	have	VBP		aux	O	
20	helped	VBN		ROOT	O	
21	to	TO		aux	O	
22	expand	VB		xcomp	O	
23	the	DT		det	O	
24	scope	NN		dobj	O	
25	of	IN		prep	O	
26	social	JJ		amod	O	
27	reporting	NN		pobj	O	
28	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	addition	NN		pobj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	to	IN		prep	O	
4	providing	VBG		pcomp	O	
5	environmental	JJ		amod	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	health	NN		conj	O	
8	and	CC		cc	O	
9	safety	NN		conj	O	
10	reporting	NN		dobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	companies	NNS		nsubj	O	
13	are	VBP		aux	O	
14	beginning	VBG		ROOT	O	
15	to	TO		aux	O	
16	report	VB		xcomp	O	
17	on	IN		prep	O	
18	all	DT		det	O	
19	aspects	NNS		pobj	O	
20	of	IN		prep	O	
21	their	PRP$		poss	O	
22	social	JJ		amod	O	
23	performance	NN		pobj	O	
24	,	,		punct	O	
25	from	IN		prep	O	
26	the	DT		det	O	
27	amount	NN		pobj	O	
28	of	IN		prep	O	
29	waste	NN		pobj	O	
30	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
31	reuse	VBP		relcl	O	
32	to	IN		prep	O	
33	the	DT		det	O	
34	wages	NNS		pobj	O	
35	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
36	pay	VBP		relcl	O	
37	to	IN		prep	O	
38	workers	NNS		pobj	O	
39	abroad	RB		advmod	O	
40	.	.		punct	O	
1	Advocates	NNS		nsubj	O	
2	of	IN		prep	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	this	DT		det	O	
4	more	RBR		advmod	O	
5	rigorous	JJ		amod	O	
6	reporting	NN		pobj	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	which	WDT		dobj	O	
9	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
10	call	VBP		relcl	O	
11	'	''		punct	O	
12	'	''		punct	O	
13	sustainability	NN		compound	O	
14	reporting	NN		oprd	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	'	''		punct	O	
17	'	''		punct	O	
18	say	VBP		ROOT	O	
19	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
20	provides	VBZ		ccomp	O	
21	the	DT		det	O	
22	most	RBS		advmod	O	
23	accurate	JJ		amod	O	
24	appraisal	NN		dobj	O	
25	of	IN		prep	O	
26	a	DT		det	O	
27	company	NN		poss	O	
28	's	POS		case	O	
29	potential	NN		pobj	O	
30	and	CC		cc	O	
31	risk	NN		conj	O	
32	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		ROOT	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	As	IN		pcomp	O	
4	your	PRP$		poss	O	
5	number	NN		pobj	O	
6	of	IN		prep	O	
7	suppliers	NNS		pobj	O	
8	and	CC		cc	O	
1	the	DT		det	O	
2	number	NN		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	of	IN		prep	O	
4	people	NNS		pobj	O	
5	looking	VBG		acl	O	
6	at	IN		prep	O	
7	you	PRP		pobj	O	
8	goes	VBZ		ccomp	O	
9	up	RP		prt	O	
10	,	,		punct	O	
11	you	PRP		nsubj	O	
12	need	VBP		ccomp	O	
13	new	JJ		amod	O	
14	tools	NNS		dobj	O	
15	for	IN		prep	O	
16	measurement	NN		pobj	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	'	''		punct	O	
19	'	''		punct	O	
20	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
21	Robert	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
22	Massie	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
23	,	,		punct	O	
24	a	DT		det	O	
25	founder	NN		appos	O	
26	and	CC		cc	O	
27	director	NN		conj	O	
28	of	IN		prep	O	
29	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
30	Global	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
31	Reporting	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
32	Initiative	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
33	,	,		punct	O	
34	a	DT		det	O	
35	group	NN		appos	O	
36	based	VBN		acl	O	
37	in	IN		prep	O	
38	Boston	NNP	GPE	pobj	O	
39	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
40	has	VBZ		aux	O	
41	been	VBN		aux	O	
42	working	VBG		relcl	O	
43	with	IN		prep	O	
44	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
45	United	NNP	ORG	compound	B-ACT	
46	Nations	NNP	ORG	pobj	I-ACT	
47	to	TO		aux	O	
48	devise	VB		advcl	B-CLAIM	+
49	internationally	RB		advmod	I-CLAIM	+
50	accepted	VBN		amod	I-CLAIM	+
51	standards	NNS		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
52	for	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
53	social	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
54	reporting	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
55	.	.		punct	O	
56	''	''		punct	O	
1	Leading	VBG		amod	O	
2	indicators	NNS		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	are	VBP		ROOT	O	
4	not	RB		neg	O	
5	just	RB		advmod	O	
6	financial	JJ		acomp	O	
7	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	``		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	More	JJR		amod	O	
4	companies	NNS		nsubj	O	
5	may	MD		aux	O	
6	decide	VB		ROOT	O	
7	that	IN		mark	O	
8	such	JJ		amod	O	
9	reporting	NN		nsubj	O	
10	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
11	good	JJ		acomp	O	
12	for	IN		prep	O	
13	business	NN		pobj	O	
14	.	.		punct	O	
1	A	DT		det	O	
2	1999	CD	DATE	nummod	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	survey	NN		nsubj	O	
4	of	IN		prep	O	
5	25,000	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
6	people	NNS		pobj	O	
7	worldwide	RB		advmod	O	
8	by	IN		prep	O	
9	Environics	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
10	International	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	a	DT		det	O	
13	research	NN		compound	O	
14	firm	NN		appos	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	showed	VBD		ROOT	O	
17	that	IN		mark	O	
18	56	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
19	percent	NN	PERCENT	nsubj	O	
20	formed	VBN		ccomp	O	
21	opinions	NNS		dobj	O	
22	of	IN		prep	O	
23	a	DT		det	O	
24	company	NN		pobj	O	
25	based	VBN		acl	O	
26	on	IN		prep	O	
27	its	PRP$		poss	O	
28	social	JJ		amod	O	
29	behavior	NN		pobj	O	
30	,	,		punct	O	
31	versus	IN		prep	O	
32	34	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
33	percent	NN	PERCENT	pobj	O	
34	based	VBN		acl	O	
35	on	IN		prep	O	
36	financial	JJ		amod	O	
37	fundamentals	NNS		pobj	O	
38	like	IN		prep	O	
39	profits	NNS		pobj	O	
40	.	.		punct	O	
1	Forty	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O	
2	percent	NN	PERCENT	nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
4	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
5	had	VBD		aux	O	
6	boycotted	VBN		ccomp	O	
7	or	CC		cc	O	
8	considered	VBN		amod	O	
9	boycotting	NN		compound	O	
10	companies	NNS		conj	O	
11	they	PRP		nsubj	O	
12	viewed	VBD		relcl	O	
13	as	IN		prep	O	
14	irresponsible	JJ		amod	O	
15	.	.		punct	O	
1	A	DT		det	O	
2	handful	NN		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	of	IN		prep	O	
4	companies	NNS		pobj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	like	IN		prep	O	
7	Royal	NNP	ORG	nmod	O	
8	Dutch	NNP	ORG	nmod	O	
9	/	SYM	ORG	punct	O	
10	Shell	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	Minnesota	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
13	Mining	NNP	ORG	conj	O	
14	and	CC	ORG	cc	O	
15	Manufacturing	NNP	ORG	conj	O	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	General	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
18	Motors	NNPS	ORG	conj	O	
19	and	CC		cc	O	
20	Ford	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
21	Motor	NNP	ORG	conj	O	
22	,	,		punct	O	
23	have	VBP		aux	O	
24	been	VBN		aux	O	
25	producing	VBG		ROOT	O	
26	sustainability	NN		compound	O	
27	reports	NNS		dobj	O	
28	since	IN		prep	O	
29	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
30	middle	NN	DATE	nsubj	O	
31	to	IN	DATE	aux	O	
32	late	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
33	1990	CD	DATE	pobj	O	
34	's	POS	DATE	case	O	
35	.	.		punct	O	
1	A	DT		det	O	
2	Web	NN		compound	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	site	NN		nsubj	O	
4	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
5	tracks	VBZ		relcl	O	
6	social	JJ		amod	O	
7	reporting	NN		dobj	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	CorporateRegister	NNP		nmod	O	
10	.	.		compound	O	
11	com	NN		conj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	counts	VBZ		ROOT	O	
14	487	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
15	sustainability	NN		compound	O	
16	reports	NNS		dobj	O	
17	published	VBN		acl	O	
18	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
19	year	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	up	RB		advmod	O	
22	from	IN		prep	O	
23	194	CD	CARDINAL	pobj	O	
24	in	IN		prep	O	
25	1995	CD	DATE	pobj	O	
26	and	CC		cc	O	
27	7	CD	CARDINAL	conj	O	
28	in	IN		prep	O	
29	1990	CD	DATE	pobj	O	
30	.	.		punct	O	
1	(	-LRB-		punct	O	
2	Social	JJ		amod	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	reports	NNS		nmod	O	
4	of	IN		prep	O	
5	all	DT		det	O	
6	kinds	NNS		pobj	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	including	VBG		prep	O	
9	environmental	JJ		pobj	O	
10	and	CC		cc	O	
11	afety	NN		conj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	number	NN		nsubj	O	
14	in	IN		prep	O	
15	the	DT		det	O	
16	thousands.)The	JJ		det	O	
17	biggest	JJS		amod	O	
18	new	JJ		amod	O	
19	entry	NN		pobj	O	
20	is	VBZ		ROOT	O	
21	McDonald	NNP	ORG	attr	O	
22	's	POS	ORG	case	O	
23	,	,		punct	O	
24	which	WDT		nsubj	O	
25	plans	VBZ		relcl	O	
26	to	TO		aux	O	
27	release	VB		xcomp	O	
28	its	PRP$		poss	O	
29	first	JJ	ORDINAL	amod	O	
30	sustainability	NN		compound	O	
31	report	NN		dobj	O	
32	the	DT	DATE	det	O	
33	week	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
34	of	IN	DATE	prep	O	
35	April	NNP	DATE	pobj	O	
36	15	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
37	.	.		punct	O	
1	With	IN		prep	O	
2	operations	NNS		pobj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	in	IN		prep	O	
4	121	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
5	countries	NNS		pobj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	McDonald	NNP	ORG	nsubj	O	
8	's	POS	ORG	case	O	
9	symbolizes	VBZ		ROOT	O	
10	the	DT		det	O	
11	expansion	NN		dobj	O	
12	of	IN		prep	O	
13	American	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
14	business	NN		pobj	O	
15	and	CC		cc	O	
16	has	VBZ		aux	O	
17	been	VBN		conj	O	
18	a	DT		det	O	
19	lightning	NN		compound	O	
20	rod	NN		attr	O	
21	for	IN		prep	O	
22	activists	NNS		pobj	O	
23	protesting	VBG		acl	O	
24	everything	NN		dobj	O	
25	from	IN		prep	O	
26	American	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
27	culture	NN		pobj	O	
28	to	IN		prep	O	
29	genetically	RB		advmod	O	
30	modified	VBN		amod	O	
31	food	NN		pobj	O	
32	.	.		punct	O	
1	Bob	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
2	Langert	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	company	NN		poss	O	
6	's	POS		case	O	
7	senior	JJ		amod	O	
8	director	NN		appos	O	
9	for	IN		prep	O	
10	social	JJ		amod	O	
11	responsibility	NN		pobj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
14	the	DT		det	O	
15	publication	NN		nsubjpass	O	
16	of	IN		prep	O	
17	a	DT		det	O	
18	sustainability	NN		compound	O	
19	report	NN		pobj	O	
20	was	VBD		auxpass	O	
21	not	RB		neg	O	
22	prompted	VBN		ccomp	O	
23	by	IN		agent	O	
24	any	DT		det	O	
25	one	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
26	incident	NN		pobj	O	
27	.	.		punct	O	
28	'	''		punct	O	
1	'	''		ROOT	O	
1	There	EX		expl	O	
2	is	VBZ		ccomp	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	more	JJR		amod	O	
4	interest	NN		attr	O	
5	in	IN		prep	O	
6	what	WP		dobj	O	
7	companies	NNS		nsubj	O	
8	like	IN		prep	O	
9	McDonald	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
10	's	POS	ORG	case	O	
11	are	VBP		aux	O	
12	doing	VBG		pcomp	O	
13	with	IN		prep	O	
14	social	JJ		amod	O	
15	-	HYPH		punct	O	
16	type	NN		compound	O	
17	issues	NNS		pobj	O	
18	,	,		punct	O	
19	'	''		punct	O	
20	'	''		punct	O	
21	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
22	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
23	.	.		punct	O	
24	''	''		punct	O	
1	We	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	want	VBP		ROOT	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	to	TO		aux	O	
4	provide	VB		xcomp	O	
5	a	DT		det	O	
6	full	JJ		amod	O	
7	view	NN		dobj	O	
8	of	IN		prep	O	
9	where	WRB		advmod	O	
10	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
11	've	VB		aux	O	
12	been	VBN		pcomp	O	
13	,	,		punct	O	
14	where	WRB		advmod	O	
15	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
16	're	VBP		ccomp	O	
17	at	IN		prep	O	
18	and	CC		cc	O	
19	where	WRB		advmod	O	
20	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
21	're	VBP		aux	O	
22	going	VBG		conj	O	
23	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	Its	PRP$		poss	O	
4	50-page	CD		nummod	O	
5	report	NN		nsubj	O	
6	will	MD		aux	O	
7	address	VB		ROOT	O	
8	issues	NNS		dobj	O	
9	like	IN		prep	O	
10	beef	NN		compound	O	
11	safety	NNP		pobj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	a	DT		det	O	
14	suppliers	NNS		poss	O	
15	'	POS		case	O	
16	code	NN		appos	O	
17	of	IN		prep	O	
18	conduct	NN		pobj	O	
19	and	CC		cc	O	
20	the	DT		det	O	
21	company	NN		poss	O	
22	's	POS		case	O	
23	treatment	NN		conj	O	
24	of	IN		prep	O	
25	overseas	JJ		amod	O	
26	employees	NNS		pobj	O	
27	and	CC		cc	O	
28	franchise	NN		compound	O	
29	owners	NNS		conj	O	
30	.	.		punct	O	
1	Other	JJ		amod	O	
2	companies	NNS		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	working	VBG		acl	O	
4	on	IN		prep	O	
5	such	JJ		amod	O	
6	reports	NNS		pobj	O	
7	for	IN		prep	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	first	JJ	ORDINAL	amod	O	
10	time	NN		pobj	O	
11	include	VBP		ROOT	O	
12	Alcoa	NNP	GPE	dobj	O	
13	,	,		punct	O	
14	International	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
15	Paper	NNP	ORG	conj	O	
16	and	CC		cc	O	
17	Siemens	NNP	ORG	conj	O	
18	.	.		punct	O	
19	''	''		punct	O	
1	There	EX		expl	O	
2	's	VBZ		ccomp	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	no	DT		det	O	
4	doubt	NN		attr	O	
5	that	IN		mark	O	
6	the	DT		det	O	
7	world	NN		nsubj	O	
8	at	IN		prep	O	
9	large	JJ		amod	O	
10	is	VBZ		aux	O	
11	looking	VBG		acl	O	
12	at	IN		prep	O	
13	the	DT		det	O	
14	broader	JJR		amod	O	
15	imprint	NN		pobj	O	
16	that	IN		dobj	O	
17	companies	NNS		nsubj	O	
18	leave	VBP		relcl	O	
19	on	IN		prep	O	
20	society	NN		pobj	O	
21	,	,		punct	O	
22	'	''		punct	O	
23	'	''		punct	O	
24	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
25	Jake	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
26	Siewert	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
27	,	,		punct	O	
28	a	DT		det	O	
29	vice	NN		compound	O	
30	president	NN		appos	O	
31	at	IN		prep	O	
32	Alcoa	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
33	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	another	DT		det	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	sign	NN		pobj	O	
4	that	IN		mark	O	
5	social	JJ		amod	O	
6	reporting	NN		nsubj	O	
7	is	VBZ		aux	O	
8	growing	VBG		acl	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	some	DT		det	O	
11	large	JJ		amod	O	
12	accounting	NN		compound	O	
13	firms	NNS		nsubj	O	
14	are	VBP		aux	O	
15	jumping	VBG		ROOT	O	
16	in	RP		advmod	O	
17	,	,		punct	O	
18	looking	VBG		advcl	O	
19	to	TO		aux	O	
20	expand	VB		xcomp	O	
21	their	PRP$		poss	O	
22	auditing	NN		nmod	O	
23	and	CC		cc	O	
24	consulting	NN		conj	O	
25	services	NNS		dobj	O	
26	.	.		punct	O	
1	Only	RB	PERCENT	advmod	O	
2	40	CD	PERCENT	nummod	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	percent	NN	PERCENT	nsubjpass	O	
4	of	IN		prep	O	
5	social	JJ		amod	O	
6	reports	NNS		pobj	O	
7	are	VBP		auxpass	O	
8	now	RB		advmod	O	
9	audited	VBN		ROOT	O	
10	.	.		punct	O	
11	''	''		punct	O	
1	A	DT		det	O	
2	lot	NN		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	of	IN		prep	O	
4	our	PRP$		poss	O	
5	clients	NNS		pobj	O	
6	and	CC		cc	O	
7	our	PRP$		poss	O	
8	clients	NNS		poss	O	
9	'	POS		case	O	
10	clients	NNS		conj	O	
11	are	VBP		aux	O	
12	asking	VBG		ccomp	O	
13	for	IN		prep	O	
14	this	DT		pobj	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	'	''		punct	O	
17	'	''		punct	O	
18	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
19	Sunil	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
20	Misser	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
21	,	,		punct	O	
22	partner	NN		appos	O	
23	in	IN		prep	O	
24	charge	NN		pobj	O	
25	of	IN		prep	O	
26	a	DT		det	O	
27	new	JJ		amod	O	
28	practice	NN		pobj	O	
29	for	IN		prep	O	
30	corporate	JJ		amod	O	
31	social	JJ		amod	O	
32	programs	NNS		pobj	O	
33	at	IN		prep	O	
34	PriceWaterhouseCoopers	NNS		pobj	O	
35	.	.		punct	O	
1	Still	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	there	EX		expl	O	
4	are	VBP		ROOT	O	
5	no	DT		det	O	
6	common	JJ		amod	O	
7	standards	NNS		attr	O	
8	or	CC		cc	O	
9	oversight	NN		compound	O	
10	groups	NNS		conj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	leaving	VBG		advcl	O	
13	wide	JJ		amod	O	
14	variability	NN		dobj	O	
15	in	IN		prep	O	
16	the	DT		det	O	
17	reports	NNS		pobj	O	
18	and	CC		cc	O	
19	audits	NN		conj	O	
20	.	.		punct	O	
1	For	IN		prep	O	
2	auditors	NNS		pobj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	conflicts	NNS		nsubj	O	
6	on	IN		prep	O	
7	the	DT		det	O	
8	financial	JJ		amod	O	
9	side	NN		pobj	O	
10	--	:		punct	O	
11	relationships	NNS		appos	O	
12	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
13	provide	VBP		relcl	O	
14	more	JJR	CARDINAL	amod	O	
15	than	IN	CARDINAL	quantmod	O	
16	one	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
17	service	NN		dobj	O	
18	to	IN		prep	O	
19	clients	NNS		pobj	O	
20	--	:		punct	O	
21	can	MD		aux	O	
22	be	VB		ROOT	O	
23	true	JJ		acomp	O	
24	on	IN		prep	O	
25	the	DT		det	O	
26	social	JJ		amod	O	
27	side	NN		pobj	O	
28	as	RB		advmod	O	
29	well	RB		advmod	O	
30	.	.		punct	O	
1	A	DT		det	O	
2	bigger	JJR		amod	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	problem	NN		nsubj	O	
4	to	TO		aux	O	
5	overcome	VB		acl	O	
6	may	MD		aux	O	
7	be	VB		ROOT	O	
8	public	JJ		amod	O	
9	skepticism	NN		attr	O	
10	of	IN		prep	O	
11	corporations	NNS		pobj	O	
12	fed	VBN		acl	O	
13	by	IN		agent	O	
14	scandals	NNS		pobj	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	such	JJ		amod	O	
17	as	IN		prep	O	
18	the	DT		det	O	
19	collapse	NN		pobj	O	
20	of	IN		prep	O	
21	Enron	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
22	and	CC		cc	O	
23	indictment	NN		conj	O	
24	of	IN		prep	O	
25	its	PRP$		poss	O	
26	auditor	NN		pobj	O	
27	,	,		punct	O	
28	Arthur	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
29	Andersen	NNP	ORG	appos	O	
30	.	.		punct	O	
1	VOLUNTARY	NN	ORG	compound	O	
2	self	NN		compound	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	-	HYPH		punct	O	
4	reporting	VBG		nsubj	O	
5	by	IN		prep	O	
6	corporations	NNS		pobj	O	
7	lacks	VBZ		ccomp	O	
8	credibility	NN		dobj	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
11	David	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
12	C.	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
13	Korten	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
14	,	,		punct	O	
15	the	DT		det	O	
16	author	NN		appos	O	
17	of	IN		prep	O	
18	''	''		punct	O	
1	When	WRB		advmod	O	
2	Corporations	NNS		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	Rule	VBP		advcl	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	World	NNP		dobj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	'	''		punct	O	
8	'	''		punct	O	
9	a	DT		det	O	
10	1995	CD	DATE	nummod	O	
11	book	NN		nsubj	O	
12	considered	VBD		ROOT	O	
13	the	DT		det	O	
14	bible	NNP		dobj	O	
15	of	IN		prep	O	
16	the	DT		det	O	
17	movement	NN		pobj	O	
18	against	IN		prep	O	
19	globalization	NN		pobj	O	
20	.	.		punct	O	
21	'	''		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	If	IN		mark	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	we	PRP		nsubj	O	
4	can	MD		aux	O	
5	not	RB		neg	O	
6	trust	VB		advcl	O	
7	management	NN		dobj	O	
8	to	TO		aux	O	
9	put	VB		xcomp	O	
10	out	RP		prt	O	
11	an	DT		det	O	
12	honest	JJ		amod	O	
13	report	NN		dobj	O	
14	to	IN		prep	O	
15	shareholders	NNS		pobj	O	
16	,	,		punct	O	
17	'	''		punct	O	
18	'	''		punct	O	
19	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
20	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
21	,	,		punct	O	
22	'	''		punct	O	
23	'	''		punct	O	
24	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
25	would	MD		aux	O	
26	be	VB		ccomp	O	
27	silly	JJ		acomp	O	
28	to	TO		aux	O	
29	put	VB		xcomp	O	
30	any	DT		det	O	
31	credibility	NN		dobj	O	
32	in	IN		prep	O	
33	these	DT		det	O	
34	social	JJ		amod	O	
35	reports	NNS		pobj	O	
36	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	``		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	Many	JJ		amod	O	
4	companies	NNS		nsubj	O	
5	may	MD		aux	O	
6	view	VB		ROOT	O	
7	social	JJ		amod	O	
8	reports	NNS		dobj	O	
9	as	IN		prep	O	
10	an	DT		det	O	
11	opportunity	NN		pobj	O	
12	to	TO		aux	O	
13	'	''		punct	O	
14	'	``		punct	O	
15	greenwash	FW		acl	O	
16	'	''		punct	O	
17	'	''		punct	O	
18	--	:		punct	O	
19	to	TO		aux	O	
20	highlight	VB		acl	O	
21	the	DT		det	O	
22	good	NN		dobj	O	
23	and	CC		cc	O	
24	omit	VB		conj	O	
25	the	DT		det	O	
26	bad	JJ		dobj	O	
27	--	:		punct	O	
28	with	IN		prep	O	
29	glossy	JJ		amod	O	
30	images	NNS		pobj	O	
31	of	IN		prep	O	
32	employees	NNS		pobj	O	
33	planting	VBG		acl	O	
34	trees	NNS		dobj	O	
35	,	,		punct	O	
36	butterflies	NNS		conj	O	
37	or	CC		cc	O	
38	cupped	VBN		conj	O	
39	hands	NNS		dobj	O	
40	holding	VBG		acl	O	
41	a	DT		det	O	
42	globe	NN		dobj	O	
43	.	.		punct	O	
44	''	''		punct	O	
1	We	PRP		nsubj	O	
2	want	VBP		ccomp	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	to	TO		aux	O	
4	see	VB		xcomp	O	
5	specific	JJ		amod	O	
6	targets	NNS		dobj	O	
7	that	WDT		nsubjpass	O	
8	can	MD		aux	O	
9	be	VB		auxpass	O	
10	measured	VBN		relcl	O	
11	year	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
12	to	IN	DATE	prep	O	
13	year	NN	DATE	pobj	O	
14	,	,		punct	O	
15	'	''		punct	O	
16	'	''		punct	O	
17	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
18	Paul	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
19	Scott	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	director	NN		appos	O	
22	of	IN		prep	O	
23	NextStep	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
24	Consulting	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
25	,	,		punct	O	
26	a	DT		det	O	
27	British	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
28	firm	NN		appos	O	
29	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
30	helps	VBZ		relcl	O	
31	companies	NNS		nsubj	O	
32	create	VB		ccomp	O	
33	these	DT		det	O	
34	reports	NNS		dobj	O	
35	and	CC		cc	O	
36	runs	VBZ		conj	O	
37	the	DT		det	O	
38	CorporateRegister	NNP	LOC	nmod	O	
39	.	.		compound	O	
40	com	NN		compound	O	
41	database	NN		dobj	O	
42	.	.		punct	O	
1	Still	RB		advmod	O	
2	,	,		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	he	PRP		nsubj	O	
4	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	'	''		punct	O	
7	'	``		punct	O	
8	producing	VBG		csubj	O	
9	a	DT		det	O	
10	report	NN		dobj	O	
11	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
12	a	DT		det	O	
13	good	JJ		amod	O	
14	way	NN		attr	O	
15	to	TO		aux	O	
16	get	VB		relcl	O	
17	management	NN		nsubj	O	
18	to	TO		aux	O	
19	sit	VB		ccomp	O	
20	up	RP		prt	O	
21	and	CC		cc	O	
22	take	VB		conj	O	
23	notice	NN		dobj	O	
24	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		ROOT	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	Indeed	RB		punct	O	
1	,	,		punct	O	
2	social	JJ		amod	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	reporting	NN		nsubj	O	
4	,	,		punct	O	
5	once	RB		advmod	O	
6	a	DT		det	O	
7	squishy	JJ		amod	O	
8	exercise	NN		appos	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	is	VBZ		aux	O	
11	becoming	VBG		ROOT	O	
12	more	RBR		advmod	O	
13	serious	JJ		acomp	O	
14	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	Global	NNP		compound	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	Reporting	NNP		compound	O	
4	Initiative	NNP		nsubj	O	
5	drafted	VBD		ROOT	O	
6	guidelines	NNS		dobj	O	
7	a	DT	DATE	det	O	
8	few	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
9	years	NNS	DATE	npadvmod	O	
10	ago	RB	DATE	advmod	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	and	CC		cc	O	
13	100	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	O	
14	big	JJ		amod	O	
15	companies	NNS		nsubj	O	
16	are	VBP		aux	O	
17	following	VBG		conj	O	
18	them	PRP		dobj	O	
19	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	Europe	NNP	LOC	pobj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	some	DT		det	O	
5	countries	NNS		nsubj	O	
6	--	:		punct	O	
7	the	DT		det	O	
8	Netherlands	NNP	GPE	appos	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	Denmark	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	Norway	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
13	and	CC		cc	O	
14	France	NNP	GPE	conj	O	
15	--	:		punct	O	
16	require	VBP		ROOT	O	
17	some	DT		det	O	
18	sort	NN		dobj	O	
19	of	IN		prep	O	
20	social	JJ		amod	O	
21	reporting	NN		pobj	O	
22	.	.		punct	O	
1	More	JJR	CARDINAL	amod	O	
2	than	IN	CARDINAL	quantmod	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	200	CD	CARDINAL	nummod	B-ACT	
4	companies	NNS		nsubj	I-ACT	
5	have	VBP		aux	O	
6	signed	VBN		ROOT	O	
7	the	DT	ORG	det	B-CLAIM	+
8	United	NNP	ORG	compound	I-CLAIM	+
9	Nations	NNP	ORG	compound	I-CLAIM	+
10	Global	NNP	ORG	compound	I-CLAIM	+
11	Compact	NNP	ORG	dobj	I-CLAIM	+
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	which	WDT		nsubj	I-CLAIM	+
14	commits	VBZ		relcl	I-CLAIM	+
15	them	PRP		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
16	to	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
17	a	DT		det	I-CLAIM	+
18	code	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
19	of	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
20	conduct	NN		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
21	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
22	includes	VBZ		relcl	O	
23	abolition	NN		dobj	O	
24	of	IN		prep	O	
25	child	NN		compound	O	
26	labor	NN		pobj	O	
27	and	CC		cc	O	
28	slave	NN		compound	O	
29	labor	NN		conj	O	
30	,	,		punct	O	
31	recognition	NN		conj	O	
32	of	IN		prep	O	
33	union	NN		compound	O	
34	rights	NNS		pobj	O	
35	and	CC		cc	O	
36	responsibility	NN		conj	O	
37	for	IN		prep	O	
38	preventing	VBG		pcomp	O	
39	environmental	JJ		amod	O	
40	damage	NN		dobj	O	
41	.	.		punct	O	
1	The	DT		det	O	
2	code	NN		nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	has	VBZ		ROOT	O	
4	no	DT		det	O	
5	enforcement	NN		compound	O	
6	provisions	NNS		dobj	O	
7	,	,		punct	O	
8	but	CC		cc	O	
9	supporters	NNS		nsubj	O	
10	say	VBP		conj	O	
11	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
12	is	VBZ		ccomp	O	
13	symbolically	RB		advmod	O	
14	important	JJ		acomp	O	
15	,	,		punct	O	
16	much	RB		advmod	O	
17	as	IN		mark	O	
18	the	DT	ORG	det	O	
19	Sullivan	NNP	ORG	compound	O	
20	Principles	NNPS	ORG	nsubj	O	
21	were	VBD		advcl	O	
22	in	IN		prep	O	
23	pressuring	VBG		pcomp	O	
24	South	NNP	GPE	compound	O	
25	Africa	NNP	GPE	dobj	O	
26	to	TO		aux	O	
27	end	VB		xcomp	O	
28	apartheid	NN		dobj	O	
29	.	.		punct	O	
1	AT	IN		compound	O	
2	Shell	NNP	ORG	ROOT	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	which	WDT		nsubj	O	
5	will	MD		aux	O	
6	publish	VB		relcl	O	
7	its	PRP$		poss	O	
8	fifth	JJ	ORDINAL	amod	O	
9	sustainability	NN		compound	O	
10	report	NN		dobj	O	
11	next	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
12	month	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
1	,	,		punct	O	
2	there	EX		expl	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	is	VBZ		ROOT	O	
4	a	DT		det	O	
5	conspicuous	JJ		amod	O	
6	sensitivity	NN		attr	O	
7	about	IN		prep	O	
8	consulting	VBG		pcomp	O	
9	with	IN		prep	O	
10	local	JJ		amod	O	
11	groups	NNS		pobj	O	
12	in	IN		prep	O	
13	the	DT		det	O	
14	planning	NN		pobj	O	
15	of	IN		prep	O	
16	new	JJ		amod	O	
17	projects	NNS		pobj	O	
18	.	.		punct	O	
1	A	DT		det	O	
2	pipeline	NN		nsubjpass	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	completed	VBN		acl	O	
4	last	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
5	fall	NN	DATE	npadvmod	O	
6	in	IN		prep	O	
7	the	DT		det	O	
8	Philippines	NNP	GPE	pobj	O	
9	,	,		punct	O	
10	for	IN		prep	O	
11	example	NN		pobj	O	
12	,	,		punct	O	
13	was	VBD		auxpass	O	
14	routed	VBN		ROOT	O	
15	to	TO		aux	O	
16	avoid	VB		advcl	O	
17	sacred	JJ		amod	O	
18	burial	NN		compound	O	
19	sites	NNS		dobj	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	coral	JJ		compound	O	
22	beds	NNS		conj	O	
23	and	CC		cc	O	
24	fishing	NN		compound	O	
25	grounds	NNS		conj	O	
26	.	.		punct	O	
1	That	DT		nsubj	O	
2	contrasts	VBZ		ROOT	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	with	IN		prep	O	
4	Shell	NNP	ORG	poss	O	
5	's	POS		case	O	
6	old	JJ		amod	O	
7	behavior	NN		pobj	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	which	WDT		nsubj	O	
10	caused	VBD		relcl	O	
11	a	DT		det	O	
12	public	JJ		amod	O	
13	backlash	NN		dobj	O	
14	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
15	hurt	VBD		relcl	O	
16	its	PRP$		poss	O	
17	reputation	NN		dobj	O	
18	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	1995	CD	DATE	pobj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	for	IN		prep	O	
5	example	NN		pobj	O	
6	,	,		punct	O	
7	when	WRB		advmod	O	
8	the	DT		det	O	
9	company	NN		nsubj	O	
10	announced	VBD		advcl	O	
11	plans	NNS		dobj	O	
12	to	TO		aux	O	
13	sink	VB		acl	O	
14	an	DT		det	O	
15	oil	NN		compound	O	
16	platform	NN		dobj	O	
17	in	IN		prep	O	
18	the	DT	LOC	det	O	
19	North	NNP	LOC	compound	O	
20	Atlantic	NNP	LOC	pobj	O	
21	and	CC		cc	O	
22	worked	VBD		conj	O	
23	with	IN		prep	O	
24	a	DT		det	O	
25	repressive	JJ		amod	O	
26	regime	NN		pobj	O	
27	in	IN		prep	O	
28	Nigeria	NNP	GPE	pobj	O	
29	,	,		punct	O	
30	protesters	NNS		nsubj	B-ACT	
31	denounced	VBD		ROOT	O	
32	the	DT		det	O	
33	company	NN		nsubj	O	
34	and	CC		cc	O	
35	Shell	NNP	ORG	poss	B-CLAIM	-
36	's	POS		case	B-CLAIM	-
37	European	JJ	NORP	amod	O	
38	sales	NNS		nsubj	O	
39	plummeted	VBD		ccomp	O	
40	.	.		punct	O	
1	Mark	NNP	PERSON	compound	O	
2	Wade	NNP	PERSON	nsubj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	the	DT		det	O	
5	sustainable	JJ		amod	O	
6	-	HYPH		punct	O	
7	development	NN		compound	O	
8	manager	NN		appos	O	
9	at	IN		prep	O	
10	Shell	NNP	ORG	pobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	said	VBD		ROOT	O	
13	those	DT		det	O	
14	protests	NNS		nsubj	O	
15	'	POS		punct	O	
16	'	''		punct	O	
17	triggered	VBD		ccomp	O	
18	our	PRP$		poss	O	
19	understanding	NN		dobj	O	
20	of	IN		prep	O	
21	the	DT		det	O	
22	importance	NN		pobj	O	
23	of	IN		prep	O	
24	building	VBG		compound	O	
25	relationships	NNS		pobj	O	
26	.	.		punct	O	
1	'	``		punct	O	
2	'	''		punct	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	In	IN		ROOT	O	
1	Shell	NNP	ORG	poss	O	
2	's	POS		case	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	sustainability	NN		compound	O	
4	report	NN		nsubj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	the	DT		det	O	
7	company	NN		nsubj	O	
8	offers	VBZ		ROOT	O	
9	an	DT		det	O	
10	annual	JJ	DATE	amod	O	
11	measure	NN		dobj	O	
12	of	IN		prep	O	
13	how	WRB		advmod	O	
14	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
15	is	VBZ		aux	O	
16	doing	VBG		pcomp	O	
17	on	IN		prep	O	
18	its	PRP$		poss	O	
19	commitments	NNS		pobj	O	
20	,	,		punct	O	
21	like	IN		prep	O	
22	reducing	VBG		pcomp	O	
23	emissions	NNS		dobj	O	
24	that	WDT		nsubj	O	
25	many	JJ		amod	O	
26	scientists	NNS		nsubj	O	
27	say	VBP		relcl	O	
28	contribute	VB		ccomp	O	
29	to	IN		prep	O	
30	global	JJ		amod	O	
31	warming	NN		pobj	O	
32	.	.		punct	O	
1	Shell	NNP	ORG	poss	B-ACT	
2	's	POS		case	B-ACT		1997/02/13/0908517
3	upcoming	JJ		amod	O	
4	report	NN		nsubj	O	
5	,	,		punct	O	
6	it	PRP		nsubj	O	
7	said	VBD		parataxis	O	
8	,	,		punct	O	
9	would	MD		aux	O	
10	show	VB		ROOT	O	
11	the	DT		det	O	
12	company	NN		nsubj	B-CLAIM	+
13	had	VBD		aux	I-CLAIM	+
14	reduced	VBN		ccomp	I-CLAIM	+
15	such	JJ		amod	I-CLAIM	+
16	emissions	NNS		dobj	I-CLAIM	+
17	by	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
18	nearly	RB	PERCENT	advmod	I-CLAIM	+
19	10	CD	PERCENT	nummod	I-CLAIM	+
20	percent	NN	PERCENT	pobj	I-CLAIM	+
21	from	IN		prep	I-CLAIM	+
22	1990	CD	DATE	nummod	I-CLAIM	+
23	levels	NNS		pobj	I-CLAIM	+
24	.	.		punct	O	
1	In	IN		prep	O	
2	contrast	NN		pobj	O		1997/02/13/0908517
3	,	,		punct	O	
4	the	DT	LAW	det	O	
5	Kyoto	NNP	LAW	compound	O	
6	treaty	NN	LAW	nsubj	O	
7	to	TO		aux	O	
8	stop	VB		acl	O	
9	global	JJ		amod	O	
10	warming	NN		dobj	O	
11	,	,		punct	O	
12	which	WDT		dobj	O	
13	the	DT	GPE	det	O	
14	United	NNP	GPE	compound	O	
15	States	NNP	GPE	nsubj	O	
16	has	VBZ		aux	O	
17	not	RB		neg	O	
